<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 3 - A N N E X - D
REF: NCI Agency Technical Report TR-2013/ACO008868/04 Version 3.1 Dated 25 September 2013 and subsequent RFC's received directly from NCIA
Copyright © 2013 NCIO/NATO - All Rights Reserved.
*****************************************************************  
-->
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v3-d">
<title>The Afghanistan Mission Network (AMN) Profile of NATO Interoperability Standards</title>
<sect1>
  <title>General</title>

  <para>NATO, through its interoperability directive, has recognized
  that widespread interoperability is a key component in achieving
  effective and efficient operations. In many of the operations
  world-wide in which the military of the NATO nations are engaged,
  they participate together with a wide variety of the military of
  other nations and non-military organizations on the ground. The NATO
  Interoperability Standards and Profile (NISP) provides the necessary
  guidance and technical components to support project implementations
  and transition to NATO Network Enabled Capability (NNEC).</para>

  <sect2>
    <title>Authorised Version</title>
    
    <para>The standards extant for the AMN are described in the NISP. This is published as ADatP-34 by the NATO C3 Board. As part of the NISP, an AMN Profile of NATO Interoperability Standards has been published among the several operational profiles permitted as part of ADatP-34. The latest authorised version can be found in Volume 4 of the NISP [ADaTP-34(G)-REV1, Volume 4 Annex D, 8 March 2013]. These are the extant and NATO agreed list of practical standards to achieve immediately usable interoperability between the national network extensions of the NATO nations, coalition partners and NATO provided capabilities.</para>
    <para>Nations participating in the AMN have agreed to comply with the AMN joining instructions, of which these standards form an integral part.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Application</title>
    
    <para>The AMN Profile will be used in the implementation of NATO Common Funded Systems. Nations participating in AMN agree to use this profile at Network Interconnection Points (NIPs) and at other Service Interoperability Points as applicable.</para>
    
    <para>NNEC Services must be able to function in a network environment containing firewalls and various routing and filtering schemes; therefore, developers must use standard and well-known ports wherever possible, and document non-standard ports as part of their service interface. Service developers must assume network behaviour and performance consistent with the existing limits of these networks, taking bandwidth limitations and potentially unreliable networks into account.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Life-Cycle of Standards</title>
    
    <para>ADatP-34 defines four stages within the life-cycle of a standard: <emphasis role="bold">emerging, mandatory, fading and retired</emphasis><footnote><para>The FMN Profile has been further refined and also additionally uses 4 obligation categories of Mandatory, Conditional, Recommended and Optional to assist with conformity assessments. Where relevant these have also been used in an AMN context.</para></footnote>. In those situations where multiple stages are mentioned, the AMN Profile recommends dates by which the transition to the next stage is to be completed by all AMN members. If a TCN (or NCI Agency) decides to implement emerging standards it is her responsibility to maintain backwards compatibility to the mandatory standard.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Forthcoming/Agreed Changes</title>
    
    <para>Volume 4 of the Joining, Membership and Exit Instructions (JMEI) is oriented around the AMN Profile of NATO Interoperability Standards. The AMN Profile is maintained within this document.</para>
    <para>The extant authorised version of the AMN Profile is as published in ADaTP-34(G). This formal published version of the AMN Profile is to only be originated from this document (i.e. Vol 4 of the JMEI published as NCI Agency Technical Report <emphasis role="bold">TR-2013/ACO008868/04</emphasis>).</para>
    <para>The NCI Agency acts as the custodian for the AMN Profile and is to be used as the conduit for changes (via her membership of the AMN AWG). This must be via the process outlined at section 2.7 of the JMEI Volume 4</para>
    <para>Any <emphasis role="bold">changes already collectively <emphasis role="underline">agreed</emphasis> by the AMN TCN and NCI Agency via the AMN AWG for use on the AMN</emphasis> but not yet published in ADaTP-34 were indicated as changes in the document. These changes will be submitted for publication in the next authorised issue of ADatP-34 (i.e. ADaTP-34(H) and thereafter).</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Relationship to NATO C3 Classification Taxonomy</title>
    
    <para>The AMN has been designed and is managed as far as possible using a
    service approach. The AMN Services are based on the NATO C3 Classification
    Taxonomy AC/322-N(2012)0092-AS1.</para> <para>The C3 Classification Taxonomy
    is used to identify particular services and associated Service
    Interoperability Point where two entities will interface and the standards
    in use by the relevant systems.</para> <para>Where required, the
    implementation of the standard is described in an annex associated with the
    Service.</para> <para>Where a composite suite of services (with their
    standards) are required to implement a suite of services that are typically
    grouped together to form a familiar “composite service” or a “user facing
    Service”, then the implementation annex is housed at the assessed “centre of
    gravity” of the composite service. This is done simply to keep the
    instructions together. This applies for those services which network
    engineers, system administrators, users or operators recognise as distinct
    (e.g. “Text based Chat”, “VoSIP” or “VTC”), and for which technical
    skills/specialisms/instructions already exist. For Example the VTC
    implementation annex is placed under “Core Enterprise Services/ Enterprise
    Support Services” despite the fact that the VTC “composite service” is also
    implemented by services in Communications Access Services, Service
    Management and Control etc..</para> <para>The C3 Classification Taxonomy is
    used to structure this document, commencing with Communications and working
    up the Taxonomy.</para></sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Relationship to the Future (Federated) Mission Network</title>
    
    <para>Subsequent NATO led missions will benefit from the modular nature of
    the AMN Profile, which will allow for maximum reuse of established
    capabilities, while accommodating unique requirements and technology
    improvements.</para>
    <para>Based on the AMN Profile, a Federated Mission
    Network Profile of NATO Interoperability Standards has been proposed and is
    anticipated to be published in the next version of ADaTP-34. This will
    support the implementation of the Future Mission Network (FMN) Concept
    [MCM-0125-2012].</para>
    <para>Given the strong linkage between AMN and FMN,
    the opportunity to maintain a single Federated Mission Network Profile is
    possible in future versions of this document, but will firstly require the
    establishment of the FMN Governance and FMN Framework Management Structures.
    To this end it is anticipated that any future development of capabilities
    for the AMN in the future should be done in the direction indicated by the
    Federated Mission Network Profile.</para>
    <para>This AMN Profile contains
    footnotes from the FMN Profile that if applied would implement the AMN in
    the direction of the FMN. These are indicated as a footnote to the
    referenced standard. Please note however: <emphasis role="bold">The FMN notes are only included for information. They are not
    yet approved by the AWG for use on the AMN.</emphasis></para></sect2>
 </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Communication Services</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Communications Services interconnect systems and mechanisms for the opaque transfer of selected data between or among access points, in accordance with agreed quality parameters and without change in the form or content of the data as sent and received.</emphasis></para>
    <para>Communications Services can be further defined as:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Transmission Services</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Transport Services</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Communications Access Services</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   <sect2>
	<title>Transmission Services</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Transmission Services cover the physical layer (also referred to as media layer or air-interface in wireless/satellite (SATCOM) communications) supporting Transport Services, as well as Communications Access Services. Support for the latter is relevant to personal communications systems, in which the User Appliances directly connect to the transmission element without any transport elements in between.</emphasis></para>
   <sect3>
   <title>Standards</title>
   <para>Although the implementation scope of AMN technically does not cover Transmission Services, there is one area that provides the foundation for the provision of federated services on the AMN. The Standards listed in the table below need to be adhered to.</para>
      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable2">
        <title>Transmission IA Services Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />

          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>

              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Information Assurance during Transmission</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Mandatory:  ACP 176 NATO SUPP 1 (NC)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>ACP 176 NATO SUPP 1 (NC) provides configuration settings necessary to ensure interoperability when different cryptographic devices (e.g. KIV-7/KG84/BID1650) are employed together.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
   </sect3>
   <sect3>
   <title>Implementation</title>
   <para>Although the implementation scope of AMN technically does not cover Transmission Services the TCN joining the AMN require guidance on options on how to provide communications within Theatre.</para>
<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing these services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex A.1: Provision of Terrestrial Communications.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex A.2: Use of Deployable CIS (including SATCOM).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
   </sect3>
   </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Transport Services</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Transport Services provide resource-facing services, providing metro and wide-area connectivity to the Communications Access Services that operate at the edges of the network. In that role, Transport Services interact with the Transmission Services using them as the physical layer fabric supporting the transfer of data over a variety of transmission bearers as and where needed.</emphasis></para>
    <para>Transport Services are further defined in the C3 Taxonomy, however the area that is most relevant to the AMN are:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Edge Transport Services</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Edge Transport Services provide the delivery or exchange of traffic flows over different Transmission Services. The traffic flows are formatted and delivered by the Communications Access Services at the edges of the network. This "edge" in Edge Transport is the Wide Area Network (WAN) edge (i.e. the provider edge). In Protected Core Networking (PCN) terms, the edge can be considered as the entry point into the Protected Core.</emphasis></para>
   <sect3>
   <title>Standards</title>
   <para>The AMN is a converged IP network applying open standards and industry best practices.  The AMN architecture uses interconnection based on IPv4 between the Mission Networks (also referred to as autonomous systems).</para><para> 
The AMN was originally conceived with IPv6 as the target for interconnecting autonomous systems (although no TCN has yet indicated that they wish to implement this on the AMN). As IPv6 is also the direction that the FMN is progressing, and as the AMN will become one the first FMN instances, IPv6 standards are now listed in the AMN Profile.</para><para>
It is now advised that all new equipment, services and applications must support a dual IPv4/IPv6 stack implementation to future-proof the AMN for the long term and to enable AMN to remain in line with the development of the FMN.</para><para>
The interconnection between Mission Networks is based on STANAG 5067 enhanced with a non-tactical connector and optional 1Gb/s Ethernet.  STANAG 5067 provides additional implementation, security and management guidance.  Due to the classification level of the AMN, dedicated transmission security (crypto) equipment is used.</para><para>
The standards for Transport and corresponding Communications Equipment are given in the table below.</para>
      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable3">
        <title>Edge Transport Services and Communications Equipment Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Edge Transport Services between autonomous systems
(IP over point-to-point Ethernet links on optical fibre)<footnote><para>FMN: A key improvement that the FMN will bring is the ability to create connectivity over a Time-division multiplexing (TDM) Wide Area Network (WAN). For this a suite of standards additional to those for a fibre based network has been drawn from TACOMs and demonstrated. The FMN Profile [NCIA TR-2013/SPW008910/01] will include implementation notes and instructions for these.</para></footnote>
</entry>
              <entry><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  ISO/IEC 11801: 2002-09, Information technology –Generic cabling for customer premises, Clause 9.  Single-mode optical fibre OS1 wavelength 1310nm.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  ITU-T G.652 (11/2009), Characteristics of a single-mode optical fibre and cable. (9/125μm)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IEC 61754-20: 2012(E), Fibre optic interconnecting devices and passive components - Fibre optic connector interfaces - Part 20: Type LC connector family.  LC-duplex single-mode connector.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IEEE Std 802.3-2013, Standard for Ethernet- Section 5 - Clause 58 - 1000BASE-LX10, Nominal transmit wavelength 1310nm.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>IPv4 over Ethernet:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IETF STD 37: 1982 / IETF RFC 826: 1982, An Ethernet Address Resolution Protocol</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>IPv6 over Ethernet (Optional):</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory (if option taken):IETF RFC 4861: 2007, Neighbor Discovery for IP version 6 (IPv6)<footnote><para>FMN: will implement IETF RFC 4861.</para></footnote>
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></entry>
  <entry><para>Use 1Gb/s Ethernet over Single-mode optical fibre (SMF).</para></entry>
            </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>2: Inter-Autonomous System (AS) routing</entry>
              <entry><para>IPv4 over Ethernet:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IETF RFC 1997:1996, BGP Communities Attribute.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Emerging: IETF RFC 3392: 2002, Capabilities Advertisement with BGP-4<footnote><para>FMN: Will implement IETF RFC 3392.</para></footnote>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  Border Gateway Protocol V4 (IETF RFC 1771, March 1995)<footnote><para>FMN: Will implement IETF RFC 4271. FMN notes: IETF RFC 4271 obsoletes IETF RFC 1771. BGP sessions must be authenticated, through a TCP message authentication code (MAC) using a one-way hash function (MD5), as described in IETF RFC 4271.</para></footnote>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Emerging: IETF RFC 4760: 2007, Multiprotocol Extensions  for  BGP-4<footnote><para>FMN: Will implement IETF RFC 4760.</para></footnote>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>32-bit autonomous system numbers:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 6793: 2012, BGP Support for Four-Octet Autonomous System (AS) Number Space.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 4360: 2006, BGP Extended Communities Attribute.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 5668: 2009, 4-Octet AS Specific BGP Extended Community.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>IPv6 over Ethernet (Optional):</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory (if option taken): IETF RFC 2545: 1999, Use of BGP-4 Multiprotocol Extensions for IPv6 Inter-Domain Routing<footnote><para>FMN: Will implement IETF RFC 2545.</para></footnote>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
            <entry><para>BGP deployment guidance in:  IETF RFC 1772: 1995, Application of the Border Gateway Protocol in the Internet.</para>
<para>Detailed Interface Control Document for “Connection Between CISAF network and TCN networks” [Thales ICD NIP Dec 2012]</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Inter-Autonomous System (AS) multicast routing</entry>
              <entry>IPv4 over Ethernet<footnote><para>FMN: Suggests as Optional: IETF RFC 4604: 2006, Using Internet Group Management Protocol Version 3 (IGMPv3) and Multicast Listener Discovery Protocol Version 2 (MLDv2) for Source-Specific Multicast.</para></footnote>:<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 3618: 2003, Multicast Source Discovery Protocol (MSDP).
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 3376: 2002, Internet Group Management Protocol, Version 3 (IGMPv3).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 4601, Protocol Independent Multicast version 2 (PIMv2) Sparse Mode (SM).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 4760: 2007 “Multiprotocol Extensions for BGP (MBGP)”.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>IPv6 over Ethernet:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Note: No standard solution for IPv6 multicast routing has yet been widely accepted.  More research and experimentation is required in this area.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>4: Unicast routing</entry>
              <entry><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IETF RFC 4632: 2006, Classless Inter-domain Routing (CIDR):  The Internet Address Assignment and Aggregation Plan.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>5: Multicast routing</entry>
              <entry><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IETF RFC 1112: 1989, Host Extensions for IP Multicasting.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IETF RFC 2908: 2000, The Internet Multicast Address Allocation Architecture</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 3171: 2001, IANA Guidelines for IPv4 Multicast Address Assignments.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 2365: 1998, Administratively Scoped IP Multicast.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
	  	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
   </sect3>
   <sect3>
   <title>Implementation</title>
   <para>The Network Interconnection Point (NIP) provides a network interconnection at the IP layer for the ISAF SECRET environment making up the AMN. It serves 3 major purposes:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Intra autonomous system (AS) routing (routing of traffic between nations or between nations and NATO, where each nation is a BGP Autonomous System).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>QoS policy enforcement (to provide end-to-end QoS for the required services).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>IPSLA compliance verification (to verify end-to-end performance compliance).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>With respect to creating the connection at the NIP and the corresponding network engineering required the following Annexes are provided:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex B.1: Connecting to the Network Interconnection Points (NIP).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
   </sect3>
   </sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Communications Access Services</title>
<para></para>
<sect3>
<title>Standards</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Implementation of Packet-Based Access Services</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Implementation of Communications Access Information Assurance (IA) Services</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Implementation of Communications Access Service Management Control (SMC) Services.</title>
<para></para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Core Enterprise Services</title>
<para></para>
<sect2>
<title>Infrastructure Services</title>
<sect3>
<title>Standards</title>
<para/>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para/>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>SOA Platform Services</title>
<sect3>
<title>Standards</title>
<para/>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para/>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Enterprise Support Services</title>
<sect3>
<title>Unified Communication and Collaboration Services</title>
<para/>
<sect4>
<title>Standards</title>
<para/>
</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para/>
</sect4>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Information Management Services</title>
<sect4>
<title>Standards</title>
<para/>
</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para/>
</sect4>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Geospatial Services</title>
<sect4>
<title>Standards</title>
<para/>
</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para/>
</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Communities of Interest Services</title>
<para></para>
<sect2>
<title>Communities of Interest Enabling Services</title>
<sect3>
<title>Situational Awareness Services</title>
<sect4>
<title>Standards</title>
<para/>
</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para/>
</sect4>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Biometric Services</title>
<sect4>
<title>Standards</title>
<para/>
</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para/>
</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Communities of Interest Specific Services</title>
<sect3>
<title>JISR COI Services</title>
<sect4>
<title>Standards</title>
<para/>
</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para/>
</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>User Facing Capabilities</title>
<para></para>
<sect2>
  <title>???</title>
<sect3>
<title>Standards</title>
<para/>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para/>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Human-to-Human Communication</title>
<para></para>
<sect2>
<title>Standards</title>
<para/>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Service Management and Control</title>
<para></para>
<sect2>
<title>Standards</title>
<para/>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para/>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Abbreviations</title>
<para></para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>References</title>
<para></para>
</sect1>





<!--
*****************************************************************

Reuse this code as needed

<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic"></emphasis></para>

<footnote><para></para></footnote>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para></para></listitem>
<listitem><para></para></listitem>
<listitem><para></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-string">
        <title>Title string</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:repeating purpose para</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>repeating Standard para</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>repeating Guidance para</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

*****************************************************************  
-->
</appendix>
