<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 3 - A N N E X - D
REF: NCI Agency Technical Report TR-2013/ACO008868/04 Version 3.1 Dated 25 September 2013 and subsequent RFC's received directly from NCIA
Copyright © 2013 NCIO/NATO - All Rights Reserved.
*****************************************************************  
-->
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v3-d">
<title>The Afghanistan Mission Network (AMN) Profile of NATO Interoperability Standards</title>
<sect1>
  <title>General</title>

  <para>NATO, through its interoperability directive, has recognized
  that widespread interoperability is a key component in achieving
  effective and efficient operations. In many of the operations
  world-wide in which the military of the NATO nations are engaged,
  they participate together with a wide variety of the military of
  other nations and non-military organizations on the ground. The NATO
  Interoperability Standards and Profile (NISP) provides the necessary
  guidance and technical components to support project implementations
  and transition to NATO Network Enabled Capability (NNEC).</para>

  <sect2>
    <title>Authorised Version</title>
    
    <para>The standards extant for the AMN are described in the NISP. This is published as ADatP-34 by the NATO C3 Board. As part of the NISP, an AMN Profile of NATO Interoperability Standards has been published among the several operational profiles permitted as part of ADatP-34. The latest authorised version can be found in Volume 4 of the NISP [ADaTP-34(G)-REV1, Volume 4 Annex D, 8 March 2013]. These are the extant and NATO agreed list of practical standards to achieve immediately usable interoperability between the national network extensions of the NATO nations, coalition partners and NATO provided capabilities.</para>
    <para>Nations participating in the AMN have agreed to comply with the AMN joining instructions, of which these standards form an integral part.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Application</title>
    
    <para>The AMN Profile will be used in the implementation of NATO Common Funded Systems. Nations participating in AMN agree to use this profile at Network Interconnection Points (NIPs) and at other Service Interoperability Points as applicable.</para>
    
    <para>NNEC Services must be able to function in a network environment containing firewalls and various routing and filtering schemes; therefore, developers must use standard and well-known ports wherever possible, and document non-standard ports as part of their service interface. Service developers must assume network behaviour and performance consistent with the existing limits of these networks, taking bandwidth limitations and potentially unreliable networks into account.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Life-Cycle of Standards</title>
    
    <para>ADatP-34 defines four stages within the life-cycle of a standard: <emphasis role="bold">emerging, mandatory, fading and retired</emphasis><footnote><para>The FMN Profile has been further refined and also additionally uses 4 obligation categories of Mandatory, Conditional, Recommended and Optional to assist with conformity assessments. Where relevant these have also been used in an AMN context.</para></footnote>. In those situations where multiple stages are mentioned, the AMN Profile recommends dates by which the transition to the next stage is to be completed by all AMN members. If a TCN (or NCI Agency) decides to implement emerging standards it is her responsibility to maintain backwards compatibility to the mandatory standard.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Forthcoming/Agreed Changes</title>
    <sect3>
	<title>Indicating Changes to the AMN Profile</title>
    <para>Volume 4 of the Joining, Membership and Exit Instructions (JMEI) is oriented around the AMN Profile of NATO Interoperability Standards. The AMN Profile is maintained within this document.</para>
    <para>The extant authorised version of the AMN Profile is as published in ADaTP-34(G). This formal published version of the AMN Profile is to only be originated from this document (i.e. Vol 4 of the JMEI published as NCI Agency Technical Report <emphasis role="bold">TR-2013/ACO008868/04</emphasis>).</para>
    <para>The NCI Agency acts as the custodian for the AMN Profile and is to be used as the conduit for changes (via her membership of the AMN AWG). This must be via the process outlined at section 2.7 of the JMEI Volume 4</para>
    <para>Any <emphasis role="bold">changes already collectively <emphasis role="underline">agreed</emphasis> by the AMN TCN and NCI Agency via the AMN AWG for use on the AMN</emphasis> but not yet published in ADaTP-34 were indicated as changes in the document. These changes will be submitted for publication in the next authorised issue of ADatP-34 (i.e. ADaTP-34(H) and thereafter).</para>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	<title>Summary of Changes to the AMN Profile</title>
	<para>The table below summarises the main changes between the AMN Profile as published in ADaTP-34(F) to the standards cited in the tables of this document.</para>
      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable1">
        <title>Summary of Changes to the AMN Profile</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="60*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Table/Subject</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Key updates</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>

		    <row>
              <entry>General (applies to all tables)</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Fuller citation of standards to enable users to accurately identify and locate the standards.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Addition of standards that are already active on the AMN but to-date had not been recorded in the profile.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Addition of footnotes where FMN capability development is proceeding more rapidly than the AMN (noting that the AMN will soon be technically a single Operational Instance of the FMN).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Consistent application of the ADatP-34 stages of the life-cycle of a standard (Emerging, Mandatory etc).</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable2" />: Transmission IA Services Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Citing of source of configuration settings necessary to ensure interoperability when different cryptographic device</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable3" />: Edge Transport Services and Communications Equipment Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Update/addition of IPv6 routing standards. This reflects the requirement that all new equipment, services and applications must support a dual IPv4/IPv6 stack implementation to future-proof the AMN for the long term and to enable AMN to remain in line with the development of the FMN.</para>
				</listitem></itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable4" />: Packet-based Communications Access Services Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Update/addition of IPv6 addressing standards (see reason above).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Removal of Network Address Translation (NAT) as an option for joining nations.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable5" />: Communications Access IA Services Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Removal/Retirement of Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol version 1.0.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable6" />: Infrastructure Services Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Update to advice on distributed time services synchronization.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Update to advice on storing and accessing information about the time of events and transactions, with particular attention to databases.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Complete exclusion of Active Directory Federation Services (ADFS) as an option.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Addition of a guidance note on Operating Systems, including rational for choice of Win 7 Enterprise for client PCs.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>
			
		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable7" />: Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) platform services and data standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Indication of intent to move to HyperText Markup Language, Version 5 (HTML 5) and Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) Level 3.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable8" />: Unified Communication and Collaboration Services and Data Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Introduction of Secure Communications Interoperability Protocol. SCIP as an option for Operation Resolute Support.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Clarification that Informal messaging (SMTP e-mail) must be labelled to a particular convention in the message header field “Keywords”.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Creation of a Basic and Enhanced XMPP profile for text-based collaboration services</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable9" />: Information Management Services and Data Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Addition of guidance on File Naming</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable10" />: Enterprise Support Geospatial Services and Data Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Citing of standards for WGS84, DTED and OpenGIS Coordinate Transformation Service</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable11" />: General Data Format Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Guidance notes for AMN on use of alpha-3 (three-letter codes) contained in STANAG 1059</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable12" />: Battlespace Management Interoperability Protocols and Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Citing of standards for Interoperability of Friendly Force Tracking Systems (FFTS)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Reiteration of required MIP standards, and noting long term direction taken by FMN (see also footnotes)</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable13" />: Biometric Data and System Interoperability Protocols and Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Nil</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable14" />: JISR Interoperability Protocols and Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Nil</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable15" />: User Application Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Indication of intent to move to HyperText Markup Language, Version 5 (HTML 5) and Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) Level 3.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Update to Office Open XML File Formats and introduction of Open Document Formants.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Addition of archiving file formats (triggered through research for AMN JMEI volume 3 (Exiting the AMN).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Full section on Representation of Dates and Times</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Advice on Internationalization of Web Design and Applications</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable16" />: Human-to-human interoperability Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Citation of NATO Glossary of terms and definitions</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommendation for Standardised Language Profile (SLP) to be added to Operational Profile.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>

		    <row>
              <entry><xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable17" />: Service Management and Control Interoperability Standards</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Nil</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>
			
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
	</sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Relationship to NATO C3 Classification Taxonomy</title>
    
    <para>The AMN has been designed and is managed as far as possible using a
    service approach. The AMN Services are based on the NATO C3 Classification
    Taxonomy AC/322-N(2012)0092-AS1.</para> <para>The C3 Classification Taxonomy
    is used to identify particular services and associated Service
    Interoperability Point where two entities will interface and the standards
    in use by the relevant systems.</para> <para>Where required, the
    implementation of the standard is described in an annex associated with the
    Service.</para> <para>Where a composite suite of services (with their
    standards) are required to implement a suite of services that are typically
    grouped together to form a familiar “composite service” or a “user facing
    Service”, then the implementation annex is housed at the assessed “centre of
    gravity” of the composite service. This is done simply to keep the
    instructions together. This applies for those services which network
    engineers, system administrators, users or operators recognise as distinct
    (e.g. “Text based Chat”, “VoSIP” or “VTC”), and for which technical
    skills/specialisms/instructions already exist. For Example the VTC
    implementation annex is placed under “Core Enterprise Services/ Enterprise
    Support Services” despite the fact that the VTC “composite service” is also
    implemented by services in Communications Access Services, Service
    Management and Control etc..</para> <para>The C3 Classification Taxonomy is
    used to structure this document, commencing with Communications and working
    up the Taxonomy.</para></sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Relationship to the Future (Federated) Mission Network</title>
    
    <para>Subsequent NATO led missions will benefit from the modular nature of
    the AMN Profile, which will allow for maximum reuse of established
    capabilities, while accommodating unique requirements and technology
    improvements.</para>
    <para>Based on the AMN Profile, a Federated Mission
    Network Profile of NATO Interoperability Standards has been proposed and is
    anticipated to be published in the next version of ADaTP-34. This will
    support the implementation of the Future Mission Network (FMN) Concept
    [MCM-0125-2012].</para>
    <para>Given the strong linkage between AMN and FMN,
    the opportunity to maintain a single Federated Mission Network Profile is
    possible in future versions of this document, but will firstly require the
    establishment of the FMN Governance and FMN Framework Management Structures.
    To this end it is anticipated that any future development of capabilities
    for the AMN in the future should be done in the direction indicated by the
    Federated Mission Network Profile.</para>
    <para>This AMN Profile contains
    footnotes from the FMN Profile that if applied would implement the AMN in
    the direction of the FMN. These are indicated as a footnote to the
    referenced standard. Please note however: <emphasis role="bold">The FMN notes are only included for information. They are not
    yet approved by the AWG for use on the AMN.</emphasis></para></sect2>
 </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Communication Services</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Communications Services interconnect systems and mechanisms for the opaque transfer of selected data between or among access points, in accordance with agreed quality parameters and without change in the form or content of the data as sent and received.</emphasis></para>
    <para>Communications Services can be further defined as:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Transmission Services</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Transport Services</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Communications Access Services</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   <sect2>
	<title>Transmission Services</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Transmission Services cover the physical layer (also referred to as media layer or air-interface in wireless/satellite (SATCOM) communications) supporting Transport Services, as well as Communications Access Services. Support for the latter is relevant to personal communications systems, in which the User Appliances directly connect to the transmission element without any transport elements in between.</emphasis></para>
   <sect3>
   <title>Standards</title>
   <para>Although the implementation scope of AMN technically does not cover Transmission Services, there is one area that provides the foundation for the provision of federated services on the AMN. The Standards listed in table <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable2" /> need to be adhered to.</para>
      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable2">
        <title>Transmission IA Services Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />

          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>

              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Information Assurance during Transmission</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Mandatory:  ACP 176 NATO SUPP 1 (NC)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>ACP 176 NATO SUPP 1 (NC) provides configuration settings necessary to ensure interoperability when different cryptographic devices (e.g. KIV-7/KG84/BID1650) are employed together.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
   </sect3>
   <sect3>
   <title>Implementation</title>
   <para>Although the implementation scope of AMN technically does not cover Transmission Services the TCN joining the AMN require guidance on options on how to provide communications within Theatre.</para>
<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing these services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex A.1: Provision of Terrestrial Communications.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex A.2: Use of Deployable CIS (including SATCOM).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
   </sect3>
   </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Transport Services</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Transport Services provide resource-facing services, providing metro and wide-area connectivity to the Communications Access Services that operate at the edges of the network. In that role, Transport Services interact with the Transmission Services using them as the physical layer fabric supporting the transfer of data over a variety of transmission bearers as and where needed.</emphasis></para>
    <para>Transport Services are further defined in the C3 Taxonomy, however the area that is most relevant to the AMN are:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Edge Transport Services</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Edge Transport Services provide the delivery or exchange of traffic flows over different Transmission Services. The traffic flows are formatted and delivered by the Communications Access Services at the edges of the network. This "edge" in Edge Transport is the Wide Area Network (WAN) edge (i.e. the provider edge). In Protected Core Networking (PCN) terms, the edge can be considered as the entry point into the Protected Core.</emphasis></para>
   <sect3>
   <title>Standards</title>
   <para>The AMN is a converged IP network applying open standards and industry best practices.  The AMN architecture uses interconnection based on IPv4 between the Mission Networks (also referred to as autonomous systems).</para><para> 
The AMN was originally conceived with IPv6 as the target for interconnecting autonomous systems (although no TCN has yet indicated that they wish to implement this on the AMN). As IPv6 is also the direction that the FMN is progressing, and as the AMN will become one the first FMN instances, IPv6 standards are now listed in the AMN Profile.</para><para>
It is now advised that all new equipment, services and applications must support a dual IPv4/IPv6 stack implementation to future-proof the AMN for the long term and to enable AMN to remain in line with the development of the FMN.</para><para>
The interconnection between Mission Networks is based on STANAG 5067 enhanced with a non-tactical connector and optional 1Gb/s Ethernet.  STANAG 5067 provides additional implementation, security and management guidance.  Due to the classification level of the AMN, dedicated transmission security (crypto) equipment is used.</para><para>
The standards for Transport and corresponding Communications Equipment are given in table <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable3" />.</para>
      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable3">
        <title>Edge Transport Services and Communications Equipment Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Edge Transport Services between autonomous systems
(IP over point-to-point Ethernet links on optical fibre)<footnote><para>FMN: A key improvement that the FMN will bring is the ability to create connectivity over a Time-division multiplexing (TDM) Wide Area Network (WAN). For this a suite of standards additional to those for a fibre based network has been drawn from TACOMs and demonstrated. The FMN Profile [NCIA TR-2013/SPW008910/01] will include implementation notes and instructions for these.</para></footnote>
</entry>
              <entry><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  ISO/IEC 11801: 2002-09, Information technology –Generic cabling for customer premises, Clause 9.  Single-mode optical fibre OS1 wavelength 1310nm.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  ITU-T G.652 (11/2009), Characteristics of a single-mode optical fibre and cable. (9/125μm)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IEC 61754-20: 2012(E), Fibre optic interconnecting devices and passive components - Fibre optic connector interfaces - Part 20: Type LC connector family.  LC-duplex single-mode connector.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IEEE Std 802.3-2013, Standard for Ethernet- Section 5 - Clause 58 - 1000BASE-LX10, Nominal transmit wavelength 1310nm.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>IPv4 over Ethernet:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IETF STD 37: 1982 / IETF RFC 826: 1982, An Ethernet Address Resolution Protocol</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>IPv6 over Ethernet (Optional):</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory (if option taken):IETF RFC 4861: 2007, Neighbor Discovery for IP version 6 (IPv6)<footnote><para>FMN: will implement IETF RFC 4861.</para></footnote>
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></entry>
  <entry><para>Use 1Gb/s Ethernet over Single-mode optical fibre (SMF).</para></entry>
            </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>2: Inter-Autonomous System (AS) routing</entry>
              <entry><para>IPv4 over Ethernet:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IETF RFC 1997:1996, BGP Communities Attribute.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Emerging: IETF RFC 3392: 2002, Capabilities Advertisement with BGP-4<footnote><para>FMN: Will implement IETF RFC 3392.</para></footnote>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  Border Gateway Protocol V4 (IETF RFC 1771, March 1995)<footnote><para>FMN: Will implement IETF RFC 4271. FMN notes: IETF RFC 4271 obsoletes IETF RFC 1771. BGP sessions must be authenticated, through a TCP message authentication code (MAC) using a one-way hash function (MD5), as described in IETF RFC 4271.</para></footnote>.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Emerging: IETF RFC 4760: 2007, Multiprotocol Extensions  for  BGP-4<footnote><para>FMN: Will implement IETF RFC 4760.</para></footnote>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>32-bit autonomous system numbers:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 6793: 2012, BGP Support for Four-Octet Autonomous System (AS) Number Space.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 4360: 2006, BGP Extended Communities Attribute.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 5668: 2009, 4-Octet AS Specific BGP Extended Community.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>IPv6 over Ethernet (Optional):</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory (if option taken): IETF RFC 2545: 1999, Use of BGP-4 Multiprotocol Extensions for IPv6 Inter-Domain Routing<footnote><para>FMN: Will implement IETF RFC 2545.</para></footnote>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
            <entry><para>BGP deployment guidance in:  IETF RFC 1772: 1995, Application of the Border Gateway Protocol in the Internet.</para>
<para>Detailed Interface Control Document for “Connection Between CISAF network and TCN networks” [Thales ICD NIP Dec 2012]</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Inter-Autonomous System (AS) multicast routing</entry>
              <entry>IPv4 over Ethernet<footnote><para>FMN: Suggests as Optional: IETF RFC 4604: 2006, Using Internet Group Management Protocol Version 3 (IGMPv3) and Multicast Listener Discovery Protocol Version 2 (MLDv2) for Source-Specific Multicast.</para></footnote>:<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 3618: 2003, Multicast Source Discovery Protocol (MSDP).
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 3376: 2002, Internet Group Management Protocol, Version 3 (IGMPv3).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 4601, Protocol Independent Multicast version 2 (PIMv2) Sparse Mode (SM).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 4760: 2007 “Multiprotocol Extensions for BGP (MBGP)”.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>IPv6 over Ethernet:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Note: No standard solution for IPv6 multicast routing has yet been widely accepted.  More research and experimentation is required in this area.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>4: Unicast routing</entry>
              <entry><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IETF RFC 4632: 2006, Classless Inter-domain Routing (CIDR):  The Internet Address Assignment and Aggregation Plan.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>5: Multicast routing</entry>
              <entry><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IETF RFC 1112: 1989, Host Extensions for IP Multicasting.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IETF RFC 2908: 2000, The Internet Multicast Address Allocation Architecture</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 3171: 2001, IANA Guidelines for IPv4 Multicast Address Assignments.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 2365: 1998, Administratively Scoped IP Multicast.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
	  	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
   </sect3>
   <sect3>
   <title>Implementation</title>
   <para>The Network Interconnection Point (NIP) provides a network interconnection at the IP layer for the ISAF SECRET environment making up the AMN. It serves 3 major purposes:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Intra autonomous system (AS) routing (routing of traffic between nations or between nations and NATO, where each nation is a BGP Autonomous System).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>QoS policy enforcement (to provide end-to-end QoS for the required services).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>IPSLA compliance verification (to verify end-to-end performance compliance).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>With respect to creating the connection at the NIP and the corresponding network engineering required the following Annexes are provided:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex B.1: Connecting to the Network Interconnection Points (NIP).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
   </sect3>
   </sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Communications Access Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Transport Communications Access Services provide end-to-end connectivity of communications or computing devices. Communications Access Services can be interfaced directly to Transmission Services (e.g. in the case of personal communications systems) or to Transport Services, which in turn interact with Transmission Services for the actual physical transport. Communications Access Services correspond to customer-facing communications services. As such, they can also be referred to as Subscriber Services, or Customer-Edge (CE) Services.</emphasis></para>

<para>With respect to the current implementation scope of AMN, the following Communications Access services apply:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Packet-Based Communications Access Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Communications Access Information Assurance (IA) Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Communications Access Service Management Control (SMC) Services. </para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Multimedia Services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<sect3>
<title>Standards</title>
<para>To provide federated services, the standards listed in table <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable4" /> and table <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable5" /> should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable4">
        <title>Packet-based Communications Access Services Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Host-to-host transport services</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF STD 6: 1980 /IETF RFC 768: 1980, User Datagram Protocol.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF STD 7: 1981 / RFC 793: 1981, Transmission Control Protocol.<footnote><para>FMN: Note that IETF RFC 793 is updated by IETF RFC 3168: 2001, The addition of Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) to IP.  However, despite the fact that IETF RFC 793 is updated by IETF RFC 3168, ECN cannot be used in parallel to the deployment of IP encryption and therefore IETF RFC 793 will remain in these circumstances.</para></footnote></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: host-to-host datagram services</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Internet Protocol:
				<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 791: 1981, Internet Protocol.</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 792: 1981, Internet Control Message Protocol.</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 919: 1994, Broadcasting Internet Datagrams.</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 922: 1984, Broadcasting Internet Datagrams in the Presence of Subnets.</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 950: 1985, Internet Standard Subnetting Procedure.</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 1112: 1989, Host Extensions for IP Multicasting.</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 1812: 1995, Requirements for IP Version 4 Routers.</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>Advised: IETF RFC 2644: 1999, Changing the Default for Directed Broadcasts in Routers.<footnote><para>FMN: will also implement IETF RFC 2644. It is advisory that AMN also follows this</para></footnote></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>IPv6 over Ethernet (Optional):</para>
				<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Recommended: IETF RFC 2460: 1998, Internet Protocol, Version 6 (IPv6) Specification.</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>Recommended: IETF RFC 3484: 2003, Default Address Selection for Internet Protocol version 6 (IPv6).</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>Recommended: IETF RFC 3810: 2004, Multicast Listener Discovery Version 2 (MLDv2) for IPv6.</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>Recommended: IETF RFC 4291: 2006, IP Version 6 Addressing Architecture.</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>Recommended: IETF RFC 4443: 2006, Internet Control Message Protocol (ICMPv6) for the Internet Protocol Version 6 (IPv6) Specification.</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>Recommended: IETF RFC 4861: 2007, Neighbor Discovery for IP version 6 (IPv6).</para></listitem> 
<listitem><para>Recommended: IETF RFC 5095: 2007, Deprecation of Type 0 Routing Headers in IPv6.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>IP networking. Accommodate both IPv4 and IPv6 addressing<footnote><para>Note that although IPv6 has always been part of the AMN Profile it has never been taken up. There has always been the intent to provide a tunnel of v6 over v4 or via a dual stack, should a TCN require it.</para></footnote>
		<footnote><para>Due to the fact that one of the early founding TCN networks of the AMN had already implemented NAT on the already existing network that became the extension, historically NAT has had to be presented as an option for the AMN. NAT however is not in line with the openness required on the AMN and has always been highly discouraged within the TCN network. It has since been removed as an option for all subsequent joining nations.</para></footnote></para>
		<para>Max Transmission Unit (MTU) reduced to 1300 bytes, Max Segment Size (MSS) set to 1260 bytes in order to accommodate IP crypto tunneling within autonomous systems</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Differentiated host-to-host datagram services<para>
(IP Quality of Service)</para>
</entry>
              <entry>
                <para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 2474: 1998, Definition of the Differentiated Services Field (DS Field) in the IPv4 and IPv6 Headers<footnote><para>FMN: Note that IETF RFC 2474 is updated by IETF RFC 3168: 2001, The addition of Explicit Congestion Notification (ECN) to IP.  However, despite the fact that IETF RFC 2474 is updated by IETF RFC 3168, ECN <emphasis role="underline">cannot</emphasis> be used in parallel to the deployment of IP encryption and therefore IETF RFC 2474 will remain in these circumstances.</para></footnote>.</para>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>updated by IETF RFC 3260: 2002, New Terminology and Clarifications for DiffServ.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 4594: 2006, Configuration Guidelines for DiffServ Service Classes.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: ITU-T Y.1540 (03/2011), Internet protocol data communication service – IP packet transfer and availability performance parameters.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: ITU-T Y.1541 (12/2011), Network performance objectives for IP-based services.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: ITU-T Y.1542 (06/2010), Framework for achieving end-to-end IP performance objectives.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: ITU-T M.2301 (07/2002), Performance objectives and procedures for provisioning and maintenance of IP-based networks.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: ITU-T J.241 (04/2005), Quality of service ranking and measurement methods for digital video services delivered over broadband IP networks.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>The AMN QoS standard was constructed based on the NATO QoS Enabled Network Infrastructure (QENI).</para>
<para>The QoS model adopted is however not quite fully compliant with IP QoS Maturity level QoS-1 as defined in the NII IP QoS Standard [NC3A TN-1417]<footnote><para>FMN: will implement QoS: IP QoS for the NII, [NC3A TN-1417]</para></footnote>  (the deviation has largely to do with the DSCP markings). See Annex C.1 for details.</para>
<para>AMN IP QoS aggregates all IP traffic into 4x classes - (Real Time (RT); Near Real Time (NRT); Network (routing, signalling, management); Best Effort).</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable5">
        <title>Communications Access IA Services Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Provide communications security over the network above the Transport Layer</entry>
              <entry><para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory:  IETF RFC 5246: 2008, Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>


</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Implementation of Packet-Based Access Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Transport Packet-based Access Services involve delivery or exchange of data (or digitised voice, video) encapsulated in IP packets. In the case of the AMN, IPv4 and IPv6 (if implemented) routed access services can be considered under this Service Category.</emphasis></para>

<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex C.1: BGP and IP Multicast Routing</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex C.2: Sample Router Configuration Template</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex C.3: Numbering Registration</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex C.4: Quality of Service</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Implementation of Communications Access Information Assurance (IA) Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Communications Access Information Assurance (IA) Services provide a foundation to implement and enforce IA policies at the communications access level.</emphasis></para>

<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex D.1: Firewalls</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex D.2: Intrusion Detection Systems</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex D.3: Intrusion Prevention Systems</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Implementation of Communications Access Service Management Control (SMC) Services.</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Communications Access Service Management and Control (SMC) Services provide the necessary means to implement and enforce SMC policies at the communications access level. Encompasses VTC Management Services, Demand Assigned Multiple Access (DAMA) Control Services and Call Management Services.</emphasis></para>

<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex E.1: Network Management</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex E.2: Incident Management</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex E.3: Performance Management</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex E.4: Internet Protocol Service Level Agreement Monitoring</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex E.5: Federated Authentication Authorization and Accounting.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Core Enterprise Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Core Enterprise Services (CES) provide generic, domain independent, technical functionality that enables or facilitates the operation and use of Information Technology (IT) resources.</emphasis></para>

<para>CES will be broken up further into:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Infrastructure Services (incl. Information Assurance (IA) services)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) Platform Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Enterprise Support Services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<sect2>
<title>Infrastructure Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Infrastructure Services provide software resources required to host services in a distributed and federated environment. They include computing, storage and high-level networking capabilities that can be used as the foundation for data centre or cloud computing implementations.</emphasis></para>


<sect3>
<title>Standards</title>

<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table  <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable6" /> should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable6">
        <title>Infrastructure Services Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: <emphasis role="underline">Distributed Time Services</emphasis>: Time synchronization</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 5905: June 2010, Network Time Protocol version 4 (NTPv4).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Fading: IETF RFC 1305: March 1992, NTPv3.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>
<para>To aid rapid post event reconstruction, ALL networked equipment will be set to process time as Coordinated Universal Time (UTC). i.e. ZULU Time Zone should apply to the whole Mission Network [AMN TPT CES Sept 2011].
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>All new capabilities shall use NTPv4. Some legacy systems may still need to use NTPv3.</para>
<para>TCN connecting to the AMN Core must use the time service of the AMN Core<footnote><para>For an FMN implementation, if TCN also provide an equivalent to the AMN Core (known in FMN terms as “Option A”), then the time service could also be provided over a network path to a stratum-1 time server on the TCN (Option A) network.</para></footnote>.</para>
<para>
A stratum-1 time server is directly linked (not over a network path) to a reliable source of UTC time (Universal Time Coordinate) such as GPS, WWV, or CDMA transmissions through a modem connection, satellite, or radio.</para>
<para>Stratum-1 devices must implement IPv4 and IPv6 so that they can be used as timeservers for IPv4 and IPv6 Mission Network Elements</para>
<para>The W32Time service on all Windows Domain Controllers is to synchronize time through the Domain hierarchy (NT5DS type).</para>
<para>Databases are to implement TIMESTAMP as specified in point 4 below</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: <emphasis role="underline">Domain Name Services</emphasis>: Naming and Addressing</entry>
              <entry>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF STD 13: 1987 /, IETF RFC 1034: 1987, Domain Names – Concepts and Facilities.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 1035: 1987, Domain Names – Implementation and specification.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Identification and addressing of objects on the network.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 1738: 1994, Uniform Resource Locators (URL).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 3986: 2005, Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI), Generic Syntax., January  2005 (updates IETF RFC 1738)</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Namespaces within XML documents shall use unique URLs or URIs for the namespace designation.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4: Infrastructure Storage Services: storing and accessing information about the time of events and transactions</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: ISO/IEC 9075(Parts 1 to 14):2011, Information technology - Database languages – SQL</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>

                <para>Databases shall stores date and time values everything in TIMESTAMP WITH TIME ZONE or TIMESTAMPTZ</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>As the AMN user community spans several time zones, applications will increasingly need to conduct transactions across different time zones. Timestamps are essential for auditing purposes. It is important that the integrity of timestamps is maintained across all Mission Network Elements. From Oracle 9i, PostgreSQL 7.3 and MS SQL Server 2008 onwards, the time zone can be stored with the time directly by using the TIMESTAMP WITH TIME ZONE (Oracle, PostgreSQL) or datetimeoffset (MS-SQL) data types.</para>
		<para>On the AMN, human interfaces may convert the time for display to the user as (e.g.) D30 (i.e. Local) as required.  See also <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable15" /> for details on representing time within applications</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5: Infrastructure IA Services:  Facilitate the access and authorization between FMN users and services.
			  <para>Directory access and management service</para>
			  </entry>
              <entry><itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 4510: 2006, version 3 of the Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAPv3), (LDAP) Technical Specification Road Map (LDAPv3).</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 4511-4519:2006, RFC 4510 and associated LDAP Technical Specification. (RFC 4511-4519)</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 2849: 2000, The LDAP Interchange Format 9 (LDIF)., RFC 2849</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>There are three options available to a Troop Contributing Nation (TCN) when joining their national network extension to the AMN:</para>
		<para>1. Join the ISAF SECRET AD forest on AMN Core</para>
		<para>2. Join the AD forest of an existing AMN TCN</para>
		<para>3. Create own AD forest for the new AMN TCN</para>
		<para>(Option 1 and 2 should be considered by the prospective Joining TCN before Option 3).</para>
		<para>Whilst LDAP is a vendor independent standard, in practice Microsoft Active Directory (AD) is a common product providing directory services on national and NATO owned Mission Network elements. It should be noted that AD provides additional services aside from LDAP like functionality.</para>
		<para>Note: Active Directory Federation Services (ADFS) will not be used on the AMN. The AMN is one logical network based on mutual trust. In such a trusted environment there is no requirement or use case for single sign on for webservices. In those cases where an outside or untrusted subdomain of a Nationally implemented Network desires access to webservices on the AMN, then those services will be granted using "local accounts created on the parent (AMN) domain.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6: <emphasis role="underline">Infrastructure IA Services</emphasis>: Digital Certificate Services</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: ITU-T X.509 (11/2008), Information technology - Open systems interconnection - The Directory: Public-key and attribute certificate frameworks
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>the version of the encoded public-key certificate shall be v3.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>the version of the encoded certificate revocation list (CRL) shall be v2.</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: NATO Public Key Infrastructure (NPKI) Certificate Policy (CertP) Rev2, AC/322D(2004)0024 REV2</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>7: <emphasis role="underline">Infrastructure IA Services</emphasis>: Authentication Services</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 1510:1993, The Kerberos Network Authentication Service (V5).</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>8: Infrastructure Processing (Operating System) Services</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Operating Systems used on the AMN must be accredited by the respective Security Accreditation Authority.</para>
				<para>As a minimum the Operating Systems should support the specifications for the above (Infrastructure IA Services).</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Clients on the AMN Core and Option 1 TCN National Network Extensions are strongly advised to use Windows 7 Enterprise due to the mid-2014 End of Support provision by Microsoft for Windows XP.</para>
		<para>Win 7 Enterprise was selected due to the inclusion of AppLocker (remote enforcement of application control policies) and integration with Sharepoint 2010 and MS Office Professional Plus 2010.</para>
		<para>Windows 2008 R2 Standard Full Edition 64 bit is strongly advised for all Domain Controllers. Note Service Pack SP1 should be installed</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>


</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex F.1: Active Directory and Joining Options</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex F.2: Recommended Build of Domain Controllers</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex F.3: Time Synchronisation</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex F.4: DNS Synchronisation</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex F.5: PKI</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex F.6: Preventive Cyber Defence</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>SOA Platform Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">SOA Platform Services provide a foundation to implement web-based services in a loosely coupled environment, where flexible and agile service orchestration is a requirement. They offer generic building blocks for SOA implementation (e.g. discovery, message busses, orchestration, information abstraction and access, etc.) and can be used as a capability integration platform in a heterogeneous service-provisioning ecosystem.</emphasis></para>

<sect3>
<title>Standards</title>
<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable7" /> should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable7">
        <title>Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) platform services and data standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>

		  <row>
              <entry>1: <emphasis role="underline">Web Platform Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 2616: 1999, Hypertext Transfer Protocol HTTP/ 1.1.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 2817: 2000, Upgrading to TLS within HTTP/ 1.1.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 3986: 2005, Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax.</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
              <entry><para>HTTP shall be used as the transport protocol for information without 'need-to-know' caveats between all service providers and consumers (unsecured HTTP traffic).</para>
			  <para>HTTPS shall be used as the transport protocol between all service providers and consumers to ensure Confidentiality requirements (secured HTTP traffic).</para>
			  <para>Unsecured and secured HTTP traffic shall share the same port.</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>2: Publishing information including text, multimedia, hyperlink features, scripting languages and style sheets on the network</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: HyperText Markup Language (HTML) 4.01 (strict)
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>ISO/IEC 15445:2000, Information technology -- Document description and processing languages -- HyperText Markup Language (HTML).</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>IETF RFC2854:2000, The 'text/html' Media Type.</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </para>
			  </listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Emerging (2014): HyperText Markup Language, Version 5 (HTML 5), W3C Candidate Recommendation, Aug 2013</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>3: Providing a common style sheet language for describing presentation semantics (that is, the look and formatting) of documents written in mark-up languages like HTML.</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), Level 2 revision 1 (CSS 2.1), W3C Recommendation, September 2009.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Emerging (2014): Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) Level 3:
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), Level 2 revision 1 (including errata) (CSS 2.1), W3C Recommendation, June 2011.
</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>CSS Style Attributes, W3C Candidate Recommendation, 12 October 2010</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Media Queries, W3C Recommendation, 19 June 2012.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>CSS Namespaces Module, W3C Recommendation, 29 September 2011.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Selectors Level 3, W3C Recommendation, 29 September 2011.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>CSS Color Module Level 3, W3C Recommendation, 07 June 2011.</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>4: General formatting of information for sharing or exchange.</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0 (Fifth Edition), W3C Recommendation, 26 November 2008.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: XML Schema Part 1: Structures Second Edition, W3C Recommendation, 28 October 2004.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes Second Edition, W3C Recommendation, 28 October 2004.</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
              <entry>XML shall be used for data exchange to satisfy those IERs on the AMN that are not addressed by a specific information exchange standard. XML Schemas and namespaces are required for all XML documents.</entry>
            </row>
			            
		  <row>
              <entry>5: Providing web content or web feeds for syndication to web sites as well as directly to user agents.</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: (Really Simple Syndication) RSS 2.0 Specification Version 2.0.11, 30 March 2009.<footnote><para>FMN: The FMN recommends maintaining RSS 2.0 for backwards compatibility</para></footnote></para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Emerging: IETF RFC 4287: 2005, The Atom Syndication Format. (Atom 1.0).<footnote><para>FMN: For the FMN the  Atom 1.0 syndication format is mandatory</para></footnote></para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Emerging: IETF RFC 5023: 2007, The Atom Publishing Protocol.<footnote><para>FMN: For the FMN the Atom Publishing protocol is mandatory</para></footnote></para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
 			  </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>6: Encoding of location as part of  web feeds</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: GeoRSS Simple encoding: Geographically Encoded Objects for RSS feeds:<para>
GeoRSS Simple encoding for &lt;georss:point>, &lt;georss:line>, &lt;georss:polygon>, &lt;georss:box> .</para></para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Recommended: GeoRSS GML Profile 1.0 a GML subset for &lt;gml:Point>, &lt;gml:LineString>, &lt;gml:Polygon>, &lt;gml:Envelope> of</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Recommended: Where GeoRSS Simple is not appropriate the OGC GeoRSS 03-105r1: 2004-02-07, OpenGIS Geography Markup Language (GML) Implementation Specification version 3.1.1.</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>

			  </entry>
              <entry><para>GML allows you to specify a coordinate reference system (CRS) other than WGS84 decimal degrees (think lat/long). If there is a need to express geography in a CRS other than WGS84, it is recommended to specify the geographic object multiple times, one in WGS84 and the others in your other desired CRSes</para>
			  <para>Schema location for GeoRSS GML Profile 1.0: http://geo rss.org /xml/1.0/gmlgeorss.xsd</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>7: Message Security for web services</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: WS-Security: SOAP Message Security 1.1.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: XML Encryption Syntax and Processing, W3C Recommendation, 10 December2002.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: XML Signature Syntax and Processing (Second Edition), W3C Recommendation, 10 June 2008.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: OASIS WS-I Basic Security Profile Version 1.1, 24 January 2010.</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
              <entry><para>Specifies how integrity and confidentiality can be enforced on messages and allows the communication of various security token formats, such as SAML, Kerberos, and X.509v3. Its main focus is the use of XML Signature and XML Encryption to provide end-to-end security.</para>
			  <para>Specifies a process for encrypting data and representing the result in XML. Referenced by WS-Security specification.</para>
			  <para>Specifies XML digital signature processing rules and syntax. Referenced by WS-Security specification</para></entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>8: Security token format</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: OASIS Standard, Security Assertion Markup Language (SAML) 2.0), March 2005.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: OASIS Standard,  Web Services Security: SAML Token Profile 1.1 incorporating approved errata 1, Nov 2006.</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
              <entry><para>Provides XML-based syntax to describe uses security tokens containing assertions to pass information about a principal (usually an end-user) between an identity provider and a web service.</para>
			  <para>Describes how to use SAML security tokens with WS-Security specification.</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>9: Security token issuing</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: OASIS Standard, WS-Trust 1.4, incorporating Approved Errata 01, 25 April 2012.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: Web Services Federation Language (WS-Federation) Version 1.1, December 2006.<footnote><para>This specification is subject to the following copyright: (c) 2001-2006 BEA Systems, Inc., BMC Software, CA, Inc., International Business Machines Corporation, Layer 7 Technologies, Microsoft Corporation, Inc., Novell, Inc. and VeriSign, Inc. All rights reserve.</para></footnote></para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: Web Services Policy 1.5 – Framework, W3C Recommendation, 04 September 2007.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: WS-Security Policy 1.3, OASIS Standard incorporating Approved Errata 01, 25 April 2012.WS-Trust 1.4</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
              <entry><para>Uses WS-Security base mechanisms and defines additional primitives and extensions for security token exchange to enable the issuance and dissemination of credentials within different trust domains.</para><para>Extends WS-Trust to allow federation of different security realms.</para><para>Used to describe what aspects of the federation framework are required/supported by federation participants and that this information is used to determine the appropriate communication options.
</para></entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>10: Transforming XML documents into other XML documents</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: XSL Transformations (XSLT) Version 2.0, W3C Recommendation, 23 January 2007.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Note that XSLT 2.0 is a revised version of the XSLT 1.0 Recommendation published on 16 November 1999</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
              <entry><para>Developer best practice for the translation of XML based documents into other formats or schemas.</para></entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>11: Configuration management of structured data standards, service descriptions and other structured metadata.</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Mandatory: ebXML v3.0: Electronic business XML Version 3.0,</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: Registry Information Model (ebRIM), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005,</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: Registry Services and Protocols (ebRS)</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: OASIS Standard, Universal Description, Discovery, and Integration Specification (UDDI v2.0).</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Emerging: OASIS Standard, Universal Description, Discovery, and Integration Specification (UDDI v3.0).<footnote><para>FMN: Note that FMN will implement UDDI v3.0</para></footnote></para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
	      </entry>
              <entry><para>Used as foundation for setup, maintenance and interaction with a (AMN) Metadata Registry and Repository for sharing and configuration management of XML metadata. Also enables federation among metadata registries/ repositories.</para></entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>12: Exchanging structured information in a decentralized, distributed environment via web services</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: W3C SOAP 1.1, Simple Object Access Protocol v1.1 (SOAP) 1.1, W3C Note, 8 May 2000</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: WSDL v1.1: Web Services Description Language (WSDL) 1.1, W3C Note, 15 March 2001.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Conditional: Representational State Transfer (REST) in accordance with:
			  <itemizedlist><listitem><para>University of California, Roy Thomas Fielding, Architectural Styles and the Design of Network-based Software Architectures: 2000, Irvine, CA.</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist></para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Emerging (2014): SOAP Version 1.2 Part 1: Messaging Framework (Second Edition), W3C Recommendation, 27 April 2007.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Emerging (2014): SOAP Version 1.2 Part 2: Adjuncts (Second Edition), W3C Recommendation, 27 April 2007.</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Emerging (2014): SOAP Version 1.2 Part 3: One-Way MEP, W3C Working Group Note, 2 July 2007</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
              <entry><para>The preferred method for implementing web-services are SOAP, however, there are many use cases (mash-ups etc.) where a REST based interface is easier to implement and sufficient to meet the IERs.</para></entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>13: Secure exchange of data objects and documents across multiple security domains</entry>
              <entry>The Draft X-Labels syntax definition is called the "NATO Profile for the XML “Confidentiality Label Syntax" and is based on version 1.0 of the RTG-031 proposed XML confidentiality label syntax, see "Sharing of information across communities of interest and across security domains with object level protection" below.</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>14: Topic based publish / subscribe web services communication</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: OASIS Standard, Web Services (WS)-Brokered Notification 1.3, approved October 1st 2006</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: OASIS Standard, WS-Base Notification 1.3, approved October 1st 2006</para></listitem>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: OASIS Standard, WS-Topics 1.3, approved October 1st 2006</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
              <entry><para>Enable topic based subscriptions for web service notifications, with extensible filter mechanism and support for message brokers.</para></entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>15: Providing transport-neutral mechanisms to address web services</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist>
			  <listitem><para>Mandatory: Web Services (WS) Addressing 1.0 – Core W3C Recommendation, 17 August 2005.</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
              <entry><para>Provides transport-neutral mechanisms to address Web services and messages which is crucial in providing end-to- message level security, reliable messaging or publish / subscribe based web services end.</para></entry>
            </row>
			
		  <row>
              <entry>16: Reliable messaging for web services</entry>
              <entry>
			  <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Mandatory: OASIS Standard, Web Services Reliable Messaging (WS-Reliable Messaging) Version 1.2, February 2009.</para></listitem>
			  </itemizedlist></entry>
              <entry><para>Describes a protocol that allows messages to be transferred reliably between nodes implementing this protocol in the presence of software component, system, or network failures.</para></entry>
            </row>
			    	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Implementation</title>

<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex G.1: Authoritative and Trusted Data Sources</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex G.2: Service Registration [TBC]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Enterprise Support Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Enterprise Support Services are a set of Community Of Interest (COI) independent services that must be available to all members within the AMN.  Enterprise Support Services facilitate other service and data providers on the federated networks by providing and managing underlying capabilities to facilitate collaboration and information management for end-users.</emphasis></para>

<para>For the purposes of this Volume, Enterprise Support Services will be broken up further into:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Unified Communication and Collaboration Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Information Management Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Geospatial Services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<sect3>
<title>Unified Communication and Collaboration Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Unified Communication and Collaboration Services provide users with a range of interoperable collaboration capabilities, based on standards that fulfill operational requirements. They will enable real-time situational updates to time-critical planning activities between coalition partners, communities of interest (e.g. the Intel community or the Logistics community), and other agencies. Levels of collaboration include awareness, shared information, coordination and joint product development.</emphasis></para>
	<para>Different use cases require different levels of protection of these communication and collaboration services. For voice or audio-based collaboration services, the AMN profile can provide interoperability standards for two different scenarios<footnote><para>FMN: Under the FMN profile, 3 scenarios are offered. The first being pure Voice over IP (VoIP) network services, i.e. conventional IP telephony. The choice of this over VoSIP being purely based on classification of the network.</para></footnote>:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>A.	Voice over Secure IP (VoSIP) network services</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>B.	Network agnostic Secure Voice Services (such as 3G, IP/4G, ISDN)</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>On AMN, VoSIP is mandatory.  If however network agnostic Secure Voice services are required in addition to VoSIP<footnote><para>The only scenario where this would apply would be in the case that crypto devices cannot be supplied, protected and managed on site and physical access to the AMN is hence not available at that location.</para></footnote>, then Secure Communications Interoperability Protocol (SCIP) specifications as defined for audio-based collaboration services (end-to-end protected voice) over any network should be used<footnote><para>If SCIP is used, then access to the AMN can only be possible if a gateway for SCIP multi-conferencing and interconnection to VoSIP networks is provided. AMN. Additionally to achieve this there would need to be agreement to re-use a Key Management system that is already deployed in ISAF (for example that used for the OMLTs).</para></footnote>. [Note this has been included due to the emerging requirements regarding Operation Resolute Support (i.e. from Jan 2015, post ISAF)]</para>
	<para>For text-based collaboration there is also a basic profile sufficient for operating this service with reduced protection requirements as well as an enhanced XMPP profile that includes additional security mechanisms.</para>

<sect4>
<title>Standards</title>

<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable8" /> should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable8">
        <title>Unified Communication and Collaboration Services and Data Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Video-based Collaboration Services (VTC)</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory (VTCoIP Signalling): ITU-T H.323 v7 (12/2009) Packet-based multimedia communications systems;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory (VTCoIP Audio encoding): ITU-T G.722.1c (2005) Corrigendum 1 (06/2008) Low-complexity coding at 24 and 32 kbit/s for hands-free operation in systems with low frame loss;</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory (VTCoIP Video encoding): ITU-T H.263 (01/2005) Video coding for low bit rate communication</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
			  <para>AMN VTC over IP is based on a QoS-Enabled Net- work Infrastructure (QENI) using Diffserve.</para>
			  <para>The AMN-Wide allowed interconnections are:</para>
			  <para>A) Peer to Peer,</para>
			  <para>B) Peer to MCU and</para>
			  <para>C) Peer to MCU to MCU to Peer</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: Audio-based Collaboration Services</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory (VoIP numbering): STANAG 4705 Ed. 1 Ratification Draft, International Network Numbering for Communications Systems in use in NATO.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory (VoIP): IETF RFC 3261: 2002, SIP: Session Initiation Protocol.<footnote><para>FMN: Also includes IETF RFC 3550:2003, RTP: A Transport Protocol for Real-Time Applications</para></footnote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory (VoIP Audio data encoding): ITU-T Recommendation G.729 Annex A (11/96), Coding of speech at 8 kbit/s using conjugate-structure algebraic-code-excited linear prediction (CS-ACELP).
				<footnote><para>The  use  of  G.729 may require a license fee and/ or royalty fee. DiffServ, PHB and DSCP defined by <emphasis role="italic">IETF RFC 2474: 1998, Definition of the Differentiated Services Field (DS Field) in the IPv4 and IPv6 Headers.</emphasis> Please also see <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable3" /> ID 3 (IP Quality of Service).</para></footnote>
				<footnote><para>FMN: FMN indicates as emerging: Emerging (2015): <emphasis role="italic">G.729 (06/12): Coding of speech at 8 kbit/s using conjugate-structure algebraic-code-excited linear prediction (CS-ACELP)</emphasis>.</para></footnote></para>
				</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
			  <para>VoSIP refers to non-protected voice service running on a classified IP network (as in the case of the AMN).</para>
			  <para>Voice Sampling Interval between Voice packets: 40ms</para>
			  <para>RTP protocol ports 16384 and/or 16385</para>
			  <para>See also detailed Interface Control Document for "Voice over Secure IP (VoSIP) Network Service" [THALES ICD 61935771-558 A Jul 2009].</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Audio-based Collaboration Services (end-to-end protected voice) (Secure Communications Interoperability Protocol. SCIP)</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Emerging: ITU-T V.150.1 (03/2004), Modem-over-IP networks: Procedures for the end-to-end connection of V-series DCEs, incorporating changes introduced by Corrigendum 1 and 2.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging: National Security Agency (NSA), SCIP-210. SCIP signalling plan. 2007.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging: NSA, SCIP-214, Interface requirements for SCIP devices to circuit switched networks.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging: NSA, SCIP-215, Interface requirements for SCIP devices to IP networks.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging: NSA, SCIP-216: Minimum Essential Requirements (MER) for V.150.1 recommendation.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging: NSA, SCIP-220: Requirements for SCIP.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging: NSA, SCIP-221: SCIP Minimum Implementation Profile (MIP).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging: NSA, SCIP-233: NATO interim cryptographic suite (NATO and coalition).</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
			  <para>Secure voice services over any network.</para>
			  <para>V.150.1 support must be end-to-end supported by unclassified voice network</para>
			  <para>SCIP-214 only applies to gateways</para>
			  <para>Note that SCIP-216 requires universal implementation.</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4: Informal messaging services (e-mail)</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 2821:2001, Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 1870:1995, SMTP Service Extension for Message Size Declaration.
</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 2822:2001, Simple Internet Messages.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging (2016): IETF RFC 5321: 2008, Simple Mail Transfer Protocol which obsoletes: IETF RFC 2821: 2001</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging (2017): IETF RFC 6477: 2012, Registration of Military Message Handling System (MMHS) Header Fields for Use in Internet Mail</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
			  <para>Conditional: messages must be labelled in the message header field “Keywords” (RFC 2822) according to the following convention:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>[MMM] [CLASSIFICATION], Releasable to [MISSION]</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			  <para>Where:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>CLASSIFICATION is the classification {SECRET, CONFIDENTIAL, RESTRICTED, UNCLASSIFIED}</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>MMM is the alpha-3 country code e.g. DEU, GBR, as defined in Table 11.ID2 with the exception that NATO will be identified by the four letter acronym “NATO”.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			  <para>Example:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Keywords:  ITA UNCLASSIFIED, Releasable to XFOR</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5: Content encapsulation within bodies of internet messages</entry>
              <entry>Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) specification:
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 2045:1996, Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) Part One: Format of Internet Message Bodies.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 2046: 1996, Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) Part Two: Media Types.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 2047: 1996, MIME (Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions) Part Three: Message Header Extensions for Non-ASCII Text.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 2049: 1996, Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) Part Five: Conformance Criteria and Examples.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 4288 : 2005, Media Type Specifications and Registration Procedures.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
			  10 MB max message size limit 
			  <para>Minimum Content-Transfer-Encoding:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>7bit</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>base64</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>binary BINARYMIME SMTP extension [IETF RFC 3030]</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			  <para>Minimum set of media and content-types:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>text/plain [IETF RFC1521]</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>text/enriched [IETF RFC1896]</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>text/html IETF [RFC1866]</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>multipart/mixed [IETF RFC 2046]</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>multipart/signed</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6: text-based collaboration services<footnote><para>FMN: It is proposed that the FMN will also adopt these Mandatory and Enhanced XMPP profiles</para></footnote></entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: Basic XMPP profile (see ID 6.1 below)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: Enhanced XMPP profile (see ID 6.2)</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
			  <para>Near-real time text-based group collaboration capability for time critical reporting and decision making in military operations.</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6.1: text-based collaboration services (basic XMPP profile)</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 6120: 2011, Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): Core</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF RFC 6121: 2011, Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP) extensions for: Instant Messaging and Presence.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: The following XMPP Extension Protocols (XEP) defined by the XMPP Standards Foundation shall also be supported:
				<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0004: Data Forms, August 2007.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0030: Service Discovery, February 2007</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0045: Multi-User Chat (MUC), July 2008</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0049: Private XML Storage, March 2004</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0050: Ad Hoc Commands, June 2005</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0054: vCard Profiles,  March 2003</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0065: SOCKS5 Byte streams, April 2011</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0078: Non-SASL Authentication, October 2008. (for support of older clients)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0091: Legacy Delayed Delivery, May 2009</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0092: Software Version, February 2007</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0096: SI File Transfer, April 2004.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0114: Jabber Component Protocol, March 2005</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0115: Entity Capabilities, February 2008.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0203: Delayed Delivery, September 2009</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0220: Server Dialback, December 2007</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0288: Bidirectional Server-to-Server Connections, October 2010</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>IETF RFC 6120 supersedes IETF RFC 3920
			  <para>IETF RFC 6121 XMPP IM supersedes IETF RFC 3921</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6.2: text-based collaboration services (enhanced XMPP profile).</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: The enhanced profile requires compliance with the basic profile as defined above plus:
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0033: Extended Stanza Addressing, September 2004</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0079: Advanced Message Processing, November 2005.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0122: Data Forms Validation. September 2005.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0199: XMPP Ping, June 2009.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0249: Direct MUC Invitation, September 2011.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0258: Security Labels in XMPP, March 2009</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP-0311: MUC Fast Reconnect, January 2012</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>Developers are also advised to consult the following IETF RFCs:
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>IETF RFC 6122: 2011, Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): Address Format</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>IETF RFC 6125: 2011, Representation and Verification of Domain-Based Application Service Identity within Internet Public Key Infrastructure Using X.509 (PKIX) Certificates in the Context of Transport Layer Security (TLS)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>IETF RFC 3923: 2004, End-to-end signing and object encryption for XMPP</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>IETF RFC 4854: 2007,XMPP URN A uniform Resource Name (URN) Namespace for Extensions to the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>IETF RFC 4979: 2007, IANA registration of an Enumservice for XMPP (see IETF RFC 3761: 2004, The E.164 to Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI) Dynamic Delegation Discovery System (DDDS) Application (ENUM)).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>IETF RFC 5122: 2008, A Internationalized Resource Identifiers (IRIs) and Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) for the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP)</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>Implementation</title>

<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex H.1: Voice/VoSIP/VTC Numbering Plans</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex H.2: VTC Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex H.3: VoSIP Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex H.4: SMTP Mail Routing</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex H.5: GAL Synchronisation</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex H.6: XMPP Text Based Chat</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex H.7: SCIP Services [TBC]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect4>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Information Management Services</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Information Management Services provide technical services "...to direct and support the handling of information throughout its life-cycle ensuring it becomes the right information in the right form and of adequate quality to satisfy the demands of an organization."  These services support organizations, groups, individuals and other technical services with capabilities to organize, store and retrieve information (in any format, structured or unstructured) through services and managed processes, governed by policies, directives, standards, profiles and guidelines.</emphasis></para>

<sect4>
<title>Standards</title>
<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable9" /> should be adhered to. Additionally all information should be labelled with the minimum metadata set by ISAF (see annex)<footnote><para>FMN: Note that the FMN Profile defines a minimum metadata set for future mission network instances.</para></footnote></para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable9">
        <title>Information Management Services and Data Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: <emphasis role="underline">Enterprise Search Services</emphasis>:  Automated information resource discover, information extraction and interchange of metadata</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: ISO 15836:2009, Information and documentation - The Dublin Core metadata element set.”</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: TIDE Information Discovery (v2.3.0, Allied Command Transformation Specification, 30 October 2009.)</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging: TIDE Transformational Baseline 3.0 – Annex C: TIDE Service Discovery (v.2.2.0, Allied Command Transformation Specification) December 2009.<footnote><para>FMN: For FMN, TIDE Service Discovery (v.2.2.0) will be mandatory</para></footnote> </para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging: SPARQL 1.1 Query Language, W3C Recommendation, 21 March 2013.<footnote><para>FMN: For FMN, SPARQL 1.1 will be mandatory</para></footnote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging: OWL 2 Web Ontology Language Document Overview (Second Edition), W3C Recommendation, 11 December 2012.<footnote><para>FMN: For FMN, OWL 2 will be mandatory</para>
				</footnote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging (2014): OpenSearch 1.1 Draft 5.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
			  <para>ISO 15836:2009 does not define implementation detail.</para>
			  <para>This profile requires a subset of metadata with UTF8 character encoding as defined in the NATO Discovery Metadata Specification (NDMS) – see</para>
			  <para>The technical implementation specifications are part of the TIDE Transformational Baseline v3.0, however, Query-by-Example (QBE), has been deprecated with the TIDE Information Discovery specs v2.3.0 and replaced by SPARQL.</para>
			  <para>The TIDE community is evaluating OpenSearch for potential inclusion into the TIDE Information Discovery specifications.  On the AMN CORE a commercial product called FAST ESP is being used to generate search indexes. This product could act as an OpenSearch "slave", but re- quires adaptation to this Open Standard but only using HTTP. For automated information discovery across the AMN all potential information sources must provide this standard search interface in order to allow  tools like FAST ESP to discover relevant information.</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: <emphasis role="underline">Enterprise Search Services</emphasis>: manual information resource discovery, classification marking and file naming conventions</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: AC322-N(2010)0025 – Guidance On File Naming<footnote><para>FMN: for FMN it is recommended that Character codes for permissible Classification Markings should be specified for each Mission Network in the IM Annex of the OPLAN.</para></footnote></para>
				</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: <emphasis role="underline">Enterprise Support Guard Services</emphasis>: General definition of Security and confidentiality metadata</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: NO-FFI-rapport 00961:2010, XML Confidentiality Label Syntax - a proposal for a NATO specification.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: NO-FFI-rapport 00962: 2010, Binding of Metadata to Data Objects - a proposal for a NATO specification.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: NCIA TN-1455-REV1, NATO Profile for the Binding of Metadata to Data Objects, Vers 1.1, December 2012.<footnote><para>NC3A TN-1455 is the NATO profile of NO-FFI 00962.</para>
				</footnote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: NCIA TN-1456-REV1, NATO Profile for the XML Confidentiality Label Syntax, Vers 1.1, January 2013.<footnote><para>NC3A TN-1456 is the NATO profile of NO-FFI 00961.</para>
				</footnote></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
			  <para>Services and applications shall implement object level labelling in order to support cross-domain information exchange using common enterprise Support Guard Services (e.g. Cross-Domain Solutions or Information Exchange Gateways)</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex I.1: ISAF Minimum Metadata Standard</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex I.1: Federating Search [TBC]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect4>
</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Geospatial Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Geospatial Services deliver network-based access to quality raster, vector and terrain data, available in varying degrees of format and complexity. Geospatial Services form a distinct class of information services through their unique requirements for collecting, converting, storing, retrieving, processing, analysing, creating, and displaying geographic data. The generic nature of Geospatial Services - "organizing information by location" - is interdisciplinary and not specific to any Community of Interest (COI) or application.</emphasis></para>

<sect4>
<title>Standards</title>
<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable10" /> should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable10">
        <title>Enterprise Support Geospatial Services and Data Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Geodetic and geophysical model of the Earth.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: NIMA Technical Report 8350.2 Third Edition incorporating Amendments 1 and 2: 23 June 2004, Department of Defense World Geodetic System 1984 Its Definition and Relationships with Local Geodetic Systems.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: Electronic format for medium resolution terrain evaluation data.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: MIL-PRF-89020 Rev. B, Performance Specification: Digital Terrain Elevation Data (DTED), 23 May 2000.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>Used to support line-of-sight analyses, terrain profiling, 3D terrain visualization, mission planning/rehearsal, and modelling and simulation.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Distribution of geospatial data as maps rendered in raster image formats.</entry>
              <entry>
               <itemizedlist>
			   <listitem><para>Mandatory: ISO 19128:2005, Geographic information - Web map server interface (WMS v.1.3.0).</para></listitem>
			   <listitem><para>Fading (Dec 2012): OGC WMS v1.0.0, v1.1.0, and v1.1.1</para></listitem>
			   <listitem><para>Mandatory: OGC 05-078r4, OpenGIS Styled Layer Descriptor (SLD) Profile of the Web Map Service Implementation Specification v.1.1.0, June 2007.</para></listitem>
			   <listitem><para>Emerging (2018): OGC 07-057r7, OpenGIS Web Map Tile Service Implementation Standard (WMTS) v.1.0.0, April 2010.</para>
			   </listitem>
			   </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>WMTS are to be provided as a complimentary service to WMS to ease access to users operating in bandwidth constraint environments. WMTS trades the flexibility of custom map rendering for the scalability possible by serving of static data (base maps) where the bounding box and scales have been constrained to discrete tiles which enables the use of standard network mechanisms for scalability such as distributed cache systems to cache images between the client and the server, reducing latency and bandwidth use.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4: Distribution of geo feature (vector) data between applications</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: OGC 04-094, Web Feature Service (WFS) v.1.1.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: OGC 06-049r1, GML Simple Feature Profile (GML 3.1.1) v.1.0.0 Compliance Level 0</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: OGC 04-095, Filter Encoding v.1.1</para>
				</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5: Electronic interchange of geospatial data as coverage, that is, digital geospatial information representing space varying phenomena</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: OGC 07-067r2, Web Coverage Service (WCS) v.1.1.1.<footnote><para>FMN: Emerging (2014) for the FMN: <emphasis role="italic">OGC 09-110r4, Web Coverage Service (WCS) v2.0, October 2010.</emphasis></para></footnote></para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>Fading (Dec 2011): v1.0.0 and v1.1.0</para>
				</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>Web Coverage Service v.1.1.1 is limited to describing and requesting grid (or "simple") coverage.</para>
			  <para>OGC Web Coverage Service (WCS) Standard Guidance Implementation Specification 1.0</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6: Catalogue services support the ability to publish and search collections of descriptive information (metadata) for geospatial data, services, and related information objects.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: OGC 07-110r4, CSW ebRIM Registry Service Part 1: ebRIM profile of CSW v.1.0.1</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: OGC 07-006r1: Catalogue Service for the Web (CSW) v.2.0.2, SOAP message</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>Catalogue Services will be supported by Core GIS FSD2 on the AMN Core.</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>7: File based storage and exchange of digital geospatial mapping (raster) data where services based access is not possible</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: GeoTIFF format specification: GeoTIFF Revision 1, Version 1.8.2, December 2000.<footnote><para>GeoTIFF 1.8.2 is public domain metadata standard embedding geo-referencing information within a TIFF revision 6.0 file.</para></footnote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: OGC 05-047r3: OpenGIS GML in JPEG 2000 for Geographic Imagery (GMLJP2) Encoding Specification 1.0.0, January 2006.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: MIL-PRF-89038, Performance Specification Compressed ARC Digitized Raster Graphics (CADRG). October 1994<footnote><para>Note for the FMN the standard cited is MIL-PRF-89038 (NOTICE 1), PERFORMANCE SPECIFICATION COMPRESSED ARC DIGITIZED RASTER GRAPHICS (CADRG) and incorporating Amendments 1 and 2. It needs to be checked if there is an impact on the AMN by removing the old 1994 citation.</para></footnote></para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: MIL-STD-2411, Department of Defense Interface Standard: Raster Product Format 6 Oct 1994<footnote><para>Note for the FMN the standard cited is MIL-STD-2411 (NOTICE 3), DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE INTERFACE STANDARD: RASTER PRODUCT FORMAT (31 MAR 2004). It needs to be checked if there is an impact on the AMN by removing the old 1994 citation.</para></footnote>.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				</entry>
              <entry>This is provided for legacy systems, implementers are encouraged to upgrade their systems to consume OGC Web Services.
			  <para>In practice, the exchange of large geospatial(raster) data sets between Geo organizations of different TCN’s is conducted in the proprietary<footnote><area>Requires LizardTech's (lizardtech.com) decoding software development kit (DSDK). The MrSID file format is a proprietary technology that provides tools for the rapid compression, viewing, and manipulation of geospatial raster and LiDAR data.</area></footnote> Multi-resolution seamless image database format (MrSID Generation 3 or 4).</para>
			  <para>Data in MrSID format could be transformed to GeoTIFF.</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>8: File based storage and exchange of non-topological geometry and attribute information or digital geospatial feature (vector) data</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: OGC 07-147r2, Keyhole Markup Language (KML) 2.2.0, April 2008.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: ESRI White Paper, ESRI Shapefile Technical Description, July 1998.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>ESRI Shapefiles are used by legacy systems and as file based interchange format. Implementers are encouraged to upgrade their systems based on OGC Web Services.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>9: <emphasis role="underline">Geospatial Coordinate Services</emphasis>: general positioning, coordinate systems, and coordinate transformations</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: OGC 01-009, OpenGIS Coordinate Transformation Service Implementation Specification Revision 1.00, January 2001.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex J.1: Geospatial Services [TBC]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Communities of Interest Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Communities of Interest (COI) Services support one or many collaborative groups of users with shared goals, interests, missions or business processes.</emphasis></para>

<para>COI Service will be broken up further into:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>COI Enabling Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>COI Specific Services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<sect2>
<title>Communities of Interest Enabling Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">COI-Enabling Services provide COI-dependant functionality required by more than one communities of interest. They are similar to Enterprise Support Services in that they provide building blocks for domain-specific service development. The distinction between the two is that Enterprise Support Services provide generic COI-independent capabilities for the entire enterprise (e.g. collaboration and information management services) and COI-Enabling Services provide those COI-dependant services that are typically shared by a larger group of COIs (e.g. operational planning and situational awareness capabilities).</emphasis></para>

<para>For the purposes of this Volume, COI-Enabling Services will be broken up further into:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>General COI-Enabling Data Formats and Standards</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Situational Awareness Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Biometric Services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<sect3>
<title>General COI-Enabling Data Formats and Standards</title>
<sect4>
<title>Standards</title>
<para>Common standards that apply to all COI Enabling Service are listed in Table <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable11" />. These should be adhered to if federated services are to be achieved.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable11">
        <title>General Data Format Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: General definition for the Representation of Dates and Times.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Mandatory: ISO 8601:2004, Data elements and interchange formats - Information interchange - Representation of dates and times</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
			  <para>Implementation of the W3C profile of ISO 8601:2004 (W3CDTF profile) is recommended.</para>
			  <para>Note: See also guidance on storage and use of time given in Table 6. IDs 1 and 4</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: General definition of letter codes for Geographical Entities</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: STANAG 1059, Letter Codes for Geographical Entities (8th edition, 2005)<footnote><para>FMN: For FMN the following alpha-2/alpha-3 codes shall be used to identify international organizations and their sub-ordinated entities: NATO: “XN”/ “XXN”, European Union: “EU” / “XEU”, United Nations: “XU”/”XUN”.</para></footnote>.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>Whenever possible, the ISO-3166 alpha-3 (three-letter codes) contained in STANAG 1059 should be used.</para>
			  <para>Alpha-3 codes “XXA”, “XXB”, “XXC”, “XXX” shall not be used to avoid potential conflicts with ISO/IEC 7501-1.</para>
			  <para>Codes “EEE” and “GER” are used as a deviation by ISAF Force Tracking System (IFTS) for EUPOL and Germany respectively.</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: General definition of letter codes for identifying Nationality of a person</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Conditional: ISO/IEC 7501-1:2008, Identification cards -- Machine readable travel documents - Part 1: Machine readable passport.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
			  <para>When STANAG 1059 3-letter codes are being used for identifying nationality, code extensions such as XXA, XXB, XXC, XXX as defined in ISO/IEC 7501-1 are to be used.</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4: General definition of geospatial coverage areas in discovery metadata</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: NIMA Technical Report 8350.2 Third Edition Amendment 1+2: 23 June 2004, Department of Defense World Geodetic System 1984 Its Definition and Relationships with Local Geodetic Systems.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: ISO 19115:2003, Geographic information – Metadata.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: ISO 19115:2003/Cor 1:2006.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: ISO 19136:2007, Geographic Information -- Geography Markup Language (GML).</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
			  <para>ISO 19139 provides encoding guidance for ISO 19115</para>	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Situational Awareness Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Situational Awareness (SA) Services provide the situational knowledge required by a military commander to plan operations and exercise command and control. This is the result of the processing and presentation of information comprehending the operational environment - the status and dispositions of friendly, adversary, and non-aligned actors, as well as the impacts of physical, cultural, social, political, and economic factors on military operations.</emphasis></para>

<sect4>
<title>Standards</title>
<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table <xref  linkend="v3t-id-reftable12" /> should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable12">
        <title>Battlespace Management Interoperability Protocols and Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>

		  <row>
              <entry>1: Expressing digital geographic annotation and visualization on, two-dimensional maps and three dimensional globes</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: TIDE Transformational Baseline Vers. 3.0, Annex A: NATO Vector Graphics (NVG) v1.5, Allied Command Transformation Specification, December 2009.<footnote><para>FMN: Emerging (2014): <emphasis role="italic">TIDE Transformational Baseline Vers. 4.0 - Annex N: NATO Vector Graphics (NVG) v2.0, Allied Command Transformation Specification, February 2013 and Open Geospatial Consortium 05-047r3, GML in JPEG 2000 for Geographic Imagery Encoding Specification 1.0.0,  (annotations and overlays).</emphasis></para></footnote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Fading: NVG 1.4</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Retired: NVG 0.3</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: Open Geospatial Consortium 07-147r2, Keyhole Markup Language (KML) 2.2, April 2008.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>NVG shall be used as the standard Protocol and Data Format for encoding and sharing of information layers.</para>
			  <para>NVG and KML are both XML based language schemas for expressing geographic annotations.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>

		  <row>
              <entry>2: Formatted military message exchange in support of:
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>SOA Platform Services/ Message-oriented Middleware Services</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Enterprise Support Services/ Unified Communication and Collaboration Services/ Text-based Collaboration Services</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			  </entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Mandatory: STANAG 5500 Ed.7:2010, Concept of NATO Message Text Formatting System (CONFORMETS) / ADatP-03 Ed. (A) Ver. 1: December 2009.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>
			  <para>ADatP-03(A) contains two different equivalent presentations of data: one as "classic" message or alternatively as XML-MTF instance.</para>
			  <para>A)	Automated processing of XML-files in static facilities/systems is much easier and thus preferred for the exchange between national AMN extensions and the AMN Core.</para>
			  <para>B)	At the tactical edge of the AMN the "classic" message format is the preferred option as this format is "leaner" and easier to transmit via tactical radio systems.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>

		  <row>
              <entry>3: Message formats for exchanging information in low bandwidth environments</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: STANAG 7149 Ed. 4  NATO Message Catalogue APP-11(C).</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>Minimum set of messages supported by the AMN Core Network:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>INCIDENT REPORT (A078)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>SARIR (J012)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>EVENTREP (J092)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>EODINCREP (J069)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>AIR SUPPORT REQUEST (F091)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>AIR TASKING ORDER (F058)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>AIRSPACE CONTROL ORDER (F011)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>PRESENCE REPORT (A009)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>SITREP (J095)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>ENEMY CONTACT REP (A023)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>CASEVACREQ (A015)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>KILLBOX MESSAGE (F083)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>INCIDENTSPOTREP (J006)</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>Emerging (2015)<footnote><para>APP-11(C) Change 2, which is satisfying urgent operational requirements and contains new message formats designed for ISAF and similar operations, was sadly not promulgated in 2012.  Their promulgation is now forecasted for 2013 with APP-11(D) (1).</para></footnote>:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>SALTATIC (A073)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>CASEVACREQ (A015)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>MEDEVAC MESSAGE (A012)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>FRIENDLY FORCE INFORMATION (J025) Note: This is the ADatP-3 representation of NFFI.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>OPSITREP IRREGULAR ACTOR (A011)</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>The following messages that are not compliant with STANAG 7149 Ed 4. could be accepted by the AMN Core Network:
			    <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>UXO IED REPORT 10LINER (UXOIED) (A075)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Joint Tactical Air Strike Request (JTAR) US DD Form 1972</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>ROZ Status / KILLBOX MESSAGE (F083)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>ENEMY CONTACT REP (A023)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>SALUTE (Size, Activity, Location, Unit/Uniform, Time, Equipment)</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>Change request proposals reflecting the requirements for those non-standard messages should be submitted within the configuration management process of ADatP-3 by those nations that are the primary originators of those messages.</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>

		  <row>
              <entry>4: Exchange of digital Friendly Force Information such as positional tracking information between systems hosted on a Mission Network and mobile tactical systems</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: AC/322-D(2006)0066 Interim NATO Friendly Force Information (FFI) Standard for Interoperability of Force Tracking Systems (FFTS).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging (2016): STANAG 5527 Ed: 1 / ADatP-36 Ed. A Ver. 1, NATO Friendly Force Information (FFI) Standard for Interoperability of Friendly Force Tracking Systems (FFTS).</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging (2015): FRIENDLY FORCE INFORMATION (J025) is the ADatP-3 MTF.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>All positional information of friendly ground forces (e.g. ground forces of Troop Contributing Nations or commercial transport companies working in support of ISAF Forces) shall be as a minimum made available in a format that can be translated into the NFFI V1.3 format (specified in STANAG 5527)
			  </entry>
            </row>

		  <row>
              <entry>5: Mediation Services: Mediate between the TDL and MN to provide weapon delivery assets with Situational Awareness on friendly forces.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Emerging (2016): STANAG 5528 Ed: 1/ ADatP-37 Ed.  A, Services to forward Friendly Force Information to weapon delivery assets.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>

		  <row>
              <entry>6: Real time automated data exchange such as radar tracking information between TDL networks and MN Message exchange Over Tactical Data Links</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: STANAG 5518, Ed.1 - Interoperability Standard for the Joint Range Extension Applications Protocol (JREAP).; see also US MIL-STD 3011</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>In combination with:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: STANAG 5516, Ed.4:2008 - Tactical  Data  Exchange (Link16)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: STANAG 5511, Feb 28, 2006 - Tactical Data Exchange (Link 11/11B); see also US MIL-STD 6011</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: STANAG 5616 Ed 4:2008 - Standards for Data Forwarding between Tactical Data Systems employing Link 11/11B, Link 16 and Link 22.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging (2016): STANAG 5516, Ed.5:2009 -Tactical Data Exchange (Link16)</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>Link-16 data is disseminated via JREAP and ad-hoc (i.e. NACT) protocols in ISAF. The transition to a full JREAP based dissemination needs to be implemented in close coordination with via the AMN Sec TMO.<para>STANAG 5516, Ed.5 is under ratification. Implementation in ISAF needs to be coordinated via the AMN Sec TMO</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>

		  <row>
              <entry>7: Exchanging information on Incident and Event information to support information exploitation.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Emerging (2014): Draft EVENTEXPLOITREP XML schema.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: NC3A JOCWatch Web Services Specification - Operational Incident Report (OIR) – 1.2, Sep 2011</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: U.S.PM Battle Command SIGACT Schema<footnote><para>It should be noted that this schema is subject to release by the US Army</para></footnote></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>This schema will be used to exchange rich and structured incident/ event information between C2 and Exploitation systems like JOCWatch and CIDNE. National capability developers are invited to contribute to the development of the final EVENTEXPLOITREP XML Schema<footnote><para>See http://tide.act.nato.int/tidepedia/index.php?title=TP_112:_Event_Exploitation_Reports_(EVENTEXPLOITREP)</para></footnote>.</para>
			  <para>Until the EVENTEXPLOITREP XML Schema definition is finalised, it is recommended to continue to use the current draft schema also known as OIR (Operational Incident Report) and the SIGACT Schema.</para>
			  <para>The SIGACT schema is used via PASS, webservices and XMPP to exchange SIGACT information at Regional Command level and below.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>

		  <row>
              <entry>8: Military Symbology interoperability</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: STANAG 2019, Ed.5:2008, Joint SmbologyAPP-6(B)<footnote><para>FMN: Mandatory: Emerging (2013): STANAG 2019, Ed.6:2011, Joint SmbologyAPP-6(C). An assessment will be required on the AMN before uplifting the edition.</para></footnote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: MIL-STD-2525B (w/Change 2), Common Warfighting Symbology, Mar 2007<footnote><para>FMN: Recommended: MIL-STD-2525C, Common Warfighting Symbology, Nov 2008. An assessment will be required on the AMN before uplifting the version.</para></footnote>.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>Note that the different standards are not fully compatible with each other and require mapping services.  A translation symbol service needs to be provided on the AMN Core Network.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>

		  <row>
              <entry>9: Digital exchange of semantically rich information about Battlespace Objects</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Mandatory: MIP C2 Information Exchange data model (C2IEDM)  [note: STANAG 5523 was cancelled]<footnote><para>FMN: Mandatory: <emphasis role="italic">Multilateral Interoperability Programme, Joint Consultation Command and Control Information Exchange Data Model (JC3IEDM) 3.1.4:2012.</emphasis> Beyond this, FMN is looking to the emerging MIP Information Model (MIM) (2018)</para></footnote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: MIP Data Exchange Mechanism (DEM) Block 2 <footnote><para></para></footnote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: AMN MIP Implementation Profile (published in Annex A to NC3A AMN MIP Workshop Final Report). RD-3188</para>
				</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>C2IEDM Business Rule F11.2 b is not applicable in the AMN scope. Implementations shall ensure that the use of CONTEXT-ASSOCIATION does not create circular references between CONTEXTs.</para>
			  <para>AMN members implementing MIP have agreed to use C2IEDM (MIP-Block 2) due to lack of fielded MIP-Block 3.1 systems by the Nations and the limited information exchange requirements of AMN Mission Threads (i.e. no requirement for Operational planning)<footnote><para>It should be noted that no further development is being pursued by the MIP community for MIP-Block 2. If AMN is to progress in line with direction of FMN, implementation needs to include MIP DEM Block 2.0 to 3.1 translation. If incorporated at the AMN Integration Core, translation of the information to other standards would also be also possible.</para></footnote>.</para>
			  <para>Any addition or expansion of this data model or data dictionaries that is deemed to be of general interest shall be submitted as a change proposal within the con- figuration control process to be considered for inclusion in the next version of the specification</para>
			  <para>The AMN Integration Core uses Ground Tracks, Event Exploit Rep, Atom, KML, NVG and initial support for JC3IEDM as the basis for its canonical model schemas. Other Schemas of immediate interest to AMN include the US Publish and Subscribe Services (PASS) Schemas POSREP, SIGACT and GRAPHICS. Altogether allow the ingestion of Track, Unit, Object Associations (ORBAT/ TASKORG), Facilities, Control Features, Airspace Control measures, Routes<footnote><para>See also https://tide.act.nato.int/tidepedia/index.php?title=C2_Integration_Cononical_Modeling.</para></footnote>information and the transformation into formats that the AMN Integration Core canonical model support.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>

			</tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex K.1: Track Management Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex K.2: Information exchange via MIP [TBC]</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex K.3: Information Exchange via the Integration Core [TBC]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Biometric Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Biometrics services record measurable biological (anatomical and physiological) and behavioural characteristics of personnel for use by automated recognition systems. Biometric enabled systems typically provide distinct services for Data Collection and for Matching/Identification.</emphasis></para>

<sect4>
<title>Standards</title>
<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable13" /> should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable13">
        <title>Biometric Data and System Interoperability Protocols and Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Interchange	of Fingerprint (Type 4 and 14) data</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007 Part 1</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>EBTS 1.2 (references ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000)</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1 (references ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>DOD EBTS 2.0</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>ISO/IEC 19794-2:2005, part 2</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: Type 10 Facial</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>EFTS v7.0, EFTS v7.1</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000, 1-2007 Part 1</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>EBTS 1.2 (references EFTS v7.0)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>DOD EBTS v2.0</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>ISO/IEC 19794-5 w/Amd1:2007, part 5</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Type 16 Iris</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000, 1-2007 Part 1</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>EBTS 1.2</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>ISO/IEC 19794-6</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.
			  </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4: Type 17 Iris</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007 Part 1</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1 (ref ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007)</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem><para>DOD EBTS v2.0</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>ISO/IEC 19794-6</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.
			  </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex L.1: [Nil]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Communities of Interest Specific Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Community of Interest (COI)-Specific Services provide specific functionality as required by particular C3 user communities in support of NATO operations, exercises and routine activities. These COI-Specific Services were previously also referred to as "functional services" or "functional area services".</emphasis></para>

<para>For the purposes of this Volume and the AMN, Standards and Implementation Instructions are currently only required for:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Joint Intelligence, Surveillance and Reconnaissance (JISR or Joint ISR) Community of Interest (COI) Services.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<sect3>
<title>JISR COI Services</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Joint Intelligence, Surveillance and Reconnaissance (JISR or Joint ISR) Community of Interest (COI) Services provide unique computing and information services for intelligence support to operations. Intelligence Support is the set of military activities that are undertaken to receive commander's direction, proactively collect information, analyse it, produce useful predictive intelligence and disseminate it in a timely manner to those who need to know.</emphasis></para>

<sect4>
<title>Standards</title>
<para>The NATO Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconnaissance Interoperability Architecture (NIIA) [AEDP-2, Ed.1:2005] provides the basis for the technical aspects of an architecture that provides interoperability between NATO nations' ISR systems. AEDP-2 provides the technical and management guidance for implementing the NIIA in ISR systems. These common standards are listed in Table <xref linkend="v3t-id-reftable14" />. These should be adhered to if federated services are to be achieved.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable14">
        <title>JISR Interoperability Protocols and Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Storing and exchanging of images and associated data</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Mandatory: STANAG 4545, Ed. Amendment 1:2000, NATO Secondary Imagery Format (NSIF)</para>
				</listitem></itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>AEDP-4, Ed. 1, NATO Secondary Imagery Format Implementation Guide, 15 Jun 07, NU.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: Providing a standard software interface for searching and retrieving for ISR products.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: STANAG 4559, Ed. 3:2010 (starting Dec 2011). NATO Standard ISR Library Interface (NSILI).<footnote><para>FMN: Emerging (2016): <emphasis role="italic">STANAG 4559, Ed. 4, NATO Standard ISR Library Interface (NSILI).</emphasis>
				</para></footnote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Fading: STANAG 4559, Ed. 2:2007 (beginning July 2011)</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>AEDP-5, Ed. 1, NATO Standard Imagery Library Interface Implementation Guide, TBS, NU</para>
			  <para>Note: STANAG 4559, Ed.2 and Ed.3 are NOT compatible with each other (<emphasis role="bold">No backwards compatibility</emphasis>). The NATO provided CSD on the AMN Core network only implements Ed.3:2010).</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Exchange of ground moving target indicator radar data</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: STANAG 4607, Ed. 2:2007 NATO Ground Moving Target Indicator (GMTI) Format.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging: STANAG 4607, Ed.3:2010.<footnote><para>FMN: Recommended: <emphasis role="italic">NATO Ground Moving Target Indicator (GMTI) Format STANAG 4607, Ed.3:2010</emphasis></para>
				</footnote></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>AEDP-7, Ed. 1, NATO Ground Moving Target Indication (GMTI) Format Implementation Guide, TBS, NU</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4: Provision of common methods for exchanging of Motion Imagery (MI)across systems</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: STANAG 4609, Ed. 2:2007 NATO Digital Motion Imagery Standard.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging: STANAG 4609, Ed. 3:2009.
				<footnote><para>FMN: Mandatory: <emphasis role="italic">NATO Digital Motion Imagery Standard STANAG 4609, Ed. 3:2009.</emphasis></para>
				</footnote></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>AEDP-8, Ed. 2, Implementation Guide For STANAG 4609NDMI , June 2007, NU</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5: Exchange of unstructured data (documents, jpeg imagery)</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Recommended: IPIWIG V4 Metadata Specification: 2009, Intelligence Projects Integration Working Group (IPIWG), Definition of metadata for unstructured Intelligence.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6: Providing a standard software interface for ex changing information about sensor planning, including information about capabilities of sensors, tasking of a sensors and status of sensor-planning requests.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Emerging: OGC 09-000: OGC Sensor Planning Service Implementation Standard v2.0, March 2011.<footnote><para>FMN: Mandatory: OGC 09-000: OGC Sensor Planning Service Implementation Standard v2.0, March 2011.</para>
				</footnote></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>For the AMN, Sensor Planning Service implementations shall adhere to the SOAP binding as defined in OGC 09-000.</para></entry>
            </row>
			</tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

</sect4>
<sect4>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex M.1: JISR Interoperability via CSD [TBC]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect4>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>User Facing Capabilities</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">User-Facing Capabilities express the requirements for the interaction between end users and all CIS Capabilities, in order to process Information Products in support of Business Processes. User-Facing Capabilities incorporate the User Appliances, as well as the User Applications that run on those appliances.</emphasis></para>

<para>For the purposes of this Volume, only the standards for User Applications need to be cited.</para>

<sect2>
  <title>User Applications</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">User Applications, also known as application software, software applications, applications or apps, are computer software components designed to help a user perform singular or multiple related tasks and provide the logical interface between human and automated activities.</emphasis></para>

  <sect3>
<title>Standards</title>
<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table <xref  linkend="v3t-id-reftable15" /> should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable15">
        <title>User Application Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
		  
            <row>
              <entry>1: Displaying content within web browsers.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory (for legacy): HyperText Markup Language (HTML) 4.01 Specification. W3C Recommendation 24 December 1999.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory (for legacy): Extensible Hypertext Markup Language (Second Edition) XHTML 1.0. A Reformulation of HTML 4 in XML 1.0. W3C Recommendation 26 January 2000, revised 1 August 2002</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Fading (for legacy): Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), Level 2 (CSS 2.0), W3C Recommendation, May 1998</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory (for legacy): Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), Level 2 revision 1 (CSS 2.1), W3C Recommendation, September 2009.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging (2014): HyperText Markup Language, Version 5 (HTML 5), W3C Candidate Recommendation, Dec 2012.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging (2014): Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) Level 3:<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), Level 2 revision 1 (including errata) (CSS 2.1), W3C Recommendation, June 2011.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>CSS Style Attributes, W3C Candidate Recommendation, 12 October 2010</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Media Queries, W3C Recommendation, 19 June 2012.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>CSS Namespaces Module, W3C Recommendation, 29 September 2011.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Selectors Level 3, W3C Recommendation, 29 September 2011.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>CSS Color Module Level 3, W3C Recommendation, 07 June 2011.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist></para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>Browser plug-ins are not covered by a single specification.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>Applications must support the following browsers: Microsoft Internet Explorer v9.0 and newer, and Mozilla Firefox 12.0 and newer<footnote><para>FMN: Has raised the minimum support for Mozilla Firefox to v16.0 and newer.</para></footnote>. When a supported browser is not true to the standard, choose to support the browser that is closest to the standard<footnote><para>E.g. using http://html5test.com to compare features for HTML5.</para></footnote>.</para>
			  <para>Some organizations or end-user devices do not allow the use of proprietary extensions such as Adobe Flash or Microsoft Silverlight. Those technologies shall be avoided.  Implementers should use open standard based solutions instead (e.g. move to HTML5 / CSS3).</para>
			  <para>Some AMN members do not allow the use of ActiveX controls in the browser. Browser plug-ins will need to be approved by AMN Change Advisory Board (CAB).</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
		  
            <row>
              <entry>2: Visualize common operational symbology within C4ISR systems in order to convey information about objects in the battlespace.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: STANAG 2019, Ed.5:2008, Joint SmbologyAPP-6(B)<footnote><para>FMN: Mandatory: STANAG 2019, Ed.6:2011, Joint SmbologyAPP-6(C)</para></footnote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: MIL-STD-2525B (w/Change 2), Common Warfighting Symbology, Mar 2007<footnote><para>FMN: Mandatory: MIL-STD-2525C, Common Warfighting Symbology, Nov 2008</para></footnote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: TIDE Transformational Baseline Vers. 3.0, Annex A: NATO Vector Graphics (NVG) v1.5, Allied Command Transformation Specification, December 2009.<footnote><para>FMN: Emerging (2014): <emphasis role="italic">TIDE Transformational Baseline Vers. 4.0 - Annex N: NATO Vector Graphics (NVG) v2.0, Allied Command Transformation Specification, February 2013</emphasis></para></footnote></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Fading: NVG 1.4</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Retired: NVG 0.3</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>All presentation service shall render tracks, tactical graphics, and MOOTW objects using this standard except in the case where the object being rendered is not covered in the standard. In these exceptional cases, additional symbols shall be defined as extensions of existing symbol standards and must be backwards compatible. These extensions shall be submitted as a request for change within the configuration management process to be considered for inclusion in the next version of the specification.</para></entry>
            </row>
		  
            <row>
              <entry>3: Reliable messaging over XMPP</entry>
              <entry>XMPP Clients must implement the following XMPP Extension Protocols (XEP):
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: XEP-0184 - Message Delivery Receipts, March 2011 (whereby the sender of a message can request notification that it has been received by the intended recipient).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>XEP 0202 - Entity Time, September 2009 (for communicating the local time of an entity)</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>All XMPP Chat Clients used on the AMN shall implement these two protocol extensions {this section will be enhanced in the next version based on a detailed recently conducted requirements analysis}.
			  </para></entry>
            </row>
		  
            <row>
              <entry>4: Collaborative generation of spreadsheets, charts, presentations and word processing documents</entry>
              <entry>Office Open XML:
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: Standard ECMA-376, Ed. 1: December 2006, Office Open XML File Formats.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging (2013): ISO/IEC 29500:2012, Information technology -- Document description and processing languages -- Office Open XML File Formats                
				<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Part 1: Fundamentals and Markup Language Reference.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Part 2: Open Packaging Conventions.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Part 3: Markup Compatibility and Extensibility.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Part 4: Transitional Migration Features.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				<para>Open Document Format:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: ISO/IEC 26300:2006, Information technology -- Open Document Format for Office Applications (OpenDocument) v1.0.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: ISO/IEC 26300:2006/Cor 1:2010.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: ISO/IEC 26300:2006/Cor 2:2011.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: ISO/IEC 26300:2006/Amd 1:2012,  Open Document Format for Office Applications (OpenDocument) v1.1</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>OASIS Open Document Format ODF 1.0 (ISO/IEC 26300) and Office Open XML (ISO/IEC 29500) are both open document formats for saving and exchanging word processing documents, spreadsheets and presentations. Both formats are XML based but differ in design and scope.
			  </para><para>ISO/IEC TR 29166:2011, Information technology -- Document description and processing languages -- Guidelines for translation between ISO/IEC 26300 and ISO/IEC 29500 document formats.</para></entry>
            </row>
		  
            <row>
              <entry>5: Document exchange, storage and archiving</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: ISO 19005-1:2005, Document management -Electronic document file format for long-term preservation –Part 1: Use of PDF 1.4 (PDF/A-1)</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Emerging (2014): ISO 19005-2:2011, Document management -- Electronic document file format for long-term preservation -- Part 2: Use of ISO 32000-1 (PDF/A-2)</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>See Operational Record Retention Schedule and AMN JMEI Exit Instructions (Vol3) for further details.</entry>
            </row>
		  
            <row>
              <entry>6: Representation of Dates and Times</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: W3C profile of ISO 8601 defined in:<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Date and Time Formats, W3C Note, 15 September 1997</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: Working with Time Zones, W3C Working Group Note, July 2011.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Conditional (for military command and control systems):<itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>AAP-6:2013, NATO glossary of terms and definitions.  Part 2-D-1, date-time group (DTG) format.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>See also Table <xref  linkend="v3t-id-reftable6" /> (ID 1 and 4) for time synchronization within and between systems</para>
			  <para>When a DTG is expressed in local time, this must use the military time zone designator. For AFG this is D30<footnote>
			  <para>A mapping of UTC offsets to military time zone designators can be found in the FMN Profile Table 12, which is based one in JC3IEDM V3.1.4/ADatP-3 BL13.1 FFIRN/FUD 1003/1. For notes on implementing timezone designators in military command and control systems please see ID 6 of Table <xref  linkend="v3t-id-reftable10" /> (User Application Standards) of the FMN Profile.</para></footnote>.</para></entry>
            </row>
		  
            <row>
              <entry>7: Internationalization  designing, developing content and (web) applications, in a way that ensures it will work well for, or can be easily adapted for, users from any culture, region, or language.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: Internationalization of Web Design and Applications Current Status, http://www.w3.org/standards/ techs/i18nauthoring</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: Internationalization of Web Architecture Current Status, http://www.w3.org/standards/ techs/i18nwebarch#w3c_all</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: Internationalization of XML Current Status,  http://www.w3.org/ standards/techs/i18nxml</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: Internationalization of Web Services Current Status,  http://www.w3.org/standards /techs/i18nwebofservices</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>Best practices and tutorials on internationalization can be found at: http://www.w3.org /International/articlelist</para></entry>
            </row>
		   </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

</sect3>
<sect3>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex N.1: Enterprise Portal Configuration</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Human-to-Human Communication</title>
<para>To work effectively in a federated mission networking environment, it is not sufficient to only standardise technical services. A key prerequisite is to also agree a common language, and terminology for force preparation, training material, user interfaces, common vocabularies etc.</para>
<sect2>
<title>Standards</title>
<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table <xref  linkend="v3t-id-reftable16" /> should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable16">
        <title>Human-to-human interoperability Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Mutual understanding of terminology</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: General terminology:  Concise Oxford English Dictionary.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: Specific military terminology: NSA AAP-6, NATO Glossary of terms and definitions.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: General language communication ability of staff working in a federated networking environment.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: Standardised Language Profile (SLP) English 3222 in accordance with STANAG 6001 Version 4</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>As an addition to SLP Profiles the following proficiency description could also be considered<footnote><para>Source: International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO) Holistic Descriptors of operational language proficiency (adapted)</para></footnote>:</para>
			  <para>For effective voice communications, a proficient speakers shall:</para>
			  <para>1. communicate effectively in voice-only (telephone/radio) and in face-to-face situations;</para>
			  <para>2. communicate on common, concrete and work-related topics with accuracy and clarity;</para>
			  <para>3. use appropriate communicative strategies to exchange messages and to recognize and resolve misunderstandings (e.g. to check, confirm, or clarify information) in a general or work-related context;</para>
			  <para>4. handle successfully and with relative ease the linguistic challenges presented by a complication or unexpected turn of events that occurs within the context of a routine mission situation or communicative task with which they are otherwise familiar; and</para>
			  <para>5. use a dialect or accent which is intelligible to the multinational mission community.</para>
			  </entry>
            </row>
			</tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Service Management and Control</title>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: 
	<emphasis role="italic">Service Management and Control (SMC) provides a collection of capabilities to coherently manage components in a federated service-enabled information technology infrastructure. SMC tools enable service providers to provide the desired quality of service as specified by the customer. In a federated environment such as the AMN, utilizing common process and data is a critical enabler to management of the network.</emphasis></para>

<sect2>
<title>Standards</title>
<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table <xref  linkend="v3t-id-reftable17" /> should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-reftable17">
        <title>Service Management and Control Interoperability Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID: Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standards</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Provide Service Management within the AMN.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Mandatory: ITIL 2011 update / ISO/IEC 20000</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>See also AMN Service Management Framework CONOPS</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: Provide the Control (Governance) required to efficiently and effectively control the AMN.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: ISACA, Control Objectives for Information and related Technology 5 Framework (COBIT 5).</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Optional: TMForum Framework Business Process Framework (eTOM) Release 1.3.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>COBIT is based on established frameworks, such as the Software Engineering Institute’s Capability Maturity Model, ISO9000, ITIL, and ISO 17799 (standard security framework, now ISO 27001).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Network management</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Mandatory: IETF STD 62: 2002, An Architecture for Describing Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP) Management Frameworks.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>Details of Simple Network Management Protocol Version 3 (SNMPv3) are defined by IETF RFC 3411 - 3418:2002.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4: SOA Platform SMC Services</entry>
              <entry>Web Services for Management:
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: Distributed Management Task Force, WS-Management Specification Version 1.0.0 (DSP0226), 12 Feb 2008.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: Distributed Management Task Force, WS-Management CIM Binding Specification Version 1.0.0 (DSP0227), 19 June 2009.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>WS-Management provides a common way for systems to access and exchange management information across the IT infrastructure.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5: Represent and share Configuration Items and details about the important attributes and relationships between them.</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: Distributed Management Task Force, CIM Schema version 2.30.0, 27 Sep 2011.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Recommended: Distributed Management Task Force, CMDB Federation Specification V1.0.1, 22 Apr 2010.</para></listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
			</tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Implementation</title>
<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex O.1: End to End Service Monitoring</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex O.2: Federation of TCN and NATO SMC Systems [TBC]</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Abbreviations</title>
<para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-abbreviations">
        <title>Abbreviations</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="15*" />
          <colspec colwidth="70*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Acronym</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row><entry>
AAA</entry><entry>Authentication, Authorization, and Accounting</entry></row><row><entry>
ACL</entry><entry>Access Control List</entry></row><row><entry>
ACO</entry><entry>Allied Command Operations</entry></row><row><entry>
ACO</entry><entry>Air Operations... Airspace Control Order</entry></row><row><entry>
ACP</entry><entry>Allied Communications Publication</entry></row><row><entry>
ACS</entry><entry>Access Control Service</entry></row><row><entry>
ACT</entry><entry>Allied Command Transformation</entry></row><row><entry>
ADAMS</entry><entry>Allied Deployment and Movement System (FAS</entry></row><row><entry>
ADSF®</entry><entry>Active Directory Federation Services</entry></row><row><entry>
ADS®</entry><entry>Active Directory Services</entry></row><row><entry>
ADS</entry><entry>Authoritative Data Sources/Stores (when in the context of Functional Services)</entry></row><row><entry>
AEP</entry><entry>AMN European Point of Presence</entry></row><row><entry>
AFPL</entry><entry>Approved Fielded Product List</entry></row><row><entry>
AMCC</entry><entry>Allied Movement Coordination Cell</entry></row><row><entry>
AMN</entry><entry>Afghanistan Mission Network</entry></row><row><entry>
AMNOC</entry><entry>Afghanistan Mission Network Operations Centre</entry></row><row><entry>
ANSF</entry><entry>Afghan National Security Forces</entry></row><row><entry>
AOR</entry><entry>Area of Responsibility</entry></row><row><entry>
APOD</entry><entry>Aerial Port Of Debarkation</entry></row><row><entry>
ARCENT</entry><entry>Army Component of U.S. Central Command</entry></row><row><entry>
ARRP</entry><entry>Alliance and Missions Requirements and Resources Plan</entry></row><row><entry>
AS</entry><entry>autonomous system</entry></row><row><entry>
ASCM</entry><entry>Airspace Control Measures</entry></row><row><entry>
ATO</entry><entry>Air Tasking Order</entry></row><row><entry>
AWCC</entry><entry>Afghan Wireless Communication Company</entry></row><row><entry>
AWG</entry><entry>Architecture Working Group</entry></row><row><entry>
BDA</entry><entry>Battle Damage Assessment</entry></row><row><entry>
BE</entry><entry>Best Effort</entry></row><row><entry>
Bi-SC</entry><entry>Bi- Strategic Command (ACO and ACT)</entry></row><row><entry>
BGP</entry><entry>Border Gateway Protocol</entry></row><row><entry>
C5ISR</entry><entry>Coalition Command, Control, Communications and Computers Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconnaissance</entry></row><row><entry>
CAB</entry><entry>Change Advisory Board</entry></row><row><entry>
CBT</entry><entry>Computer Based Training</entry></row><row><entry>
CDS</entry><entry>Cross Domain Solution</entry></row><row><entry>
CCP</entry><entry>Configuration Change Proposal</entry></row><row><entry>
CE</entry><entry>Crisis Establishment (manpower)</entry></row><row><entry>
CES</entry><entry>Core Enterprise Services</entry></row><row><entry>
CIAV</entry><entry>Coalition Interoperability Assurance and Validation</entry></row><row><entry>
CIDNE®</entry><entry>Combined Information Data Network Exchange (FAS)</entry></row><row><entry>
CIDR</entry><entry>Classless Inter-domain Routing</entry></row><row><entry>
CIMIC</entry><entry>Civil-Military Co-operation</entry></row><row><entry>
CIS</entry><entry>communication and information systems</entry></row><row><entry>
CJMCC</entry><entry>Combined Joint Movement Coordination Centre</entry></row><row><entry>
CMB</entry><entry>Change Management Board</entry></row><row><entry>
CMDB</entry><entry>Configuration Management DataBase</entry></row><row><entry>
CoI</entry><entry>Community of Interest</entry></row><row><entry>
COIN</entry><entry>Counter Insurgency (Campaign)</entry></row><row><entry>
COMIJC</entry><entry>Commander IJC</entry></row><row><entry>
CONOP</entry><entry>Concept of Operation</entry></row><row><entry>
COP</entry><entry>Common Operational Picture</entry></row><row><entry>
COTS</entry><entry>Commercial Off The Shelf</entry></row><row><entry>
CORSOM</entry><entry>Coalition Reception, Staging and Onward Movement (FAS)</entry></row><row><entry>
CPU</entry><entry>Central Processing Unit</entry></row><row><entry>
CPOF</entry><entry>Command Post of the Future (FAS)</entry></row><row><entry>
CRCB</entry><entry>Crisis Response Coordination Board</entry></row><row><entry>
CMRB</entry><entry>CRO Management Resource Board</entry></row><row><entry>
CSD</entry><entry>Coalition Shared Database</entry></row><row><entry>
CTE2</entry><entry>Coalition Test and Evaluation Environment</entry></row><row><entry>
CUR</entry><entry>Crisis Response Operations Urgent Requirement</entry></row><row><entry>
CX-I</entry><entry>CENTRIXS-ISAF</entry></row><row><entry>
DCIS</entry><entry>Deployed CIS</entry></row><row><entry>
DGI</entry><entry>Designated Geospatial Information</entry></row><row><entry>
DML</entry><entry>Definitive Media Library</entry></row><row><entry>
DNS`</entry><entry>Domain Name Service</entry></row><row><entry>
DSCP</entry><entry>Differentiated Services Code Point</entry></row><row><entry>
E2E</entry><entry>End to End (E2E)</entry></row><row><entry>
eBGP</entry><entry>External BGP</entry></row><row><entry>
ECM</entry><entry>Electronic Counter Measures</entry></row><row><entry>
EG</entry><entry>AMN Executive Group</entry></row><row><entry>
EVE</entry><entry>Effective Visible Execution Module (FAS)</entry></row><row><entry>
FAS</entry><entry>Functional Area System</entry></row><row><entry>
FDCM</entry><entry>Final Disconnection Coord Meeting</entry></row><row><entry>
FMS</entry><entry>Foreign Military Sales</entry></row><row><entry>
FP</entry><entry>Force Protection</entry></row><row><entry>
FRAGO</entry><entry>Fragmentary Order</entry></row><row><entry>
FS</entry><entry>Functional Service</entry></row><row><entry>
FSC</entry><entry>Forward Schedule of Change</entry></row><row><entry>
FTP</entry><entry>File Transfer Protocol</entry></row><row><entry>
GAL</entry><entry>Global Address List</entry></row><row><entry>
GeoMetOc</entry><entry>Geospatial Meteorological and Oceanographic</entry></row><row><entry>
GIRoA</entry><entry>Government of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan</entry></row><row><entry>
HN</entry><entry>Host Nation</entry></row><row><entry>
HPOV®</entry><entry>HP (Hewlett Packard) OpenView</entry></row><row><entry>
HTTP</entry><entry>Hypertext Transfer Protocol</entry></row><row><entry>
IANA</entry><entry>Internet Assigned Number Authority</entry></row><row><entry>
iBGP</entry><entry>internal BGP</entry></row><row><entry>
ICC</entry><entry>Integrated Command and Control (FAS)</entry></row><row><entry>
ICD</entry><entry>Interface Control Documentation</entry></row><row><entry>
ICMP</entry><entry>Internet Control Message Protocol</entry></row><row><entry>
IDC</entry><entry>Information Dominance Center (in IJC)</entry></row><row><entry>
IEC</entry><entry>International Electrotechnical Commission</entry></row><row><entry>
IED</entry><entry>Improvised Explosive Device</entry></row><row><entry>
IEEE</entry><entry>Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers</entry></row><row><entry>
IER</entry><entry>Information Exchange Requirement</entry></row><row><entry>
IETF</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force</entry></row><row><entry>
IFTS</entry><entry>ISAF Force Tracking System (FAS)</entry></row><row><entry>
IJC</entry><entry>ISAF Joint Command</entry></row><row><entry>
IKM</entry><entry>Information and Knowledge Management</entry></row><row><entry>
IOC</entry><entry>Initial Operating Capability</entry></row><row><entry>
IORRB</entry><entry>ISAF Operational Requirements Review Board</entry></row><row><entry>
IP</entry><entry>Internet Protocol</entry></row><row><entry>
IPM</entry><entry>Internet Performance Manager</entry></row><row><entry>
IPS</entry><entry>Intrusion Prevention System</entry></row><row><entry>
IPSLA</entry><entry>Internet Protocol Service Level Agreement</entry></row><row><entry>IPSLA-MA</entry><entry>IPSLA Management Agent</entry></row><row><entry>
IPT</entry><entry>Integrated Planning Team</entry></row><row><entry>
ISAB</entry><entry>ISAF Security Accreditation Board</entry></row><row><entry>
ISAF</entry><entry>International Security Assistance Force</entry></row><row><entry>ISFCC</entry><entry>ISAF Strategic Flight Coordination Centre</entry></row><row><entry>ISO</entry><entry>International Organization for Standardization</entry></row><row><entry>
ISR</entry><entry>Intelligence Surveillance and Reconnaissance</entry></row><row><entry>
ITU</entry><entry>International Telecommunication Union</entry></row><row><entry>
JALLC</entry><entry>Joint Analysis Lessons Learned Centre (Lisbon)</entry></row><row><entry>
JFC</entry><entry>Joint Force Command</entry></row><row><entry>
JFCBS</entry><entry>
JMEI</entry><entry>Joining, Membership and Exit Instructions</entry></row><row><entry>JOCWATCH</entry><entry>Joint Operations Centre Watchkeeper’s Log (FAS)</entry></row><row><entry>
JOIIS</entry><entry>Joint Operations/Intelligence Information System (FAS)</entry></row><row><entry>
JTS</entry><entry>Joint Targeting System (FAS)</entry></row><row><entry>
KAIA-N</entry><entry>Kabul International Airport – North (the military portion of the Airport)</entry></row><row><entry>
KPI</entry><entry>Key Performance Indicators</entry></row><row><entry>
LAN</entry><entry>Local Area Network</entry></row><row><entry>
LNO</entry><entry>Liaison Officer</entry></row><row><entry>
LoA</entry><entry>Letter of Agreement</entry></row><row><entry>
LogFAS</entry><entry>Logistics Functional Area System</entry></row><row><entry>
LOS</entry><entry>Line of Sight</entry></row><row><entry>
mBGP</entry><entry>Multi Protocol BGP</entry></row><row><entry>
MAJIIC</entry><entry>Multi-Sensor Aerospace-Ground Joint Intelligence, Surveillance and Reconnaissance (ISR) interoperability coalition</entry></row><row><entry>
MCI</entry><entry>Mission Critical Information</entry></row><row><entry>
MEDEVAC</entry><entry>Medical Evacuation</entry></row><row><entry>
MIP</entry><entry>Multilateral Interoperability Programme</entry></row><row><entry>
MMR</entry><entry>minimum military requirement</entry></row><row><entry>
MNDDP</entry><entry>Multinational Detailed (re)Deployment Plan </entry></row><row><entry>
MOU</entry><entry>Memorandum of Understanding</entry></row><row><entry>
MTU</entry><entry>Maximum Transmission Unit</entry></row><row><entry>
NAT</entry><entry>Network Address Translation</entry></row><row><entry>
NATEX</entry><entry>National Expert</entry></row><row><entry>
NC3B</entry><entry>NATO Consultation, Command And Control Board</entry></row><row><entry>
NCI Agency</entry><entry>NATO Communications and Information Agency</entry></row><row><entry>
NCIO</entry><entry>NATO Communications and Information Organisation</entry></row><row><entry>
NCIRC TC</entry><entry>NATO Computer Incident Response Capability Technical Centre</entry></row><row><entry>
NDSS</entry><entry>NATO Depot and Supply System (FAS)</entry></row><row><entry>
NETOPS</entry><entry>Network Operations</entry></row><row><entry>
NIMP</entry><entry>NATO Information Management Policy</entry></row><row><entry>
NIMM</entry><entry>NATO Information Management Manual </entry></row><row><entry>
NIP</entry><entry>Network Interconnection Point</entry></row><row><entry>
NITB</entry><entry>NATO Intel Toolbox (FAS)</entry></row><row><entry>
NRA</entry><entry>NATO Registration Authority</entry></row><row><entry>
NOS</entry><entry>NATO Office of Security</entry></row><row><entry>
NRT</entry><entry>Near Real Time</entry></row><row><entry>
NSAB</entry><entry>NATO Security Accreditation Board</entry></row><row><entry>
NTM-A</entry><entry>NATO Training Mission - Afghanistan</entry></row><row><entry>
NU</entry><entry>NATO Unclassified</entry></row><row><entry>
OAIS</entry><entry>Open Archival information System</entry></row><row><entry>
OF-5</entry><entry>Officer Rank (Colonel or Equiv)</entry></row><row><entry>
OPORDER</entry><entry>Operational Order</entry></row><row><entry>
OPT</entry><entry>Operational Planning Team</entry></row><row><entry>
OU</entry><entry>Organizational Unit</entry></row><row><entry>
PDF/A</entry><entry>Portable Document Format used for digital preservation of electronic documents</entry></row><row><entry>
PDIM</entry><entry>Primary Directive on Information Management</entry></row><row><entry>
PE</entry><entry>Peacetime Establishment (manpower)</entry></row><row><entry>
PKI</entry><entry>Public Key Infrastructure</entry></row><row><entry>
PNG</entry><entry>Packet Network Gateways</entry></row><row><entry>
POC</entry><entry>Point of Contact</entry></row><row><entry>
PoP</entry><entry>Point of Presence</entry></row><row><entry>
RFC</entry><entry>Request for Change (ITIL)</entry></row><row><entry>
RFC</entry><entry>Request for Comments (Network Working Group, IETF)</entry></row><row><entry>
PRT</entry><entry>Provincial Reconstruction Team</entry></row><row><entry>
QoS</entry><entry>Quality of Service</entry></row><row><entry>
RC</entry><entry>Regional Command</entry></row><row><entry>
RAMNOC</entry><entry>Regional Afghanistan Mission Network Operations Centre</entry></row><row><entry>
RFC</entry><entry>Request for Change</entry></row><row><entry>
RIR</entry><entry>Regional Internet Registry</entry></row><row><entry>
RLP</entry><entry>Recognised Logistics Picture</entry></row><row><entry>
RT</entry><entry>Real Time</entry></row><row><entry>
SACM</entry><entry>Service Asset and Configuration Management</entry></row><row><entry>SCCM</entry><entry>System Center Configuration Manager</entry></row><row><entry>
SDD</entry><entry>Service Delivery Division (NCI Agency (Service Delivery))</entry></row><row><entry>
SDE®</entry><entry>Service Desk Express (FAS)</entry></row><row><entry>
SGI</entry><entry>Supplementary Geospatial Information (supplementary to DGI)</entry></row><row><entry>
SHAPE</entry><entry>Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe (i.e. HQ ACO)</entry></row><row><entry>
SLA</entry><entry>Service Level Agreement</entry></row><row><entry>
SME</entry><entry>Subject Matter Expert</entry></row><row><entry>
SMF</entry><entry>Service Management Framework (Implementation of ITIL)</entry></row><row><entry>
SMF</entry><entry>Single-mode optical fibre (Equipment)</entry></row><row><entry>
SMTP</entry><entry>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol</entry></row><row><entry>
SNMP</entry><entry>Simple Network Management Protocol </entry></row><row><entry>
SNMP MIB</entry><entry>Simple Network Management Protocol Management information base</entry></row><row><entry>
SoC</entry><entry>Statement of Compliance</entry></row><row><entry>
SoF</entry><entry>Special Operations Forces</entry></row><row><entry>
SOP</entry><entry>Standard Operating Procedure</entry></row><row><entry>
SRTS</entry><entry>Service Requesting Tasking System</entry></row><row><entry>
SSH</entry><entry>Secure Shell</entry></row><row><entry>
SSL</entry><entry>Secure Sockets Layer</entry></row><row><entry>
STD</entry><entry>Standard</entry></row><row><entry>
SVT</entry><entry>Service Validation and Testing</entry></row><row><entry>
TA </entry><entry>Technical Agreement</entry></row><row><entry>
TACACS+</entry><entry>Terminal Access Controller Access Control System plus</entry></row><row><entry>
TCN</entry><entry>Troop Contributing Nation</entry></row><row><entry>
TDS</entry><entry>Trusted Data Sources</entry></row><row><entry>
THoC</entry><entry>Theatre Head of Contracts</entry></row><row><entry>
TMO</entry><entry>Technical Management Office (of the AMN Secretariat)</entry></row><row><entry>
TNMA</entry><entry>Theatre Network Management Architect</entry></row><row><entry>
TOA</entry><entry>Transfer of Authority</entry></row><row><entry>
TPT</entry><entry>Technical Planning Team</entry></row><row><entry>
TRN</entry><entry>Theatre Route Network</entry></row><row><entry>
TSSB</entry><entry>Theatre Sustainment and Synchronisation Board</entry></row><row><entry>
TTP</entry><entry>Tactics, Techniques and Procedures</entry></row><row><entry>
UDP</entry><entry>User Datagram Protocol</entry></row><row><entry>
VoIP</entry><entry>Voice over IP</entry></row><row><entry>
VoSIP</entry><entry>Voice over Secure IP</entry></row><row><entry>
VM</entry><entry>Virtual Machine</entry></row><row><entry>
VTC</entry><entry>Video Tele Conference</entry></row><row><entry>
WAN</entry><entry>Wide Area Network</entry></row><row><entry>
WebTAS®</entry><entry>Web Enabled Temporal Analysis System (FAS)</entry></row><row><entry>
WSUS®</entry><entry>Windows Server Update Services</entry></row><row><entry>
XML</entry><entry>Extensible Mark-up Language</entry></row></tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>References</title>
<para>
      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-References">
        <title>References</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="70*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Reference</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
        <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>ADaTP-34(F)Vol4D Jan 2012</entry>
              <entry>Allied Data Publication 34 (ADaTP-34(F)) STANAG 5524, NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles (NISP), Volume 4 Interoperability Profiles and Guidance, Section D (page 93), The AMN Profile of NATO Interoperability Standards. 19 January 2012. NATO UNCLASSIFIED. [Commencing page 335 in pdf file NU-NISPv6-ADatP34(F)]</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>AC/322-N(2012)0092-AS1</entry>
              <entry>NATO Consultation Command and Control Board. C3 Classification Taxonomy. AC/322- N(2012)0092-AS1. 19 June 2012. NATO UNCLASSIFIED. [NU-AC322-N(2012)0092-AS1.pdf]</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>MCM-0125-2012</entry>
              <entry>Military Committee. Future Mission Network Concept MCM-0125-2012. 19 November 2012. NATO UNCLASSIFIED.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>NC3A TN1417</entry>
              <entry>NATO C3 Agency. Reference Document 2933, IP QoS Standardisation for the NII, RC 7, R.M. van Selm, G. Szabo, R. van Engelshoven, R. Goode, NATO C3 Agency, The Hague, The Netherlands, 15 June 2010 (Pre publication of Technical Note 1417, expected Q4 2010).NATO Unclassified [NU-RD2933-IP-QoS-Standard-for-the-NII-draft-rc7.pdf]</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>NCIA TR-2013/SPW008910/01</entry>
              <entry>Friedrich, G. Federated Mission Networking Interoperability Standards Profile for Mission Execution Environments, version 0.7 (FMN Profile v0.7). NATO Communications and Information Agency Technical Report  TR-2013/SPW008910/01. 20 September 2013.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>SHAPE CCD J6/CISOPAMN/66/13</entry>
              <entry>SHAPE CCD J6. Afghanistan Mission Network Governance Directive – Version 2. SH/CCD J6/CISOPAMN/66/13. 15 April 2013. NATO UNCLASSIFIED.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Thales ICD NIP Dec 2012</entry>
              <entry>THALES Customer Service & Support, NATO SATCOM & FOC CIS for ISAF Interface Control Document (ICD) Between CISAF network and TCN networks. ICD NIP TCN_62543313_558_L. 13 December 2012, NATO UNCLASSIFIED. [NU-ICD NIP TCN_62543313_558_L.pdf]</entry>
            </row>
		</tbody>
        </tgroup>
	</table>
</para>
</sect1>
</appendix>
