<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 3 -   A N N E X Web Services
*****************************************************************  
-->

<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>

<appendix id="v3-WSP">
          <title>Web Services Profiles</title>
            <sect1>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>The Web Services Interoperability organization (WS-I) is a
            global industry organization that promotes consistent and reliable
            interoperability among Web services across platforms, applications
            and programming languages. They are providing Profiles
            (implementation guidelines), Sample Applications (web services
            demonstrations), and Tools (to monitor Interoperability). The
            forward looking WS-I is enhancing the current Basic Profile and
            providing guidance for interoperable asynchronous and reliable
            messaging. WS-I's profiles will be critical for making Web
            services interoperability a practical reality.</para>
            <para>The first charter, a revision to the existing WS-I Basic
            Profile Working Group charter, resulted in the development of the
            Basic Profile 1.2 and the future development of the Basic Profile
            2.0. The Basic Profile 1.2 will incorporate asynchronous messaging
            and will also consider SOAP 1.1 with Message Transmission
            Optimization Mechanism (MTOM) and XML-binary optimized Packaging
            (XOP). The Basic Profile 2.0 will build on the Basic Profile 1.2
            and will be based on SOAP 1.2 with MTOM and XOP. The second
            charter establishes a new working group, the Reliable Secure
            Profile Working Group, which will deliver guidance to Web services
            architects and developers concerning reliable messaging with
            security.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: In 2006, work began
            on Basic Profile 2.0 and the Reliable Secure Profile 1.0. In 2007
            the Basic Profile 1.2, the Basic Security Profile 1.0 was
            approved. More information about WS-I can be found at
            www.ws-i.org.</para>
          </sect1>

</appendix>
