<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 3 -   A N N E X - G - SIP Template Document

*****************************************************************  
-->

<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>

<appendix id="v3-g">
  <title>Service Interface Profile (SIP) Template Document
  </title>

  <sect1>
    <title>References</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>[C3 Taxonomy] C3 Classification Taxonomy v. 1.0, AC/322-N(2012)0092</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[CESF 1.2] Core Enterprise Services Framework v. 1.2, AC/322-D(2009)0027</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[DEUeu SDS] Technical Service Data Sheet. Notification Broker v.002, IABG</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[NAF 3.0] NATO Architectural Framework v. 3.0, AC/322-D(2007)0048</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[NC3A RD-3139] Publish/Subscribe Service Interface Profile Proposal v.1.0,
          NC3A RD-3139</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[NDMS] Guidance On The Use Of Metadata Element Descriptions For Use In
          The NATO Discovery Metadata Specification (NDMS). Version 1.1, AC/322-D(2006)0007</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[NISP] NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[NNEC FS] NNEC Feasibility Study v. 2.0</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[RFC 2119] Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels, IETF</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[SOA Baseline] Core Enterprise Services Standards Recommendations. The
          Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) Baseline Profile, AC/322-N(20122)0205</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://ws-i.org/Profiles/BasicProfile-1.2-2010-11-09.html#philosophy">[WS-I Basic Profile]</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Background</title>
    <para>Within the heterogeneous NATO environment, experience has shown that different
      services implement differing standards, or even different profiles of
      the same standards. This means that the interfaces between the services
      of the CES need to be tightly defined and controlled. This is the only
      way to achieve interoperability between diverse systems and system implementations.
      Recommendations for the use of specific open standards for the individual
      CES are laid down in the C3B document “CES Standards Recommendations -
      The SOA Baseline Profile” [SOA Baseline], which will also be included
      as a dedicated CES set of standards in the upcoming NISP version.</para>
    <para>Our experience shows that while open standards are a good starting point,
      they are often open to different interpretations which lead to interoperability
      issues. Further profiling is required and this has been independently
      recognised by NCIA (under ACT sponsorship) and IABG (under sponsorship
      of IT-AmtBw).</para>
    <para>The SDS (for example [DEU SDS], IABG) and SIP (for example [NC3A RD-3139],
      NCIA) have chosen slightly different approaches. The SIP tries to be implementation
      agnostic, focusing on interface and contract specification, with no (or
      minimal, optional and very clearly marked) deviations from the underlying
      open standard. The SDS is more implementation specific, providing internal
      implementation details and in some cases extends or modifies the underlying
      open standard, based on specific National requirements. Our previous experience
      with the former CES WG while working on [SOA Baseline] is that Nations
      will not accept any implementation details that might constrain National
      programmes. Therefore, a safer approach seems to focus on the external
      interfaces and protocol specification.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Scope</title>
    <para>The aim of this document is to define a template based on the NCIA and
      IABG proposal for a standard profiling document, which from now on will
      be called Service Interface Profile (SIP).</para>
    <para>Additionally, this document provides guiding principles and how the profile
      relates to other NATO documentation.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Service Interface Profile Relationships to Other Documents</title>
    <para>SIPs were introduced in the NNEC Feasibility Study [NNEC FS] and further
      defined in subsequent NATO documents. In essence:</para>
    <para>SIP describes the stack-of-standards that need to be implemented at an
      interface, as described in the [NNEC FS]</para>
    <para>SIPs are technology dependent and are subject to change - provisions need
      to be made to allow SIPs to evolve over time (based on [NNEC FS])</para>
    <para>SIP represents the technical properties of a key interface used to achieve
      interoperability within a federation of systems (see [NAF 3.0])</para>
    <para>SIP reference documents to be provided by NATO in concert with the Nations
      (see [CESF 1.2])</para>
    <para>The SIP will not be an isolated document, but will have relationships
      with many other external and NATO resources, as depicted in the picture
      <xref linkend="SIP-documentrelationships" endterm="SIP-documentrelationships-title"/>:</para>
    <figure id="SIP-documentrelationships" float="0">
      <title id="SIP-documentrelationships-title">Document relationships</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="../figures/SIP_Document_Relationships.svg" format="SVG" />
         </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>[C3 Taxonomy] – the C3 Taxonomy captures concepts from various communities
          and maps them for item classification, integration and harmonization purposes.
          It provides a tool to synchronize all capability activities for Consultation,
          Command and Control (C3) in the NATO Alliance. The C3 Taxonomy level 1
          replaces the Overarching Architecture.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Reference Architectures – defined for specific subject areas to guide
          programme execution.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[NISP] – provides a minimum profile <footnote><para>Please note that word
          “profile” can be used at different levels of abstraction and slightly
          different meanings. In the NISP context, “profile” means a minimal set
          of standards identified for a given subject area (e.g. AMN Profile, CES/SOA
          Baseline Profile). In the context of SIP, “profile” means more detailed
          technical properties of an interface specified with a given standard(s).</para></footnote>
          of services and standards that are sufficient to provide
          a useful level of interoperability.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[SOA Baseline] – recommends a set of standards to fulfil an initial subset
          of the Core Enterprise Service requirements by providing a SOA baseline
          infrastructure. As such, it is intended to be incorporated into the NISP
          as a dedicated CES set of standards.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>SIPs - will provide a normative profile of standards used to implement
          a given service. As such it provides further clarification to standards
          as provided in the NISP/SOA Baseline. The SIP may also contain NATO specific
          and agreed extensions to given standards.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>There will be multiple national/NATO implementations of a given SIP. These
          implementations must implement all mandatory elements of a SIP and in
          addition can provide own extensions, which can be documented in a Nationally
          defined document, e.g. in a form of a Service Description Sheet.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The process, governance and the responsible bodies for the SIPs need to
      be urgently determined. This includes the implementation of a repository
      to store the different artefacts.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Guiding principles for a consolidated SIP/SDS Profile</title>
    <para>The following guiding principles derived from the WS-I Basic Profile<footnote><para>Based
      on <ulink url="http://ws-i.org/Profiles/BasicProfile-1.2-2010-11-09.html#philosophy"/></para></footnote>
      are proposed to drive the development of a consolidated SIP/SDS Profile:</para>
    <para>The Profile SHOULD provide further clarifications to open and NATO standards
      and specifications. This cannot guarantee complete interoperability, but
      will address the most common interoperability problems experienced to
      date.</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Profile SHOULD NOT repeat referenced specifications but make them
          more precise.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Profile SHOULD make strong requirements (e.g., MUST, MUST NOT) wherever
          feasible; if there are legitimate cases where such a requirement cannot
          be met, conditional requirements (e.g., SHOULD, SHOULD NOT) are used.
          Optional and conditional requirements introduce ambiguity and mismatches
          between implementations. The keywords "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED",
          "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
          "OPTIONAL" are to be interpreted as described in [IETF RFC 2119].</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Profile SHOULD make statements that are testable wherever possible.
          Preferably, testing is achieved in a non-intrusive manner (e.g., by examining
          artefacts "on the wire").</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Profile MUST provide information on externally visible interfaces,
          behaviour and protocols, but it SHOULD NOT provide internal implementation
          details. It MAY also state non-functional requirements to the service
          (e.g., notification broker must store subscription information persistently
          in order to survive system shutdown).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Profile MUST clearly indicate any deviations and extensions from the
          underlying referenced specifications. It is RECOMMENDED that any extensions
          make use of available extensibility points in the underlying specification.
          The extensions MUST be made recommended or optional in order to not break
          interoperability with standard-compliant products (e.g. COTS) that will
          not be able to support NATO specific extensions. Extensions SHOULD be
          kept to the minimum.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>When amplifying the requirements of referenced specifications, the Profile
          MAY restrict them (e.g., change a MAY to a MUST), but not relax them (e.g.,
          change a MUST to a MAY).</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If a referenced specification allows multiple mechanisms to be used interchangeably,
          the Profile SHOULD select those that best fulfil NATO requirements, are
          well-understood, widely implemented and useful. Extraneous or underspecified
          mechanisms and extensions introduce complexity and therefore reduce interoperability.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Backwards compatibility with deployed services is not a goal of the SIP,
          but due consideration is given to it.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Although there are potentially a number of inconsistencies and design
          flaws in the referenced specifications, the SIP MUST only address those
          that affect interoperability.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Proposed structure for a consolidated SIP/SDS Profile</title>
    <para>Based on analysis of the “Technical Service Data Sheet for Notification
      Broker v.002”, [NC3A RD-3139] and “RD-3139 Publish/Subscribe Service Interface
      Profile Proposal v.1.0” [DEU SDS] the following document structure is
      proposed for the consolidated Profile:</para>
      <table>
        <title>Service Interface Profile</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Section</emphasis></entry>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Keywords</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Should contain relevant names of the [C3 Taxonomy] services plus other
                relevant keywords like the names of profiled standards.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Metadata </emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Metadata of the document, that should be based on the NATO Discovery Metadata
                Specification [NDMS] and MUST include: Security classification, Service
                name (title), Version, Unique identifier, Date, Creator, Subject, Description,
                Relation with other SIPs. The unique identifier MUST encode a version
                number and C3 Board needs to decide on a namespace. It needs to be decided
                whether URN or URL should be used to format the identifier.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>General description of the service being profiled.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Record of changes and amendments</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>The list of changes should include version number, date, originator and
                main changes. The originator should identify an organisation/Nation (not
                a person).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Table of Contents</emphasis></entry>
              <entry><emphasis role="italic">Self-explanatory</emphasis></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Table of Figures</emphasis></entry>
              <entry><emphasis role="italic">Self-explanatory</emphasis></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">1. Introduction</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Should provide an overview about the key administrative information and
                the goals/non-goals of the service</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">1.1 Purpose of the document</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Same for all SIPs. Does not contain a service specific description. <emphasis role="italic">“Provide a set of specifications, along with clarifications, refinements, interpretations and amplifications of those specifications which promote interoperability.”</emphasis></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">1.2 Audience</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>The envisioned audience consists of: Project Managers procuring Bi-SC
                or NNEC related systems; The architects and developers of service consumers
                and providers; Coalition partners whose services may need to interact
                with NNEC Services; Systems integrators delivering systems into the NATO
                environment</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">1.3 Notational Conventions</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Describes the notational conventions for this document: <emphasis role="italic">italics</emphasis> Syntax derived from underpinning standards should use the Courier font.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">1.4 Taxonomy allocation</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Provides information on the position and description of the service within
                the [C3 Taxonomy]</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">1.5 Terminology/Definitions</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Introducing service specific terminology used in the document with short
                descriptions for every term.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">1.6 Namespaces</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Table with the prefix and the namespaces used in the document.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">1.7 Goals</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Service specific goals of the profile. They will tell which aspects of
                the service will be covered by the profile, e.g. identify specific protocols,
                data structures, security mechanisms etc.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">1.8 Non-goals</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>An explanation for not addressing the listed non-goals potentially relevant
                in a given context. This section may contain references to external documents
                dealing with the identified issues (e.g. security mechanisms are described
                in different SIP/document).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">1.9 References</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Normative and non-normative references to external specifications.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">1.10 Service relationship</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Relationships to other services in the [C3 Taxonomy].</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold"> 1.11 Constraints</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Preconditions to run the service; when to use and when not to use the
                service. <emphasis role="italic">service is not intended to work with encrypted messages</emphasis>”</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">2. Background (non-normative)</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Descriptive part of the document</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">2.1 Description of the operational requirements </emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Description of the operational background of the service to give an overview
                where and in which environment the service will be deployed.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">2.2 Description of the Service</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Purpose of the service, its functionality and intended use. Which potential
                issues can be solved with this service?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">2.3 Typical Service Interactions</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Most typical interactions the service can take part in. Should provide
                better understanding and potential application of a service and its context.
                This part is non-normative and will not be exhaustive (i.e. is not intended
                to illustrate all possible interactions). Interactions can be illustrated
                using UML interaction, sequence, use case, and/or state diagrams.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">3. Service Interface Specification (normative)</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Prescriptive part of the document (not repeating the specification)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">3.1 Interface Overview</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Introduction with a short description (containing operations, etc.) of
                the interface. Short overview table with all operations identifying which
                ones are defined by the SIP as mandatory, recommended or optional. Any
                extensions to underlying services (e.g. new operations) must be clearly
                marked. Specific example: Response “service unavailable” if operations
                are not implemented/available.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">3.2 Technical Requirements</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Description of the specific technical requirements. Generic non-functional
                requirements</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">3.3 Operations </emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Detailed description of mandatory, recommended and optional operations:
                input, output, faults, sequence diagram if necessary. Clearly mark extensions
                to the underlying referenced standards. Any non-standard behaviour must
                be explicitly requested and described, including specific operations or
                parameters to initiate it. Specific examples : Explicitly request non-standard
                filter mode; explicitly request particular transport mode. - Internal
                faults could be handled as an unknown error. Additional information (internal
                error code) can be ignored by the user.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">3.4 Errors (Optional section)</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Description of the specific errors and how the recipient is informed about
                them.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">4. References</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Contains document references.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">Appendices (optional) </emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Service specific artefacts (non-normative and normative), e.g. WSDLs /
                Schemas for specific extensions</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Testing</title>
    <para>As indicated in the guiding principles, the profile should make statements
      that are testable. An attempt should be made to make any testable assertions
      in SIPs explicit in a similar way to the WS-I profiles, i.e. by highlighting
      the testable assertions and even codifying them such that an end user
      of the SIP can run them against their service to check conformance. It
      should also be possible to come up with testing tools and scenarios similar
      to those defined by the WS-I for the Basic
      Profile<footnote><para><ulink url="http://www.ws-i.org/docs/BPTestMethodology-WorkingGroupApprovalDraft-042809.pdf"/></para></footnote>.</para>
    <para>It needs to be decided how formal testing could be organized. Possibilities
      include dedicated testing body, multinational venues and exercises (like
      CWIX) and others.</para>
  </sect1>
</appendix>
