<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 3 - FMN SPIRAL 1.1 PROFILE
*****************************************************************  
-->

<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v3-fmn-spiral-1">
  <title>Federated Mission Networking Spiral 1.1 Standards Profile</title>
<!--     <figure id="f3-fmn-logo">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/FMN_Logo_Color_With_Text_Side.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        </figure>
--> 
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This document defines the Standards Profile for Federated
    Mission Networking (FMN) Spiral 1. FMN Standards Profiles provide
    a suite of interoperability standards and other standardized
    profiles for interoperability of selected community of interest
    services, core services and communications services in a
    federation of mission networks. It places the required
    interoperability requirements, standards and specifications in
    context for FMN Affiliates.</para>
    
    <para>FMN Standards Profiles are generic specifications at a
    logical level. They allow for independent national technical
    service implementations, without the loss of essential
    interoperability aspects.</para>
    
    <para>FMN is founded on a service-oriented approach. The
    interoperability standards applicable to these services are
    identified and specified in line with the NATO C3 Taxonomy.</para>
<sect2>
<title>Disclaimer</title>
<para>The information in this document is derived from the Enterprise Mapping (EM) Wiki, a data analysis and enterprise architecture tool based on Semantic MediaWiki technology and hosted by the Technology and Human Factors (THF) Branch at Headquarters Supreme Allied Commander Transformation (HQ SACT).</para>
<para>This document is generated overnight in an automated process and stamped with a date on the cover page. Hence, a baselined version is not exclusively identified by a version marking and the date on the cover must be used for version control.</para>
</sect2>
    
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>The diagram below presents an overview of the profile structure.</para>

      <figure id="f3-fmn-profiles">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/fmn-profile-structure.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        </figure>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
<title>FMN Spiral 1 Profile</title>  
<sect2>
  <title>Scope</title>

    <para>The Federated Mission Networking (FMN) Spiral 1 standards profile defines interface standards for the services that are required to deploy a Mission Network Elements (FMN capability option A). Mission Network Extensions (option B) and Hosted Users (option C) may not meet these minimum service and service interoperability requirements. Connectivity and service provision throughout the federation is regulated by hosting agreements between participants.</para>
    
   <para>FMN Spiral 1 refers to an FMN maturity level in which separate physical infrastructures exist per mission and per security classification level. This spiral is an evolution of the fielded baseline of the Afghanistan Mission Network (AMN). Notably, biometrics interoperability standards were removed and the network architecture has changed from a hub-and-spoke to a
meshed concept.</para>

   <para>Mission Network Extensions must be provided with their local area networks (including IP management) within the physical and cyber security boundaries of the hosting Mission Network Element. The services must function in a network environment that contains firewalls and various routing and filtering schemes; therefore, developers must use standards and well-known port specifications wherever possible, and document non-standard configurations as part of their service interface.</para>

  </sect2> 

  <sect2>
    <title>Interoperability</title>

    <para>In the context of Federated Mission Networking, the purpose of standardization is to enable interoperability in a multi-vendor, multi-network, multi-service environment. Technical interoperability must be an irrefutable and inseparable element in capability development and system implementation - without it, it is not possible to realize connections and service deliveries across the federation and hence, information sharing will not be achieved.</para>

    <para>Within NATO, interoperability is defined as "the ability to act together coherently, effectively and efficiently to achieve allied tactical, operational and strategic objectives". In the context of information exchange, interoperability means that a system, unit or forces of any service, nation can transmit data to and receive data from any other system, unit or forces of any service
or nation, and use the exchanged data to operate effectively together.</para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>Standards and Profiles</title>
    
    <para>For successful Federated Mission Networking, technical
    interface standards are critical enablers that have to be
    collectively followed and for which conformity by all
    participating members is important.</para>

    <para>Standards are aggregated in profiles. A standards profile is
    a set of standards for a particular purpose, covering certain
    services in the C3 taxonomy, with a guidance on implementation
    when and where needed. As profiles serve a particular purpose,
    they can be used in different environments, and therefore, they
    are not specific to a single overarching operational or technical
    concept. Profiles for Federated Mission Networking may and will be
    reused in other profiles.</para>

    <para>Generally, the scope of a profile in the EM Wiki is limited:
    it will focus on only a few services and a limited scope of
    functionality. Therefore, a full profile with a wider scope
    (ranging to an environment, a system or a concept) will have to
    consist of a selection of profiles, that together cover the full
    capability of that overarching profile. For organization of these
    standards and profiles, the overarching profile - in this case the
    FMN Spiral 1 Profile - is broken down in a hierarchical tree that
    forms a number of functional branches, ending in the leaves that
    are the profiles which contain the actual assignments of standards
    and their implementation guidance.</para>

    <para>In the profiles, interoperability standards fall into four
    obligation categories:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Mandatory - Mandatory interoperability standards must be met to enable Federated Mission Networking</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Conditional - Conditional interoperability standards must be present under certain specific circumstances</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Recommended - Recommended interoperability standards may be excluded for valid reasons in particular circumstances, but the full implications must be understood and carefully weighed</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Optional - Optional interoperability standards are truly optional</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Sources</title>
    
    <para>The interoperability standards profile in this document is derived from standards that are maintained by a selection of
standardization organizations and conformity and interoperability resources. Some of these are included in the NATO
Interoperability Standards and Profiles. Furthermore, standards are used from:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>International Organization for Standardization (ISO) standards</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>International Electrotechnical Commission (IEC) standards</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>International Telecommunication Union (ITU) Radiocommunication (R) Recommendations</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>International Telecommunication Union (ITU) Telecommunication (T) Recommendations</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) Requests for Comments (RFC)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) Recommendations</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Multilateral Interoperability Programme (MIP) standards</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Secure Communications Interoperability Profiles (SCIP)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP) Extension Protocols (XEP)</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Federated Communications and Networking Profile</title>

    <para>The Federated Communications and Networking Profile arranges
    standards profiles for the facilitation of the platform and
    communications infrastructure of federated mission
    networks.</para>

    <sect3>
       <title>Federated Communications Profile</title>

       <para>The Federated Communications Profile arranges standards profiles for the addressing, routing, forwarding, quality and
       security of IP traffic over federated mission networks.</para>
       
      <?dbmerge profile="fmn-fed-com"?>

    </sect3>


    <sect3>
      <title>Federated Networking Profile</title>

      <para>The Federated Networking Profile arranges standards
      profiles for the establish network logic above the
      communications layer of federated mission networks.</para>

      <?dbmerge profile="fmn-fed-net"?>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Federated Human-to-Human Communications Profile</title>

    <para>The Federated Human-to-Human Communications Profile arranges
    standards profiles for the facilitation of information sharing and
    exchange on user platforms.</para>

    <sect3>
      <title>Federated Unified Collaboration Profile</title>

      <para>The Federated Unified Collaboration Profile arranges
      standards profiles for a range of interoperable collaboration
      capabilities to support real-time situational updates to
      time-critical planning activities between coalition partners,
      communities of interest and other participants. Levels of
      collaboration include awareness, shared information,
      coordination and joint product development.</para>

      <?dbmerge profile="fmn-uni-collab"?>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Federated Information Management Profile</title>

      <para>The Federated Information Management Profile arranges standards profiles for the handling of information throughout its
life-cycle and the support of capabilities to organize, store and retrieve information through services and managed processes,
governed by policies, directives, standards, profiles and guidelines.</para>

      <?dbmerge profile="fmn-fed-inf-mgnt"?>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Federated Web Hosting Profile</title>
      <para>The Federated Web Hosting Profile arranges standards profiles for the facilitation of web-based services in a loosely coupled
environment, where flexible and agile service orchestration is a requirement on the basis of a Service Oriented Architecture
(SOA).</para>
      <?dbmerge profile="fmn-fed-web-host"?>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  </sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Related Information</title>
<sect2>
<title>Standards</title>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable1"><title>GeoRSS Geography Markup Language</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>GeoRSS Geography Markup Language</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Geography Markup Language (GML) is an XML grammar written in XML Schema for the modelling, transport, and storage of geographic information. GML provides a variety of kinds of objects for describing geography including features, coordinate reference systems, geometry, topology, time, units of measure and generalized values. A geographic feature is "an abstraction of a real world phenomenon; it is a geographic feature if it is associated with a location relative to the Earth?. So a digital representation of the real world can be thought of as a set of features.
GeoRSS GML represents the encoding of GeoRSS' objects in a simple GML version
3.1.1 profile. Each section details the construction of GeoRSS' five objects, followed by some informative use cases. As with all GeoRSS encodings, if not specified, the implied coordinate reference system is WGS84 with coordinates written in decimal degrees.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable2"><title>GeoRSS Simple</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>GeoRSS Simple</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The Simple serialization of GeoRSS is designed to be maximally concise, in both representation and conception. Each of the four GeoRSS objects require only a single tag.
This simplicity comes at the cost of direct upward compatibility with GML. However, it is straightforward to devise transformations from this Simple serialization to the GML serialization through the GML model. For many needs, GeoRSS Simple will be sufficient.
Some publishers and users may prefer to seperate lat/long pairs by a comma rather than whitespace. This is permissible in Simple; GeoRSS parsers should just treat commas as whitespace.
The first example shows GeoRSS Simple within an Atom 1.0 entry. This serialization applies just as well to an RSS 2.0 or RSS 1.0 item; it can also be associated with the entire feed. The rest of the examples show only the encoding of the objects and attributes.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable3"><title>IEEE 802.3</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Standard for Ethernet</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Ethernet local area network operation is specified for selected speeds of operation from 1 Mb/s to 100 Gb/s using a common media access control (MAC) specification and management information base (MIB). The Carrier Sense Multiple Access with Collision Detection (CSMA/CD) MAC protocol specifies shared medium (half duplex) operation, as well as full duplex operation. Speed specific Media Independent Interfaces (MIIs) allow use of selected Physical Layer devices (PHY) for operation over coaxial,
twisted-pair or fiber optic cables. System considerations for multisegment shared access networks describe the use of Repeaters that are defined for operational speeds up to 1000 Mb/s. Local Area Network (LAN) operation is supported at all speeds. Other specified capabilities include various PHY types for access networks, PHYs suitable for metropolitan area network applications, and the provision of power over selected twisted-pair PHY types.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>IEEE</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2013-08-27</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable4"><title>ISO 19005-1</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Document management -- Electronic document file format for long-term preservation -- Part 1: Use of PDF 1.4 (PDF/A-1)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>ISO 19005-1 specifies how to use the Portable Document Format (PDF) 1.4 for long-term preservation of electronic documents. It is applicable to documents containing combinations of character, raster and vector data.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Organization for Standardization (ISO)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2005-10-01</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable5"><title>ISO 19005-2</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Document management -- Electronic document file format for long-term preservation -- Part 2: Use of ISO 32000-1 (PDF/A-2)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>ISO 19005-2 specifies the use of the Portable Document Format (PDF) 1.7, as formalized in ISO 32000-1, for preserving the static visual representation of page-based electronic documents over time.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Organization for Standardization (ISO)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2011-07-01</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable6"><title>ISO 32000-1</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Document management -- Portable document format -- Part 1: PDF 1.7</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>ISO 32000-1 specifies a digital form for representing electronic documents to enable users to exchange and view electronic documents independent of the environment in which they were created or the environment in which they are viewed or printed. It is intended for the developer of software that creates PDF files (conforming writers), software that reads existing PDF files and interprets their contents for display and interaction (conforming readers) and PDF products that read and/or write PDF files for a variety of other purposes (conforming products).</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Organization for Standardization (ISO)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2008-07-01</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable7"><title>ISO/IEC 10918-1</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Information technology -- Digital compression and coding of continuous-tone still images: Requirements and guidelines</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This standard specifies processes for converting source image data to compressed image data, processes for converting compressed image data to reconstructed image data, coded representations for compressed image data, and gives guidance on how to implement these processes in practice. Is applicable to continuous-tone - grayscale or colour - digital still image data and to a wide range of applications which require use of compressed images. Is not applicable to bi-level image data.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Organization for Standardization (ISO)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1994-02-17</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable8"><title>ISO/IEC 10918-3</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Information technology -- Digital compression and coding of continuous-tone still images: Extensions</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This standard sets out requirements and guidelines for encoding and decoding extensions to the processes defined by CCITT Recommendation T.81 / ISO/IEC 10918-1, and for the coded representation of compressed image data of these extensions. This standard also defines tests for determining whether implementations comply with the requirements for the various encoding and decoding extensions.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Organization for Standardization (ISO)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1997-05-29</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable9"><title>ISO/IEC 11801</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Information technology - Generic cabling for customer premises</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Within customer premises, the importance of the cabling infrastructure is similar to that of other fundamental building utilities such as heating, lighting and mains power. As with other utilities, interruptions to service can have a serious impact. Poor quality of service due to lack of design foresight, use of inappropriate components, incorrect installation, poor administration or inadequate support can threaten an organisation's effectiveness.
This International Standard provides:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>users with an application independent generic cabling system capable of supporting a wide range of applications;</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>users with a flexible cabling scheme such that modifications are both easy and economical;</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>building professionals (for example, architects) with guidance allowing the accommodation of cabling before specific requirements are known; that is, in the initial planning either for construction or refurbishment;</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>industry and applications standardization bodies with a cabling system which supports current products and provides a basis for future product development.</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Organization for Standardization (ISO)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2002-09-01</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable10"><title>ISO/IEC 15445</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Information technology -- Document description and processing languages -- HyperText Markup Language (HTML)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The HyperText Markup Language (HTML) is an application of the International Standard ISO 8879 -- Standard Generalized Markup Language (SGML). It provides a simple way of structuring hypertext documents and of placing references in one document which point to another. This International Standard is a refinement of the World Wide Web Consortium's (W3C's) Recommendation for HTML 4.0: it provides further rules to condition and refine the use of the W3C Recommendation in a way which emphasizes the use of stable and mature features, and represents accepted SGML practice. Documents which conform to this International Standard also conform to the strict DTD provided by the W3C Recommendation for HTML 4.01.
This International Standard makes a clear and important distinction between conforming systems and validating systems. A conforming system operates correctly when handling documents which conform to this International Standard, but is not required to operate correctly when the documents do not conform. A validating system is more powerful: it detects all SGML and HTML errors in a document. Frequently browsers are conforming systems whereas authoring tools check for validity.
This International Standard does not define error handling procedures.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Organization for Standardization (ISO)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2000-05-15</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable11"><title>ISO/IEC 26300</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Information technology -- Open Document Format for Office Applications (OpenDocument) v1.0</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>ISO/IEC 26300 defines an XML schema for office applications and its semantics. The schema is suitable for office documents, including text documents, spreadsheets, charts and graphical documents like drawings or presentations, but is not restricted to these kinds of documents.
ISO/IEC 26300 provides for high-level information suitable for editing documents. It defines suitable XML structures for office documents and is friendly to transformations using XSLT or similar XML-based tools.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Organization for Standardization (ISO)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-12-01</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable12"><title>ITU-R Recommendation TF.460</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Standard-frequency and time-signal emissions</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Standard-frequency and time-signal emissions</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable13"><title>ITU-T Recommendation E.164</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>The international public telecommunication numbering plan</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The international public telecommunication numbering plan</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable14"><title>ITU-T Recommendation G.652</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Characteristics of a single-mode optical fibre and cable</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Characteristics of a single-mode optical fibre and cable</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable15"><title>ITU-T Recommendation G.722</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>7 kHz audio-coding within 64 kbit/s</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>7 kHz audio-coding within 64 kbit/s</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable16"><title>ITU-T Recommendation G.729</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Coding of speech at 8 kbit/s using conjugate-structure algebraic-code-excited linear prediction (CS-ACELP)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Coding of speech at 8 kbit/s using conjugate-structure algebraic-code-excited linear prediction (CS-ACELP)</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable17"><title>ITU-T Recommendation H.225.0</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Call signalling protocols and media stream packetization for packet-based multimedia communication systems</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Call signalling protocols and media stream packetization for packet-based multimedia communication systems</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable18"><title>ITU-T Recommendation H.239</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Role management and additional media channels for ITU-T H.300-series terminals</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Role management and additional media channels for ITU-T H.300-series terminals</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable19"><title>ITU-T Recommendation H.245</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Control protocol for multimedia communication</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Control protocol for multimedia communication</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable20"><title>ITU-T Recommendation H.263</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Video coding for low bit rate communication</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Video coding for low bit rate communication</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable21"><title>ITU-T Recommendation H.264</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Advanced video coding for generic audiovisual services</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Advanced video coding for generic audiovisual services</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable22"><title>ITU-T Recommendation H.323</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Packet-based multimedia communications systems</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Packet-based multimedia communications systems</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable23"><title>ITU-T Recommendation J.241</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Quality of service ranking and measurement methods for digital video services delivered over broadband IP networks</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Quality of service ranking and measurement methods for digital video services delivered over broadband IP networks</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable24"><title>ITU-T Recommendation M.2301</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Performance objectives and procedures for provisioning and maintenance of IP-based networks</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Performance objectives and procedures for provisioning and maintenance of IP-based networks</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable25"><title>ITU-T Recommendation V.150.1</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Modem-over-IP networks: Procedures for the end-to-end connection of V-series DCEs</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Modem-over-IP networks: Procedures for the end-to-end connection of V-series DCEs</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable26"><title>ITU-T Recommendation X.509</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Information technology - Open Systems Interconnection - The Directory: Public-key and attribute certificate frameworks</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Information technology - Open Systems Interconnection - The Directory: Public-key and attribute certificate frameworks</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable27"><title>ITU-T Recommendation Y.1540</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Internet protocol data communication service - IP packet transfer and availability performance parameters</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Internet protocol data communication service - IP packet transfer and availability performance parameters</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable28"><title>ITU-T Recommendation Y.1541</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Network performance objectives for IP-based services</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Network performance objectives for IP-based services</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable29"><title>ITU-T Recommendation Y.1542</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Framework for achieving end-to-end IP performance objectives</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Framework for achieving end-to-end IP performance objectives</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>International Telecommunications Union (ITU)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable30"><title>NISP Standard - IEC 61754-20</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Interface standard for LC connectors with protective housings related to IEC 61076-3-106</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This part of IEC 61754 covers connectors with protective housings. The housing is defined as variant 4 in IEC 61076-3-106:2006. These connectors use a push-pull coupling mechanism.
To connect the fibres inside the housing the LC interface is used as described in IEC 61754-20:2002.
The fully assembled variants (connectors) described in this document incorporate fixed and free connectors.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>IEC</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2012-05-01</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable31"><title>NISP Standard - REST</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Representational State Transfer (REST)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The World Wide Web has succeeded in large part because its software architecture has been designed to meet the needs of an Internet-scale distributed hypermedia application. The modern Web architecture emphasizes scalability of component interactions, generality of interfaces, independent deployment of components, and intermediary components to reduce interaction latency, enforce security, and encapsulate legacy systems. In this article we introduce the Representational State Transfer (REST) architectural style, developed as an abstract model of the Web architecture and used to guide our redesign and definition of the Hypertext Transfer Protocol and Uniform Resource Identifiers. We describe the software engineering principles guiding REST and the interaction constraints chosen to retain those principles, contrasting them to the constraints of other architectural styles. We then compare the abstract model to the currently deployed Web architecture in order to elicit mismatches between the existing protocols and the applications they are intended to support.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>ACM</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2000Z</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable32"><title>NISP Standard - STANAG 4290</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Standard for Gateway Multichannel Cable Link (Optical)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This STANAG defines the multiplexing scheme and physical connector for use with the fibre optical transmission in conjunction with the STANAG 4206 Tactical Digital Gateway.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>NATO Standardization Office</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2015-03-25</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable33"><title>RFC 0826</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Ethernet Address Resolution Protocol: Or Converting Network Protocol Addresses to 48.bit Ethernet Address for Transmission on Ethernet Hardware</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The implementation of protocol P on a sending host S decides, through protocol P's routing mechanism, that it wants to transmit to a target host T located some place on a connected piece of 10Mbit Ethernet cable. To actually transmit the Ethernet packet a 48.bit Ethernet address must be generated. The addresses of hosts within protocol P are not always compatible with the corresponding Ethernet address (being different lengths or values). Presented here is a protocol that allows dynamic distribution of the information needed to build tables to translate an address A in protocol P's address space into a 48.bit Ethernet address.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1982-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable34"><title>RFC 1034</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Domain names - concepts and facilities</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This RFC is an introduction to the Domain Name System (DNS), and omits many details which can be found in a companion RFC, "Domain Names - Implementation and Specification"(RFC-1035). That RFC assumes that the reader is familiar with the concepts discussed in this memo.
A subset of DNS functions and data types constitute an official protocol. The official protocol includes standard queries and their responses and most of the Internet class data formats (e.g., host addresses).</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1987-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable35"><title>RFC 1035</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Domain names - implementation and specification</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This RFC describes the details of the domain system and protocol, and assumes that the reader is familiar with the concepts discussed in a companion RFC, "Domain Names - Concepts and Facilities"(RFC-1034).
The domain system is a mixture of functions and data types which are an official protocol and functions and data types which are still experimental. Since the domain system is intentionally extensible, new data types and experimental behavior should always be expected in parts of the system beyond the official protocol. The official protocol parts include standard queries, responses and the Internet class RR data formats (e.g., host addresses).</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1987-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable36"><title>RFC 1112</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Host extensions for IP multicasting</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memo specifies the extensions required of a host implementation of the Internet Protocol (IP) to support multicasting. It is the recommended standard for IP multicasting in the Internet. Distribution of this memo is unlimited.
IP multicasting is the transmission of an IP datagram to a "host group", a set of zero or more hosts identified by a single IP destination address. A multicast datagram is delivered to all members of its destination host group with the same "best-efforts"reliability as regular unicast IP datagrams, i.e., the datagram is not guaranteed to arrive intact at all members of the destination group or in the same order relative to other datagrams.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1989-08Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable37"><title>RFC 1738</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Uniform Resource Locators (URL)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document specifies a Uniform Resource Locator (URL), the syntax and semantics of formalized information for location and access of resources via the Internet. The specification is derived from concepts introduced by the World- Wide Web global information initiative, whose use of such objects dates from 1990 and is described in "Universal Resource Identifiers in WWW", RFC 1630. The specification of URLs is designed to meet the requirements laid out in "Functional Requirements for Internet Resource Locators".</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1994-12Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable38"><title>RFC 1870</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>SMTP Service Extension for Message Size Declaration</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memo defines an extension to the SMTP service whereby an SMTP client and server may interact to give the server an opportunity to decline to accept a message (perhaps temporarily) based on the client's estimate of the message size.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1995-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable39"><title>RFC 1985</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>SMTP Service Extension for Remote Message Queue Starting</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memo defines an extension to the SMTP service whereby an SMTP client and server may interact to give the server an opportunity to start the processing of its queues for messages to go to a given host. This extension is meant to be used in startup conditions as well as for mail nodes that have transient connections to their service providers.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1996-08Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable40"><title>RFC 1997</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>BGP Communities Attribute</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Border Gateway Protocol is an inter-autonomous system routing protocol designed for TCP/IP internets. This document describes an extension to BGP which may be used to pass additional information to both neighboring and remote BGP peers. The intention of the proposed technique is to aid in policy administration and reduce the management complexity of maintaining the Internet.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1996-08Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable41"><title>RFC 2034</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>SMTP Service Extension for Returning Enhanced Error Codes</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memo defines an extension to the SMTP service (RFC-821, RFC-1869) whereby an SMTP server augments its responses with the enhanced mail system status codes defined in RFC 1893. These codes can then be used to provide more informative explanations of error conditions, especially in the context of the delivery status notifications format defined in RFC 1894.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1996-10Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable42"><title>RFC 2045</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) Part One: Format of Internet Message Bodies</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>STD 11, RFC 822, defines a message representation protocol specifying considerable detail about US-ASCII message headers, and leaves the message content, or message body, as flat US-ASCII text. This set of documents, collectively called the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions, or MIME, redefines the format of messages to allow for
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>textual message bodies in character sets other than US-ASCII,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>an extensible set of different formats for non-textual message bodies,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>multi-part message bodies, and</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>textual header information in character sets other than US-ASCII.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1996-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable43"><title>RFC 2046</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) Part Two: Media Types</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>STD 11, RFC 822 defines a message representation protocol specifying considerable detail about US-ASCII message headers, but which leaves the message content, or message body, as flat US-ASCII text. This set of documents, collectively called the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions, or MIME, redefines the format of messages to allow for
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>textual message bodies in character sets other than US-ASCII,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>an extensible set of different formats for non-textual message bodies,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>multi-part message bodies, and</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>textual header information in character sets other than US-ASCII.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1996-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable44"><title>RFC 2047</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>MIME (Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions) Part Three: Message Header Extensions for Non-ASCII Text</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>STD 11, RFC 822, defines a message representation protocol specifying considerable detail about US-ASCII message headers, and leaves the message content, or message body, as flat US-ASCII text. This set of documents, collectively called the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions, or MIME, redefines the format of messages to allow for
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>textual message bodies in character sets other than US-ASCII,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>an extensible set of different formats for non-textual message bodies,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>multi-part message bodies, and</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>textual header information in character sets other than US-ASCII.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1996-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable45"><title>RFC 2049</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) Part Five: Conformance Criteria and Examples</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>STD 11, RFC 822, defines a message representation protocol specifying considerable detail about US-ASCII message headers, and leaves the message content, or message body, as flat US-ASCII text. This set of documents, collectively called the Multipurpose Internet MaiL Extensions, or MIME, redefines the format of messages to allow for
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>textual message bodies in character sets other than US-ASCII,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>an extensible set of different formats for non-textual message bodies,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>multi-part message bodies, and</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>textual header information in character sets other than US-ASCII.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1996-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable46"><title>RFC 2181</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Clarifications to the DNS Specification</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document considers some areas that have been identified as problems with the specification of the Domain Name System, and proposes remedies for the defects identified. Eight separate issues are considered:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>IP packet header address usage from multi-homed servers,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>TTLs in sets of records with the same name, class, and type,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>correct handling of zone cuts,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>three minor issues concerning SOA records and their use,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>the precise definition of the Time to Live (TTL)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Use of the TC (truncated) header bit</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>the issue of what is an authoritative, or canonical, name,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>and the issue of what makes a valid DNS label.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1997-07Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable47"><title>RFC 2365</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Administratively Scoped IP Multicast</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the "administratively scoped IPv4 multicast space"to be the range 239.0.0.0 to 239.255.255.255. In addition, it describes a simple set of semantics for the implementation of Administratively Scoped IP Multicast. Finally, it provides a mapping between the IPv6 multicast address classes (RFC 1884) and IPv4 multicast address classes.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1998-07Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable48"><title>RFC 2409</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>The Internet Key Exchange (IKE)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes a protocol to obtain authenticated keying material for use with ISAKMP, and for other security associations such as AH and ESP for the IETF IPsec DOI. ISAKMP provides a framework for authentication and key exchange but does not define them. ISAKMP is designed to be key exchange independant; that is, it is designed to support many different key exchanges.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1998-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable49"><title>RFC 2453</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>RIP Version 2</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document specifies an extension of the Routing Information Protocol (RIP) to expand the amount of useful information carried in RIP messages and to add a measure of security. A companion document will define the SNMP MIB objects for RIP-2. An additional document will define cryptographic security improvements for RIP-2.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1998-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable50"><title>RFC 2474</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Definition of the Differentiated Services Field (DS Field) in the IPv4 and IPv6 Headers</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Differentiated services enhancements to the Internet protocol are intended to enable scalable service discrimination in the Internet without the need for per-flow state and signaling at every hop. A variety of services may be built from a small, well-defined set of building blocks which are deployed in network nodes. The services may be either end-to-end or intra-domain; they include both those that can satisfy quantitative performance requirements (e.g., peak bandwidth) and those based on relative performance (e.g., "class"differentiation). Services can be constructed by a combination of:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>setting bits in an IP header field at network boundaries (autonomous system boundaries, internal administrative boundaries, or hosts),</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>using those bits to determine how packets are forwarded by the nodes inside the network, and</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>conditioning the marked packets at network boundaries in accordance with the requirements or rules of each service.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1998-12Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable51"><title>RFC 2616</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Hypertext Transfer Protocol -- HTTP/1.1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is an application-level protocol for distributed, collaborative, hypermedia information systems. It is a generic, stateless, protocol which can be used for many tasks beyond its use for hypertext, such as name servers and distributed object management systems, through extension of its request methods, error codes and headers. A feature of HTTP is the typing and negotiation of data representation, allowing systems to be built independently of the data being transferred.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1999-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable52"><title>RFC 2782</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>A DNS RR for specifying the location of services (DNS SRV)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes a DNS resource record (RR) which specifies the location of the server(s) for a specific protocol and domain.
The SRV RR allows administrators to use several servers for a single domain, to move services from host to host with little fuss, and to designate some hosts as primary servers for a service and others as backups. Clients ask for a specific service/protocol for a specific domain (the word domain is used here in the strict RFC 1034 sense), and get back the names of any available servers.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2000-02Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable53"><title>RFC 2784</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Generic Routing Encapsulation (GRE)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Generic Routing Encapsulation (GRE)</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2000-03Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable54"><title>RFC 2798</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Definition of the inetOrgPerson LDAP Object Class</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>While the X.500 standards define many useful attribute types (X520) and object classes (X521), they do not define a person object class that meets the requirements found in today's Internet and Intranet directory service deployments. We define a new object class called inetOrgPerson for use in LDAP and X.500 directory services that extends the X.521 standard organizationalPerson class to meet these needs.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2000-04Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable55"><title>RFC 2817</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Upgrading to TLS Within HTTP/1.1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memo explains how to use the Upgrade mechanism in HTTP/1.1 to initiate Transport Layer Security (TLS) over an existing TCP connection. This allows unsecured and secured HTTP traffic to share the same well known port (in this case, http: at 80 rather than https: at 443). It also enables "virtual hosting", so a single HTTP + TLS server can disambiguate traffic intended for several hostnames at a single IP address.
Since HTTP/1.1 defines Upgrade as a hop-by-hop mechanism, this memo also documents the HTTP CONNECT method for establishing end-to- end tunnels across HTTP proxies. Finally, this memo establishes new IANA registries for public HTTP status codes, as well as public or private Upgrade product tokens.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2000-05Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable56"><title>RFC 2849</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>The LDAP Data Interchange Format (LDIF) - Technical Specification</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes a file format suitable for describing directory information or modifications made to directory information. The file format, known as LDIF, for LDAP Data Interchange Format, is typically used to import and export directory information between LDAP-based directory servers, or to describe a set of changes which are to be applied to a directory.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2000-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable57"><title>RFC 2854</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>The 'text/html' Media Type</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document summarizes the history of HTML development, and defines the "text/html"MIME type by pointing to the relevant W3C recommendations; it is intended to obsolete the previous IETF documents defining HTML, including RFC 1866, RFC 1867, RFC 1980, RFC 1942 and RFC 2070, and to remove HTML from IETF Standards Track.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2000-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable58"><title>RFC 2890</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Key and Sequence Number Extensions to GRE</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Generic Routing Encapsulation (GRE) specifies a protocol for encapsulation of an arbitrary protocol over another arbitrary network layer protocol. This document describes extensions by which two fields, Key and Sequence Number, can be optionally carried in the GRE Header.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2000-09Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable59"><title>RFC 2908</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>The Internet Multicast Address Allocation Architecture</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document proposes a multicast address allocation architecture (MALLOC) for the Internet. The architecture is modular with three layers, comprising a host-server mechanism, an intra-domain server- server coordination mechanism, and an
inter-domain mechanism.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2000-09Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable60"><title>RFC 2920</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>SMTP Service Extension for Command Pipelining</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memo defines an extension to the Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP) service whereby a server can indicate the extent of its ability to accept multiple commands in a single Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) send operation. Using a single TCP send operation for multiple commands can improve SMTP performance significantly.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2000-09Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable61"><title>RFC 3171</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>IANA Guidelines for IPv4 Multicast Address Assignments</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memo provides guidance for the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA) in assigning IPv4 multicast addresses.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2001-08Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable62"><title>RFC 3207</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>SMTP Service Extension for Secure SMTP over Transport Layer Security</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes an extension to the SMTP (Simple Mail Transfer Protocol) service that allows an SMTP server and client to use TLS (Transport Layer Security) to provide private, authenticated communication over the Internet. This gives SMTP agents the ability to protect some or all of their communications from eavesdroppers and attackers.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2002-02Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable63"><title>RFC 3261</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>SIP: Session Initiation Protocol</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes Session Initiation Protocol (SIP), an application-layer control (signaling) protocol for creating, modifying, and terminating sessions with one or more participants. These sessions include Internet telephone calls, multimedia distribution, and multimedia conferences.
SIP invitations used to create sessions carry session descriptions that allow participants to agree on a set of compatible media types. SIP makes use of elements called proxy servers to help route requests to the user's current location, authenticate and authorize users for services, implement provider call-routing policies, and provide features to users. SIP also provides a registration function that allows users to upload their current locations for use by proxy servers. SIP runs on top of several different transport protocols.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2002-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable64"><title>RFC 3262</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Reliability of Provisional Responses in Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document specifies an extension to the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) providing reliable provisional response messages. This extension uses the option tag 100rel and defines the Provisional Response ACKnowledgement (PRACK) method.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2002-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable65"><title>RFC 3264</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>An Offer/Answer Model with Session Description Protocol (SDP)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines a mechanism by which two entities can make use of the Session Description Protocol (SDP) to arrive at a common view of a multimedia session between them. In the model, one participant offers the other a description of the desired session from their perspective, and the other participant answers with the desired session from their perspective. This offer/answer model is most useful in unicast sessions where information from both participants is needed for the complete view of the session. The offer/answer model is used by protocols like the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP).</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2002-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable66"><title>RFC 3311</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>The Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) UPDATE Method</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This specification defines the new UPDATE method for the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP). UPDATE allows a client to update parameters of a session (such as the set of media streams and their codecs) but has no impact on the state of a dialog. In that sense, it is like a re-INVITE, but unlike re-INVITE, it can be sent before the initial INVITE has been completed. This makes it very useful for updating session parameters within early dialogs.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2002-10Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable67"><title>RFC 3376</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>"Internet Group Management Protocol, Version 3"</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document specifies Version 3 of the Internet Group Management Protocol, IGMPv3. IGMP is the protocol used by IPv4 systems to report their IP multicast group memberships to neighboring multicast routers. Version 3 of IGMP adds support for "source filtering", that is, the ability for a system to report interest in receiving packets
*only* from specific source addresses, or from *all but* specific source addresses, sent to a particular multicast address. That information may be used by multicast routing protocols to avoid delivering multicast packets from specific sources to networks where there are no interested receivers.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2002-10Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable68"><title>RFC 3392</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Capabilities Advertisement with BGP-4</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines a new Optional Parameter, called Capabilities, that is expected to facilitate the introduction of new capabilities in the Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) by providing graceful capability advertisement without requiring that BGP peering be terminated.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2002-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable69"><title>RFC 3428</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) Extension for Instant Messaging</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Instant Messaging (IM) refers to the transfer of messages between users in near real-time. These messages are usually, but not required to be, short. IMs are often
used in a conversational mode, that is, the transfer of messages back and forth is fast enough for participants to maintain an interactive conversation.
This document proposes the MESSAGE method, an extension to the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) that allows the transfer of Instant Messages. Since the MESSAGE request is an extension to SIP, it inherits all the request routing and security features of that protocol. MESSAGE requests carry the content in the form of MIME body parts.
MESSAGE requests do not themselves initiate a SIP dialog; under normal usage each Instant Message stands alone, much like pager messages. MESSAGE requests may be sent in the context of a dialog initiated by some other SIP request.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2002-12Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable70"><title>RFC 3461</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP) Service Extension for Delivery Status Notifications (DSNs)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memo defines an extension to the Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP) service, which allows an SMTP client to specify (a) that Delivery Status Notifications (DSNs) should be generated under certain conditions, (b) whether such notifications should return the contents of the message, and (c) additional information, to be returned with a DSN, that allows the sender to identify both the recipient(s) for which the DSN was issued, and the transaction in which the original message was sent.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2003-01Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable71"><title>RFC 3550</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>RTP: A Transport Protocol for Real-Time Applications</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memorandum describes RTP, the real-time transport protocol. RTP provides end-to-end network transport functions suitable for applications transmitting real-time data, such as audio, video or simulation data, over multicast or unicast network services. RTP does not address resource reservation and does not guarantee quality-of-service for real-time services. The data transport is augmented by a control
protocol (RTCP) to allow monitoring of the data delivery in a manner scalable to large multicast networks, and to provide minimal control and identification functionality. RTP and RTCP are designed to be independent of the underlying transport and network layers. The protocol supports the use of RTP-level translators and mixers.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2003-07Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable72"><title>RFC 3618</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Multicast Source Discovery Protocol (MSDP)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The Multicast Source Discovery Protocol (MSDP) describes a mechanism to connect multiple IP Version 4 Protocol Independent Multicast Sparse-Mode (PIM-SM) domains together. Each PIM-SM domain uses its own independent Rendezvous Point (RP) and does not have to depend on RPs in other domains. This document reflects existing MSDP implementations.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2003-10Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable73"><title>RFC 3629</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>"UTF-8, a transformation format of ISO 10646"</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>ISO/IEC 10646-1 defines a large character set called the Universal Character Set (UCS) which encompasses most of the world's writing systems. The originally proposed encodings of the UCS, however, were not compatible with many current applications and protocols, and this has led to the development of UTF-8, the object of this memo. UTF-8 has the characteristic of preserving the full US-ASCII range, providing compatibility with file systems, parsers and other software that rely on US-ASCII values but are transparent to other values.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2003-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable74"><title>RFC 3798</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Message Disposition Notification</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memo defines a MIME content-type that may be used by a mail user agent (MUA) or electronic mail gateway to report the disposition of a message after it has been successfully delivered to a recipient. This content-type is intended to be
machine-processable. Additional message headers are also defined to permit Message Disposition Notifications (MDNs) to be requested by the sender of a message. The purpose is to extend Internet Mail to support functionality often found in other messaging systems, such as X.400 and the proprietary "LAN-based"systems, and often referred to as "read receipts,""acknowledgements", or "receipt notifications."The intention is to do this while respecting privacy concerns, which have often been expressed when such functions have been discussed in the past.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2004-05Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable75"><title>RFC 3885</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>SMTP Service Extension for Message Tracking</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memo defines an extension to the SMTP service whereby a client may mark a message for future tracking.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2004-09Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable76"><title>RFC 3920</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): Core</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): Core</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2004-10Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable77"><title>RFC 3921</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): Instant Messaging and Presence</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): Instant Messaging and Presence</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2004-10Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable78"><title>RFC 3986</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a compact sequence of characters that identifies an abstract or physical resource. This specification defines the generic URI syntax and a process for resolving URI references that might be in relative form, along with guidelines and security considerations for the use of URIs on the Internet. The URI syntax defines a grammar that is a superset of all valid URIs, allowing an implementation to parse the common components of a URI reference without knowing the scheme-specific requirements of every possible identifier. This specification does not define a generative grammar for URIs; that task is performed by the individual specifications of each URI scheme.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2005-01Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable79"><title>RFC 4028</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Session Timers in the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines an extension to the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP). This extension allows for a periodic refresh of SIP sessions through a re-INVITE or UPDATE request. The refresh allows both user agents and proxies to determine whether the SIP session is still active. The extension defines two new header fields: Session-Expires, which conveys the lifetime of the session, and Min-SE, which conveys the minimum allowed value for the session timer.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2005-04Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable80"><title>RFC 4120</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>The Kerberos Network Authentication Service (V5)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document provides an overview and specification of Version 5 of the Kerberos protocol, and it obsoletes RFC 1510 to clarify aspects of the protocol and its intended use that require more detailed or clearer explanation than was provided in RFC 1510. This document is intended to provide a detailed description of the protocol, suitable for implementation, together with descriptions of the appropriate use of protocol messages and fields within those messages.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2005-07Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable81"><title>RFC 4121</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>The Kerberos Version 5 Generic Security Service Application Program Interface (GSS-API) Mechanism: Version 2</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines protocols, procedures, and conventions to be employed by peers implementing the Generic Security Service Application Program Interface (GSS-API) when using the Kerberos Version 5 mechanism.
RFC 1964 is updated and incremental changes are proposed in response to recent developments such as the introduction of Kerberos cryptosystem framework. These changes support the inclusion of new cryptosystems, by defining new per-message tokens along with their encryption and checksum algorithms based on the cryptosystem profiles.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2005-07Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable82"><title>RFC 4271</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>A Border Gateway Protocol 4 (BGP-4)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document discusses the Border Gateway Protocol (BGP), which is an inter-Autonomous System routing protocol.
The primary function of a BGP speaking system is to exchange network reachability information with other BGP systems. This network reachability information includes information on the list of Autonomous Systems (ASes) that reachability information traverses. This information is sufficient for constructing a graph of AS connectivity for this reachability from which routing loops may be pruned, and, at the AS level, some policy decisions may be enforced.
BGP-4 provides a set of mechanisms for supporting Classless Inter- Domain Routing (CIDR). These mechanisms include support for advertising a set of destinations as an IP prefix, and eliminating the concept of network "class"within BGP. BGP-4 also introduces mechanisms that allow aggregation of routes, including aggregation of AS paths.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-01Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable83"><title>RFC 4287</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>The Atom Syndication Format</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document specifies Atom, an XML-based Web content and metadata syndication format.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2005-12Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable84"><title>RFC 4288</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Media Type Specifications and Registration Procedures</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines procedures for the specification and registration of media types for use in MIME and other Internet protocols.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2005-12Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable85"><title>RFC 4303</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>IP Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes an updated version of the Encapsulating Security Payload (ESP) protocol, which is designed to provide a mix of security services in IPv4 and IPv6. ESP is used to provide confidentiality, data origin authentication, connectionless integrity, an anti-replay service (a form of partial sequence integrity), and limited traffic flow confidentiality.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2005-12Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable86"><title>RFC 4329</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Scripting Media Types</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes the registration of media types for the ECMAScript and JavaScript programming languages and conformance requirements for implementations of these types.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-04Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable87"><title>RFC 4360</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>BGP Extended Communities Attribute</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes the "extended community"BGP-4 attribute. This attribute provides a mechanism for labeling information carried in BGP-4. These labels can be used to control the distribution of this information, or for other applications.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-02Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable88"><title>RFC 4412</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Communications Resource Priority for the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines two new Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) header fields for communicating resource priority, namely, "Resource-Priority"and
"Accept-Resource-Priority". The "Resource-Priority"header field can influence the behavior of SIP user agents (such as telephone gateways and IP telephones) and SIP proxies. It does not directly influence the forwarding behavior of IP routers.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-02Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable89"><title>RFC 4422</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) is a framework for providing authentication and data security services in connection-oriented protocols via replaceable mechanisms. It provides a structured interface between protocols and mechanisms. The resulting framework allows new protocols to reuse existing mechanisms and allows old protocols to make use of new mechanisms. The framework also provides a protocol for securing subsequent protocol exchanges within a data security layer.
This document describes how a SASL mechanism is structured, describes how protocols include support for SASL, and defines the protocol for carrying a data security layer over a connection. In addition, this document defines one SASL mechanism, the EXTERNAL mechanism.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable90"><title>RFC 4505</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Anonymous Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) Mechanism</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>On the Internet, it is common practice to permit anonymous access to various services. Traditionally, this has been done with a plain- text password mechanism using "anonymous"as the user name and using optional trace information, such as an email address, as the password. As plain-text login commands are not permitted in new IETF protocols, a new way to provide anonymous login is needed within the context of the Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) framework.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable91"><title>RFC 4510</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP): Technical Specification Road Map</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) is an Internet protocol for accessing distributed directory services that act in accordance with X.500 data and service models. This document provides a road map of the LDAP Technical Specification.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable92"><title>RFC 4511</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP): The Protocol</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes the protocol elements, along with their semantics and encodings, of the Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP). LDAP provides access to distributed directory services that act in accordance with X.500 data and service models. These protocol elements are based on those described in the X.500 Directory Access Protocol (DAP).</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable93"><title>RFC 4512</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP): Directory Information Models</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) is an Internet protocol for accessing distributed directory services that act in accordance with X.500 data and service models. This document describes the X.500 Directory Information Models, as used in LDAP.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable94"><title>RFC 4513</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP): Authentication Methods and Security Mechanisms</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes authentication methods and security mechanisms of the Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP). This document details establishment of Transport Layer Security (TLS) using the StartTLS operation.
This document details the simple Bind authentication method including anonymous, unauthenticated, and name/password mechanisms and the Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) Bind authentication method including the EXTERNAL mechanism.
This document discusses various authentication and authorization states through which a session to an LDAP server may pass and the actions that trigger these state changes.
This document, together with other documents in the LDAP Technical Specification (see Section 1 of the specification's road map), obsoletes RFC 2251, RFC 2829, and RFC 2830.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable95"><title>RFC 4514</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP): String Representation of Distinguished Names</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The X.500 Directory uses distinguished names (DNs) as primary keys to entries in the directory. This document defines the string representation used in the Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) to transfer distinguished names. The string representation is designed to give a clean representation of commonly used distinguished names, while being able to represent any distinguished name.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable96"><title>RFC 4515</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP): String Representation of Search Filters</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) search filters are transmitted in the LDAP protocol using a binary representation that is appropriate for use on the network. This document defines a human-readable string representation of LDAP search filters that is appropriate for use in LDAP URLs (RFC 4516) and in other applications.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable97"><title>RFC 4516</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP): Uniform Resource Locator</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes a format for a Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) Uniform Resource Locator (URL). An LDAP URL describes an LDAP search operation that is used to retrieve information from an LDAP directory, or, in the context of an LDAP referral or reference, an LDAP URL describes a service where an LDAP operation may be progressed.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable98"><title>RFC 4517</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP): Syntaxes and Matching Rules</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Each attribute stored in a Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) directory, whose values may be transferred in the LDAP protocol, has a defined syntax that constrains the structure and format of its values. The comparison semantics for values of a syntax are not part of the syntax definition but are instead provided through separately defined matching rules. Matching rules specify an argument, an assertion value, which also has a defined syntax. This document defines a base set of syntaxes and matching rules for use in defining attributes for LDAP directories.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable99"><title>RFC 4518</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP): Internationalized String Preparation</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The previous Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) technical specifications did not precisely define how character string matching is to be performed. This led to a number of usability and interoperability problems. This document defines string preparation algorithms for character-based matching rules defined for use in LDAP.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable100"><title>RFC 4519</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP): Schema for User Applications</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document is an integral part of the Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) technical specification. It provides a technical specification of attribute types and object classes intended for use by LDAP directory clients for many directory services, such as White Pages. These objects are widely used as a basis for the schema in many LDAP directories. This document does not cover attributes used for the administration of directory servers, nor does it include directory objects defined for specific uses in other documents.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable101"><title>RFC 4523</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) Schema Definitions for X.509 Certificates</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP) Schema Definitions for X.509 Certificates</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable102"><title>RFC 4566</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>SDP: Session Description Protocol</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memo defines the Session Description Protocol (SDP). SDP is intended for describing multimedia sessions for the purposes of session announcement, session invitation, and other forms of multimedia session initiation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-07Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable103"><title>RFC 4582</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>The Binary Floor Control Protocol (BFCP)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Floor control is a means to manage joint or exclusive access to shared resources in a (multiparty) conferencing environment. Thereby, floor control complements other functions -- such as conference and media session setup, conference policy manipulation, and media control -- that are realized by other protocols.
This document specifies the Binary Floor Control Protocol (BFCP). BFCP is used between floor participants and floor control servers, and between floor chairs (i.e., moderators) and floor control servers.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable104"><title>RFC 4594</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Configuration Guidelines for DiffServ Service Classes</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes service classes configured with Diffserv and recommends how they can be used and how to construct them using Differentiated Services Code Points (DSCPs), traffic conditioners, Per-Hop Behaviors (PHBs), and Active Queue Management (AQM) mechanisms. There is no intrinsic requirement that particular DSCPs, traffic conditioners, PHBs, and AQM be used for a certain service class, but as a policy and for interoperability it is useful to apply them consistently.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-08Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable105"><title>RFC 4601</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Protocol Independent Multicast - Sparse Mode (PIM-SM): Protocol Specification (Revised)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document specifies Protocol Independent Multicast - Sparse Mode (PIM-SM). PIM-SM is a multicast routing protocol that can use the underlying unicast routing information base or a separate multicast- capable routing information base. It builds
unidirectional shared trees rooted at a Rendezvous Point (RP) per group, and optionally creates shortest-path trees per source.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-08Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable106"><title>RFC 4616</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>The PLAIN Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) Mechanism</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines a simple clear-text user/password Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) mechanism called the PLAIN mechanism. The PLAIN mechanism is intended to be used, in combination with data confidentiality services provided by a lower layer, in protocols that lack a simple password authentication command.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-08Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable107"><title>RFC 4627</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>The application/json Media Type for JavaScript Object Notation (JSON)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>JavaScript Object Notation (JSON) is a lightweight, text-based, language-independent data interchange format. It was derived from the ECMAScript Programming Language Standard. JSON defines a small set of formatting rules for the portable representation of structured data.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-07Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable108"><title>RFC 4632</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Classless Inter-domain Routing (CIDR): The Internet Address Assignment and Aggregation Plan</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memo discusses the strategy for address assignment of the existing 32-bit IPv4 address space with a view toward conserving the address space and limiting the growth rate of global routing state. This document obsoletes the original Classless
Inter-domain Routing (CIDR) spec in RFC 1519, with changes made both to clarify the concepts it introduced and, after more than twelve years, to update the Internet community on the results of deploying the technology described. This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-08Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable109"><title>RFC 4752</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>"The Kerberos V5 ("GSSAPI") Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) Mechanism"</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) is a framework for adding authentication support to connection-based protocols. This document describes the method for using the Generic Security Service Application Program Interface
(GSS-API) Kerberos V5 in the SASL.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-11Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable110"><title>RFC 4760</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Multiprotocol Extensions for BGP-4</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines extensions to Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) -4 to enable it to carry routing information for multiple Network Layer protocols (e.g., IPv6, IPX, L3VPN, etc.). The extensions are backward compatible - a router that supports the extensions can interoperate with a router that doesn't support the extensions.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2007-01Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable111"><title>RFC 4954</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>SMTP Service Extension for Authentication</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines a Simple Mail Transport Protocol (SMTP) extension whereby an SMTP client may indicate an authentication mechanism to the server, perform an authentication protocol exchange, and optionally negotiate a security layer for subsequent protocol interactions during this session. This extension includes a profile of the Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) for SMTP.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2007-07Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable112"><title>RFC 5023</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>The Atom Publishing Protocol</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The Atom Publishing Protocol (AtomPub) is an application-level protocol for publishing and editing Web resources. The protocol is based on HTTP transfer of Atom-formatted representations. The Atom format is documented in the Atom Syndication Format.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2007-10Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable113"><title>RFC 5280</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure Certificate and Certificate Revocation List (CRL) Profile</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This memo profiles the X.509 v3 certificate and X.509 v2 certificate revocation list (CRL) for use in the Internet. An overview of this approach and model is provided as an introduction. The X.509 v3 certificate format is described in detail, with additional information regarding the format and semantics of Internet name forms.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2008-05Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable114"><title>RFC 5321</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document is a specification of the basic protocol for Internet electronic mail transport. It consolidates, updates, and clarifies several previous documents, making all or parts of most of them obsolete. It covers the SMTP extension mechanisms and best practices for the contemporary Internet, but does not provide details about particular extensions. Although SMTP was designed as a mail transport and delivery protocol, this specification also contains information that is important to its use as a "mail submission"protocol for "split-UA"(User Agent) mail reading systems and mobile environments.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2008-10Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable115"><title>RFC 5668</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>4-Octet AS Specific BGP Extended Community</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines a new type of Border Gateway Protocol (BGP) extended community (RFC4360): a 4-octet AS specific extended community. This type of extended community is similar to the 2-octet AS specific extended community, except that it can carry a 4-octet Autonomous System number.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2009-10Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable116"><title>RFC 5905</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Network Time Protocol Version 4: Protocol and Algorithms Specification</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The Network Time Protocol (NTP) is widely used to synchronize computer clocks in the Internet. This document describes NTP version 4 (NTPv4), which is backwards compatible with NTP version 3 (NTPv3), described in RFC 1305, as well as previous versions of the protocol. NTPv4 includes a modified protocol header to accommodate the Internet Protocol version 6 address family. NTPv4 includes fundamental improvements in the mitigation and discipline algorithms that extend the potential accuracy to the tens of microseconds with modern workstations and fast LANs. It includes a dynamic server discovery scheme, so that in many cases, specific server configuration is not required. It corrects certain errors in the NTPv3 design and implementation and includes an optional extension mechanism.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2010-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable117"><title>RFC 6960</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>X.509 Internet Public Key Infrastructure Online Certificate Status Protocol - OCSP</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document specifies a protocol useful in determining the current status of a digital certificate without requiring Certificate Revocation Lists (CRLs). Additional mechanisms addressing PKIX operational requirements are specified in separate documents. This document obsoletes RFCs 2560 and 6277. It also updates RFC 5912.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2013-06Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable118"><title>RFC 7296</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Internet Key Exchange Protocol Version 2 (IKEv2)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes version 2 of the Internet Key Exchange (IKE) protocol. IKE is a component of IPsec used for performing mutual authentication and establishing and maintaining Security Associations (SAs). This document obsoletes RFC 5996, and includes all of the errata for it. It advances IKEv2 to be an Internet Standard.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2014-10Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable119"><title>RFC 7427</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Signature Authentication in the Internet Key Exchange Version 2 (IKEv2)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The Internet Key Exchange Version 2 (IKEv2) protocol has limited support for the Elliptic Curve Digital Signature Algorithm (ECDSA). The current version only includes support for three Elliptic Curve groups, and there is a fixed hash algorithm tied to each group. This document generalizes IKEv2 signature support to allow any signature method supported by PKIX and also adds signature hash algorithm negotiation. This is a generic mechanism and is not limited to ECDSA; it can also be used with other signature algorithms.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2015-01Z</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable120"><title>RSS 2.0</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Really Simple Syndication version 2.0</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>RSS is a Web content syndication format. It is a dialect of XML. All RSS files must conform to the XML 1.0 specification, as published on the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) website.
At the top level, a RSS document is a element, with a mandatory attribute called version, that specifies the version of RSS that the document conforms to. If it conforms to this specification, the version attribute must be 2.0. Subordinate to the element is a single element, which contains information about the channel (metadata) and its contents.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>RSS Advisory Board</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2009-03-30</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable121"><title>SCIP-210</title>
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row><entry>Title</entry><entry>SCIP Signaling Plan</entry></row>
<row>	<entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document specifies the signaling requirements for the Secure Communication Interoperability Protocol (SCIP) operational modes. The requirements represent the efforts of a working group established for the development, analysis, selection, definition and refinement of signaling for the operational modes of a new class of secure voice and data terminals intended for use on the emerging digital narrowband channels. These channels include digital cellular systems such as GSM and CDMA, digital mobile satellite systems, and a variety of other narrowband digital systems that are also within the scope of interest for the working group. The SCIP signaling is designed to be sufficiently flexible so that subsequent updates and revisions may include various future networks of interest.
The purpose of this document is to define the signaling for point-to-point and multipoint secure communication among terminals operating over narrowband digital networks. The Signaling Plan defines:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>The exchange of keys, certificates or other information between point-to-point terminals preparatory to the exchange of secure voice or data traffic,
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The transmission of secure voice traffic among the user terminals for point-to-point and multipoint operation using the DoD standard MELP or NATO standard MELPe vocoder at 2400 bps, and the ITU-T Recommendation G.729 Annex D CS-ACELP vocoder at 6400 bps,
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The transmission of secure data traffic between the user terminals for point-to-point
secure data communication,
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The security control signaling necessary to establish, maintain, and terminate the secure mode of operation,
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The signaling to support point-to-point electronic or over-the-air rekey of the keys or keying material used by the terminals,
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>The signaling point of departure to allow vendors to add proprietary signaling and modes of operation to the interoperable standard modes defined by the remainder of the signaling plan.
</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
The purpose of this Signaling Plan is to support communication between SCIP terminals independent of the transport network being used (e.g., digital wireless networks, IP networks, and PSTN/ISDN networks). The signaling is intended to operate using commercially available standards based data services, and standard Interworking Functions (IWFs) with no need for additional specialized interworking functions or operations.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>U.S. National Security Agency (NSA)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2013-01-08</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable122"><title>SCIP-214</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Network-Specific Minimum Essential Requirements (MERs) for SCIP Devices</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document provides an index to the specifications of the network-specific interface Minimum Essential Requirements (MERs) for Secure Communication Interoperability Protocol (SCIP) devices. The MERs for each network-specific interface are defined in separate SCIP-214 modules that are independently under configuration control. Note that although SCIP-215 and SCIP-216 are not SCIP-214 modules, they are included in the index in order to provide a complete collection of network-specific interface MER documents. This document also provides a SCIP network architecture diagram and the SCIP Document Family Tree of Interface Requirements.
The purpose of SCIP-214 and the associated modules is to provide the
network-specific interface MERs for SCIP devices. The design of SCIP devices requires both the SCIP application and lower layer communications interface requirements. The documentation of the lower layer communications interface MERs will enable interoperability among devices that operate within each specific network.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>U.S. National Security Agency (NSA)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2011-07-08</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable123"><title>SCIP-215</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>SCIP over IP Implementation Standard and Minimum Essential Requirements (MER)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>The background and strategy for the development of this interoperable methodology was captured in the Program Plan for the Establishment of an FNBDT over IP Standard, Revision 1.0, February 10, 2005. A detailed trade study was also conducted and the results were captured in the Trade study FNBDT over IP Protocol Stack Scenarios, February 9, 2005. The following sections detail a SCIP over IP standard methodology for interoperability across existing and emerging packet switched networks as well as legacy circuit switched networks. The intent of this document is to establish the implementation standard for the encapsulation of SCIP information for transmission over packet-based networks. It will also establish the Minimum Essential Requirements (MER) for the implementation of SCIP signaling by a SCIP/IP capable device to guarantee that secure voice and data interoperability will be achieved in the target network architectures of the future. Note that this document focuses on the requirements for the edge terminals and that the requirements for MER compliant
V.150.1 gateways are defined in SCIP-216, MER for V.150.1 Gateways.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>U.S. National Security Agency (NSA)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2011-07-08</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable124"><title>SCIP-216</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Minimum Essential Requirements (MER) for V.150.1 Gateways Publication</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>A large fielded base of fax machines, modems, and telephony devices are in existence today that utilize ITU V-series modulations. As DoD communications networks transition from the circuit- switched technologies traditionally used on the PSTN to Internet Protocol based solutions, the need for seamless interoperability between
V-series devices on the PSTN and IP devices will continue to grow. The often-used method for transporting modem signals across the IP network with a G.711 stream is unsatisfactory given the large bandwidth consumed and susceptibility to modem retrains. ITU V.150.1 resolves these issues with its definition of a standard for modem relay.
The primary goal of this document is to define the requirements that are levied against
V.150.1 gateways that interoperate with Secure Communications Interoperability Protocol (SCIP) devices on IP and PSTN networks. However, other types of IP devices could utilize gateways that conform to these requirements to provide more robust connectivity to modem-based PSTN endpoints. In addition, this document attempts to scale down the task of V.150.1 implementers on DoD networks by identifying only those requirements that are minimum and essential, though occasionally some optional recommendations are made. Furthermore, this document aims to clarify any ambiguities within the V.150.1 specification. This document is organized into 4 major sections. First, this document describes the target use cases and architectures. Next, the basic subset of V.150.1 requirements that are mandated by this specification is defined. Afterwards, the core set of procedures that implementers of this specification must support are identified and defined. Finally, the structures of the V.150.1 message types required by this specification are defined.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>U.S. National Security Agency (NSA)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2011-07-08</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable125"><title>SCIP-220</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Requirements for SCIP</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes the requirements for the Secure Communications Interoperability Protocol (SCIP).</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>U.S. National Security Agency (NSA)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable126"><title>SCIP-221</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>SCIP Minimum Implementation Profile (MIP)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document describes the Minimum Implementation Profile (MIP) for the Secure Communications Interoperability Protocol (SCIP).</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>U.S. National Security Agency (NSA)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable127"><title>SCIP-233</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Cryptography Specification - Main Module</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document specifies the cryptography requirements and associated Operational Modes for the Secure Communication Interoperability Protocol (SCIP) family of equipment. Cryptography requirements that are common to all SCIP devices are included in this SCIP Cryptography Specification - Main Module. The remaining cryptography requirements are included in Reference Modules that are referenced from this Main Module. The relevant Minimum Implementation Profile (MIP) specifies which of these requirements must be implemented to be SCIP compliant.
The overall structure of this document is a Main Module (SCIP-233) supported by a set of independent Reference Modules (SCIP-233.xxx) containing specific cryptographic functions. The Main Module contains the Interoperable Keyset Type list and specifies common processing. The Reference Modules are grouped into series. Reference Modules Series 100 specifies Key Material, Series 200 specifies Call Setup Encryption, Series 300 specifies Key Processing, Series 400 specifies Cryptographic Processing, Series 500 specifies Secure Traffic Processing, Series 600 specifies Traffic Encryption Algorithms, and Series 700 specifies Rekey Processing.
This document also references existing cryptographic specifications, defined in Section 1.3, as appropriate. Where necessary, either because existing material is inconsistent or incomplete, or because new cryptography is being defined, requirements will be specified herein and will take precedence over other non-SCIP documents.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>U.S. National Security Agency (NSA)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2012-08-06</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable128"><title>STANAG 4705</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>International Network Numbering for Communications Systems in Use in NATO</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry><para>2010-10Z</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>NATO Standardisation Agency (NSA)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable129"><title>STANAG 4711</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>INTEROPERABILITY POINT QUALITY OF SERVICE (IP QOS)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>NATO Standardisation Agency (NSA)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable130"><title>STANAG 5046</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>THE NATO MILITARY COMMUNICATIONS DIRECTORY SYSTEM</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry><para>1995-08-08</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>NATO Standardisation Agency (NSA)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable131"><title>W3C Note - Simple Object Access Protocol 1.1</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Simple Object Access Protocol version 1.1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>SOAP is a lightweight protocol for exchange of information in a decentralized, distributed environment. It is an XML based protocol that consists of three parts: an envelope that defines a framework for describing what is in a message and how to process it, a set of encoding rules for expressing instances of application-defined datatypes, and a convention for representing remote procedure calls and responses. SOAP can potentially be used in combination with a variety of other protocols; however, the only bindings defined in this document describe how to use SOAP in combination with HTTP and HTTP Extension Framework.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2000-05-08</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable132"><title>W3C Note - Web Services Description Language 1.1</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Web Services Description Language 1.1</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>WSDL is an XML format for describing network services as a set of endpoints operating on messages containing either document-oriented or procedure-oriented information.
The operations and messages are described abstractly, and then bound to a concrete network protocol and message format to define an endpoint. Related concrete endpoints are combined into abstract endpoints (services). WSDL is extensible to allow description of endpoints and their messages regardless of what message formats or network protocols are used to communicate, however, the only bindings described in this document describe how to use WSDL in conjunction with SOAP 1.1, HTTP GET/POST, and MIME.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable133"><title>W3C Recommendation - CSS Color Module Level 3</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>CSS Color Module Level 3</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>CSS Color Module Level 3</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2011-06-07</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable134"><title>W3C Recommendation - CSS Namespaces Module Level 3</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>CSS Namespaces Module Level 3</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>CSS Namespaces Module Level 3</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2014-03-20</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable135"><title>W3C Recommendation - CSS Style Attributes</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>CSS Style Attributes</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>CSS Style Attributes</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2013-11-07</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable136"><title>W3C Recommendation - Cascading Style Sheets Level 2 Revision 1 (CSS 2.1) Specification</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Cascading Style Sheets Level 2 Revision 1 (CSS 2.1) Specification</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Cascading Style Sheets Level 2 Revision 1 (CSS 2.1) Specification</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2011-06-07</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable137"><title>W3C Recommendation - Character Model for the World Wide Web 1.0: Fundamentals</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Character Model for the World Wide Web 1.0: Fundamentals</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Character Model for the World Wide Web 1.0: Fundamentals</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2005-02-15</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable138"><title>W3C Recommendation - Cross-Origin Resource Sharing</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Cross-Origin Resource Sharing</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Cross-Origin Resource Sharing</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2014-01-16</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable139"><title>W3C Recommendation - HTML5</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>HTML5</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>HTML5</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2014-10-28</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable140"><title>W3C Recommendation - Internationalization Tag Set (ITS) Version 1.0</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Internationalization Tag Set (ITS) Version 1.0</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Internationalization Tag Set (ITS) Version 1.0</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2007-04-03</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable141"><title>W3C Recommendation - Internationalization Tag Set (ITS) Version 2.0</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Internationalization Tag Set (ITS) Version 2.0</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Internationalization Tag Set (ITS) Version 2.0</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2013-10-29</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable142"><title>W3C Recommendation - Media Queries</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Media Queries</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Media Queries</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2012-06-19</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable143"><title>W3C Recommendation - Ruby Annotation</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Ruby Annotation</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Ruby Annotation</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2001-05-31</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable144"><title>W3C Recommendation - Selectors Level 3</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Selectors Level 3</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Selectors Level 3</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2011-09-29</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable145"><title>W3C Recommendation - Web Services Addressing 1.0 - Core</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Web Services Addressing 1.0 - Core</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Web Services Addressing 1.0 - Core</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2006-05-09</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable146"><title>W3C Recommendation - Web Services Description Language (WSDL) Version 2.0 SOAP 1.1 Binding</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Web Services Description Language (WSDL) Version 2.0 SOAP 1.1 Binding</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>Web Services Description Language (WSDL) Version 2.0 SOAP 1.1 Binding</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2007-06-26</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable147"><title>W3C Recommendation - XHTML 1.0 in XML Schema</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>XHTML 1.0 in XML Schema</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>XHTML 1.0 in XML Schema</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2002-09-02</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable148"><title>W3C Recommendation - XML 1.0 Recommendation</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>XML 1.0 Recommendation</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>XML 1.0 Recommendation</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>1998-02-10</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable149"><title>W3C Recommendation - XML Schema Part 1: Structures</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>XML Schema Part 1: Structures</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>XML Schema Part 1: Structures</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2001-05-02</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable150"><title>W3C Recommendation - XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2001-05-02</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable151"><title>XEP-0004</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Data Forms</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the standards process followed by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2007-08-13</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable152"><title>XEP-0030</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Service Discovery</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the standards process followed by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2008-06-06</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable153"><title>XEP-0045</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Multi-User Chat</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the standards process followed by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2012-02-08</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable154"><title>XEP-0049</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Private XML Storage</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the standards process followed by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2004-03-01</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable155"><title>XEP-0050</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Ad-Hoc Commands</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the standards process followed by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2005-06-30</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable156"><title>XEP-0054</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>vcard-temp</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the standards process followed by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2008-07-16</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable157"><title>XEP-0092</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Software Version</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the standards process followed by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2007-02-15</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable158"><title>XEP-0096</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>SI File Transfer</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the standards process followed by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2004-04-13</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable159"><title>XEP-0114</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Jabber Component Protocol</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the standards process followed by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2012-01-25</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable160"><title>XEP-0115</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Entity Capabilities</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the standards process followed by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2008-02-26</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable161"><title>XEP-0203</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Delayed Delivery</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the standards process followed by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2009-09-15</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable162"><title>XEP-0220</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Server Dialback</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the standards process followed by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2014-08-05</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

<table frame="all" id="v3t-id-fmn-stdtable163"><title>XEP-0288</title>		
<tgroup cols="2"><colspec colwidth="35*"/><colspec colwidth="60*"/><tbody><row>	<entry>Title</entry><entry>Bidirectional Server-to-Server Connections</entry></row>
<row><entry>Description</entry><entry><para>This document defines the standards process followed by the XMPP Standards Foundation.</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>Standards Organization</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row>
<row><entry>Date</entry><entry>2013-09-26</entry></row>
<row><entry>Publisher</entry><entry>XMPP Standards Foundation (XSF)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table>

</sect2>
</sect1>
  
</appendix>
