<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd"[]>
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles</title>
    <subtitle>Mid to Far Term</subtitle>
    <corpauthor>C3 CCSC NATO Open Systems Working Group</corpauthor>
    <productname class="trade">Allied Data Publication 34</productname>
    <biblioid class="pubnumber">ADatP-34</biblioid>
    <volumenum>3</volumenum>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>4.3</revnumber>
        <date>28 June 2010</date>
        <revremark></revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <productnumber>$Id$</productnumber>
  </bookinfo>
  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>This document is a draft under development by the NATO Open Systems Working Group (NOSWG)
 under the authority the NATO Consultation, Command and Control Board (NC3B).
  In due course it is expected to be noted by the NATO C3 Board making the Volume 2 standards and profiles mandatory for use in NATO common funded systems, and to be made available to the general public as a replacement for ADatP-34(D).</para>
    <para>NATO Network-Enabled Capability (NNEC) aims to provide an
    environment where connected collectors, decision-makers, effectors, and
    information sources are integrated in a common network of networks and can
    be provided with, search for, or supply data and information from any
    location under user-adapted format and within user relevant time
    constraints. Advantage is taken of the great advances within civilian
    information and communication technology. Solutions under network-oriented
    concept are based on:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Service-Oriented Architecture (SOA)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Federation of systems, including federated networks.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Situation adapted combinations of units and systems</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <figure float="0">
      <title>NNEC Concept</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="../figures/nnecConcept.svg" format="SVG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>Volume 3 of this NISP will continue the evolution from platform based legacy systems to the federated Network Enabled Capabilities environment where the functionality is made generally available as "services on the net". Ultimately the goal is that the functionality of the most useful services shall be available to authorized users in each situation. The focus of this section of the volume is on the mid-term perspective having a time frame of 2 to 10 years into the future from the publication of this version of the NISP. This timeframe encompasses the realization of a fully network enabled NATO environment.</para>
    <para>Within this part of the document, the focus is on the mid-term to far-term
    perspective. This perspective has a time frame of 2 to 10 years
    into the future from the publication of this version of the NISP. This time frame should encompass the realisation of a fully network enabled NATO coalition environment.</para>
    <!--
    <title>Mid-Term Emerging Technologies And Standards</title>
-->
    <para>The purpose of this section is to identify a number of key emerging
    (commercial) technologies that are relevant to NATO and to provide a
    useful level of analysis about their possible application within military
    systems. While the emerging technologies discussed in this section are not
    exhaustive, the content of this section does draw significantly upon the
    technology tracking efforts of the NOSWG member nations. Once technologies
    are identified and their applicability analysed, then informed decisions
    can be made on what role each technology or standard will play in the
    current technical architecture. The rapid pace of technological change
    carries with it the potential benefits of faster and more cost-effective
    improvements in operational capability; however, the rapidity of change
    upon a broad technology front also makes the task of identifying emerging
    technologies particularly difficult.</para>
    <para>The intention of this element of the NISP volume 3 is to be
    informative, whilst maintaining brevity, on a range of technologies.
    Consequently, the information is presented as a series of short articles
    that cover the essential points of interest. This flexible format is
    intended to facilitate the rapid change of content that will inevitably
    happen between issues of the NISP.</para>
    <sect1>
      <title>Communications &amp; Networking</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Disruption Tolerant Networking (DTN)</title>
        <para>Disruption Tolerant Networking (DTN) are comprised of
        technologies that will provide network services when no end-to-end
        path exists through the network because of periodic or intermittent
        disruptions. Disruption may occur because of the limits of wireless
        radio range, sparsity of mobile nodes, energy resources, enemy attack,
        and noise. Such a robust communications network would have to be
        autonomic, secure and opportunistic.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Implications</emphasis>: The research in
        this area is principally aimed at providing internet-like services and
        supporting "long-haul" reliable transmission in interplanetary space,
        but it has applications in other environments as well. The work done
        to overcome delays caused by interplanetary distances can easily be
        appealed to tactical military networks. Distance delays are just a
        subset of the more general group of Disruption sources.</para>
        <sect3>
          <title>Bundle Protocols</title>
          <para>Research goals in this area are to provide disruption
          tolerance by organizing information flow into bundles. These bundles
          are to be routed through an "intelligent" network that can manage
          the delivery of the bundles to the maximal extent permitted by the
          available topology. This method will allow messages to pass through
          the network with successive responsibilities, rather than the
          traditional end-to-end scheme. The mechanism of bundling will allow
          a network node to hold data if the next hop in the network is
          unavailable.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: The Internet
          Engineering Task Force (IETF) has recently published RFC 4838 and
          RFC 5050 to provide the common defining framework for the formation
          and transport of bundles of data. In 2008, the Bundle Protocol was
          successfully tested in space on the UK-DMC Disaster Monitoring
          Constellation satellite.</para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Licklider Transmission Protocol (LTP)</title>
          <para>The Licklider Transmission Protocol (LTP) was designed to
          provide retransmission-based reliability over links characterized by
          extremely long message round-trip times (RTTs) and/or frequent
          interruptions in connectivity.</para>
          <para>The Licklider Transmission Protocol (LTP) would replace both
          IP and TCP. Picturing protocols as layers in a stack, if the bottom
          layer is the physical wire line or radio wave connecting two
          devices, the Licklider Transmission Protocol sits just above that.
          It makes the link between two routers more reliable than IP and
          TCP.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: In 2008, the IRTF
          Working Group of the IETF established an experimental RFC (RFC 5326)
          on this topic</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Wireless Networking</title>
        <para>Several wireless network standards have been developed to
        encompass the wide range of mobile environments and
        applications.</para>
        <figure float="0">
          <title>Standards, Mobility, and Data Rates</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../figures/stdsMobDR.svg" format="SVG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <sect3>
          <title>Wireless Personal Area Network (WPAN)</title>
          <para>A wireless personal area network (WPAN) is a computer network
          used for communication among computers, I/O peripherals (such as
          keyboards, printers, scanners, etc) and devices (such as wireless
          access points, cell phones and personal digital assistants) within
          reach of a person. The devices may or may not belong to the person
          in question. The range of a WPAN is typically less than 10 metres,
          and up to 1 kilometre under ideal conditions. WPANs can be used to
          replace cables between computers and their peripherals, to establish
          communities, or to establish location aware services. WPANs can be
          used for communication among the personal devices themselves
          (intra-personal communication), or for connecting to a higher level
          network and the Internet (an up link).</para>
          <table>
            <title>PAN Summary</title>
            <tgroup cols="4">
              <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="25*" />
              <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="25*" />
              <colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="25*" />
              <colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="25*" />
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry align="center">
                    <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                  <entry align="center">
                    <emphasis role="bold">Frequencies</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                  <entry align="center">
                    <emphasis role="bold">Spectrum
                  Type</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Data Rates</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Bluetooth</entry>
                  <entry>2.4GHz</entry>
                  <entry>Unlicensed ISM</entry>
                  <entry>2.1 Mbit/s</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Wibree</entry>
                  <entry>2.4GHz</entry>
                  <entry>Unlicensed ISM</entry>
                  <entry>1 Mbit/s</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>ZigBee</entry>
                  <entry>868 MHz, 915 MHz, 2.4GHz</entry>
                  <entry>Unlicensed ISM</entry>
                  <entry>40-250 kbit/s</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Wireless USB, UWB</entry>
                  <entry>5GHz+</entry>
                  <entry>Unlicensed UWB</entry>
                  <entry>250 kbit/s</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Importance</emphasis>: A key concept in
          WPAN technology is known as plugging in. Ideally, when any two
          WPAN-equipped devices come into close proximity (within several
          metres of each other) or within a few kilometres of a central
          server, they can communicate as if connected by a cable. Another
          important feature is the ability of each device to lock out other
          devices selectively, preventing needless interference or
          unauthorised access to information.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Implications</emphasis>: Collaboration
          between units in the same physical area is possible. Useful on the
          battlefield as a method for soldier communications and
          monitoring.</para>
          <sect4>
            <title>IEEE 802.15.1 (Bluetooth 3.0)</title>
            <para>The next version of Bluetooth, currently code named ,
            includes a number of features to increase security, usability and
            value of Bluetooth. The following features are defined:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Atomic Encryption Change - allows encrypted links to
                change their encryption keys periodically, increasing
                security, and also allowing role switches on an encrypted
                link.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Extended Inquiry Response - provides more information
                during the inquiry procedure to allow better filtering of
                devices before connection. This information includes the name
                of the device, and a list of services, with other
                information.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Sniff Sub-rating - reducing the power consumption when
                devices are in the sniff low power mode, especially on links
                with asymmetric data flows. Human interface devices (HID) are
                expected to benefit the most with mice and keyboards
                increasing the battery life from 3 to 10 times those currently
                used.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>QoS Improvements - these will enable audio and video
                data to be transmitted at a higher quality, especially when
                best effort traffic is being transmitted in the same
                piconet.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Simple Pairing - this improvement will radically improve
                the pairing experience for Bluetooth devices, while at the
                same time increasing the use and strength of security. It is
                expected that this feature will significantly increase the use
                of Bluetooth.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Bluetooth technology already plays a part in the rising
            Voice over IP (VoIP) scene, with Bluetooth headsets being used as
            wireless extensions to the PC audio system. As VoIP becomes more
            popular, and more suitable for general home or office users than
            wired phone lines, Bluetooth may be used in Cordless handsets,
            with a base station connected to the Internet link.</para>
            <para>The version of Bluetooth after , code-named , has many of
            the same features, but is most notable for plans to adopt
            Ultra-wideband radio technology. This will allow Bluetooth use
            over UWB radio, enabling very fast data transfers,
            synchronisations and file pushes, while building on the very low
            power idle modes of Bluetooth. The combination of a radio using
            little power when no data is transmitted, and a high data rate
            radio used to transmit bulk data, could be the start of software
            radios. Bluetooth, given its worldwide regulatory approval, low
            power operation, and robust data transmission capabilities,
            provides an excellent signalling channel to enable the soft radio
            concept.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: On 28 March 2006,
            the Bluetooth Special Interest Group (SIG) announced its selection
            of the WiMedia Alliance Multi-Band Orthogonal Frequency Division
            Multiplexing (MB-OFDM) version of Ultra-wideband (UWB) for
            integration with current Bluetooth wireless technology. UWB
            integration will create a version of the globally popular
            Bluetooth wireless technology with a high speed/high data rate
            option. This new version of Bluetooth technology will meet the
            high-speed demands of synchronising and transferring large amounts
            of data as well as enabling high quality video and audio
            applications for portable devices, multi-media projectors and
            television sets, wireless VoIP. At the same time, Bluetooth
            technology will continue catering to the needs of very low power
            applications such as mice, keyboards and mono headsets, enabling
            devices to select the most appropriate physical radio for the
            application requirements, thereby offering the best of both
            worlds.</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Wireless Local Area Network (WLAN)</title>
          <para>A wireless local area network (WLAN) is the linking of two or
          more computers without using wires. WLAN utilises spread-spectrum
          technology based on radio waves to enable communication between
          devices in a limited area, also known as the basic service set. This
          gives users the mobility to move around within a broad coverage area
          and still be connected to the network.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Importance</emphasis>: Wireless Local
          Area Networks are more convenient, mobile, deployable, expandable,
          and cheaper than wired networks.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Implications</emphasis>: The wireless
          nature of such networks allows users to access network resources
          from nearly any convenient location within their primary networking
          environment. Initial setup of an infrastructure-based wireless
          network requires little more than a single access point. Eliminates
          the cost, time, and labour of running physical cables.</para>
          <sect4>
            <title>IEEE 802.11 (WiFi)</title>
            <para>Many are familiar with 802.11, also known as WiFi, as a
            short-range wireless networking protocol for home and office
            connections. 802.11 represent a family of wireless standards. The
            802.11 series has been developed by the IEEE over the past 10
            years as part of the range of communications protocols under the
            802 standards series.</para>
            <para>Each family member is identified by a letter suffix to the
            series name. Currently these letters run from "a" to "w", although
            there is the original base 802.11 wireless standard as well. Note
            that there is no L standard. Some family members represent
            amendments (a, b, g, i) to the original standard, whereas some
            represents enhancements or extensions (c-f, h-j, n).</para>
            <para>The 802.11 family of protocols share two common frequency
            bands, 2.4GHz and 5GHz, the so-called Industrial, Scientific and
            Medical (ISM) bands. Further more, each of these bands are divided
            into 14 channels. The availability of channels is regulated by
            nation, constrained in part by how each nation allocates radio
            spectrum to various services. At one extreme, Japan permits the
            use of all 14 channels (with the exclusion of 802.11g/n from
            channel 14), while at the other Spain allowed only channels 10 and
            11 (later all of the 14 channels have been allowed ), to which
            France adds 12 and 13. Most other European countries are almost as
            liberal as Japan, disallowing only channel 14, while North America
            and some Central and South American countries further disallow 12
            and 13. The emerging standards within the 802.11 family are as
            follows:</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">802.11-2007</emphasis>: Consolidated
            amendments 802.11a,b,d,e,g,h,i,j with the original base standard
            to form the latest base standard. <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Approved as standard in March of
            2007.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">802.11k</emphasis>: Intended to
            improve the way traffic is distributed within a network by
            discovering the best available access point. In a wireless , each
            device normally connects to the access point (AP) that provides
            the strongest signal. Depending on the number and geographic
            locations of the subscribers, this arrangement can sometimes lead
            to excessive demand on one AP and underutilisation of others,
            resulting in degradation of overall network performance. In a
            network conforming to 802.11k, if the AP having the strongest
            signal is loaded to its full capacity, a wireless device is
            connected to one of the underutilised APs. Even though the signal
            may be weaker, the overall throughput is greater because more
            efficient use is made of the network resources. 802.11k and
            802.11r are the key industry standards now in development that
            will enable seamless Basic Service Set (BSS) transitions in the
            WLAN environment. <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Still
            in draft form, but expected to be ratified in 2008.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">802.11n</emphasis>: Focuses on
            improvements on the 802.11 standard to obtain data throughput of
            at least 100Mbps, improved coverage, and longer range. Such
            advances will be achievable through multiple-input/multiple-output
            (MIMO) communication. MIMO uses multiple radios simultaneously
            transmitting and receiving different signals to and from at least
            two radios on the client side to and from two or more on the
            access point. <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Expected to
            be ratified in 2009. There are still some interoperability issues.
            There are many products available based on the pre-draft
            standard.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">802.11p</emphasis>: "Wireless Access
            in Vehicular Environments (WAVE)" - Wireless communication between
            fast moving vehicles or between a fast moving vehicle and a
            stationary object. This standard supports speeds of minimum of
            200km/h and ranges of up to 1km. It uses 850-5.925 GHz band and
            defines enhancements to 802.11 required to support Intelligent
            Transportation Systems (ITS) applications. The vision is for
            nationwide network that enables communications between vehicles
            and roadside access points or other vehicles. Such networks would
            enable toll collection, vehicle safety services, and commerce
            transactions via cars. <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>:
            Expected to be ratified in 2009. This standard would be the
            foundation for projects like the Communications, Air-interface,
            Long and Medium range (CALM) system in Europe, and Dedicated Short
            Range Communications (DSRC) in the United States.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">802.11r</emphasis>: "Fast Roaming" -
            This proposed standard will specify fast Basic Service Set (BSS)
            transitions that address the faster transfer of a station from one
            access point to another. Faster transitions are essential to
            support real time applications such as VoIP ("voice over IP", or
            Internet-based telephony) via mobile phones designed to work with
            wireless Internet networks, instead of (or in addition to)
            standard cellular networks. This will permit connectivity aboard
            vehicles in motion, with fast handoffs from one base station to
            another managed in a seamless manner. Handoffs are supported under
            the "a", "b" and "g" implementations. <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Ratified and published in July of
            2008.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">802.11s</emphasis>: "Mesh Networking"
            - Wireless Distribution System (WDS) protocol that is able to
            auto-configure paths between APs. <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: ???</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">802.11u</emphasis>: "Inter-working
            with External Networks" - The primary focus is on inter-working
            with cellular networks.<emphasis role="bold"> Status</emphasis>:
            Ongoing; still being evaluated.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">802.11v</emphasis>: "Wireless Network
            Management" - Management (monitoring, configuring, updating) of
            attached stations through layer 2. It is to complement 802.11k
            that gathers information from the stations.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">802.11y</emphasis>: "3650-3700 MHz
            Operation in the U.S" - This amendment to 802.11-2007 would allows
            WiFi "like" equipment to operate at higher power levels with a
            range of up to 5 kilometres in the United States. It introduces
            three new concepts to the 802.11-2007 standard: Contention Based
            Protocol, Extended Channel Switch Announcement, and Dependent
            Station Enablement. Even though the current form is specific to
            operations in the United States, care was taken so that, if the
            light licensing concept was well received, it would not be
            necessary to start the 3+ year task group process in order for
            802.11y devices to operate in other countries or in other
            frequency bands. As a result, lightly licensed 802.11 devices will
            be able to operate in any 5, 10, or 20Â MHz channel that
            regulators make available by simply adding entries to the country
            and regulatory information tables in Annex I and J of 802.11. Has
            implications in the following areas: Back haul for Municipal Wi-Fi
            networks, Industrial automation/controls, Campus/Enterprise
            networking, Last Mile Wireless Broadband Access, Fixed Point to
            point links, Fixed point to mobile links, and Public safety and
            security networks. <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>:
            Submitted for approval in June of 2008; Still not ratified.</para>
            <table>
              <title>Emerging 802.11x Summary</title>
              <tgroup cols="3">
                <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="15*" />
                <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" />
                <colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="25*" />
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry>
                      <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                      <emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                      <emphasis role="bold">Status </emphasis>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>IEEE 802.11k</entry>
                    <entry>Radio resource measurement enhancements</entry>
                    <entry>Ongoing</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>IEEE 802.11n</entry>
                    <entry>Higher throughput improvements (e.g. MIMO)</entry>
                    <entry>Ongoing. Estimated ratification in 2009</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>IEEE 802.11p</entry>
                    <entry>WAVE -Wireless Access for the Vehicular Environment
                    (such as ambulances and passenger cars)</entry>
                    <entry>Ongoing. Estimated ratification in 2009.</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>IEEE 802.11r</entry>
                    <entry>Fast roaming</entry>
                    <entry>Ratified in July of 2008</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>IEEE 802.11s</entry>
                    <entry>EWireless mesh networking</entry>
                    <entry>Ongoing</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>IEEE 802.11t</entry>
                    <entry>Wireless Performance Prediction (WPP) -test methods
                    and metrics</entry>
                    <entry>Ongoing</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>IEEE 802.11u</entry>
                    <entry>Inter-working with non-802 networks (e.g.,
                    cellular)</entry>
                    <entry>Ongoing</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>IEEE 802.11v</entry>
                    <entry>Wireless network management</entry>
                    <entry>Ongoing</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>IEEE 802.11w</entry>
                    <entry>Protected Management Frames</entry>
                    <entry>Ongoing</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>IEEE 802.11y</entry>
                    <entry>3650-3700 Operation in USA with wide range</entry>
                    <entry>Ongoing. Estimated ratification in 2009.</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Mobile Broadband Wireless Access (MBWA)</title>
          <para>While many military installations have some sort of high-speed
          network backbone connected by fibre optic cabling, many of the
          buildings do not have high-speed connections to the backbone. This
          is because fibre-optic cabling, necessary for most high-speed
          communications, must first be installed in the ground.</para>
          <para>Three emerging mobile data architectures have the most promise
          to eliminate the need for cables. In an effort to further improve
          mobile technology bandwidth, the IEEE 802 standards group which is
          already developing 802.11 (Wireless , WLAN), 802.15 (Personal Area
          Networks, PAN), 802.17 (Fixed Broadband Wireless Access, FBWA) has
          turned its attention to a new standardisation efforts on mobile
          broadband wireless access (MBWA).</para>
          <para>As with many civil based technologies the key question is
          likely to be the performance of the system under stress (e.g.
          Interference/jamming). However, there exists a possibility of a low
          cost wireless network offering all IP connectivity for easy
          integration with other component networks, rapid base-station
          deployment, basic network security (allowing higher security to
          layer on top) and high performance to many users.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Importance</emphasis>: Installing fibres
          is a disruptive, costly and time-consuming process. Trenching costs
          become prohibitive to reach remote areas, such as transportation
          depots and ranges. Also, right-of-way issues and physical barriers
          such as lakes and historical grounds can increase the cost of
          installing fibre-optic cabling.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Implications</emphasis>: In the tactical
          world, MBWA may be well suited for quickly establishing links
          between temporary camps, command centres, and vehicles.</para>
          <table>
            <title>Data Architecture</title>
            <tgroup cols="6">
              <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" />
              <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" />
              <colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" />
              <colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" />
              <colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" />
              <colspec colname="col6" colnum="6" />
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry align="center" morerows="1" nameend="col2" namest="col1" valign="middle">
                    <emphasis role="bold">Characteristics</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                  <entry align="center" nameend="col6" namest="col3" valign="middle">
                    <emphasis role="bold">Mobile Data
                  Architectures</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry align="center" colname="col3" valign="middle">
                    <emphasis role="bold">802.16e</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                  <entry align="center" colname="col4" valign="middle">
                    <emphasis role="bold">802.20</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                  <entry align="center" colname="col5" valign="middle">
                    <emphasis role="bold">HiperMAN</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                  <entry align="center" colname="col6" valign="middle">
                    <emphasis role="bold">4G+</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry align="left" valign="middle">Standard
                  Type</entry>
                  <entry />
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">Open</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">Open</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">Open</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">Open</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry morerows="1" valign="middle">Cell Radius</entry>
                  <entry>Line-of-sight</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col3" valign="middle">48
                  km</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col4" valign="middle">-</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col5" valign="middle">10
                  km</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col6" valign="middle">-</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Non Line-of-sight</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">3
                  km</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">-</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">4km</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">-</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry align="left" valign="middle">Cell
                  Speed</entry>
                  <entry />
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">60
                  miles/hr</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">250
                  km/hr</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">-</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">-</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry align="left" colname="col1" morerows="2" valign="middle">Data Rate</entry>
                  <entry>Moving</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col3" valign="middle">&lt; 10
                  Mbps</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col4" valign="middle">-</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col5" valign="middle">-</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col6" valign="middle">280
                  Mbit/s</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry align="left" colname="col2" valign="middle">Stationary</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col3" valign="middle">10
                  Mbps</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col4" valign="middle">-</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col5" valign="middle">14
                  Mbit/s</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col6" valign="middle">1
                  Gbit/s</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Peak</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col3" valign="middle">70
                  Mbps</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col4" valign="middle">1
                  Mbps</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col5" valign="middle">63
                  Mbit/s</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col6" valign="middle">-</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry align="left" colname="col1" valign="middle">Spectrum</entry>
                  <entry />
                  <entry align="right" colname="col3" valign="middle">&lt; 6
                  GHz</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col4" valign="middle">-</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col5" valign="middle">5.725-5.875 GHz</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col6" valign="middle">-</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry align="left" colname="col1" valign="middle">Architecture</entry>
                  <entry />
                  <entry align="right" colname="col3" valign="middle">Packet</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col4" valign="middle">Packet</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col5" valign="middle">Packet</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col6" valign="middle">Packet/Circuit</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry align="left" colname="col1" valign="middle">Bands</entry>
                  <entry />
                  <entry align="right" colname="col3" valign="middle">Selectable Between 2-6 GHz</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col4" valign="middle">Licensed
                  Bands below 3.5 GHz</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col5" valign="middle">Selectable Between 2-11 GHz (Mainly 3.5
                  GHz)</entry>
                  <entry align="right" colname="col6" valign="middle">Licensed
                  Bands below 2.7 GHz</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry align="left" valign="middle">Latency</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle" />
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">Low</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">Low</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">High</entry>
                  <entry align="right" valign="middle">High</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
          <sect4>
            <title>Mobile Telephone (4G+)</title>
            <para>Although the new 3G systems (mobile phone companies have
            invested heavily in this technology) have just been launched not
            long ago, many companies have already started on researching and
            developing on the fourth generation (4G) system. Researchers are
            hoping that the 4G system can reach a much faster speed, a
            connection speed over 100Mb per second during connection, tighter
            network security and also bring up the quality during
            communication no matter on voice or video calls. Via mobile
            phones, many things such as the security system, surveillance on
            certain items could be done easily.</para>
            <para>One 4G+ standardisation effort called Ultra Mobile Broadband
            (UMB) is being coordinated by 3GPP2 (Collaboration between five
            Asian and North American standards bodies. It will improve the
            CDMA2000 mobile phone standard for next generation applications
            and requirements. The proposed system intends to employ OFDMA
            technology along with advanced antenna techniques to provide peak
            rates of up to 280 Mbit/s. Goals for UMB include significantly
            improving system capacity, greatly increasing user data rates
            throughout the cell, lowering costs, enhancing existing services,
            making possible new applications, and making use of new spectrum
            opportunities. The technology will provide users with concurrent
            IP-based services in a full mobility environment.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: The UMB
            standardisation is expected to be completed in late 2007, with
            commercialisation taking place around mid-2009 or early
            2010.</para>
          </sect4>
          <sect4>
            <title>High Capacity Spatial Division Multiple Access (HC-SDMA, or
            iBurst)</title>
            <para>The HC-SDMA interface provides wide-area broadband wireless
            data-connectivity for fixed, portable and mobile computing devices
            and appliances. The protocol is designed to be implemented with
            smart antenna array techniques to substantially improve the radio
            frequency (RF) coverage, capacity and performance for the
            system.</para>
            <para>The HC-SDMA interface operates on a similar premise as GSM
            or CDMA2000 for cellular phones, with hand-offs between HC-SDMA
            cells reportedly providing the user with a seamless wideband
            wireless experience even when moving at the speed of a car or
            train.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: HC-SDMA is being
            incorporated by ISO TC204 WG16 into its standards for use of
            wireless broadband systems in the continuous communications
            standards architecture, known as CALM. The IEEE 802.20 working
            group had adopted a technology proposal that includes the use of
            the HC-SDMA standard for the 625kHz Multi-Carrier Time Division
            Duplex (TDD) mode. Technology is available Asia, Europe, Africa,
            Middle East, and North America.</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Ad-Hoc Networking</title>
          <sect4>
            <title>Mobile Ad-Hoc Networks (MANET)</title>
            <para>A mobile ad-hoc network (MANET) is a self-configuring
            network of mobile routers (and associated hosts) connected by
            wireless links. The routers are free to move randomly and
            arbitrarily organise themselves. Accordingly, the topology of the
            wireless network may change rapidly and unpredictably. Such a
            network may operate in a standalone fashion, or may be connected
            to the larger Internet. With attributes such as minimal
            configuration and quick deployment make ad hoc networks
            appropriate for situations like disasters (natural or man-made),
            medical emergencies, military conflicts, etc.</para>
            <para>The earliest predate the Internet and were called "packet
            radio" networks. These early packet radio systems were part of the
            motivation of the original Internet Protocol suite. Current are
            designed principally for military utility; examples include Joint
            Tactical Radio System (JTRS) and the High-Capacity Data Radio
            (HCDR).</para>
            <para>The widespread IEEE 802.11 ("WiFi") wireless protocol
            incorporates an ad-hoc networking system when no wireless access
            points are present, although it would be considered a very
            low-grade ad-hoc protocol by specialists in the field. The IEEE
            802.11 system only handles traffic within a local "cloud" of
            wireless devices. Each node transmits and receives data, but does
            not route anything between the network's systems. However,
            higher-level protocols can be used to aggregate various IEEE
            802.11 ad-hoc networks into .</para>
          </sect4>
          <sect4>
            <title>Sensor Networks</title>
            <para>A sensor network is composed of a large number of sensor
            nodes that are densely deployed either inside an area of operation
            or very close to it. The sensor nodes are tiny, low-cost,
            low-power, self-organising and multi-functional (sensing, data
            processing, and communicating). Since the sensor nodes can be
            random deployed, such networks are ideal in inaccessible terrains
            or disaster relief operations</para>
            <table id="v3t-sensor-adhoc">
              <title>Sensor vs. Ad-Hoc</title>
              <tgroup cols="3">
                <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="33*" />
                <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="33*" />
                <colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="34*" />
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry align="center">
                      <emphasis role="bold">Characteristics</emphasis>
                    </entry>
                    <entry align="center" valign="middle">
                      <emphasis role="bold">Sensor Networks</emphasis>
                    </entry>
                    <entry align="center">
                      <emphasis role="bold">Traditional
                    Ad-Hoc</emphasis>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Communication</entry>
                    <entry>Broadcast</entry>
                    <entry>Point-to-Point</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Node Numbers</entry>
                    <entry>Large</entry>
                    <entry>Small</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Node Density</entry>
                    <entry>High</entry>
                    <entry>Low</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Node ID</entry>
                    <entry>None</entry>
                    <entry>Individual</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Failure Rate</entry>
                    <entry>High</entry>
                    <entry>Low</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Mobility</entry>
                    <entry>No</entry>
                    <entry>Yes</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>
            <para>The differences between a sensor network and a traditional
            ad-hoc network can be seen in <xref linkend="v3t-sensor-adhoc" />.
            The protocols and algorithms used in traditional ad-hoc networks
            do not work well with sensor networks primarily because of the
            relatively large number of sensor nodes used by sensor
            networks.</para>
            <figure float="0">
              <title>Sensor Field</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../figures/sensorField.svg" format="SVG" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Radio</title>
          <sect4>
            <title>Radio over Internet Protocol (RoIP)</title>
            <para>Radio over IP is an method of converting analog radio
            signals into packets that transmited over an IP network. This
            capability of integrating disparate data and video signals with an
            IP infrasturcture could be the long disatnce hauler of short
            distance radio signals. With RoIP, there are no interoperability
            issues, all radio signals (e.g. VHF, UHF, POTS telephone, cellular
            telephone, SATCOM, air-to-ground) are packetized the same.
            Demodulation and detection of the orignal message is done after it
            has been transported.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Draft standard is
            being developed by NIST, for the Bridging System Interface (BSI)
            hardware and software that enables radio gateway interoperability
            on a RoIP system. A half-dozen companies now offer Radio Over IP
            solutions. The tactical use of this technology has been
            demonstrated by coalition military forces in Afganistan and Iraq
            to protect convoys spread out across large geographic
            distances.</para>
          </sect4>
          <sect4>
            <title>Radio Frequency Identification (RFID)</title>
            <para>Radio Frequency Identification technology shares some
            similar characteristics with IP technology. IP is a remarkably
            flexible addressing system for information while RFID is a
            flexible addressing system for physical objects. RFID creates "an
            Internet of things" - a world of objects connected by Internet
            technologies. Indeed, it is possible that this new Internet of
            objects could significantly affect network architecture in the
            years to come.</para>
            <para>RFID is the labelling system behind IP-enabled inventory and
            supply. Standard RFID tags contain three times the amount of
            information that can be stored in bar codes. They transmit data
            without contact or Line-of-sight with the reader, and can be read
            through dust, snow, ice, paint, or grime - conditions that render
            optical technologies, like bar coding, useless. Long-range tags
            can be read at speeds achievable by cars or trains, automated toll
            readers are a good example of this.</para>
            <para>Capacitor / Coil (1) RFID reader Broadcasts electromagnetic
            signal to tag (4). The tag's coils release an encoded radio wave
            containing the information in the tag, which the reader then
            demodulates.(2) Antenna in the tag receives the signal from the
            reader and stores charge in a capacitor.(3) When the capacitor has
            built up enough energy, it releases it over time to the tag's
            coils.</para>
            <figure float="0">
              <title>RFID Example</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../figures/rfidExample.svg" format="SVG" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>Most RFID tags are passive and read-only. With a virtually
            unlimited operating lifetime, they consist of little more than a
            computer chip and an antenna. A compatible reader provides power
            to the tag over short distances between a few centimetres to
            thirty meters. The tag 'awakens' and reports any information it
            has available to the reader. Active tags, on the other hand, are
            self-powered, have longer ranges than passive tags, and are
            constantly reporting relevant information to any reader within
            range. Active tags are becoming increasingly common, especially on
            expensive items, or cartons of items. A reader installed in a
            lock, for example, can automatically receive information from
            active tags in every vessel and shipping box that passes through.
            Additionally, some RFID tags are writable as well as
            readable.</para>
            <para>Security is the key challenge with RFID. If a NATO nation
            implements RFID in its supply chain, and does not want other NATO
            nations to track its shipments and inventory, then that nation
            would perceive RFID technology as a significant security
            vulnerability.</para>
            <para>Some researchers have proposed schemes that would require
            tags to authenticate readers, transmitting information only to
            authorised readers. The tags would have to store ID numbers for
            authorised readers, and a reader would have to broadcast its ID to
            the tag. To protect the reader's ID and prevent others from
            eavesdropping and stealing the information, the reader uses either
            a fixed or randomly generated number to hash (encrypt) its ID. If
            the tag cannot authenticate the reader's identity, the tag will
            refuse to transmit the information it stores. Like most security
            tactics, this scheme is vulnerable to attacks, such as man in the
            middle, or reverse engineering.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Importance</emphasis>: An advanced way
            to automate the tracking of people and things.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Implications</emphasis>: Improved
            logistics through better management of supplies and
            inventories.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Because of the
            potential market, several vendors are actively researching
            security and legacy integration issues. The big challenge to RFID
            is its integration into existing systems. Several vendors are
            developing RFID middle-ware that will link new RFID systems into
            existing back-end infrastructures. middle-ware, for example, can
            help with the current lack of standards in RFID. If an
            organisation picks a standard that changes or loses its market
            prevalence, middle-ware can transform the data from readers into
            the format supported by back-end systems.</para>
          </sect4>
          <sect4>
            <title>Software Defined Radio (SDR)</title>
            <para>Software Defined Radio (SDR) technology uses software to
            modulate and demodulate radio signals. This flexible approach
            would solve the problem of having to carry several types of
            special purpose radio. Ideally, one radio could can receive and
            transmit a new form of radio protocol just by running new
            software. All functionality and expandability is built upon the
            Software Communications Architecture (SCA), an international open
            architecture framework available from the Object Management Group
            (OMG).</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Importance:</emphasis> Reduces the
            need for troops to carry multiple radios.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Implications</emphasis>: Adaptable
            radios can solve cross-nation, and cross organisation
            communication interoperability problems.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: All the pieces
            needed to make this technology work in a tactical military
            environment are not ready. The biggest hurdles are form-factor,
            power consumption, and antenna size. Packaging such a radio that
            can handle every waveform used on a battlefield is daunting.
            Putting a 50 lb radio with a 30 foot antenna on the back of a foot
            solider is not practical.</para>
          </sect4>
          <sect4>
            <title>Cognitive Radio Technology</title>
            <para>Cognitive Radio technology is, when combined with Software
            Defined Radio technology, an effort to efficiently utilise the
            electromagnetic spectrum. The argument is that in any given region
            of the world, some portions of the spectrum are over utilised
            while some are underutilised. A cognitive radio will analyse the
            local spectrum and determine where there are spectrum "holes", or
            under-used spectrum. It is in these "holes" that the adaptive
            radio will operate by using software defined radio technology to
            reconfigure its broadcasting characteristics as needed.</para>
            <para>The real issue is how that spectrum is managed, not the lack
            of available spectrum. A cognitive radio will not only analyse the
            spectrum usage, but negotiate usage with nearby devices. Compare
            the scheme to a driver's reacting to what she sees other drivers
            doing. If you are in a traffic lane that is heavy, maybe it's time
            for you to shift to another lane that is not so busy. When
            shifting lanes, however, a driver needs to follow rules that
            prevent her from bumping into others.</para>
            <para>The MAC layer of the IEEE 802.22 wireless standard will be
            based in Cognitive Radio Technology. It needs to be also able to
            adapt dynamically to changes in the environment by sensing the
            spectrum. The MAC layer will consist of two structures: Frame and
            Superframe. A superframe will be formed by many frames. The
            superframe will have an SCH (Superframe Control Header) and a
            preamble. These will be sent by the BS in every channel that it's
            possible to transmit and not cause interference. When a CPE is
            turned on, it will sense the spectrum, find out which channels are
            available and will receive all the needed information to attach to
            the BS. Two different types of spectrum measurement will be done
            by the CPE: in-band and out-of-band. The in-band measurement
            consists in sensing the actual channel that is being used by the
            BS and CPE. The out-of-band measurement will consist in sensing
            the rest of the channels. The MAC layer will perform two different
            types of sensing in either in-band or out-of-band measurements:
            fast sensing and fine sensing. Fast sensing will consist in
            sensing at speeds of under 1ms per channel. This sensing is
            performed by the CPE and the BS and the BS's will gather all the
            information and will decide if there is something new to be done.
            The fine sensing takes more time (approximately 25 ms per channel
            or more) and it is utilized based on the outcome of the previous
            fast sensing mechanism. These sensing mechanisms are primarily
            used to identify if there is an incumbent transmitting, and if
            there is a need to avoid interfering with it.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Importance:</emphasis> Enables
            efficient usage of available limited spectrum.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Implications</emphasis>: Ideal
            companion technology to Software Defined Radio Technology.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Approved by IEEE in
            january of 2008, the 802.22 standard is the first wireless
            standard based on cognitive radios.</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Wired Networking</title>
        <para>When compared to wireless networking, the more mature wired
        networking area provides benefits in cost, reliabilty and
        performance.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Implications</emphasis>: The need for
        wired networking will be dictated by the operational
        environment.</para>
        <sect3>
          <title>Fibre-Channel over Ethernet (FCoE)</title>
          <para>Fibre-Channel over ethernet allows Fibre-Channel devices to
          connect with one another over ethernet based networks. With FCoE,
          native Fibre-Channel frames are encapsulated into ethernet frames to
          be sent over a 10-Gbit Ethernet network. Considered a low-cost, high
          performance alternative to Fibre-Channel over long distances. The
          main applications that benifet from this technology are sStorage
          Area Networks (SANs). With FCoE, network (IP) and storage (SAN) data
          traffic can be consolidated using a single network switch. This
          consolidation can:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>reduce the number of network interface cards required to
              connect to disparate storage and IP networks</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>reduce the number of cables and switches</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>reduce power and cooling costs</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>increase utilization of servers through server
              virtualization technologies</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Not yet apporved as a
          standard by INCITS, InterNational Committee for Information
          Technology Standards organisaton, but several vendors are shipping
          products that will support the future standard. Expected to be
          ratified in late 2009 or early 2010.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Transport Layer</title>
        <sect3>
          <title>Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP)</title>
          <para>The Stream Control Transmission Protocol operates on top of
          the Internet Protocol (IP), and is defined in the RFC 2960 (IETF
          standard). SCTP was developed to provide reliable transport of SS7
          messages over an IP network.</para>
          <para>The Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP) is a new IP
          transport protocol that operates on top of the Internet Protocol
          (IP), and is defined in the RFC 2960 (IETF standard). It exists at
          an equivalent level with UDP (User Datagram Protocol) and TCP
          (Transmission Control Protocol), which provide transport layer
          functions to many Internet applications.</para>
          <para>Like TCP, SCTP provides a reliable transport service, ensuring
          that data is transported across the network without error and in
          sequence. Like TCP, SCTP is a session-oriented mechanism, meaning
          that a relationship is created between the endpoints of an SCTP
          association prior to data being transmitted, and this relationship
          is maintained until all data transmission has been successfully
          completed.</para>
          <para>Unlike TCP, SCTP provides a number of functions that are
          critical for telephony signalling transport, and at the same time
          can potentially benefit other applications needing transport with
          additional performance and reliability.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: SCTP has been
          approved by the IETF as a Proposed Standard. The error check
          algorithm has since been modified. Future changes and updates will
          be reflected in the IETF RFC index. SCTP has been implemented on
          several OS: Windows XP, Linux, AIX, BSD, Solaris, and QNX
          Neutrino.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Green Information Technology</title>
      <para>There has always been a push to make technology faster. Now,
      emerging new trends are driving technologies to become more efficient as
      well. The drivers of these new trends vary from higher energy costs to
      environmental concerns. In the past, military interests in technology
      were less concern with how efficient it was, than how competent it was
      in producing a desired effect.</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Implications</emphasis>: Reduction of power
      consumption during mlitary operations directly effects the costs of
      conducting such operations. From a NATO perspective, cost-savings
      incurred through efficiency will have larger impact on participants with
      less finanical resources to devote to NATO operations.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>IEEE 802.3az (Green Ethernet)</title>
        <para>The goals of the IEEE 802.3az task force are pretty
        straightforward: define a mechanism to reduce power consumption during
        periods of low link utilization and a protocol to coordinate
        transitions to or from a lower level of power consumption. It'll work
        only on new hardware, of course, but that hardware should be fully
        backward-compatible. Using "channel staggering" in combination with a
        few other technologies may lead to a 50-85% power savings.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: First draft of the
        specification should by out by the end of 2008, though the final
        version won't be ratified until early of 2010.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>IEEE 1680 (Environmental Assessment)</title>
        <para>Modern IT systems rely upon a complicated mix of people,
        networks and hardware; as such, a green computing standard must be
        systemic in nature, and address increasingly sophisticated problems.
        The IEEE 1680 standard defines 51 criteria used in the assessment of
        computing products for enironmental imapct. Impact is measure by
        reduced use of hazardous materials, maximum energy efficiency during a
        product's lifetime, and promotion of recyclability or biodegradability
        of defunct products. Products that passes at least 21of the the 51
        criteria, are eligble to be certified as Energy-Star or EPEAT
        compliant.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Ratified in 2006, the
        standard was viewed as ambiguous in how to apply specific criteria.
        Recent verification rounds has prompted detailed clarification and
        established Interpretations of some portions of the IEEE 1680
        standard. With the new supplemental guidance it should be more widely
        accepted over the next 3-5 years.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Cloud Computing</title>
      <para>The "Cloud" in Cloud computing describes a combination of
      inter-connected networks. This technology area focuses on breaking up a
      task into sub-tasks. The sub-tasks are then executed simultaneously on
      two or more computers that are communicating with each other over the
      &#x201C;Cloud&#x201D;. Later, the completed sub-tasks are reassembled to form the
      completed original main task. There are many different types of
      distributed computing systems and many issues to overcome in
      successfully designing one. Many of these issues deal with accommodating
      a wide-ranging mix of computer platforms with assorted capabilities that
      could potentially be networked together</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Implications</emphasis>: The main goal of a
      cloud computing system is to connect users and resources in a
      transparent, open, and scalable way. Ideally this arrangement is
      drastically more fault tolerant and more powerful than many combinations
      of stand-alone computer systems. If practiced in a NATO environment,
      member nations would consume their IT services in the most
      cost-effective way, over a broad range of services (for example,
      computational power, storage and business applications) from the
      "cloud," rather than from on-premises equipment.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>Platforms</title>
        <para>Cloud-computing platforms have given many businesses flexible
        access to computing resources, ushering in an era in which, among
        other things, startups can operate with much lower infrastructure
        costs. Instead of having to buy or rent hardware, users can pay for
        only the processing power that they actually use and are free to use
        more or less as their needs change. However, relying on cloud
        computing comes with drawbacks, including privacy, security, and
        reliability concerns.</para>
        <sect3>
          <title>Amazon's Elastic Compute Cloud (EC2)</title>
          <para>Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud (Amazon EC2) is a web service
          that provides resizable compute capacity in the cloud. It is
          designed to make web-scale computing easier for developers. If your
          application needs the processing power of 100 CPUs then you scale up
          your demand. Conversely, if your application is idle then you scale
          down then amount of computing resources that you allocate.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>:The first company to
          successfully levearge the excess computing resources from its
          primary bussiness. Currently, CPU cycles and storage are at pennies
          per hour or GB.</para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Microsoft's Azure Services Platform</title>
          <para>Windows® Azure is a cloud services operating system that
          serves as the development, service hosting and service management
          environment for the Azure Services Platform. Windows Azure provides
          developers with on-demand compute and storage to host, scale, and
          manage Web applications on the Internet through Microsoft® data
          centers.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: During the Community
          Technology Preview (CTP) developers invited to the program, which
          includes all attendees of the Microsoft Professional Developers
          Conference 2008 (PDC), receive free trial access to the Azure
          Services Platform SDK, a set of cloud-optimized modular components
          including Windows Azure and .NET Services, as well as the ability to
          host their finished application or service in Microsoft
          datacenters.</para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Google App Engine</title>
          <para>Google App Engine enables you to build web applications on the
          same scalable systems that power Google applications. App Engine
          applications are easy to build, easy to maintain, and easy to scale
          as your traffic and data storage needs grow. With App Engine, there
          are no servers to maintain: You just upload your application, and
          it's ready to serve to your users. Google App Engine applications
          are implemented using the Python programming language.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Currently in the
          preview release stage. You can use up to 500MB of persistent storage
          and enough CPU and bandwidth for about 5 million page views a month
          for free. Later on if you want additional computing resources, you
          will have to purchase it.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Grid Computing</title>
        <para>Grid computing is the collective name of technologies that
        attempt to combine a set of distributed nodes into a common resource
        pool. The term grid computing stems from an analogy with electric
        power grids that combine a large set of resources (power plants,
        transformers, power lines) into simple well defined product (the power
        outlet) that the user can use without having to know the details of
        the infrastructure behind it.</para>
        <para>Typical for grid computing is also that it offers a framework
        for management of node memberships, access control, and life cycle
        management. Common applications of grid computing allow well defined
        organisations to share computational resources or storage resources so
        that resources may be used efficiently and resource demanding tasks
        can be performed that would otherwise have required large specialised
        and/or local investments.</para>
        <figure float="0">
          <title>Grid Computing</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../figures/gridComputing.svg" format="SVG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>While some grid computing systems have been designed for a
        specific purpose, some standards for Grid infrastructure have also
        evolved that make the task of setting up a Grid easier and provide a
        common interface to application developers. Such standardisation
        efforts have resulted in Globus Toolkit [51] and OGSA (Open Grid
        Services Architecture) [53].</para>
        <para>The Global Grid Forum (GGF) [52] is a set of working groups
        where much work on grid computing standardisation is ongoing, and that
        also is behind the OGSA standard. Their web site is a good source of
        information about ongoing work in the field and examples of grid
        projects.</para>
        <sect3>
          <title>Globus Toolkit</title>
          <para>Globus Toolkit [51] offers tools and APIs for building secure
          grid infrastructures. It offers a secure infrastructure (GSI) on top
          of which support for resource management, information services, and
          data management is provided. It is being developed by Globus
          Alliance [50], and is among other applications being used as a
          foundation for implementation of OGSA.</para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>OGSA</title>
          <para>OGSA [53] (developed by the Global Grid Forum, GGF [52])
          builds on a combination of Globus Toolkit [51] (developed by the
          Globus Alliance [50]) and Web service technologies to model and
          encapsulate resources in the Grid. A number of special Web service
          interfaces are defined by OGSA that support service management,
          dynamic service creation, message notification, and service
          registration. A number of implementations of OGSA have been made,
          including for example OGSI (Open Grid Services Infrastructure) and
          WSRF (Web Services Resource Framework, developed by OASIS [47]).
          Today, WSRF is the chosen basis for further development of
          OGSA</para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>OSGi</title>
          <para>OSGi is a standard for a framework for remotely manageable
          networked devices [25]. Applications can be securely provisioned to
          a network node running an OSGi framework during runtime and thus
          provides the possibility to dynamically manage the services and
          functionality of the network node. The OSGi model is based upon a
          service component architecture, where all functionality in the node
          is provided as "small" service components (called bundles). All
          services are context aware of each other and heavily adapt their
          functionality depending on what other services are available.
          Services must degrade gracefully when the services they depend upon
          are not available in the framework. These network nodes are designed
          to reliably provide their services 24/7/365. Adding an OSGi Service
          Platform to a networked node/device adds the capability to manage
          the life cycle of the software components in the device. Adding new
          services thus makes it more future proof and gives the node
          flexibility.</para>
          <para>OSGi adopts a SOA based approach where all bundles deployed
          into an OSGi framework are described using well defined service
          interfaces. The bundle uses the framework's name service for
          publishing offered services and to retrieve services needed by the
          bundle itself. OSGi works well together with other standards and
          initiatives for example Jini or Web Services. OSGi is also an
          example of a technology where integration is carried out in the Java
          environment but the actual implementation of the services can be
          written in other languages, such as C.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Decentralised Computing</title>
        <para>Another trend in distributed system is to decrease the
        dependence on centralised resources. A centralised resource is
        typically some service of function implemented by dedicated nodes in
        the distributed system that many of or all other nodes depend on to
        perform their own services or functions. Examples of such services are
        shared databases, network routing and configuration functions, and
        name or catalogue services. Obviously, this may cause dependability
        problems as the centralised server becomes a potential single point of
        failure (). From some points of view, decentralisation (i.e To
        decrease the dependence single nodes), is therefore a property to
        strive for. However, decentralisation may also result in a (sometimes
        perceived) loss of control that fits poorly with traditional ways of
        thinking of, for example, security. Decentralisation can thus have a
        rather long-reaching impact on the way distributed systems are
        designed.</para>
        <para>Taken to its extreme, decentralisation strives for distributed
        systems where all nodes are considered equal in all respects (except
        of course their performance and capacity), i.e., all nodes are
        considered to peers. This is the foundation to peer-to-peer (P2P)
        systems, which will be discussed later. In such systems,
        decentralisation is realised by offering mechanisms to maintain a
        global shared state that is not stored by any single node.</para>
        <sect3>
          <title>Peer-to-Peer (P2P)</title>
          <para>Peer-to-peer, or P2P for short, is a technology trend that has
          received much attention in recent years. Unfortunately, much of this
          attention has been oriented towards questionable applications of
          P2P, such as illegal file sharing, rather than towards its merits as
          a technology that addresses important problems with traditional
          distributed systems.</para>
          <para>The fundamental idea behind P2P is, as is implied by its name,
          that all participating nodes in a distributed system shall be
          treated as peers, or equals. This is a clear deviation from the
          client/server concept, where some nodes play a central role as
          servers and other nodes play a role as clients. In those systems,
          the server nodes become critical for the system function, and thus
          need to be dependable, highly accessible, and dimensioned to handle
          a sometimes unpredictable workload. Obviously this may make a server
          node both a performance bottleneck and a dependability risk. P2P
          addresses such problems.</para>
          <figure float="0">
            <title>Peer-To-Peer</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/peer2peer.svg" format="SVG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>The fundamental important property of many P2P applications is
          that they allow storage of named objects, such as files, services,
          or database entries, to be spread over all nodes in a system instead
          of having to store and access them on centralised server nodes.
          Object names can be numbers or character strings; whichever is
          appropriate for the applications. Once stored in the system, any
          node can access a named object just by knowing its name. This means
          that a P2P system can have a global shared state that does not
          depend on any centralised node.</para>
          <para>While in principle avoiding a centralised solution, many early
          P2P systems, such as the Napster file sharing system actually relied
          on some central functions in order to implement the mapping from
          object names to object locations. However, in later generations of
          P2P decentralisation has been taken another step further, by the
          introduction of overlay networks, earlier in this report mentioned
          as a form of virtual networks.</para>
          <para>With an overlay network, a distributed means of finding the
          node that is responsible for storing an object with a given name is
          provided. Typically the set of all possible object names, called the
          name space, is divided into subsets such that each node becomes
          responsible for one subset of the name space. This means that the
          need for centralised resources is completely avoided. For a node to
          become part of a P2P system, i.e. To join the overlay network, all
          that is needed is knowledge of any other node already part of the
          system. As nodes join and leave the system, the responsibility for
          name space subsets is automatically redistributed.</para>
          <para>The development of overlay network based P2P systems has been
          driven by a striving to improve scalability, guarantees, and
          robustness. Today, a logarithmic logical scalability can be
          achieved, which means that to find a given node from any other node
          in the system requires at most logk(N) node-to-node messages to be
          sent, where k is some constant and N is the maximum number of nodes
          in the system. Note, however, that this scalability measure does not
          automatically translate into an exact measure of the actual time it
          takes to send a message between two nodes as this time will depend
          also on the distribution of nodes on the underlying physical
          network.</para>
          <para>The scalability issue has been addressed by a number of
          proposed P2P implementation techniques developed within academic
          research projects such as Chord [40], Pastry [41], and Tapestry
          [42]. However, scalability has been taken yet another step further
          by the DKS system developed at the Swedish Institute of Computer
          Science (SICS. In DKS, the amount of administrative traffic required
          to keep track of nodes in the overlay network is significantly
          reduced, and dimensioning parameters of the system can be fine-tuned
          in a very general framework (that actually treats the other
          mentioned techniques as special cases) so as to improve the
          practical scalability.</para>
          <para>Another important aspect of P2P systems is also the guarantees
          that can be given that any named object stored in the systems also
          can found. Such guarantees have improved over the P2P technology
          generations, and 100% guarantees can now be given by the DKS system
          assuming that there are no errors such as physical communication
          failures that make nodes unreachable. As intermittent or lasting
          communication failures must be expected in any practical system,
          techniques for improving the fault tolerance by means of replication
          of data have been investigated and are now being included into the
          general frameworks of P2P technologies.</para>
          <para>However, practical applications of new P2P technologies like
          DKS in distributed systems need to be investigated in order to
          determine how well scalability and robustness functions in practise
          given the impact of underlying infrastructure and application
          properties. An example of an ongoing such project investigates the
          properties of a DKS based implementation of central service in the
          OpenSIS standard [49].</para>
          <para>To summarise, P2P technologies have matured into a practical
          way of organising distributed systems in a decentralised way that is
          both highly scalable and reliable. Excellent reviews and
          descriptions of P2P technologies can be found in [16], [19], and
          [20].</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Currently the
          advantages of P2P technologies (pooling computing power, pooling
          bandwidth of the participants, and elimination of the server/client
          distinction) don't outweigh the disadvantages (legal obstacles, and
          security vulnerabilities)</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Service Delivery Platform (SDP)</title>
      <para>Service Delivery Platform (SDP) is an architecture that enables
        the quick development, deployment and integration (convergence) of
        broadband, video, wireless and wire-line services can cater to many
        technologies including VoIP, IPTV, HSD (High Speed Data), Mobile
        Telephony, Online Gaming, etc.</para>
      <para>Examples of a converged architecture:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>A user can see incoming phone calls (Wire-line or Wireless),
            IM buddies (PC) or the location of friends (GPS Enabled Device) on
            their television screen.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A user can order VoD (Video on Demand) services from their
            mobile phone or watch streaming video that they have ordered as a
            video package for both home and mobile phone.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>SDPs in the converged services world need to be designed and
        engineered using information and identity engineering techniques as a
        core discipline because a is supporting online users their services. A
        needs to be a real time multi function system that interfaces to the
        back office systems for billing and to the network infrastructure
        systems. From an information engineering perspective there could be
        20-100 information items associated with a user, their devices and
        their content and if there are 10 million users on the system, it
        means that the needs scale up to associate with a billion pieces of
        information used in random ways. SDPs also need to address the issues
        of converged services management, account control, self care, and
        entitlements as well as presence based event type services. Service
        Delivery Platform, identity engineering and white papers on presence
        based services can be found at *www.wwite.com.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol v.3 (LDAP)</title>
        <para>The following is a partial list of RFCs specifying LDAPv3
          extensions:</para>
        <table>
          <title>Summary of LDAP Related RFCs</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="15*" />
            <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="85*" />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 2247</entry>
                <entry>Use of DNS domains in distinguished names</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 2307</entry>
                <entry>Using LDAP as a Network Information Service</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 2589</entry>
                <entry>LDAPv3: Dynamic Directory Services Extensions</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 2649</entry>
                <entry>LDAPv3 Operational Signatures</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 2696</entry>
                <entry>LDAP Simple Paged Result Control</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 2798</entry>
                <entry>inetOrgPerson LDAP Object Class</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 2849</entry>
                <entry>The LDAP Data Interchange Format (LDIF)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 2891</entry>
                <entry>Server Side Sorting of Search Results</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 3045</entry>
                <entry>Storing Vendor Information in the LDAP root
                  DSE</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 3062</entry>
                <entry>LDAP Password Modify Extended Operation</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 3296</entry>
                <entry>Named Subordinate References in LDAP
                  Directories</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 3671</entry>
                <entry>Collective Attributes in LDAP</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 3672</entry>
                <entry>Subentries in LDAP</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 3673</entry>
                <entry>LDAPv3: All Operational Attributes</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 3687</entry>
                <entry>LDAP Component Matching Rules</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 3698</entry>
                <entry>LDAP: Additional Matching Rules</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 3829</entry>
                <entry>LDAP Authorisation Identity Controls</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 3866</entry>
                <entry>Language Tags and Ranges in LDAP</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 3909</entry>
                <entry>LDAP Cancel Operation</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 3928</entry>
                <entry>LDAP Client Update Protocol</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4370</entry>
                <entry>LDAP Proxied Authorisation Control</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4373</entry>
                <entry>LBURP</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4403</entry>
                <entry>LDAP Schema for UDDI</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4522</entry>
                <entry>LDAP: Binary Encoding Option</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4523</entry>
                <entry>LDAP: X.509 Certificate Schema</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4524</entry>
                <entry>LDAP: COSINE Schema (replaces RFC 1274)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4525</entry>
                <entry>LDAP: Modify-Increment Extension</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4526</entry>
                <entry>LDAP: Absolute True and False Filters</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4527</entry>
                <entry>LDAP: Read Entry Controls</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4528</entry>
                <entry>LDAP: Assertion Control</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4529</entry>
                <entry>LDAP: Requesting Attributes by Object Class</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4530</entry>
                <entry>LDAP: entryUUID</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4531</entry>
                <entry>LDAP Turn Operation</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4532</entry>
                <entry>LDAP Who am I? Operation</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>RFC 4533</entry>
                <entry>LDAP Content Sync Operation</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Composite Adaptive Directory Services</title>
        <para>Data bases have been with the IT industry for 30 years and
          traditional directories for the last 20 years and they will be with
          us in the future. However, with the larger scale, converged services
          and event driven (presence) systems now being developed world wide
          (e.g. 3G-IMS), information, identity and presence services
          engineering and the technologies that support it will require some
          evolution. This could take the form of CADS (Composite Adaptive
          Directory Services) and CADS supported Service Delivery Platforms.
          CADS is an advanced directory service and contains functions for
          managing identity, presence, content and adaptation algorithms for
          self tuning and with its unique functions, greatly simplifies and
          enhances the design of converged services SDPs. See Service Delivery
          Platform</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Networked Computing</title>
      <para>Networked computing is a set of technologies that treats the
        network as a computing platform, enables machine to machine
        communication, and offer efficient new ways to help networked
        computers organise and draw conclusions from online data.</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Implications</emphasis>: Reusable,
        repurposable, and reconnectable data/services will promote the
        convergence of Service Oriented Architecture and the Semantic
        Web.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>Web Services</title>
        <para>Web Services are software systems that enable machine to
          machine interaction over a network. The Web Services present
          themselves as web based Application Programming Interfaces (API)
          that use XML messages to communicate. No one standard defines Web
          Services, but is comprised of four core standards:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Extensible Markup Language
              (XML)</emphasis> - A simple platform independent language used
              to facilitate communication between different computing systems.
              (W3C)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Service Object Access Protocol
              (SOAP) 1.2</emphasis> - A protocol for exchanging XML based
              messages over networks using HTTP, HTTPS, SMTP, or XAMPP
              protocols. (W3C)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Web Services Description language
              (WSDL) 2.0</emphasis> - XML document format that describes
              interfaces and protocols need to connect to a Web Service.
              (W3C)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Universal Discovery, Description,
              and Integration (UDDI)</emphasis> - XML based registry that can
              be queried by SOAP messages, and return WSDL documents so that
              Web Services can be found and connected to. (OASIS)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>There are several efforts to extend the capabilities of Web
          Services.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">WS-Security </emphasis>- Defines how
              to use XML Encryption and XML Signature in SOAP to secure
              message exchanges, as an alternative or extension to using HTTPS
              to secure the channel.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">WS-Reliability</emphasis> - An OASIS
              standard protocol for reliable messaging between two Web
              services.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">WS-ReliableMessaging</emphasis> - A
              protocol for reliable messaging between two Web services, issued
              by Microsoft, BEA and IBM it is currently being standardised by
              the OASIS organisation</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">WS-Addressing</emphasis> - A way of
              describing the address of the recipient (and sender) of a
              message, inside the SOAP message itself.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">WS-Transaction</emphasis> - A way of
              handling transactions.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <sect3>
          <title>Web Service Specifications</title>
          <table>
            <title>Summary of Emerging Web Services Technologies</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="50*" />
              <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="50*" />
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Technology</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>WS-BPEL</entry>
                  <entry>Process composition</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>WSCI</entry>
                  <entry>Process composition</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>WSDM</entry>
                  <entry>Management and infrastructure</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>JBI</entry>
                  <entry>Process composition</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>SCA</entry>
                  <entry>Process composition</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Java-EE</entry>
                  <entry>Management and infrastructure</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Java-RMI</entry>
                  <entry>Distributed systems</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>.NET</entry>
                  <entry>Management and infrastructure</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Jini</entry>
                  <entry>Distributed systems, Service selection,
                      Management and infrastructure</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Rio</entry>
                  <entry>Distributed systems, Service selection, Process
                      composition, Management and infrastructure</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
          <sect4>
            <title>Business Process Execution Language for Web Services
              (WS-BPEL or BPEL4WS)</title>
            <para>The Business Process Execution Language (BPEL) originally
              proposed by Microsoft, and Siebel Systems. It is XML-based and
              is designed as a layer on top of WSDL that allows a standardised
              way of describing business process flows in terms of web
              services. A BPEL process can be used either to describe an
              executable work flow in a node (orchestration), or to describe
              the protocol for interaction between participants in a business
              process (choreography). <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>:
              As of January 2007, BPEL4WS is now an OASIS standard also
              referred to as WS-BPEL version 2.0. [23].</para>
          </sect4>
          <sect4>
            <title>Web Service Choreography Interface (WSCI)</title>
            <para>Other Web service based standards for Web service
              orchestration and choreography are , developed by Sun, , BEA,
              and Intalio, and BPML, initiated by Intalio, Sterling Commerce,
              Sun, and through the non-profit (Business Process Management
              Initiative) corporation. (Web Services Choreography Interface)
              extends WSDL (rather than being built on top of WSDL like BPEL)
              and focuses on the collaborative behaviour of either a service
              user or a service provider. <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: The WSCI specification is one of
              the primary inputs into the W3C's Web Services Choreography
              Working Group which published a Candidate Recommendation on
              WS-DSL version 1.0 on November 2005 to replace WSCI.</para>
          </sect4>
          <sect4>
            <title>Web Service Distributed Management (WSDM)</title>
            <para>Web Services Distributed Management (WSDM) [70] is an
              OASIS [45] standard that specifies infrastructure support for
              the integration of web service management aspects across
              heterogeneous systems. This is done through management specific
              messaging via web services. It consists of main parts:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>WSDM-MUWS. Deals with Management Using Web Services
                  (MUWS), i.e., the fundamental capabilities required to
                  manage a resource.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>WSDM-MOWS. Deals with Management of Web Services
                  (MOWS), and builds on MUWS to specify how web services (as a
                  kind of resource) are managed.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </sect4>
          <sect4>
            <title>Java Business Integration (JBI)</title>
            <para>Java Business Integration (JBI) is a Java Specification
              Request (JSR 208) [72] that aims to extend Java (including Java
              EE) with an integration environment for business process
              specifications like , BPEL4WS and those proposed by the W3C
              Choreography Working Group [71]. It is an example of a
              technology that implements Enterprise Service Bus (ESB)
              concepts.</para>
          </sect4>
          <sect4>
            <title>Java Remote Method Invocation (JRMI)</title>
            <para>Java Remote Method Invocation (JRMI), is a Java specific
              standard for access to Java objects across a distributed system
              [39].</para>
          </sect4>
          <sect4>
            <title>Jini</title>
            <para>Jini network technology [29] [30] is an open architecture
              that enables developers to create network-centric services that
              are highly adaptive to change. An architecture based on the idea
              of a federation rather than central control, Jini technology can
              be used to build adaptive networks that are scalable, evolvable
              and flexible as typically required in dynamic computing
              environments. Jini technology provides a flexible infrastructure
              for delivering services in a network and for creating
              spontaneous interactions between clients that use these services
              regardless of their hardware or software implementations.</para>
            <para>The Jini architecture specifies a discovery mechanism used
              by clients and services to find each other on the network and to
              work together to get a task accomplished. Service providers
              supply clients with portable Java technology based objects that
              implements the service and gives the client access to the
              service. The actual network interaction used can be of any type
              such as Java [39], CORBA [38], or [54], because the object
              encapsulates (hides) the communication so that the client only
              sees the Java object provided by the service.</para>
            <para>The Rio Project [31] extends the Jini technology [29] [30]
              to provide dynamic adaptive network architecture and uses a
              nomadic SOA approach. In a nomadic SOA services can migrate and
              self optimise their architectural structure to respond to the
              changing service environment.</para>
            <para>A fundamental tenet of distributed systems is they must be
              crafted with the reality that changes occur on the network.
              Compute resources have assets diminished or fail and new ones
              are introduced into the network. Applications executing on
              compute resources may fail, or suffer performance degradation
              based on diminishing compute resource capabilities and/or
              assets. Technology used must provide distributed,
              self-organizing, network-centric capabilities. Enables a
              dynamic, distributed architecture capable of adapting to
              unforeseen changes on the network.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Importance</emphasis>: This
              architecture can facilitate the construction of distributed
              systems in the form of modular co-operating services.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Implications</emphasis>: Can provide
              a more stable, fault-tolerant, scalable, dynamic, and flexible
              solution. Jini also provide the ability to do a better job at
              upgrading systems, keeping everything running including old
              clients.</para>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Originally
              developed and maintained by Sun Microsystems, but now that
              responsibility is being transferred to the Apache Software
              Foundation under the project name of River. There are many
              initiatives that are based on the Jini technology such as
              various grid architectures and [31].</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Web Service Frameworks</title>
          <para>A list of Frameworks:</para>
          <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="5" title="Frameworks">
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Platform</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Destination</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Specification</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Protocols</emphasis>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Apache Axis</entry>
                  <entry>Java/C++</entry>
                  <entry>Client/Server</entry>
                  <entry>WS-ReliableMessaging, WS-Coordination, WS-Security,
                    WS-AtomicTransaction, WS-Addressing</entry>
                  <entry>SOAP, WSDL</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>JSON RPC Java</entry>
                  <entry>Java</entry>
                  <entry>Server</entry>
                  <entry>-</entry>
                  <entry>JSON-RPC</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Java Web</entry>
                  <entry>Java</entry>
                  <entry>Client/Server</entry>
                  <entry>WS-Addressing, WS-Security</entry>
                  <entry>SOAP</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Services Development Pack</entry>
                  <entry>Java</entry>
                  <entry>Client/Server</entry>
                  <entry>-</entry>
                  <entry>WSDL</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Web Services Interoperability Technology</entry>
                  <entry>Java</entry>
                  <entry>Client/Server</entry>
                  <entry>WS-Addressing, WS-ReliableMessaging,
                    WS-Coordination, WS-AtomicTransaction, WS-Security,
                    WS-Security Policy, WS-Trust, WS-SecureConversation,
                    WS-Policy, WS-MetadataExchange</entry>
                  <entry>SOAP, WSDL, MTOM</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Web Services Invocation Framework</entry>
                  <entry>Java</entry>
                  <entry>Client</entry>
                  <entry>-</entry>
                  <entry>SOAP, WSDL</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Windows Communication Foundation</entry>
                  <entry>.Net</entry>
                  <entry>Client/Server</entry>
                  <entry>WS-Addressing, WS-ReliableMessaging,
                    WS-Security</entry>
                  <entry>SOAP, WSDL</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>XFire</entry>
                  <entry>Java</entry>
                  <entry>Client/Server</entry>
                  <entry>WS-Addressing, WS-Security</entry>
                  <entry>SOAP, WSDL</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>XML Interface for Network Services</entry>
                  <entry>Java</entry>
                  <entry>Server</entry>
                  <entry>-</entry>
                  <entry>SOAP, WSDL</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>gSOAP</entry>
                  <entry>C/C++</entry>
                  <entry>Client/Server</entry>
                  <entry>WS-Addressing, WS-Discovery, WS-Enumeration,
                    WS-Security</entry>
                  <entry>SOAP, XML-RPC, WSDL</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>NuSOAP</entry>
                  <entry>PHP</entry>
                  <entry>Server</entry>
                  <entry>-</entry>
                  <entry>SOAP, WSDL</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Web Services Platforms</title>
          <sect4>
            <title>Java 2 Edition (J2EE)</title>
            <para>Java Enterprise Edition (formerly known as Java 2
              Platform, Enterprise Edition or J2EE up to version 1.4) [35] is
              a specification of a platform and a code library that is part of
              the Java Platform. It is used mainly for developing and running
              distributed multi-tier Java applications, based largely on
              modular software components running on a platform (application
              server). The platform provides the application with support for
              handling of transactions, security, scalability, concurrency and
              management of deployed applications. Applications are easily
              ported between different Java EE application servers.
              Applications developed for the Java EE can easily support Web
              Services. Java EE is often compared to Microsoft .Net [36], a
              comparison that is beyond the scope of this document. But it
              shall be noted that .Net is a product and framework closely
              related to development for the Windows operating system whereas
              Java EE is a specification that is followed by many product
              vendors.</para>
          </sect4>
          <sect4>
            <title>Microsoft .NET</title>
            <para>Microsoft .NET framework [36] is a Microsoft product
              closely related to application development for the Windows
              platform [36]. The framework includes the closely related C#
              programming language (even if it is a formal ISO standard) and
              the Common Language Runtime (CLR), which simplified is
              Microsoft's response to JAVA. Programs written for the NET.
              Framework execute in which provides the appearance of an
              application virtual machine, so that programmers need not
              consider the capabilities of the specific CPU that will execute
              the program. The framework also includes libraries for
              development of web service applications.</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Semantic Web</title>
        <para>The Semantic Web initiative will make searches more accurate
          and enable increasingly sophisticated information services like
          intelligent agents that can find products and services, schedule
          appointments and make purchases. The initiative includes a sort of
          grammar and vocabulary that provide information about a document's
          components; this information will enable Web software to act on the
          meaning of Web content. Semantic Web software and Web services
          promise to shift the nature of the Web from a publishing and
          communications medium to an information management
          environment.</para>
        <para>Semantic Web software includes a special set of Extensible
          Mark-up Language (XML) tags that includes Uniform Resource
          Identifiers (URL), a Resource Description Framework (RDF), and a Web
          Ontology Language (OWL).</para>
        <para>Semantic Web software makes it possible for an intelligent
          agent to carry out the request "show me the Unmanned Aerial Vehicles
          (UAV) operating in the current area of responsibility" even if there
          is no explicit list, because it knows that "area of responsibility"
          has the property "location" with the value "Kandahar", and in
          searching a directory of UAVs it knows to skip UAVs belonging to the
          United States, whose location value is "Kabul", but include German
          UAVs, whose location value is "Kandahar".</para>
        <para>Semantic Web software organises Web information so that search
          engines and intelligent agents can understand properties and
          relationships. A university, for example, could be defined as an
          institution of higher education, which is a class of objects that
          has a set of properties like a population of students.</para>
        <para>The World Wide Web Consortium released standards in February
          2004 that define the two foundation elements of the Semantic Web
          initiative: the Resource Description Framework (RDF), which provides
          a structure for interpreting information, and the Web Ontology
          Language (OWL), which provides a means for defining the properties
          and relationships of objects in Web information.</para>
        <para>Web services provide a way for software to communicate with
          each other over the Web, enabling a form of distributed computing in
          which simple services can be combined to carry out complicated tasks
          like financial transactions.</para>
        <para>Our most fundamental sensors are our senses themselves. They
          are quite sophisticated, the product of a complex evolutionary
          design. And yet we've improved on them as time has passed:
          telescopes and microscopes extend our eyes, thermometers extend our
          touch, and satellite dishes extend our ears. In addition, virtual
          sensors have been used for many years to monitor our computing
          environments. Smaller and more powerful computer processors allow
          sensors to be small and inexpensive enough that they can be
          everywhere. And with the advent of trillions and trillions of IPv6
          addresses, they can all be networked.</para>
        <para>Networks, human or technological, are designed to communicate
          information from one point to others. But the value of a network is
          entirely dependent on the information it contains. And so the
          sensors that feed information into a network play a crucial role in
          maximising a network's value. Simply put, the better the sensors and
          the better the information they provide, the more valuable the
          network becomes.</para>
        <para>Advanced sensors that report directly about their physical
          environment will enable truly revolutionary applications. Already
          there are sensors that can detect, measure, and transmit any
          physical quality such as temperature, pressure, colour, shape,
          sound, motion, and chemical composition. And, as sensors are
          becoming more sophisticated, they are also shrinking in size. Some
          are so tiny that they are difficult to detect.</para>
        <para>Emerging sensor network technologies will be autonomous,
          intelligent, and mobile. These sensors will reconfigure themselves
          to achieve certain tasks. These requirements will provide rigid
          requirements for the computing, and delivery systems of the future.
          The networks and computing systems must reorganise themselves to
          serve the distributed agents with needs to communicate and exchange
          decisions, actions, and knowledge to other agents in secured
          environment.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Service Component Architecture</title>
        <para>Service component architecture (SCA) [73] is a technology
          development initiative driven by a group of middle-ware vendors. SCA
          extends and complements existing standards for service
          implementation and for web services; the goal is to simplify
          application development and implementation of SOA.</para>
        <para>SCA components operate at a business level and are decoupled
          from the actual implementation technology and infrastructure used.
          SCA uses Service Data Objects (SDO) [74] to represent the business
          data that forms parameters and return value between the services.
          SCA thus provides uniform Service access and uniform Service data
          representation.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: The current SCA
          specifications are published in a draft version (0.9) at the
          vendor's web sites [73].</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Security</title>
      <para>There is an explosion of protocols and standards dealing with
      identities. These range from identity, authentication, access control,
      compliance, workflow, policy, storage, etc. From these protocols and
      standards we are seeing infrastructure that is being developed to
      support them. There is a growing trend to provide security
      infrastructure openly so that there is interoperability and
      collaboration in the "Security Environment". From this infrastructure
      many applications will be written, such as signal sigon.</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Implication</emphasis>: For an enterprise,
      this means a lower cost of password and account management, and lower
      user frustration by allowing users to control of their login.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>Authentication</title>
        <sect3>
          <title>OpenID</title>
          <para>OpenID is a decentralised single sign-on system. Websites
          using OpenID allow web users to abandon the need to remember
          traditional authentication tokens such as user name and password.
          Instead, they only need to be previously registered on a website
          with an OpenID "identity provider", sometimes called an i-broker.
          Since OpenID is decentralised, any website can employ OpenID
          software as a way for users to sign in; OpenID solves the problem
          without relying on any centralised website to confirm digital
          identity.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: OpenID is
          increasingly gaining adoption among large sites, with organisations
          like AOL acting as a provider. In addition, integrated OpenID
          support has been made a high priority in Firefox 3 and Microsoft is
          working on implementing OpenID 2.0 in Windows Vista. A non-profit
          organisation,OpenID Europe, was created in 2007 to support and
          promote the OpenID framework in Europe.</para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Bandit Project</title>
          <para>The Bandit project is a worldwide open source community that
          enables open yet secure enterprise computing through an Open
          Identity System. Bandit's components will create an environment
          where, the right people get the right access to the right IT systems
          at the right time. The Bandit project is sponsored by Novell, which
          contributes significant engineering, management and infrastructure
          resources. Novell, in consultation with the Bandit community, sets
          the project engineering goals and retains ultimate responsibility
          for the project.<figure float="0"><title>Bandit High Level Architecture</title><mediaobject><imageobject><imagedata align="center" fileref="../figures/banditHLA.svg" format="SVG" userlevel="" width="90%" /></imageobject></mediaobject></figure></para>
          <para>Bandit's current emphasis is in the following areas:
          <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Provide simple application access to multiple identity
                stores</para></listitem><listitem><para>Support multiple and pluggable authentication methods to
                provide consistent application access</para></listitem><listitem><para>Provide a simple application interface to unify system
                access based on roles</para></listitem><listitem><para>Allow applications to easily participate in a common
                compliance system</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>:Work is being done on
          version 2 of the Common Identity component and the Role Engine
          component.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Risk Analytical Engines</title>
        <para>Risk Analytical Engines are used predict risk based on models.
        Risk assessments are done real-time.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">implications</emphasis>: Risk Analytical
        Engines are used in a variety of industries such as financial, health,
        and customer service. But it is the potential use in enterprise
        identity management and network intrusion detection that makes it an
        attractive technology category.</para>
        <sect3>
          <title>Predictive Model Markup Language (PMML)</title>
          <para>Predictive Model Markup Language (PMML) describes predictive
          analytical models that are conventionally used to analyse data in a
          data warehouse. PMML provides a method for systems, or computer
          programs to access an analytical model by providing a web services
          abstraction of the analytical model. This allows the invocation of
          the analytical model hosted by an analytic engine through a web
          services interface to the analytic engine. Invocation of the
          analytical model through the web services interface may be
          independent of the analytic engine hosting the analytical
          model.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Mid Term Emerging Standards</title>
      <para>This purpose of this chapter is to specify the NISP mid term emerging standards.
          The document organises these standards into five service areas. These service areas
          are listed in volume 2.</para>
      <para>This section presents all associated standards in tabular form.
          The tables refine each service area into one or more service categories, with
          service components mapping to the emerging mid term category (see NISP vol. 1).
          A remarks column provides optional supplementary information on each standard plus
          CCEB-specific information. The NISP Rationale Document (RD) provides further explanation
          on why service and standards categories have been selected.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v3s1-omat">
      <title>Operational Mission/Activities/Tasks</title>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Operational Mission/Activities/Tasks -->
      <para>This service area is detailed in the corresponding section of volume 2.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge type="servicearea" name="omat" mode="midterm"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v3s1-uis">
      <title>User Information Services</title>
      <!-- Service Area Table: User Information Services -->
      <para>This service area is detailed in in the corresponding section of volume 2.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge type="servicearea" name="uis" mode="midterm"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v3s1-ts">
      <title>Technical Services</title>
      <para>This service area is detailed in in the corresponding section of volume 2.</para>
      <!-- Service Area Table: COI Services -->
      <sect2>
        <title>List of COI Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerges type="subarea" name="ts-coi" mode="midterm"?>
      </sect2>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Information Integration Services -->
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Information Integration Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge type="subarea" name="ts-integ" mode="midterm"?>
      </sect2>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Communications Services -->
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Communications Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge type="subarea" name="ts-com" mode="midterm"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v3s1-ias">
      <title>Information Assurance</title>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Information Assurance -->
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge type="servicearea" name="ias" mode="midterm"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v3s1-esm">
      <title>Service Management and Control</title>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Service Management and Control -->
      <para condition="ignore" />
      <?dbmerge type="servicearea" name="esm" mode="midterm"?>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Evolution to a Federated NNEC</title>
      <para>This section of Volume 3 of the NATO Interoperability Standards &amp; Protocols
    (NISP) will continue the evolution from the legacy platform based systems to a federated Network Enabled
    Capabilities environment. Within this part of the document, the focus is
    on the far-term perspective of 7 to 10 years into the future from the publication of this version of the NISP. This should encompass the realization of a fully
    network enabled NATO federated environment.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Scope</title>
      <para>The scope of this section will cover that final transitional period
      when NATO transforms its environment to one that follows the approach of
      a NATO Network-Enabled Capability (NNEC). This section will
      identify the emerging technologies.</para>
      <para>The far-term period will mark the migration from separate wired
      and wireless technologies and applications, and more about service
      portability between various networks and seamless service mobility. The
      NATO network of the future will leverage both smart devices and network
      intelligence to delivery services in this seamless fashion.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Networking</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Mobile Ad-hoc Network (MANET)</title>
        <para>MANET can be set up to connect military groups that need to
        maintain communications while on the move. Wireless sensor networks,
        on the other hand, are stationary. They are often deployed in areas
        hostile to humans and relay on a variety of observational data that
        are passed onto military personnel stationed at safer vantage
        points.</para>
        <para>The potential integration of these two network types can provide
        the cornerstone of a truly 'network-centric' communications
        infrastructure. However, in order for NATO to fully utilize wireless
        technology, future technology should be focused on addressing the
        current deficiencies in wireless technology. These include:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Improvements in extending wireless range capabilities</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Increasing transfer rates</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Technology that will create more resilient/reliable
            links</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Evolving routing protocols to better secure wireless
            networks</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Technology that will not only choose the best path for
            routing packets but will also choose the best frequency as
            well.</para>
            <figure float="0">
              <title>Mobile AdHoc Network</title>
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata align="center" fileref="../figures/MANET2Topology.svg" format="SVG" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <sect3>
          <title>Ad Hoc On-Demand Distance Vector (AODV)</title>
          <para>The Ad Hoc On-Demand Distance Vector routing protocol is
          intended for use by mobile nodes in an ad hoc network. It offers
          quick adaptation to dynamic link conditions, low processing and
          memory overhead, low network utilization, and establishment of both
          unicast and multicast routes between sources and destinations. It
          uses destination sequence numbers to ensure loop freedom at all
          times (even in the face of anomalous delivery of routing control
          messages), solving problems (such as ``counting to infinity'')
          associated with classical distance vector protocols.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Importance: </emphasis> Designed for ad
          hoc mobile networks and is capable of both unicast and multicast
          routing.</para>
          <figure float="0">
            <title>Ad Hoc Networking</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center" fileref="../figures/AdHoc2.svg" format="SVG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Dynamic Source Routing (DSR)</title>
          <para>The Dynamic Source Routing (DSR) is a routing protocol for
          wireless mesh networks. It is similar to AODV in that it forms a
          route on-demand when a transmitting computer requests one. However,
          it uses source routing instead of relying on the routing table at
          each intermediate device.</para>
          <para>Determining source routes requires accumulating the address of
          each device between the source and destination during route
          discovery. The accumulated path information is cached by nodes
          processing the route discovery packets. The learned paths are used
          to route packets. To accomplish source routing, the routed packets
          contain the address of each device the packet will traverse. This
          may result in high overhead for long paths or large addresses, like
          IPv6. To avoid using source routing, DSR optionally defines a flow
          id option that allows packets to be forwarded on a hop-by-hop
          basis.</para>
          <para>This protocol is truly based on source routing whereby all the
          routing information is maintained (continually updated) at mobile
          nodes. It has only 2 major phases which are Route Discovery and
          Route Maintenance. Route Reply would only be generated if the
          message has reached the intended destination node (route record
          which is initially contained in Route Request would be inserted into
          the Route Reply).</para>
          <para>To return the Route Reply, the destination node must have a
          route to the source node. If the route is in the Destination Node's
          route cache, the route would be used. Otherwise, the node will
          reverse the route based on the route record in the Route Reply
          message header (symmetric links). In the event of fatal
          transmission, the Route Maintenance Phase is initiated whereby the
          Route Error packets are generated at a node. The erroneous hop will
          be removed from the node's route cache; all routes containing the
          hop are truncated at that point. Again, the Route Discovery Phase is
          initiated to determine the most viable route.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Importance: </emphasis> The protocol
          allows multiple routes to any destination and allows each sender to
          select and control the routes used in routing its packets. Also
          allows for a very rapid recovery when routes in the network
          change.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Status: </emphasis> IETF DSR Draft-
          version 1.0 has had many successful implementations. One of which is
          the open source DSR-UU that can run on Linux. DSR-UU implements most
          of the basic DSR features specified in the DSR draft (version 10).
          One big exception is flow extensions.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Knowledge Based Networking</title>
        <para>A Knowledge Based Network would make decisions about the
        wireless spectrum and have intelligent nodes that could automatically
        optimize the network. If a connection spans reliable and unreliable
        parts of a network, there could be performance issues: if a packet
        makes it through the reliable region but is dropped in the unreliable
        part, it would have to be resent through the entire connection. A
        Knowledge Based Network would automatically break this connection into
        two smaller connections, one across the reliable region and one across
        the unreliable region. Then, if data is lost across the unreliable
        part, it would only need to be re-sent along that region of the
        network. This technique could increase bandwidth tenfold.</para>
        <para>Also, in a knowledge based network it would take note of
        frequently accessed data and save copies on the edge of the network
        for quick access: the idea is If one soldier needs a piece of map
        data, then the guys around him will need it too. Artificial
        intelligence could even decide which protocols to use.</para>
        <para>Such an intelligent network would not only understand how to
        move data; it would also be able to understand what the data meant to
        users. This idea is based on this concept of the Semantic Web, which
        called for Web pages to include machine-readable data in addition to
        content intended to be read by people. Software agents would use this
        data to understand the meaning of documents instead of simply
        searching for keywords.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Data Strategies</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Situation-Dependent Information Extraction</title>
        <para>Situation-dependent information extraction uses advanced
        algorithms to support situation associative processing and improve
        human systems collaboration. Tools are needed to go beyond static data
        filtering and template matching. Early work has shown that Bayesian
        networks, statistical analysis, and hidden Markov models can be used
        to extract meaning and context from complex and cluttered data
        streams. Application of the se techniques for disparate sensors that
        are not temporally or specially matched would enable NATO to detect,
        discern, analyze, and understand the actions of stealthy adversaries
        embedded in complex domains.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance: </emphasis>Effective
        implementation and utilization of these tools in conjunction with
        better understanding of the operational environment and adversary
        activities will improve performance of NATO forces across the
        decision-making spectrum from tactical to strategic, and cross the
        pre- to post-conflict timeline. Improvements in link analysis and
        intent inference will result in faster and more complete understanding
        of options leading to better decisions.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Mega-Scale Data Management</title>
        <para>Future operations can be expected to require the contextual
        exploitation capability to handle exabytes of data at transfer rates
        of terabytes per second, coupled to decision timelines in seconds to
        minutes. As the threat base evolves, there will be a greater
        dependence on integrated, multiple-domain sensors with much greater
        dynamic range, spatial reach, sample rate, and temporal history.
        Mega-scale data management will apply an integrated, federated, and
        scalable data framework to link disparate information sources and
        provide robust knowledge management to permit conclusions based on
        contextual relationships. It will also incorporate a robust security
        and access in a timely manner. Advanced automated decision tools will
        increase the war fighter&#x2019;s ability to make timely decisions with an
        explicit evidential basis and reduced the level of information
        overload often experienced in answering prioritized information
        requests. User-defined knowledge sharing will minimize catastrophic
        errors due to cognitive biases and other limitations.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance: </emphasis>Member nations must
        take a look at the private sector and emulate data management tools
        being explored in this area. Member nations must become more agile and
        responsive adapters of commercial advances in this and related fields
        in order to achieve the anticipated operational demands of future data
        management requirements.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Application Vulnerability Description Language (AVDL)</title>
        <para>Application Vulnerability Description Language (AVDL) is a
        security interoperability standard for creating a uniform method of
        describing application security vulnerabilities using XML. With the
        growing adoption of web-based technologies, applications have become
        far more dynamic, with changes taking place daily or even hourly.
        Consequently, enterprises must deal with a constant flood of new
        security patches from their application and infrastructure
        vendors.</para>
        <para>To make matters worse, network-level security products do little
        to protect against vulnerabilities at the application level. To
        address this problem, enterprises today have deployed a host of
        best-of-breed security products to discover application
        vulnerabilities, block application-layer attacks, repair vulnerable
        web sites, distribute patches, and manage security events. Enterprises
        have come to view application security as a continuous life-cycle.
        Unfortunately, there is currently no standard way for the products
        these enterprises have implemented to communicate with each other,
        making the overall security management process far too manual,
        time-consuming, and error prone.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance: </emphasis> AVDL will create a
        uniform way of describing application security vulnerabilities. This
        information may be utilized by application security gateways to
        recommend the optimal attack prevention policy for that specific
        application. Remediation products could use AVDL files to suggest the
        best course of action for correcting problems, while reporting tools
        could use AVDL to correlate event logs with areas of known
        vulnerability.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Status:</emphasis>The AVDL 1.0
        specification was approved by OASIS in May 2004.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Common Alerting Protocol (CAP)</title>
        <para>The Common Alerting Protocol is a simple but general format for
        exchanging all-hazard emergency alerts and public warnings over all
        kinds of networks. CAP is a XML-based data format for exchanging
        public warnings and emergencies between alerting technologies. CAP
        allows a warning message to be consistently disseminated
        simultaneously over many warning systems to many applications. CAP
        increases warning effectiveness and simplifies the task of activating
        a warning for responsible officials. Individuals can receive
        standardized alerts from many sources and configure their applications
        to process and respond to the alerts as desired.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Flexible geographic targeting using latitude/longitude boxes
            and other geospatial representations in three dimensions;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Multilingual and multi-audience messaging;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Phased and delayed effective times and expirations;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enhanced message update and cancellation features;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Template support for framing complete and effective warning
            messages;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Digital encryption and signature capability; and,</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Facility for digital images, audio and video.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance: </emphasis> The Common
        Alerting Protocol will enhance organizations 'situational awareness'
        at all levels by providing a continual real-time database of all
        warnings, even local ones. It will extend the reach of warning
        messages and enhance the effectiveness of those messages by providing
        timely corroboration of warnings from several sources. This system
        will also simplify the work of alerting officials by giving them a
        write-it-once method for issuing warnings over multiple dissemination
        systems without duplicate effort.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: The 1.0 specification
        was approved by OASIS in, 2004. Based on experience with 1.0, the
        OASIS Emergency Management Technical Committee adopted an updated 1.1
        specification in October 2005. At a meeting in October, 2006 the 1.1
        specification was taken under consideration by the International
        Telecommunications for adoption as an ITU recommendation.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Emergency Data Exchange Language, Distribution Element (EDXL
        DE)</title>
        <para>Emergency Data Exchange Language, Distribution Element
        (EDXL-DE), facilitates emergency information sharing and data exchange
        across local, regional, tribal, national, and international
        organizations in the public and private sectors. This standard has the
        ability to transmit any content, from files to technical data exchange
        information.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance: </emphasis> Same as
        CAP.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Status: </emphasis>20 June 2006 - The
        OASIS international standards consortium approved the Emergency Data
        Exchange Language Distribution Element (EDXL-DE) version 1.0 as an
        OASIS Standard.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Nanotechnology</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Carbon Nanotube Computers</title>
        <para>For decades, the size of silicon-based transistors has decreased
        steadily while their performance has improved. As the devices approach
        their physical limits, though, researchers have started looking to
        less conventional structures and materials. Single-walled carbon
        nanotubes are one prominent candidate -- already researchers have
        built carbon nanotube transistors that show promising performance.
        According to estimates, carbon nanotubes have the potential to produce
        transistors that run 10 times faster than even anticipated future
        generations of silicon-based devices, while at the same time using
        less power.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Importance: </emphasis> Could help make large-scale
        integrated circuits built out of carbon nanotubes possible, leading to
        ultrafast, low-power processors. The need to power IT equipment
        becomes less of a factor in planning military operations.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Status: </emphasis> Researchers at have overcome an
        important obstacle to building computers based on carbon nanotubes, by
        developing a way to selectively arrange transistors that were made
        using the carbon molecules.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Flexible Silicon</title>
        <para>Most flexible electronics, such as those used in e-paper and
        roll-up displays for mobile devices, rely on transistors made of
        either organic polymers, printed directly on a plastic substrate, or
        amorphous, or noncrystalline, silicon. However, transistors made of
        these materials can't perform at the gigahertz speeds needed for
        complex circuitry or antennas.</para>
        <para>People have for some time been able to make slow flexible
        electronics, but the speed of the transistors has been limited. The
        next step has been to make the transistors out of high-quality,
        single-crystal silicon instead of organic polymers and amorphous
        silicon because electrons simply move faster in single-crystal
        silicon.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance: </emphasis> This technology
        opens possibilities to new flexible electronics that can be
        implemented in a wide variety of military applications. Imagine you
        are an infantry soldier and you look to your wrist computer to get
        your bearings, known positions of friend and foe and even a weather
        report. Flexible electronics has the potential to revolutionize the
        way in which information is disseminated on the battlefield.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Status: </emphasis>Researchers have made
        ultra thin silicon transistors that operate more than 50 times faster
        than previous flexible-silicon devices. The advance could help make
        possible flexible high-end electronics that would be useful in a
        variety of applications, from computers to communication.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Microphotonic Devices</title>
        <para>Optical fibers can quickly transmit huge amounts of data. But
        the technology for sorting and sending photons lags far behind the
        microelectronics that generates and process the data, putting a crimp
        on bandwidths. In the past few years, scientists and engineers have
        made great strides in miniaturizing photonic devices and integrating
        them onto a single chip. Such advances allow for cheaper
        manufacturing, smaller sizes, and higher performance. Along the way
        they've developed techniques for working with materials common to the
        semiconductor industry, which is a step toward integrating photonics
        and electronics on the same chip. And these researchers have made
        structures with phenomenal precision, in some cases down to distances
        smaller than those that separate atoms.</para>
        <para>Even with these successes, however, a major obstacle remained.
        Light delivered via cylindrical fiber optics breaks into different
        polarizations, or orientations of light waves. In devices at the
        microscale, the outputs change depending on if the waves are oriented
        vertically or horizontally so they're suited to processing only
        certain polarizations, which can lead to weakened signals. If
        researchers are limited to using horizontally polarized light, for
        example, they end up throwing away vertically polarized light and lose
        half the signal strength. That's a problem particularly when sending
        signals over long distances, such as between continents.</para>
        <para>One approach to this problem is to run light through more than
        one device, each specifically designed to process one polarization.
        Researchers at MIT's Research Laboratory of Electronics took a
        different approach. Rather than building separate devices for
        different light polarizations, they invented a device for converting
        vertically polarized light into horizontally polarized light. First,
        the device splits light into its horizontally and vertically polarized
        components, directing these into separate channels. Then it gradually
        rotates the vertically polarized light to make it horizontal. At this
        point, the light in both channels has the same polarization. This
        makes it possible to use identical devices to process that light. As a
        result, all of the light is processed in the same way, allowing clear,
        strong signals.</para>
        <para>The current advance pertains only to those photonic applications
        that involve light with multiple polarizations and those
        communications applications that involve fiber optics. There hasn't
        been much economic pressure in the past couple of years to develop
        technology for these applications because of a glut in bandwidth, but
        now communications demands are increasing again.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance:</emphasis> Paves the way to
        cheaper, more complex, and higher-performance optical networks. When
        you integrate things like this, the complexity and the performance of
        the kinds of filtering we can do are a little more advanced than the
        methods that are used today. For example, sensor assemblies using
        photonic components are immune to electromagnetic interference and
        electrical component failure in adverse environments.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Status: </emphasis> Researchers at MIT's
        Research Laboratory of Electronics report in the current issue of
        Nature Photonics that they have developed a method for overcoming a
        fundamental problem in using photonics in communications.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Invisible Transistors</title>
        <para>Researchers have fabricated high ­performance, transparent
        thin-film transistors (TFTs) using a low-cost, low-temperature method.
        They use indium oxide as both a semiconductor and a conductor,
        combining the inorganic material with organic insulators on top of a
        transparent substrate. The resulting transistors perform nearly as
        well as the much more expensive polysilicon transistors used to
        control pixels in high-end TVs and computer monitors.</para>
        <para>On glass that's been coated with a transparent electrode, the
        researchers deposit the organic insulating materials, which form a
        multilayered lattice. To deposit the indium oxide, the researchers use
        a standard technique called ion-assisted deposition, in which an ion
        beam controls the crystallization and adhesion of the oxide. Changing
        the oxygen pressure during the process varies the conductivity of the
        indium oxide, which can thus be used as a semiconductor in one part of
        the device and as a conductor in other parts.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance:</emphasis> The new TFTs could
        replace the opaque transistors used to control pixels in digital
        displays. Because the low-temperature method can deposit transistors
        on flexible plastics, it could lead to see-through displays affixed to
        curved surfaces such as windshields and helmet visors. The method is
        also cheap enough, and easy enough to adapt for large-scale
        manufacturing, that it could make such displays affordable. Imagine a
        vehicle windshield that displays a map to your destination, military
        goggles with targets and instructions displayed right before a
        soldier's eyes.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Status: </emphasis> Negotiations for
        licensing the technology have begun. Prototype displays could be ready
        within 18 months. The researchers hope to improve the performance of
        the transistors so that they could serve as processors or memory
        cells.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Human-Computer Interface</title>
      <para>The idea of eliminating the gap between human thought and computer
      responsiveness is an obvious one, and a number of companies are working
      hard on promising technologies. One of the most obvious such
      technologies is voice recognition software that allows the computer to
      type as you speak, or allows users to control software applications by
      issuing voice commands.</para>
      <para>Even the most advanced and accurate software in this category has
      an accuracy that is impressive, and the technology is far ahead of voice
      recognition technology from a mere decade ago, but it's still not at the
      point where people can walk up to their computer and start issuing voice
      commands without a whole lot of setup, training, and fine tuning of
      microphones and sound levels. Widespread, intuitive use of voice
      recognition technology still appears to be years away.</para>
      <para>And yet our interface with the Internet remains the lowly personal
      computer. With its clumsy interface devices (keyboard and mouse,
      primarily), the personal computer is a makeshift bridge between the
      ideas of human beings and the world of information found on the
      Internet. These interface devices are clumsy and simply cannot keep pace
      with the speed of thought of which the human brain is capable.</para>
      <para>Consider this: a person with an idea who wishes to communicate
      that idea to others must translate that idea into words, then break
      those words into individual letters, then direct her fingers to punch
      physical buttons (the keyboard) corresponding to each of those letters,
      all in the correct sequence. Not surprisingly, typing speed becomes a
      major limiting factor here: most people can only type around sixty words
      per minute. Even a fast typist can barely achieve 120 words per minute.
      Yet the spoken word approaches 300 words per minute, and the speed of
      'thought' is obviously many times faster than that.</para>
      <para>Pushing thoughts through a computer keyboard is sort of like
      trying to put out a raging fire with a garden hose: there is simply not
      enough bandwidth to move things through quickly enough. As a result,
      today's computer / human interface devices are significant obstacles to
      breakthroughs in communicative efficiency.</para>
      <para>The computer mouse is also severely limited. I like to think of
      the mouse as a clumsy translator of intention: if you look at your
      computer screen, and you intend to open a folder, you have to move your
      hand from your keyboard to your mouse, slide the mouse to a new location
      on your desk, watch the mouse pointer move across the screen in an
      approximate mirror of the mouse movement on your desk, then click a
      button twice. Thats a far cry from the idea of simply looking at the
      icon and intending it to open.</para>
      <para>Today's interface devices are little more than rudimentary
      translation tools that allow us to access the world of personal
      computers and the Internet in a clumsy, inefficient way. Still, the
      Internet is so valuable that even these clumsy devices grant us
      immeasurable benefits, but a new generation of computer/human interface
      devices would greatly multiply those benefits and open up a whole new
      world of possibilities for exploiting the power of information and
      knowledge.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>Hand Controlled Computers</title>
        <para>Another recent technology that represents a clever approach to
        computer / human interfaces is the iGesture Pad by a company called
        Fingerworks (http://www.FingerWorks.com). With the iGesture Pad, users
        place their hands on a touch sensitive pad (about the size of a mouse
        pad), then move their fingers in certain patterns (gestures) that are
        interpreted as application commands. For example, placing your fingers
        on the pad in a tight group, then rapidly opening and spreading your
        fingers are interpreted as an Open command.</para>
        <para>For more intuitive control of software interfaces, what is
        needed is a device that tracks eye movements and accurately translates
        them into mouse movements: so you could just look at an icon on the
        screen and the mouse would instantly move there.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance: </emphasis> This technology
        represents a leap in intuitive interface devices, and it promises a
        whole new dimension of control versus the one-dimensional mouse click.
        Keystrokes and mouse clicks limit a soldier's degree of
        freedom.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Status:</emphasis> It's still a somewhat
        clumsy translation of intention through physical limbs. Interestingly,
        some of the best technology in this area comes from companies building
        systems for people with physical disabilities. For people who can't
        move their limbs, computer control through alternate means is
        absolutely essential.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Head Moving Tracking Technology</title>
        <para>One approach to this is tracking the movement of a person's head
        and translating that into mouse movements. One device, the Head Mouse
        (Origin Instruments), does exactly that. You stick a reflective dot on
        your forehead, put the sensor on top of your monitor, and then move
        your head to move your mouse.</para>
        <para>Another company called Madentec (http://www.Madentec.com) offers
        a similar technology called Tracker One. Place a dot on your forehead,
        and then you can control the mouse simply by moving your head.</para>
        <para>In terms of affordable head tracking products for widespread
        use, a company called NaturalPoint (http://www.NaturalPoint.com) seems
        to have the best head tracking technology at the present: a product
        called SmartNav. Add a foot switch and you can click with your
        feet.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance: </emphasis> Allows for
        hands-free control via head movement.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Status:</emphasis> Current implementations
        present a learning curve for new users, but it works as
        promised.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Eye Tracking Movements</title>
        <para>While tracking head movement is in many ways better than
        tracking mouse movement, a more intuitive approach, it seems, would be
        to track actual eye movements. A company called LC Technologies, Inc.
        is doing precisely that with their EyeGaze systems
        (http://www.lctinc.com/products.htm). By mounting one or two cameras
        under your monitor and calibrating the software to your screen
        dimensions, you can control your mouse by simply looking at the
        desired position on the screen.</para>
        <para>This technology was originally developed for people with
        physical disabilities, yet the potential application of it is far
        greater. In time, I believe that eye tracking systems will become the
        preferred method of cursor control for users of personal
        computers.</para>
        <para>Eye tracking technology is quickly emerging as a technology with
        high potential for widespread adoption by the computing public.
        Companies such as Tobii Technology (http://www.tobii.se), Seeing
        Machines (http://www.SeeingMachines.com), SensoMotoric Instruments
        (http://www.smi.de), Arrington Research
        (http://www.ArringtonResearch.com), and EyeTech Digital Systems
        (http://www.eyetechds.com) all offer eye tracking technology with
        potential for computer / human interface applications. The two most
        promising technologies in this list, in terms of widespread
        consumer-level use, appear to be Tobii Technology and EyeTech Digital
        Systems.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance: </emphasis> Allows for
        hands-free control via eye movement.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Brain-Computer Interface</title>
        <para>Moving to the next level of human-computer interface technology,
        the ability to control your computer with your thoughts alone seems to
        be an obvious goal. The technology is called Brain Computer Interface
        technology, or BCI.</para>
        <para>Although the idea of brain-controlled computers has been around
        for a while, it received a spike of popularity in 2004 with the
        announcement that nerve-sensing circuitry was implanted in a monkey's
        brain, allowing it to control a robotic arm by merely thinking. Brain
        activity produces electrical signals that are detectable on the scalp
        or cortical surface or within the brain. BCIs translate these signals
        from mere reflections of brain activity into outputs that communicate
        the user&#x2019;s intent without the participation of peripheral nerves and
        muscles. BCIs can be non-invasive or invasive. Non-invasive BCIs
        derive the user&#x2019;s intent from scalp-recorded electroencephalographic
        (EED) activity. While invasive BCIs derive the user&#x2019;s intent from
        neuronal action potentials or local field potentials recorded from
        within the cerebral cortex or from its surface. Researchers have
        studied these systems mainly in nonhuman primates and to a limited
        extent in humans. Invasive BCIs face substantial technical
        difficulties and involve clinical risks. Surgeons must implant the
        recording electrodes in or on the cortex. The devices must function
        well for long periods and they risk infection and may pose other
        damage to the brain.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance:</emphasis> Imagine the
        limitless applications of direct brain control. People could easily
        manipulate cursors on the screen or control electromechanical devices.
        They could direct software applications, enter text on virtual
        keyboards, or even drive vehicles on public roads. Today, all these
        tasks are accomplished by our brains moving our limbs, but the limbs,
        technically speaking, don't have to be part of the chain of
        command.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Status: </emphasis>The lead researchers in
        the monkey experiment are now involved in a commercial venture to
        develop the technology for use in humans. The company, Cyberkinetics
        Inc. hopes to someday implant circuits in the brains of disabled
        humans and then allow those people to control robotic arms,
        wheelchairs, computers or other devices through nothing more than
        brain behaviour.</para>
        <figure float="0">
          <title>Brain Computer Interface</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="../figures/BCI.svg" format="SVG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Tactile Feedback</title>
        <para>Another promising area of human-computer interface technology is
        being explored by companies like Immersion Corporation
        (http://www.Immersion.com), which offers tactile feedback hardware
        that allows users to 'feel' their computer interfaces.</para>
        <para>Slide on Immersion's CyberGlove, and your computer can track and
        translate detailed hand and finger movements. Add their CyberTouch
        accessory, and tiny force feedback generators mounted on the glove
        deliver the sensation of touch or vibration to your fingers. With
        proper software translation, these technologies give users the ability
        to manipulate virtual objects using their hands. It's an intuitive way
        to manipulate objects in virtual space, since nearly all humans have
        the natural ability to perform complex hand movements with practically
        no training whatsoever.</para>
        <para>Another company exploring the world of tactile feedback
        technologies is SensAble Technologies. Their PHANTOM devices allow
        users to construct and feel three-dimensional objects in virtual
        space. Their consumer-level products include a utility for gamers that
        translate computer game events into tactile feedback (vibrations,
        hitting objects, gun recoil, etc.).</para>
        <para>On a consumer level, Logitech makes a device called the IFeel
        Mouse that vibrates or thumps when your mouse cursor passes over
        certain on-screen features. Clickable icons, for example, feel like
        bumps as you mouse over them. The edges of windows can also deliver
        subtle feedback.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance:</emphasis> Key technology for
        modeling &amp; simulation, and simulated training. Tactile feedback
        has potential for making human-computer interfaces more intuitive and
        efficient;even if today's tactile technologies are clunky first
        attempts. The more senses we can directly involve in our control of
        computers, the broader the bandwidth of information and intention
        between human beings and machines.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Status: </emphasis> Hasn't seen much
        success in the marketplace.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Three Dimensional Displays</title>
        <para>The long-promised 3D computer monitor finally seems to be close
        to reality. Manipulating complex windows, documents and virtual
        objects on a two-dimensional display -- as is standard today -- is
        rather limiting. With a 3D monitor, we could work in layers or
        position documents and objects in 3D space rather than squeezing them
        down to a tiny toolbar at the bottom of one screen.</para>
        <para>For human beings, 3D space is intuitive. We get it without
        training. That's because we live in a world of 3D objects and space,
        and our perception is hard-wired to understand spatial relationships.
        That's why gamers who play first-person shooters like Quake can
        mentally retrace their way through enormous maps (levels) in their
        heads, eyes closed, without even trying: the human brain was built to
        remember and navigate 3D space.</para>
        <para>Recent breakthroughs in 3D display promise to make computing
        more intuitive and powerful. Companies like LightSpace Technologies
        (http://www.lightspacetech.com) are already selling desktop 3D display
        monitors that display true 3D images without the need for special
        glasses.</para>
        <para>The trouble is, Windows and Mac operating systems weren't
        written with 3D displays in mind. So there's no capability to stack
        windows or view the depth of objects. It's a classic chicken-and-egg
        conundrum: who's going to buy 3D displays if the software can't
        support them, and why would software makers write 3D layering logic if
        nobody owns the displays?</para>
        <para>In time, thanks to the cool factor of 3D displays, the
        technology will eventually receive enough attention to warrant the
        necessary R&amp;D investment by operating system developers like
        Microsoft and Apple. No doubt, future generations will conduct all
        their computing with the aid of 3D displays, and the very idea of 2D
        displays will seem as outdated as black &amp; white movies do to us
        today.</para>
        <para>Another new 3D display device is the Perspecta Spatial 3D globe,
        seen at: http://www.actuality-systems.com/index.php/actuality. This
        device displays 3D objects or animations inside a globe. Users can
        walk around the globe and view the objects from any angle. It's a
        rather expensive item, of course, so early applications for this
        product focus on medical and research tasks. In time, however, the
        technology will drop in price, bringing it within reach of more
        consumers.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance:</emphasis> For that, we will
        ultimately need a tabletop 3D display system that lays flat on your
        desk (like an LCD monitor laying down) and projects 3D images into the
        space above the panel. This would be a true volumetric 3D display
        system, and it's here that the technology truly represents a
        breakthrough. Program application windows could literally be stacked
        from the rear to the front, and if you peeked around the side of the
        display, you could see a side view of all the windows at once. With
        proper software control, objects or documents could be placed in true
        3D space: desktop icons, for example, could be lined up along the very
        back row. Games could display true 3D scenes as if you're actually in
        them, and CAD engineers would have the ability to observe their
        designs in true 3D space. Better yet, if coupled with a motion
        tracking glove or similar technology, users could use their hands to
        grasp, move, resize or otherwise manipulate elements in 3D space.
        This, of course, opens up an unlimited universe of possibilities for
        computer / human interaction.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Automated Language Processing</title>
        <para>Foreign language speech and text are indispensable sources of
        intelligence, but the vast majority of this information is unexamined.
        Foreign language data and their corresponding providers are massive
        and growing in numbers daily. Moreover, because the time to transcribe
        and translate foreign documents is so labor intensive, compounded by
        the lack of linguists with suitable language skills to review it all,
        much foreign language speech and text are never exploited for
        intelligence and counterterrorism purposes. New and powerful foreign
        language technology is needed to allow English-speaking analysts to
        exploit and understand vastly more foreign speech and text than is
        currently possible today.</para>
        <figure float="0">
          <title>Language Processing</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="../figures/LanguageProcessing.svg" format="SVG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <sect3>
          <title>Speech-to-Text Transcription</title>
          <para>Automatic speech-to-text transcription seeks to produce rich,
          readable transcripts of foreign news broadcasts and conversations
          (over noisy channels and/or in noisy environments) despite
          widely-varying pronunciations, speaking styles, and subject matter.
          Goals for speech-to-text transcription include: (1) providing high
          accuracy multilingual word-level transcription from speech at all
          stages of processing and across multiple genres, topics, speakers,
          and channels ( such as, Arabic, Chinese, the Web, news, blogs,
          signals intelligence, and databases); (2) representing and
          extracting &#x201C;meaning&#x201D; out of spoken language by reconciling and
          resolving jargon, slang, code-speak, and language ambiguities; (3)
          dynamically adapting to (noisy) acoustics, speakers, topics, new
          names, speaking-styles, and dialects; (4) improving relevance to
          deliver the information decision-makers need; (5) assimilating and
          integrating speech across multiple sources to support exploration
          and analysis to enable natural queries and drill-down; and (6)
          increased portability across languages, sources, and information
          needs.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Importance:</emphasis> Examples of
          critical technologies include: improved acoustic modeling; robust
          feature extraction; better discriminative estimation models;
          improved language and pronunciation modeling; and language
          independent approaches that are able to learn from examples by using
          algorithms that exploit advances in computational power plus the
          large quantities of electronic speech and text that are now
          available. The ultimate goal is to create rapid, robust technology
          that cab be ported cheaply and easily to other languages and
          domains.</para>
        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Foreign-to-English Translation</title>
          <para>Goals for foreign to English translation include: (1)
          providing high accuracy machine translation and structural metadata
          annotation from multilingual text document and speech transcription
          input at all stages of processing and across multiple genres,
          topics, and mediums ( such as, Arabic, Chinese, the Web, news,
          blogs, signals intelligence, and databases); (2) understanding or at
          least deriving semantic intent from input strings regardless of
          source; (3) reconciling and resolving semantic differences,
          duplications, inconsistencies, and ambiguities across words,
          passages, and documents; (4) more efficient discovery of important
          documents, more relevant and accurate facts while decreasing the
          amount of time required to do it, and passages for distillation; (5)
          providing enriched translation output that is formatted, cleaned-up,
          clear, unambiguous, and meaningful to decision-makers; (6)
          eliminating the need for human intervention and minimized delay of
          information delivery; and (7) fast development of new language
          capability, swift response to breaking events, and increased
          portability across languages, sources, and information needs.</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Importance:</emphasis> Examples of
          critical technologies include: improved dynamic language modeling
          with adaptive learning; advanced machine translation technology that
          utilizes heterogeneous knowledge sources; better inference models;
          language-independent approaches to create rapid robust technology
          that can be ported cheaply and easily to any language and domain;
          syntactic and semantic representation techniques to deal with
          ambiguous meaning and information overload; and cross- and mono-
          lingual, language-independent information retrieval to detect and
          discover the exact data in any language quickly and accurately, and
          to flag new data that may be of interest.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Portable Power</title>
      <para>It seems that no matter how advanced notebook computers get, their
      battery life remains at a standstill: 2-3 hours from most models,
      regardless of price. From electric vehicles to portable electronics,
      today's battery capacity lags far behind the steady improvements in
      other areas of technology. Despite the hype and advertising from battery
      manufacturers, today's chemical batteries are virtually identical to
      ones sold three decades ago.</para>
      <para>It's not that battery manufacturers aren't trying to develop
      something better: efforts to improve battery capacity and power density
      have been underway for years. Despite the research, arguably the best
      technology they have produced yet is the ingenious battery testing strip
      that you can use to check how quickly your batteries have gone
      dead.</para>
      <para>Today's battery technology is simply outdated. The chemicals are
      extremely hazardous to the environment (Nickel-Cadmium, for example, is
      made from two heavy metals that are toxic to practically all forms of
      life on the planet), dangerous to nearby users (risk of explosions),
      heavy (standard car batteries can weigh 70+ pounds) and unreliable. They
      charge slowly, their output voltage wavers, and their size becomes a
      major limiting factor when designing portable electronics like digital
      cameras.</para>
      <para>Portable power is a crucial enabling technology for a vast array
      of applications. Some of these applications include:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Wearable Computers</emphasis> - Smaller
          batteries will make wearable computers more comfortable and
          convenient. A power pack the size of a matchbox might power a
          wearable computer for an entire day.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Robotics</emphasis> - Autonomous robots
          require an enormous amount of electrical power for the operation of
          motors, artificial muscles and CPUs. Today's chemical batteries just
          don't deliver the horsepower. AIBO, Sony's robotic pet, only barks
          for 2-3 hours on a typical charge, and the working prototypes of
          humanoid robots from Japan only have enough juice for brief public
          performances.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Medical Devices</emphasis> - The
          miniaturization of medical devices depends heavily on increasing the
          power density of batteries. From portable monitoring systems to
          handheld diagnostic devices, the battlefield medicine would benefit
          greatly from a breakthrough in power density and portability.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Electric Vehicles</emphasis> - To date,
          total electric vehicles have not succeeded in military applications
          primarily due to their lack of range (power density). That's the
          fault of the battery technology: it requires a thousand pounds of
          batteries to drive a vehicle the same distance delivered by four
          gallons of gasoline. While hybrid vehicles are finding tremendous
          success in the marketplace by packing both batteries and combustion
          engines under the same hood, tomorrow's vehicles could run off
          batteries alone if high density power storage systems were
          available.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Space Exploration</emphasis> - The
          limitations of portable power are critical when it comes to space
          exploration. Battery requirements shape the scope of entire
          missions. The primary factor limiting the life and utility of the
          2004 Mars rovers, for example, was battery life. With the help of
          higher density power systems, space exploration takes a quantum leap
          forward and unleashes spectacular new possibilities in remote
          sensing vehicles and manned missions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Solar Power Systems</emphasis> - Solar
          power is clean, renewable, safe, reliable and environmentally
          friendly. Unfortunately, it's expensive to install, and the single
          greatest cost often comes from the batteries, not the solar panels.
          Batteries for solar systems are typically large, heavy, dangerous
          (risk of explosions), expensive and short-lived (many need replacing
          in a mere five years). A breakthrough in power density and storage
          costs could revolutionize the solar industry, making residential and
          commercial solar systems far more affordable. If battery costs could
          be halved, it would subtract five years from the average twenty-year
          return on solar systems.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>These are just a few of the many important applications of high
      density portable power. Remember, though, it's not just the density that
      matters: it's the cost as well. To herald a genuine breakthrough, the
      next wave of technology needs to be better on all counts: size, weight
      and cost.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>Fuel Cells</title>
        <para>The most promising candidate technology that meets this
        requirement is fuel cell technology. Fuel cells are clean, small and
        lightweight, and will eventually be cheap to produce. The choice of
        fuels for those fuel cells, however, remains undecided.</para>
        <para>One of the promising contenders is zinc -- one of the most
        abundant minerals in the planet. With the help of fuel cell membranes,
        zinc particles release electricity when oxidized by exposing them to
        air. Once all the zinc is oxidized, the zinc particles can be quickly
        "recharged" (reversing the oxidation process with the help of
        electricity) and used again. This process can be endlessly repeated,
        since the zinc never wears out.</para>
        <para>Zinc is promising because it offers high density portable power
        (far greater power density than chemical batteries), a
        widely-available element, and outstanding safety (zinc won't explode
        if exposed to flames or high temperatures). The industry leader in
        portable zinc power is Metallic Power
        (http://www.metallicpower.com)</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Methanol Fuel Cells</title>
        <para>Zinc power isn't seeing many headlines these days. Much of the
        news about portable fuel cells seems focused on methanol. These
        so-called Direct Methanol Fuel Cells (DMFCs) convert methanol (a
        common alcohol that can be derived from corn, among other renewable
        sources) into electricity. NEC, Samsung, and already have working
        prototypes of DMFCs for notebook computers or portable
        electronics.</para>
        <para>The problem with methanol is its combustibility: methanol
        ignites easily and has a flash point ranging from room temperature to
        130 degrees (F), depending on the concentration of water in the
        mixture. That makes it an illegal explosive according to the laws of
        many countries, meaning that DMFCs would not be allowed on airplanes
        unless existing regulations are changed.</para>
        <para>Methanol also has the drawback of not being easily renewed by
        consumers. Few people have the know-how to distill methanol in their
        own garage, meaning that consumers would be dependent on DMFC
        manufacturers for methanol recharge kits. Like ink jet printer refill
        kits, this is where DMFC manufacturers will probably make the bulk of
        their profits.</para>
        <para>In the end, however, the choice of fuel isn't as important as
        the widespread adoption of a fuel cell battery standard. Today's
        chemical batteries are holding back promising applications for
        emerging technologies, and only a breakthrough in portable power can
        overcome those limitations. Fuel cells can make the leap, and their
        adoption by consumers and manufacturers alike is all but
        assured.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance:</emphasis> Fuel cells are very
        useful as power sources and offer significant savings of loads, in
        weight and volume, compared to conventional power sources. Because
        fuel cells have no moving parts and do not involve combustion, in
        ideal conditions they can achieve up to 99.9999% reliability. This
        equates to less than one minute of down time in a six year
        period.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Optical Computing</title>
      <para>Optical computing would provide much higher computing speeds.
      Developments have centered on devices such as VCSELS (Vertical Cavity
      Surface-Emitting Lasers) for data input, SLMs (Spatial Light Modulators)
      for putting information on light beams and high speed APDs (Avalanche
      Photo-Diodes) for data output. More work remains before digital optical
      computers will be available commercially.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>Quantum Computing</title>
        <para>A quantum computer would store information, not as strings of
        ones and zeros as in a &#x2018;classical&#x2019; computer, but as a series of
        quantum mechanical states. Quantum physics allows particles to be in
        more than one state at a time, so that it is possible for a particle
        in a quantum computer to hold more than one bit of information,
        referred to as a &#x2018;qubit&#x2019;. The quantum computer would allow very fast
        parallel computing capability. A functional quantum computer is still
        beyond the grasp of current technology, and many obstacles must be
        overcome before a usable computer can be built. A major problem is
        that slight outside disruption, e.g. heat or light, will cause a
        system to lose its quantum coherence, while the very process of
        retrieving results would also upset the coherence.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance:</emphasis> Integer
        factorization is believed to be computationally infeasible with an
        ordinary computer for large integers that are the product of only a
        few prime numbers (e.g., products of two 300-digit primes). By
        comparison, a quantum computer could efficiently solve this problem
        using Shor's algorithm to find its factors. This ability would allow a
        quantum computer to "break" many of the cryptographic systems in use
        today.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Data Storage</title>
        <para>Data storage media will need to improve to keep pace with
        computer processing power, and may be achieved via optical disk
        technologies and applications of parallelism. Promising areas involve
        the use of holographic memory, offering 64 billion bits storage
        capacity on a laser activated crystal the size of a compact disk.
        Holographic data storage captures information using an optical
        inference pattern within a thick, photosensitive optical material.
        Light from a single laser beam is divided into two separate beams, a
        reference beam and an object or signal beam; a spatial light modulator
        is used to encode the object beam with the data for storage. An
        optical inference pattern results from the crossing of the beams&#x2019;
        paths, creating a chemical and/or physical change in the
        photosensitive medium; the resulting data is represented in an optical
        pattern of dark and light pixels. By adjusting the reference beam
        angle, wavelength, or media position, a multitude of holograms
        (theoretically, several thousand) can be stored on a single
        volume.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Importance:</emphasis> The theoretical
        limits for the storage density of this technique are approximately
        tens of per cubic centimeter. In addition, holographic data storage
        can provide companies a method to preserve and archive information.
        The write-once, read many (WORM) approach to data storage would ensure
        content security, preventing the information from being overwritten or
        modified. Manufacturers believe this technology can provide safe
        storage for content without degradation for more than 50 years, far
        exceeding current data storage options.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Far Term Emerging Standards</title>
      <para>This purpose of this section is to specify the NISP far term emerging standards.
          The document organises these standards into five service areas. These service areas
          are listed in volume 2.</para>
      <para>This section presents all associated standards in tabular form.
          The tables refine each service area into one or more service categories, with
          service components mapping to the emerging far term category (see NISP vol. 1).
          A remarks column provides optional supplementary information on each standard plus
          CCEB-specific information. The NISP Rationale Document (RD) provides further explanation
          on why service and standards categories have been selected.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v4s1-omat">
      <title>Operational Mission/Activities/Tasks</title>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Operational Mission/Activities/Tasks -->
      <para>This service area is detailed in the corresponding section of volume 2.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge type="servicearea" name="omat" mode="farterm"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v4s1-uis">
      <title>User Information Services</title>
      <!-- Service Area Table: User Information Services -->
      <para>This service area is detailed in in the corresponding section of volume 2.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge type="servicearea" name="uis" mode="farterm"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v4s1-ts">
      <title>Technical Services</title>
      <para>This service area is detailed in in the corresponding section of volume 2.</para>
      <!-- Service Area Table: COI Services -->
      <sect2>
        <title>List of COI Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge type="subarea" name="ts-coi" mode="farterm"?>
      </sect2>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Information Integration Services -->
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Information Integration Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge type="subarea" name="ts-integ" mode="farterm"?>
      </sect2>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Communications Services -->
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Communications Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge type="subarea" name="ts-com" mode="farterm"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v4s1-ias">
      <title>Information Assurance</title>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Information Assurance -->
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge type="servicearea" name="ias" mode="farterm"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v4s1-esm">
      <title>Service Management and Control</title>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Service Management and Control -->
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge type="servicearea" name="esm" mode="farterm"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <appendix>
    <title>Acronyms</title>
    <table>
      <title>Standards organisations</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="col1" colwidth="13*" />
        <colspec colname="col2" colwidth="87*" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry nameend="col2" namest="col1">
              <emphasis role="bold">Standards organisations</emphasis>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>IETF</entry>
            <entry>Internet Engineering Task Force</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>IEEE</entry>
            <entry>International Electronics and Electrical Engineering
            Society</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>INCITS</entry>
            <entry>International Committee for Internet Technology
            Standards</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>IEC</entry>
            <entry>International Electrotechnical Commission</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>ISO</entry>
            <entry>International Standards organisation</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>ITU</entry>
            <entry>International Telecomunications Union</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>OASIS</entry>
            <entry>organisation for the Advancement of Structured Information
            Standards</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>OMG</entry>
            <entry>Object Management Group</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>TTA</entry>
            <entry />
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>W3C</entry>
            <entry>World Wide Web Consortium</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>WS-I</entry>
            <entry>Web Services Interoperability Organisation</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <table>
      <title>Terms</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="14*" />
        <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="86*" />
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry nameend="col2" namest="col1">
              <emphasis role="bold">Terms</emphasis>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>1xRTT</entry>
            <entry>2.5G CDMA data service up to 384 kbps</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>AMPS</entry>
            <entry>Advanced mobile phone service</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>AODV</entry>
            <entry>Ad Hoc On-Demand Distance Vector</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>AVDL</entry>
            <entry>Application Vulnerability Description Language</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>BICES</entry>
            <entry>Battlefield Information Collection and Exploitation</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>BPIF</entry>
            <entry>Business Process Infrastructure Framework</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>BRAN</entry>
            <entry>Broadband Radio Access Network</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>C3</entry>
            <entry>Command, Control, and Communications</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CAP</entry>
            <entry>Common Alerting Protocol</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CDMA</entry>
            <entry>Code division multiple access</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CIS</entry>
            <entry>Computer Information System</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>COI</entry>
            <entry>Community of Interest</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>COTS</entry>
            <entry>Commerical-of-the-Shelf</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>CPP</entry>
            <entry>Collaboration Protocol Profile</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>DHCP</entry>
            <entry>Dynamic Host Configuration Protocol</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>DISA</entry>
            <entry>Defense Information Systems Agency [US]</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>DSR</entry>
            <entry>Dynamic Source Routing</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>EARS</entry>
            <entry>Effective Affordable Reusable Speech-to-text</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>ebXML</entry>
            <entry>Electronic Bussiness Extensible Modelling Langauge</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>EDGE</entry>
            <entry>Enhanced data for global evolution</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>EDXL DE</entry>
            <entry>Emergency Data Exchange Language, Distribution
            Element</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>ETSI</entry>
            <entry>European Telecommunications Standards Institute</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>FDMA</entry>
            <entry>Frequency division multiple access</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>GPRS</entry>
            <entry>General packet radio system</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>GSI</entry>
            <entry>Grid Security Infrastructure</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>GSM</entry>
            <entry>Global system for mobile</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>HTTP</entry>
            <entry>HyperText Transfer Protocol</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>IEG</entry>
            <entry>Information Exchange Gateway</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>IP</entry>
            <entry>Internet Protocol</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>LAN</entry>
            <entry>Local Area Network</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>MAC</entry>
            <entry>Media Access Control</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>MANET</entry>
            <entry>Mobile Ad-hoc Network</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>MBWA</entry>
            <entry>Mobile Broadband Wireless Access</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>NATO</entry>
            <entry>North Atlantic Treaty organisation</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>NC3TA</entry>
            <entry>NATO Command, Control, and Communications Technical
            Architecture</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>NCOE</entry>
            <entry>Net Centric Operational Environment</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>NCOW</entry>
            <entry>Net Centric Operations and Warfare</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>NGO</entry>
            <entry>Non-Government organisation</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>NMT</entry>
            <entry>Nordic mobile telephone</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>NNEC</entry>
            <entry>NATO Network Enabled Capability</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>NNEC-DS</entry>
            <entry>NNEC Data Strategy</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>NRF</entry>
            <entry>NATO Reaction Force</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>OASIS</entry>
            <entry>Organization for the Advancement of Structured Information
            Standards</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>OGSA</entry>
            <entry>Open Grid Services Architecture</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>OSGi</entry>
            <entry>Open Services Gateway Initiative</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>P2P</entry>
            <entry>Peer-to-Peer</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>PDC</entry>
            <entry>Personal digital cellular</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>PSTN</entry>
            <entry>Pubic switched telephone network</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>QoS</entry>
            <entry>Quality of Service</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>RHQ AFNORTH</entry>
            <entry>Regional Headquarters Allied Forces North Europe</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>SHAPE</entry>
            <entry>Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>SLA</entry>
            <entry>Service Level Agreements</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>SOA</entry>
            <entry>Service Oriented Architecture</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>SOA-RM</entry>
            <entry>SOA Reference Model</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>SOAP</entry>
            <entry>Simple Object Access Protocol</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>TACS</entry>
            <entry>Total access communications system</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>TDMA</entry>
            <entry>Time division multiple access</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>TFT</entry>
            <entry>Thin-Film Transistors</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>UDDI</entry>
            <entry>Universal Description and Discovery Interface</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>W3C</entry>
            <entry>World Wide Web Consortium</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>WCDMA</entry>
            <entry>Wideband CDMA</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>XML</entry>
            <entry>Extensible Modelling Langauge</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </appendix>
  <bibliography>
    <title>References</title>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>1</abbrev>
      <title>2020 Vison: Business Transformation Through Technology
      Innovation</title>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <firstname>Hossein</firstname>
          <surname>Eslambolchi</surname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <copyright>
        <year>2006</year>
      </copyright>
      <isbn>0929306392</isbn>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Silicone Press</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>2</abbrev>
      <title>Hype Cycle for Emerging Technologies, 2006</title>
      <subtitle>Gartner's 2006 Emerging Technologies Hype Cycle Highlights Key
      Technology Themes</subtitle>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <firstname>Jackie</firstname>
          <surname>Fenn</surname>
          <firstname>David</firstname>
          <surname>Cearley</surname>
          <firstname>Ray</firstname>
          <surname>Valdes</surname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <copyright>
        <year>2006</year>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Gartner Group</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>3</abbrev>
      <title>Challenges of Information Technology Management in the 21st
      Century: 2000 Information Resources Management Association International
      Conference</title>
      <subtitle />
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <firstname>Mehdi</firstname>
          <surname>Khosrowpour</surname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <copyright>
        <year>2000</year>
      </copyright>
      <isbn>1878289845</isbn>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Idea Group Publishing</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>4</abbrev>
      <title>The Ten Most Important Technologies for Humanity</title>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <firstname>Mike</firstname>
          <surname>Adams</surname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <copyright>
        <year>2005</year>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Truth Publishing International, Ltd</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>5</abbrev>
      <title>2005 Defense Technology Area Plan</title>
      <subtitle>DoD's Key Technology Areas</subtitle>
      <copyright>
        <year>2005</year>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>US Department of Defense</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>1</abbrev>
      <title>2020 Vision: Business Transformation Through Technology
      Innovation</title>
      <copyright>
        <year>2006</year>
      </copyright>
      <isbn>0929306392</isbn>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Silicone Press</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>2</abbrev>
      <title>Challenges of Information Technology Management in the 21st
      Century: 2000 Information Resources Management Association International
      Conference</title>
      <copyright>
        <year>2000</year>
      </copyright>
      <isbn>1878289845</isbn>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Idea Group Publishing</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>3</abbrev>
      <!--
<ulink
       url="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=soa-rm"></ulink>
-->
      <title>Reference Model for Service Oriented Architectures</title>
      <subtitle>Working Draft 11, OASIS Open, 15 December 2005</subtitle>
      <author>
        <surname>Rebekah</surname>
      </author>
      <copyright>
        <year>2005</year>
        <holder>OASIS</holder>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>OASIS</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>4</abbrev>
      <!--
<ulink
      url="http://www.adobe.com/enterprise/pdfs/Services_Oriented_Architecture_from_Adobe.pdf"></ulink>
-->
      <title>Service Oriented Architecture White Paper</title>
      <copyright>
        <year>2005</year>
        <holder>Adobe Systems Incorporated</holder>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Adobe Systems Incorporated</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>5</abbrev>
      <title>Service-Oriented Architecture Compass: Business Value, Planning
      and Roadmap</title>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <surname>Bieberstein</surname>
        </author>
        <author>
          <firstname>Sanjay</firstname>
          <surname>Bose</surname>
        </author>
        <author>
          <surname>Fiammante</surname>
        </author>
        <author>
          <surname>Jones</surname>
        </author>
        <author>
          <firstname>Rawn</firstname>
          <surname>Shah</surname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <copyright>
        <year>2006</year>
      </copyright>
      <isbn>0-13-187002-5</isbn>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>6</abbrev>
      <title>SOA Service Oriented Architecture Best Practices</title>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <firstname>Dirk</firstname>
          <surname>Krafzig</surname>
        </author>
        <author>
          <firstname>Karl</firstname>
          <surname>Banke</surname>
        </author>
        <author>
          <firstname>Dirk</firstname>
          <surname>Slama</surname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <copyright>
        <year>2004</year>
        <holder>Prentice Hall</holder>
      </copyright>
      <isbn>0-13-146575-9</isbn>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Prentice Hall</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>7</abbrev>
      <!--
<ulink
      url="http://www.mip-site.org/publicsite/Baseline_2.0/MTIR-MIP_Tactical_C2IS_Interoperability_Requirements/MTIR 2.2 including annexes A to G version Sep 24 2004.pdf">MIP
      Tactical C2IS Interoperability Requirements (MTIR)</ulink>

-->
      <title>Multi-lateral Interoperability Programme Working Group,, Version
      2.2, 27 September 2003</title>
      <copyright>
        <year>2003</year>
      </copyright>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>8</abbrev>
      <title>TACOMS Post 2000, Final Study Report, WP13202, Technology
      Independent Network Architecture Concept Study,
      TACOMS/WP13202/RD/TACONE/813</title>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>9</abbrev>
      <title>NATO RESPONSE FORCE - NATO's Expeditionary Capability, Background
      Briefing</title>
      <copyright>
        <year>2002</year>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Colorado Springs Defense Ministers
        Meeting</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>10</abbrev>
      <title>NATO Network Enabled Capabilities Feasibility Study, Version 1.0,
      30 June 2005.</title>
      <copyright>
        <year>2005</year>
        <holder>NATO C3 Agency</holder>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>NATO C3 Agency</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>11</abbrev>
      <title>DoD Architecture Framework Working Group, DoD Architecture
      Framework Deskbook, Version 1.0, 9 February 2004</title>
      <copyright>
        <year>2004</year>
      </copyright>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>12</abbrev>
      <title>Defense, C4ISR Framework Compliant Information, Technology
      Architectures, White Paper</title>
      <author>
        <firstname>Jeffery</firstname>
        <surname>Coffin</surname>
      </author>
      <copyright>
        <year>2001</year>
      </copyright>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>13</abbrev>
      <title>Using Architectures for Interoperability Assessments,
      Briefing</title>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Office of Assistant Secretary of the
        Navy</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>14</abbrev>
      <title>Systems Architecture Framework (NAF), 7 October 2003</title>
      <copyright>
        <year>2003</year>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>NATO C3 Agency</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>15</abbrev>
      <!--
<ulink
      url="http://www.extremetech.com/article2/0,1558,2023640,00.asp?kc=ETRSS02129TX1K0000532"></ulink>
-->
      <title>WiBree Standard To Challenge Bluetooth</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.extremetech.com/article2/0,1558,2023640,00.asp?kc=ETRSS02129TX1K0000532</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Rueters and eWEEk</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>16</abbrev>
      <title>Internet distributed computing, web services, peer-to-peer, grid
      computing, ad hoc networks</title>
      <subtitle>IEEE Computer, Vol 36, Number 5, May 2003</subtitle>
      <copyright>
        <year>2003</year>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>IEEE Computer Society Publications</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>17</abbrev>
      <title>Web Services, Business Process Modelling.</title>
      <subtitle>IEEE Computer,Vol 36 number 10, October 2003</subtitle>
      <copyright>
        <year>2003</year>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>IEEE Computer Society Publications</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>18</abbrev>
      <title>Virtualization and Grid Computing.</title>
      <subtitle>IEEE Computer, Vol 38 number 4, April 2005</subtitle>
      <copyright>
        <year>2005</year>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>IEEE Computer Society Publications</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>19</abbrev>
      <title>Theme Issue On Peer-to-Peer Computing</title>
      <subtitle>Communications of the ACM, Vol 46 number 2, February
      2003</subtitle>
      <copyright>
        <year>2003</year>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>ACM Publications Office</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>20</abbrev>
      <title>Discusses Peer-to-Peer Computing</title>
      <subtitle>Communications of the ACM, Vol 46 number 9, September
      2003</subtitle>
      <copyright>
        <year>2003</year>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>ACM Publications Office</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>21</abbrev>
      <title>An introduction to virtualisation,
      http://www.kernelthread.com/publications/virtualization</title>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>22</abbrev>
      <title>Business process modelling initiative, now merged with business
      processing management initiative. http://www.bpmi.org.</title>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>23</abbrev>
      <title>OASIS BPEL working group,
      http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=wsbpel</title>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>24</abbrev>
      <title>ebXML, http://www.ebxml.org</title>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>25</abbrev>
      <title>The OSGi Standard Forum</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.osgi.org</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>26</abbrev>
      <title>Ad Hoc Networks: New Life For An Old Concept</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.eurescom.de/message/messageMar2005/Ad_hoc_networks_New_life_for_an_old_concept.asp</subtitle>
      <copyright>
        <year>2005</year>
      </copyright>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>27</abbrev>
      <title>OWL Web Ontology Language Overview.</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.w3.org/TR/owl-features</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>W3C</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>28</abbrev>
      <title>Semantic Web Overview</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.w3.org/2001/sw/Activity</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>W3C</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>29</abbrev>
      <title>Sun's Jini Description</title>
      <subtitle>http://java.sun.com/developer/products/jini/index.jsp</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Sun Microsystems</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>30</abbrev>
      <title>Jini Community resource</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.jini.org/</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Apache Projects</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>31</abbrev>
      <title>Jini Project</title>
      <subtitle>http://rio.jini.org/</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>32</abbrev>
      <title>WSMO Working Group Homepage</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.wsmo.org/</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>33</abbrev>
      <title>Towards Intelligent Web Services: Web Service Modelling Ontology
      (WSMO)</title>
      <subtitle>Conference Paper on WSMO, Proceedings of the Conference on
      Intelligent Computing (ICIC),August 23-26, 2005</subtitle>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <firstname />
          <surname>Feier</surname>
        </author>
        <author>
          <firstname>Dieter</firstname>
          <surname>Fensel</surname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <copyright>
        <year>2005</year>
      </copyright>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>34</abbrev>
      <title>Web Services Homepage (DAML-S, OWL-S)</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.daml.org/services/owl-s/</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Defense Advance Research Projects Agency
        (DARPA)</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>35</abbrev>
      <title>Java EE</title>
      <subtitle>http://java.sun.com/javaee/index.jsp</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Sun Microsystems</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>36</abbrev>
      <title>Microsoft .NET Developer Homepage</title>
      <subtitle>http://msdn.microsoft.com/netframework/</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Microsoft Inc.</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>37</abbrev>
      <title>SDL Forum</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.sdl-forum.org/</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>SDL Forum Society</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>38</abbrev>
      <title>Homepage (CORBA, IDL)</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.omg.org/</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>The Object Management Group (OMG)</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>39</abbrev>
      <title>Java</title>
      <subtitle>http://java.sun.com/products/jdk/rmi</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Sun Microsystems</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>40</abbrev>
      <title>Chord</title>
      <subtitle>http://pdos.csail.mit.edu/chord</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>MIT</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>41</abbrev>
      <title>Pastry</title>
      <subtitle>http://research.microsoft.com/~antr/pastry</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Microsoft Inc.</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>42</abbrev>
      <title>Tapestry</title>
      <subtitle>http://oceanstore.cs.berkeley.edu/tapestry</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>43</abbrev>
      <title>DKS</title>
      <subtitle>http://dks.sics.se</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>44</abbrev>
      <title>Grid Enabled Scalable Self-Organizing Services (GES3): A
      Vinnova-funded project between SICS and KTH</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.sics.se/dsl/ges3</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Sweedish Royal Institute of Technonlogy</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>45</abbrev>
      <title>OASIS, http://www.oasis-open.org</title>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>organisation for the Advancement of Structured
        Information Standards (OASIS)</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>46</abbrev>
      <title>Reference Rodel for Service Oriented Architecture SOA-RM,
      Comittee draft 1.0, 7 February 2006</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=soa-rm</subtitle>
      <copyright>
        <year>2006</year>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>organisation for the Advancement of Structured
        Information Standards (OASIS)</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>47</abbrev>
      <title>OASIS WSRF technical committee</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=wsrf</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>organisation for the Advancement of Structured
        Information Standards (OASIS)</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>48</abbrev>
      <title>FMA Technology Support Study, June 2005</title>
      <copyright>
        <year>2005</year>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>The Swedish Defence Material
        Administration(FMV)</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>49</abbrev>
      <title>OpenSIS</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.opensis.org</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>50</abbrev>
      <title>Globus Alliance</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.globus.org</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>51</abbrev>
      <title>Globus Toolkit</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.globus.org/toolkit</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>52</abbrev>
      <title>Global Grid Forum</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.ggf.org</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>53</abbrev>
      <title>OGSA</title>
      <subtitle>http://forge.gridforum.org/projects/ogsa-wg</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>54</abbrev>
      <title>SOAP Version 1.2 Part 0: Primer</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.w3.org/TR/2003/REC-soap12-part0-20030624/</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>55</abbrev>
      <title>Component Object Model Technologies</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.microsoft.com/com/default.mspx</subtitle>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>Microsoft</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>56</abbrev>
      <title>Web Services Description Working Group</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.w3.org/2002/ws/desc/</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>57</abbrev>
      <title>Web Services Description Language 1.1</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.w3.org/TR/wsdl</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>58</abbrev>
      <title>UDDI</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.uddi.org/</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>59</abbrev>
      <title>RDF</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.w3.org/RDF/</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>60</abbrev>
      <title>RSS 0.9</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.tragicdoughnuts.com/rss/0.9.html</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>61</abbrev>
      <title>RSS 0.91</title>
      <subtitle>http://my.netscape.com/publish/formats/rss-spec-0.91.html</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>62</abbrev>
      <title>RSS 1.0</title>
      <subtitle>http://web.resource.org/rss/1.0/</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>63</abbrev>
      <title>RSS 1.1</title>
      <subtitle>http://inamidst.com/rss1.1/</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>64</abbrev>
      <title>RSS 2.0</title>
      <subtitle>http://inamidst.com/rss1.1/</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>65</abbrev>
      <title>Atom, RFC 4287</title>
      <subtitle>http://tools.ietf.org/html/4287</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>66</abbrev>
      <title>DAML+</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.daml.org/2001/03/daml+oil-index</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>67</abbrev>
      <title>WSMF</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.wsmo.org/papers/publications/wsmf.paper.pdf</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>68</abbrev>
      <title>WSMX Working group</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.wsmo.org/wsmx/index.html</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>69</abbrev>
      <title>WSML Working group</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.wsmo.org/wsml/</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>70</abbrev>
      <title>OASIS WSDM technical committee</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=wsdm</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>71</abbrev>
      <title>W3C Choreography Working Group</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.w3.org/2002/ws/chor</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>72</abbrev>
      <title>Java Specification Request (JSR 208)</title>
      <subtitle>http://www.jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=208</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>73</abbrev>
      <title>Service Component Architecture (SCA)</title>
      <subtitle>http://www-128.ibm.com/developerworks/library/specification/ws-sca/</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>74</abbrev>
      <!--
<ulink
      url="http://dev2dev.bea.com/pub/a/2005/11/sdo.html"></ulink>
-->
      <title>Service Data Objects (SDO)</title>
      <subtitle>http://dev2dev.bea.com/pub/a/2005/11/sdo.html</subtitle>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>75</abbrev>
      <title>Evolution of a Software-Defined Radio Receiver's RF Front-End, RF
      IC Symp., paper RMO1A-5, June 2006.</title>
      <copyright>
        <year>2006</year>
      </copyright>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>76</abbrev>
      <title>The Software Radio Architecture, Mag., vol. 33, no. 5, May 1995,
      pp. 2638.</title>
      <pagenums>26-38</pagenums>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>77</abbrev>
      <title>Beyond Technical Interoperability; Introducing a Reference Model
      for Measures of Merit for Coalition Interoperability, June 17-19,
      2003</title>
      <authorgroup>
        <author>
          <firstname>Tolk</firstname>
          <surname>Andreas</surname>
        </author>
      </authorgroup>
      <copyright>
        <year>2003</year>
        <holder>Command and Control Research Program (CCRP)</holder>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>8th International Command and Control Research and
        Technology Symposium (ICCRTS)</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry>
      <abbrev>78</abbrev>
      <title>The Global Technology Revolution 2020, In-Depth Analyses</title>
      <authorgroup>
        <corpauthor>Richard Silberglitt, Philip S. AntÃ³n, David R. Howell,
        Anny Wong</corpauthor>
      </authorgroup>
      <copyright>
        <year>2006 RAND Corporation</year>
      </copyright>
      <isbn>0-8330-3975-X</isbn>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>RAND Corporation</publishername>
      </publisher>
    </biblioentry>
  </bibliography>
</book>
