<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd"[]>
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles</title>
	<titleabbrev>NISP</titleabbrev>
    <subtitle>Profiles</subtitle>
    <volumenum>3</volumenum>
    <corpauthor>C3B Interoperability Profiles Capability Team</corpauthor>
    <productname
      class="trade">Allied Data Publication 34</productname>
    <biblioid
      class="pubnumber">ADatP-34</biblioid>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>9.2</revnumber>
        <date>14 November 2016</date>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <subjectset><subject><subjectterm>DO NOT REMOVE</subjectterm></subject></subjectset>
  </bookinfo>
  <!--
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 1
 *****************************************************************
-->
  <chapter
    id="v3c1-iop">
    <title>Interoperability Profile Guidance</title>
    <sect1
      id="v3c1-iopcb">
      <title>Profile Conceptual Background</title>

      <para>ISO/IEC TR 10000 <xref
          linkend="ref-iso10000-3"/> defines the
      concept of profiles as a set of one or more base standards and/or
      International Standardized Profiles, and, where applicable, the
      identification of chosen classes, conforming subsets, options and
      parameters of those base standards, or International Standardized Profiles
      necessary to accomplish a particular function.</para>

      <para>The NATO C3 Board (C3B) Interoperability Profiles Capability Team (IP CaT) has extended the profile
      concept to encompass references to NAF architectural views <xref
          linkend="ref-naf3"/>, characteristic protocols, implementation options,
      technical standards, Service Interoperability Points (SIOP), and related
      profiles.</para>

      <para>Nothing in this guidance precludes the referencing of National
      profiles or profiles developed by non-NATO organizations in the
      NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles (NISP).</para>

    </sect1>
    <sect1
      id="v3c1-ioppurpose">
      <title>Purpose of Interoperability Profiles</title>
      <para>Interoperability Profiles aggregate references to the characteristics of other profiles types to provide a consolidated perspective.</para>

      <para>Interoperability Profiles identify essential profile
      elements including Capability Requirements and other NAF
      architectural views <xref linkend="ref-naf3"/>, characteristic protocols,
      implementation options, technical standards, Service
      Interoperability Points, and the relationship with other
      profiles such as the system profile to which an application
      belongs. Interoperability profiles will be incorporated in the
      NISP for a
      specified NATO Common Funded System or Capability Package to
      include descriptions of interfaces to National Systems where
      appropriate.</para>

      <para>NATO and Nations use profiles to ensure that all
      organizations will architect, invest, and implement capabilities
      in a coordinated way that will ensure interoperability for NATO and
      the Nations. Interoperability Profiles will provide context and
      assist or guide information technologists with an approach for
      building interoperable systems and services to meet required
      capabilities.</para>

    </sect1>
    <sect1
      id="v3c1-iopappl">
      <title>Applicability</title>
      <para>The NISP affects the full NATO project life cycle.  NISP stakeholders include engineers, designers, technical project managers, procurement staff, architects and other planners.  Architectures, which identify the components of system operation, are most applicable during the development and test and evaluation phase of a project.  The NISP is particularly applicable to a federated environment, where interoperability of mature National systems requires an agile approach to architectures.</para>
      <para>The IP CaT has undertaken the development of interoperability profiles in order to meet the need for specific guidance at interoperability points between NATO and Nations systems and services required for specific capabilities. As a component of the NISP, profiles have great utility in providing context and interoperability specifications for using mature and evolving systems during exercises, pre-deployment or operations. Application of these profiles also provides benefit to Nations and promotes maximum opportunities for interoperability with NATO common funded systems as well as national to national systems. Profiles for system or service development and operational use within a mission area enable Nations enhanced readiness and availability in support of NATO operations.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1
      id="v3c1-iopgfd">
      <title>Guidelines for Interoperability Profile Development</title>
      <para>Due to the dynamic nature of NATO operations, the complex Command and Control structure, and the diversity of Nations and Communities of Interest (COI), interoperability must be anchored at critical points where information and data exchange between entities exists. The key drivers for defining a baseline set of interoperability profiles include:
      <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Identify the Service Interoperability Points and define the Service Interface Profiles</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use standards consistent with the common overarching and reference architectures</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Develop specifications that are service oriented and independent of the technology implemented in National systems where practical</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use mature technologies available within the NATO Information Enterprise</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Develop modular profiles that are reusable in future missions or capability areas</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use an open system approach to embrace emerging technologies</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <para>The starting point for development of a profile is to clearly define
      the Service Interoperability Point where two entities will interface and
      the standards in use by the relevant systems.</para>

      <para>The use of "shall" in this guidance document is intended to
      establish a minimum level of content for NATO and NATO candidate profiles,
      but is suggested-but-not-binding on non-NATO profiles (national, NGO,
      commercial and other entities).</para>

      <para>The NISP is the governing authoritative reference for NATO interoperability profiles. Doctrine, Organization, Training, Materiel, Leadership and education, Personnel, Facilities and Interoperability (DOTMLPFI) capability analysis may result in a profile developer determining that some of the capability elements may not be relevant for a particular profile. In such cases, the "not applicable" sections may either be marked "not applicable" or omitted at the author's discretion.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1
      id="v3c1-ioptaxonmy">
      <title>Profile Taxonomy</title>
      <para>The objective of the interoperability profile taxonomy is to provide a classification scheme that can categorize any profile. In order to achieve this objective, the classification scheme is based on NATO Architecture Framework views and DOTMLPFI characteristics.</para>
      <para>The taxonomy illustrated in the figure below will also provide a mechanism to create short character strings, used as a root mnemonic to uniquely identify profiles.
</para>
      <figure
        id="f1-ioptaxy"
        float="0">



        <title>Interoperability Profile Taxonomy</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata
              align="center"
              fileref="../figures/ioptaxy.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>
    <sect1
      id="v3c1-iopstructure">
      <title>Structure of Interoperability Profile Documentation</title>
      <para>This section identifies typical elements of Interoperability Profile Documentation.</para>
      <sect2
        id="v3c1-iopid">
        <title>Identification</title>
        <para>Each NATO or candidate NATO Interoperability Profile <emphasis
            role="bold">shall</emphasis> have a unique identifier assigned to it when accepted for inclusion in the NISP. This <emphasis
            role="bold">shall</emphasis> be an alpha-numeric string appended to the root mnemonic from the NISP profile taxonomy.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2
        id="v3c1-iopelements">
        <title>Profile Elements</title>
        <para>Profile elements provide a coherent set of descriptive inter-related information to NATO, national, NGO, commercial and other entities ('actors') desiring to establish interoperability.</para>
        <para>Profiles are not concepts, policies, requirements, architectures, patterns, design rules, or standards. Profiles provide context for a specific set of conditions related to the aforementioned documents in order to provide guidance on development of systems, services, or even applications that must consider all of these capability related products. Interoperability Profiles provide the contextual relationship for the correlation of these products in order to ensure interoperability is 'built-in' rather than considered as an 'after-thought'.</para>
        <sect3
          id="v3c1-iopas">
          <title>Applicable Standards</title>
          <para>Each profile <emphasis
              role="bold">shall</emphasis> document the standards required to support this or other associated profiles and any implementation specific options. The intention of this section is to provide an archive that shows the linkage between evolving sets of standards and specific profile revisions.
</para>
          <table
            frame="all"
            id="rd-iopas-1">
            <title>Applicable Standards</title>
            <tgroup
              align="left"
              cols="4">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>ID</entry>
                  <entry>Purpose/Service</entry>
                  <entry>Standards</entry>
                  <entry>Guidance</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>A unique profile identifier</entry>
                  <entry>A description of the purpose or service</entry>
                  <entry>A set of relevant Standard Identifier from the NISP</entry>
                  <entry>Implementation specific guidance associated with this profile (may be a reference to a separate annex or document)</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
        </sect3>
        <sect3
          id="v3c1-ioprp">
          <title>Related Profiles</title>
          <para>Each profile should document other key related system or service profiles in a cross reference table. The intention of this section is to promote smart configuration management by including elements from other profiles rather than duplicating them in part or in whole within this profile. Related profiles would likely be referenced in another section of the profile.
</para>
          <table
            frame="all"
            id="rd-ioprp-1">
            <title>Related Profiles</title>
            <tgroup
              align="left"
              cols="4">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Profile ID</entry>
                  <entry>Profile Description</entry>
                  <entry>Community of Interest</entry>
                  <entry>Associated SIOPs</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>A unique profile identifier</entry>
                  <entry>A short description of the profile</entry>
                  <entry>Air, Land, Maritime, Special Ops, etc.</entry>
                  <entry>Unique SIOP identifiers</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1
      id="v3c1-iopvc">
      <title>Verification and Conformance</title>
      <para>Each profile <emphasis
          role="bold">shall</emphasis> identify authoritative measures to
          determine verification and conformance with agreed quality assurance,
          Key Performance Indicators (KPIs), and Quality of Service standards
          such that actors are satisfied they achieve adequate
          performance. All performance requirements must be quantifiable and measurable; each requirement must include a performance (what), a metric (how measured), and a criterion (minimum acceptable value).</para>
      <para>Stakeholders are invited to provide feedback
          to improve a profile's verification and conformance criteria.</para>
      <para>Verification and Conformance is considered in terms of the
          following five aspects: <orderedlist
          inheritnum="ignore"
          continuation="restarts"> <listitem><para>Approach to Validating
          Service Interoperability Points </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Relevant Maturity Level Criteria </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Key Performance Indicators (KPIs)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Experimentation</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Demonstration</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
      <sect2
        id="v3c1-iopavsip">
        <title>Approach to Validating Service
          Interoperability Points</title>
        <para>Each profile should describe the
          validation approach used to demonstrate the supporting service
          interoperability points. The intention of this section is to describe
          a high-level approach or methodology by which stakeholders may
          validate interoperability across the SIOP(s). </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2
        id="v3c1-ioprnmlc">
        <title>Relevant Maturity Level
          Criteria</title>
        <para>Each profile should describe the Maturity criteria
          applicable to the profile. The intention of this section is to
          describe how this profile supports the achievement of improved
          interoperability. </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2
        id="v3c1-iopkpi">
        <title>Key Performance Indicators (KPIs)</title>
        <para>Each profile should describe the associated Key Performance
          Indicators (KPIs) to establish a baseline set of critical core
          capability components required to achieve the enhanced
          interoperability supported by this profile. The intention of this
          section is to assist all stakeholders and authorities to focus on the
          most critical performance-related items throughout the capability
          development process. </para>
        <table
          frame="all"
          id="rd-iopkpi-1">
          <title>Key Performance Indicators (KPIs)<footnote><para>'notional' KPIs shown in the table are for illustrative
          purposes only.</para></footnote></title>
          <tgroup
            align="left"
            cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Key Performance Indicators
          (KPI)</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>KPI #1: Single (named) Architecture</entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>KPI #2: Shared Situational Awareness</entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>KPI #3: Enhanced C2</entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>KPI #4: Information
          Assurance</entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>KPI #5:
          Interoperability</entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>KPI #6:
          Quality of Service</entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>KPI #7:
          TBD</entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </sect2>
      <sect2
        id="v3c1-iope">
        <title>Experimentation</title>
        <para>Each profile should document
          experimentation venues and schedules that will be used to determine
          conformance. The intention of this section is to describe how
          experimentation will be used to validate conformance. </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2
        id="v3c1-iopd">
        <title>Demonstration</title>
        <para>Each profile
          should document demonstration venues and schedules that demonstrate
          conformance. The intention of this section is to describe how
          demonstration will be used to validate conformance. </para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1
      id="v3c1-iopcmg">
      <title>Configuration Management and
          Governance</title>
      <sect2
        id="v3c1-iopcm">
        <title>Configuration
          Management</title>
        <para>Each profile <emphasis
            role="bold">shall</emphasis> identify the current approach or
          approaches toward configuration management (CM) of core documentation
          used to specify interoperability at the Service Interoperability
          Point. The intention of this section is to provide a short description
          of how often documents associated with this profile may be expected to
          change, and related governance measures that are in place to monitor
          such changes [e.g., the IP CaT]. </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2
        id="v3c1-iopg">
        <title>Governance</title>
        <para>Each profile <emphasis
            role="bold">shall</emphasis> identify <emphasis
            role="bold">one or
          more authorities</emphasis> to provide feedback and when necessary,
          Request for Change Proposals (RFCP) for the Profile in order to ensure
          inclusion of the most up-to-date details in the NISP. The intention of
          this section is to provide a clear standardized methodology by which
          stakeholders may submit recommended changes to this profile. </para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1
      id="v3c1-iopad">
      <title>Annex Descriptions</title>
      <para>The following
          describes a list of potential <emphasis
          role="bold">optional</emphasis> annexes to be used as needed. The
          intention of this section is to place all classified and most lengthy
          information in Annexes so that the main document stays as short as
          possible. In cases where tables in the main document become quite
          lengthy, authors may opt to place these tables in Annex D. </para>
      <para>Annex A - Classified Annex (use only if necessary)</para>
      <para>Annex A-1 - Profile elements (classified subset)</para>
      <para>Annex A-2 - (Related) Capability Shortfalls</para>
      <para>Annex
          A-3 - (Related) Requirements (classified subset)</para>
      <para>Annex
          A-4 - (Related) Force Goals</para>
      <para>Annex A-5 - other relevant
          classified content</para>
      <para>Annex B - Related Architecture Views
          (most recent)</para>
      <para>Annex B-1 - Capability Views (NCV)</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>NCV-1, Capability Vision</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NCV-2, Capability Taxonomy</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NCV-4, Capability Dependencies</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NCV-5, Capability to Organizational
          Deployment Mapping</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NCV-6,
          Capability to Operational Activities Mapping</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NCV-7, Capability to Services Mapping</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Annex B-2 - Operational Views
          (NOV)</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>NOV-1, High-Level
          Operational Concept Description</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NOV-2, Operational Node Connectivity Description</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NOV-3, Operational Information
          Requirements</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Annex B-3 -
          Service Views (NSOV)</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>NSOV-1,
          Service Taxonomy</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NSOV-2, Service
          Definitions (Reference from NAR)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NSOV-3, Services to Operational Activities Mapping (in
          conjunction with NCV-5, NCV-6, NCV-7, NSV-5 and NSV-12)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Quality of Services metrics for the
          profiled services</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Annex B-4 -
          System Views (NSV)</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>NSV-1,
          System Interface Description (used to identify Service
          Interoperability Point (SIOP))</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NSV-2, Systems Communication Description</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NSV-2d, Systems Communication Quality Requirements</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NSV-3, Systems to Systems Matrix</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NSV-5, Systems Function to Operational Activity Traceability
          Matrix</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NSV-7, System Quality
          Requirements Description</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NSV-12,
          Service Provision</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Annex B-5 -
          Technical Views (NTV)</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>NTV-1,
          Technical Standards Profile. Chapter 4 of the NAF Ref (B) provides
          more specific guidance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NTV-3,
          Standard Configurations</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Annex
          C - Program / Inter-Programme Plans</para>
      <para>Annex C-1 - (Related)
          Mid-Term Plan excerpt(s)</para>
      <para>Annex C-2 - (Related) Programme
          Plan excerpt(s)</para>
      <para>Annex D - Other Relevant Supporting
          Information</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <bibliography>
    <title>References</title>

    <biblioentry
      id="ref-naf3">
      <abbrev>NAF3</abbrev>
      <title>NATO Architecure Framework Version 3</title>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>NATO C3 Agency</publishername>
      </publisher>
      <copyright>
        <year>2007</year>
      </copyright>
    </biblioentry>
    <biblioentry
      id="ref-iso10000-3">
      <title>Information technology - Framework and taxonomy of International Standardized Profiles - Part 3: Principals and Taxonomy for Open System Environment Profiles</title>
      <copyright>
        <year>1998</year>
      </copyright>
      <publisher>
        <publishername>ISO</publishername>
      </publisher>
      <pubsnumber>ISO/IEC TR 10000-3</pubsnumber>
    </biblioentry>
  </bibliography>
<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    Minimum Interoperability PROFILE
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol3-annex-MinInterop.xml"
    xpointer="v3-MinInterop" />
<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    X-TMS-SMPTP PROFILE
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol3-annex-X-TMS-SMTP.xml"
    xpointer="v3-X-TMS-SMTP" />

<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    Web Services PROFILE
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol3-annex-WSP.xml"
    xpointer="v3-WSP" />


<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    NRF GENERIC PROFILE
 *****************************************************************

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol3-annex-nrf.xml"
    xpointer="v3-nrf" />
 *****************************************************************
                    TACTICAĹ ESB PROFILE
Deleted by RFCP 20140717-I1.2-Vol2
 *****************************************************************

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol3-annex-esb.xml"
    xpointer="v3-esb" />
 *****************************************************************
                    AMN PROFILE
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol3-annex-amn.xml"
    xpointer="v3-amn" />

<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    CES PROFILE
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol3-annex-ces.xml"
    xpointer="v3-ces" />

<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    SIP TEMPLATE
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol3-annex-sip.xml"
    xpointer="v3-sip" />


<!--
 *****************************************************************
           FMN PROFILE SPIRAL 1.1
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol3-annex-fmn-spiral-1.xml"
    xpointer="v3-fmn-spiral-1" />

<!--
 *****************************************************************
           Archive PROFILE
 *****************************************************************
 -->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol3-annex-archive.xml"
    xpointer="v3-archive" />
<!--
 *****************************************************************

           Core Services PROFILE
 *****************************************************************
 -->

  <xi:include

    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol3-annex-core-services.xml"
    xpointer="v3-csp" />
<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    EXTERNAL PROFILES  (Always include last)
 *****************************************************************
    <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol3-annex-external.xml"
    xpointer="v3-external" />
-->

</book>
