<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
        Vol 3 -   A N N E X  - Archive Profile

*****************************************************************  
-->

<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>

<appendix id="v3-archive">
  <title>Profile for the Long Term Preservation of NATO Digital Information of Permanent value</title>

<para>
  This profile outlines the file formats (Section 1) and package structures
  (Section 2) approved by the Archives Committee for the long-term
  preservation of NATO digital information of permanent value.
</para>
<para>
  NATO information custodians shall provide information in these formats
  and structures to the NATO Archivist.
</para>
<para>
  Further guidance on best practice will be issued in the near future.
  The contents of this profile shall become part of Volume 3 of the NATO
  Interoperability Standards and Profiles [AC/322-N(2013)0197, 2013].
</para>
<sect1 id="part-i-file-formats-for-long-term-preservation">
  <title>File Formats for Long Term Preservation</title>
  <para>
    The following sustainable file formats are approved by the Archives
    Committee for the long term preservation of NATO digital information
    of permanent value. The formats are ordered by content type. A brief
    characterization of the generic requirements for the preservation of
    content is included.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="data-sets">
    <title>Data sets**</title>
    <para>
      Data sets are typically collections of individual values or larger
      coherent structures such as messages. The data set might be an
      export from a database or the results of an information exchange
      between systems.
    </para>
    <para>
      There is typically a structure associated with the data set,
      either implicitly contained within the data set (e.g. a table
      structure of an Excel document or a database), or explicitly
      defined (e.g. as a schema definition)
    </para>
    <para>
      DATA SETS STANDARDS TABLE HERE
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="text">
    <title>Text</title>
    <para>
      Documents consisting primarily of textual descriptions are the
      most prevalent and important category of information of permanent
      value in the NATO context. Text documents might also include
      embedded diagrams, pictures, or other non- text material. These
      items shall not be separated from the text and kept as part of the
      document.
    </para>
    <para>
      TEXT STANDARDS TABLE HERE
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="still-images">
    <title>Still Images</title>
    <para>
      Still images are visual representations, including photographs,
      graphs, and diagrams. Still images can be divided into two main
      types, bitmap (or raster) images and vector images. Bitmap images
      are typically photographs produced by scanners and cameras at a
      fixed resolution, while vector images consist of scalable objects.
      Both types can be combined, e.g. in course of action diagrams
      where a bitmap image of an area can have symbology vector
      overlays.
    </para>
    <para>
      STILL IMAGE STANDARDS TABLE
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="moving-images">
    <title>Moving Images</title>
    <para>
      Moving images are digital recordings of still images at a
      particular frame rate and resolution. A compression is often
      applied by only capturing the difference between adjacent frames.
      Moving images are typically combined with audio data and packaged
      into a common container.
    </para>
    <para>
      MOVING IMAGE STANDARDS TABLE
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sound">
    <title>Sound</title>
    <para>
      Sound files contain recordings of voice or other audio. This
      includes audio recordings from meetings if they contain
      information of permanent value.
    </para>
    <para>
      SOUND STANDARDS TABLE
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="geospatial">
    <title>Geospatial</title>
    <para>
      Geospatial information is typically produced, used, and contained
      in geographic information systems (GIS). The information is
      related to the still image category, as geospatial information
      consists of bitmap or vector images plus additional attributes
      associated with particular locations depicted in the image data.
    </para>
    <para>
      GEOSPATIAL STANDARDS TABLE
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="web-archive">
    <title>Web Archive</title>
    <para>
      The web archive type concern the archival of entire web sites,
      portals, or parts of them. While some information might be
      contained in static web pages and is therefore easy to capture,
      other parts might be dynamically rendered.
    </para>
    <para>
      Web archives typically contain structured textual descriptions as
      well as still and moving images.
    </para>
    <para>
      WEB ARCHIVE STANDARDS
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="package-structures-for-long-term-preservation">
  <title>Package Structures for Long Term Preservation</title>
  <para>
    NATO digital information of permanent value shall be processed by
    their Information Custodians into single digital information items
    with associated metadata and packaged into submission and archival
    information package structures
    <ulink url="ISO,%20Space%20data%20and%20information%20transfer%20systems%20–%20Open%20archival">ISO
    14721, 2003</ulink>.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="submission-information-package">
    <title>Submission Information Package</title>
    <para>
      NATO digital information of permanent value selected by
      Information Custodians for long term preservation should be
      delivered to the NATO Archivist as a Submission Information
      Package (SIP).
    </para>
    <para>
      The SIP consists of two parts: the actual information packaged as
      a single digital information item and a set of metadata associated
      with this item (see Figure 1)Figure 1
    </para>
    <para>
      The single digital information item has the following structure:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">Content</emphasis>: Information of one
          of the seven types listed under 4a-g). For certain types of
          content, primarily data sets (4a), several pieces of
          information might be grouped. A schema provided as part of the
          Data Definition can be used to describe the structure of these
          groupings. For other types such as documents, images, or
          recordings, information items shall be included individually.
          Items might contain other objects that should also be
          preserved in a sustainable format. For example, an archived
          email message could have text documents as attachments that
          should be stored in the sustainable formats listed in 4b).
          Guidance on granularity and grouping will be provided by the
          Archives Committee.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Data Definition:</emphasis> If the Content consists
          of structured data, a separate Data Definition shall be
          included that describes the logical structure of the Content.
          This is primarily applicable to Content of the types Data Set
          (4a), Geospatial (4f), and Web Archive (4g). The format of the
          Data Definition shall be XML Schema 1.1.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Visualization: A visualization and human readable
          representation of contextual information is optional. The
          format used for the context information shall be one of those
          listed under 4a–g).
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      The individual parts (Content, Data Definition and Visualization)
      shall be packaged as a single digital information item by using
      the Open Packaging Conventions [ISO 29500-2:2012, 2012] format.
    </para>
    <para>
      The file name of the packaged single digital information item
      shall follow the NATO Guidance on File Naming [AC/322-N(2010)0025,
      2010]. OPC does not define an extension; the .zip extension shall
      be used for packages for long term preservation.
    </para>
    <para>
      The packaged single digital information item shall contain a basic
      set of metadata for the container. OPC supports a subset of six
      Dublin Core metadata elements (creator, description, identifier,
      language, subject, and title) and two Dublin Core terms (created,
      modified). The elements shall be filled by the Information
      Custodian when the OPC container for the single digital
      information item is created. Note that this metadata refers to the
      container itself, not to its contents. For example, the creation
      date is the date the container was created, not the creation date
      of the content.
    </para>
    <para>
      In addition to the OPC container metadata, the Information
      Custodian will generate a full metadata description for the
      content of the SIP, including the classification of the single
      digital information item.
    </para>
    <para>
      The SIP metadata follows the NATO Core Metadata Specification
      (NCMS) <ulink url="">AC/322-D(2014)xxxx, 2014</ulink> and the NATO
      Labelling Specification [AC/322- D(2014)yyyy/zzzz, 2014], 2014.
      Values for all mandatory elements shall be assigned by the
      Information Custodian. The NATO Archivist shall reject all
      submissions with incomplete metadata.
    </para>
    <para>
      No information of permanent value packaged in a SIP and submitted
      by the Information Custodian shall be destroyed unless the SIP has
      been explicitly acknowledged and accepted by the NATO Archivist.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="archival-information-package">
    <title>Archival Information Package</title>
    <para>
      If the content of the SIP submitted by an Information Custodian
      for long-term preservation are accepted by the NATO Archivist, the
      SIP will be processed into an Archival Information Package (AIP).
    </para>
    <para>
      The AIP consists of the same structure as the SIP, i.e. the single
      digital information item for long-term preservation packaged as an
      OPC container, and the NCMS-compliant metadata information bound
      to the container.
    </para>
    <para>
      As part of the Ingest process, the metadata supplied with the SIP
      will be augmented by preservation metadata approved by the NATO
      Archivist. In addition, NATO Archivist shall become the custodian
      for the AIP.
    </para>
    <para>
      The preservation metadata will be an extension to the NCMS
      metadata. The extension shall be based on the PREMIS metadata set
      <ulink url="PREMIS%20Editorial%20Committee,%20PREMIS%20Data%20Dictionary%20for%20Preservation">PREMIS
      Metadata, 2008</ulink>.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="references">
  <title>References</title>
  <para>
    <ulink url="">AC/322-D(2014)xxxx, 2014</ulink>4:
  </para>
  <para>
    Consultation, Command and Control Board (2014, in prep), NATO Core
    Metadata
  </para>
  <para>
    Specification, AC/322-D(2014)xxxx, NATO Unclassified.
  </para>
  <para>
    Consultation, Command and Control Board (2014, in prep), Information
    Management Directive for Confidentiality Labelling of NATO
    Information, AC/322-D(2014)xxxx, NATO Unclassified.
  </para>
  <para>
    The 2014 AC/322 documents are in the process of being established.
    Once the documents are approved the applicable document reference
    number will be inserted under references.
  </para>
  <para>
    [AC/322(2014)xxxx, 2014]: Consultation, Command and Control Board
    (2014, in prep), Information Management Guidance for Confidentiality
    Labelling of NATO Information, AC/322(2014)xxxx, NATO Unclassified.
  </para>
  <para>
    [AC/322-N(2013)0197, 2013]: Consultation, Command and Control Board
    (2013), NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles, Version 8
    (NISP V8), AC/322-N(2013)0197, NATO Unclassified, Releasable to
    Australia/New Zealand/Singapore.
  </para>
  <para>
    [AC/322-N(2010)0025, 2010]: Consultation, Command and Control Board
    (2010), Guidance on File Naming, AC/3222-N(2010)0025, NATO
    Unclassified, Releasable to PfP.
  </para>
  <para>
    information system – Reference model, First Edition, ISO 14721:2003.
  </para>
  <para>
    languages -- Office Open XML File Formats -- Part 2: Open Packaging
    Conventions, ISO/IEC29500-2:2012.
  </para>
  <para>
    Metadata, Version 2.0, March 2008.
  </para>
</sect1>


</appendix>
