<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 3 - A N N E X - D
REF: NCI Agency Technical Report TR-2013/ACO008868/04
*****************************************************************  
-->
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v3-d">
    <title>The Afghanistan Mission Network (AMN) Profile of NATO Interoperability Standards</title>
<para>Ref(A): NCI Agency Technical Report TR-2013/ACO008868/04 - Dated 01 July 2013</para>
  <sect1>
  <sect2>
    <title>General</title>

    <para>NATO, through its interoperability directive, has recognized that widespread interoperability is a key component in achieving effective and efficient operations. In many of the operations world-wide in which the military of the NATO nations are engaged, they participate together with a wide variety of the military of other nations and non-military organizations on the ground. The NATO Interoperability Standards and Profile (NISP) provides the necessary guidance and technical components to support project implementations and transition to NATO Network Enabled Capability (NNEC).</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Authorised Version</title>
    
    <para>The standards extant for the AMN are described in the NISP. This is published as ADatP-34 by the NATO C3 Board. As part of the NISP, an AMN Profile of NATO Interoperability Standards has been published among the several operational profiles permitted as part of ADatP-34. The latest authorised version can be found in Volume 4 of the NISP [ADaTP-34(G)-REV1, Volume 4 Annex D, 8 March 2013]. These are the extant and NATO agreed list of practical standards to achieve immediately usable interoperability between the national network extensions of the NATO nations, coalition partners and NATO provided capabilities.</para>
<para>Nations participating in the AMN have agreed to comply with the AMN joining instructions, of which these standards form an integral part.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Application</title>
    
    <para>The AMN Profile will be used in the implementation of NATO Common Funded Systems. Nations participating in AMN agree to use this profile at Network Interconnection Points (NIPs) and at other Service Interoperability Points as applicable.</para>
    
    <para>NNEC Services must be able to function in a network environment containing firewalls and various routing and filtering schemes; therefore, developers must use standard and well-known ports wherever possible, and document non-standard ports as part of their service interface. Service developers must assume network behaviour and performance consistent with the existing limits of these networks, taking bandwidth limitations and potentially unreliable networks into account.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Life-Cycle of Standards</title>
    
    <para>ADatP-34 defines four stages within the life-cycle of a standard: emerging, mandatory, fading and retired. In those situations where multiple stages are mentioned, the AMN Profile recommends dates by which the transition to the next stage is to be completed by all AMN members. If a TCN (or NCI Agency) decides to implement emerging standards it is her responsibility to maintain backwards compatibility to the mandatory standard.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Forthcoming/Agreed Changes</title>
    
    <para>Volume 4 of the Joining, Membership and Exit Instructions (JMEI) is oriented around the AMN Profile of NATO Interoperability Standards. The AMN Profile is maintained within this document.</para>
    <para>The extant authorised version of the AMN Profile is as published in ADaTP-34(G). This formal published version of the AMN Profile is to only be originated from this document (i.e. Vol 4 of the JMEI published as NCI Agency Technical Report <cite>TR-2013/ACO008868/04</cite>).</para>
    <para>The NCI Agency acts as the custodian for the AMN Profile and is to be used as the conduit for changes (via her membership of the AMN AWG). This must be via the process outlined at section 2.7 of the JMEI Volume 4</para>
    <para>Any changes already collectively agreed by the AMN TCN and NCI Agency via the AMN AWG for use on the AMN but not yet published in ADaTP-34 were indicated as changes in the document. These changes will be submitted for publication in the next authorised issue of ADatP-34 (i.e. ADaTP-34(H) and thereafter).</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Relationship to NATO C3 Classification Taxonomy</title>
    
    <para>The AMN has been designed and is managed as far as possible using a service approach. The AMN Services are based on the NATO C3 Classification Taxonomy [<cite>AC/322-N(2012)0092-AS1</cite>].</para>
    <para>The C3 Classification Taxonomy is used to identify particular services and associated Service Interoperability Point where two entities will interface and the standards in use by the relevant systems.</para>
    <para>Where required, the implementation of the standard is described in an annex associated with the Service.</para>
    <para>Where a composite suite of services (with their standards) are required to implement a suite of services that are typically grouped together to form a familiar “composite service” or a “user facing Service”, then the implementation annex is housed at the assessed “centre of gravity” of the composite service. This is done simply to keep the instructions together. This applies for those services which network engineers, system administrators, users or operators  recognise as distinct (e.g. “Text based Chat”, “VoSIP” or “VTC”), and for which technical skills/specialisms/instructions already exist. For Example the VTC implementation annex is placed under “Enterprise Support Services” despite the fact that the VTC is also affected by settings implemented in “Communications Access Services”.</para>
    <para>The C3 Classification Taxonomy is used to structure this document, commencing with Communications and working up the Taxonomy from beneath.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Relationship to the Future (Federated) Mission Network</title>
    
    <para>Subsequent NATO led missions will benefit from the modular nature of the AMN Profile, which will allow for maximum reuse of established capabilities, while accommodating unique requirements and technology improvements.</para>
    <para>Based on the AMN Profile, a Federated Mission Network Profile of NATO Interoperability Standards has been proposed and is anticipated to be published in the next version of ADaTP-34. This will support the implementation of the Future Mission Network (FMN) Concept [<cite>MCM-0125-2012</cite>].</para>
    <para>Given the strong linkage between AMN and FMN, the opportunity to maintain a single Federated Mission Network Profile is possible in future versions of this document, but will firstly require the establishment of the FMN Governance and FMN Framework Management Structures. To this end it is anticipated that any future development of capabilities for the AMN in the future should be done in the direction indicated by the Federated Mission Network Profile.</para>
    <para>This AMN Profile contains footnotes from the FMN Profile that if applied would implement the AMN in the direction of the FMN. These are indicated as a footnote to the referenced standard. Please note however: <emphasis role="bold"><emphasis role="bold">The FMN notes are only included for information. They are not yet approved by the AWG for use on the AMN.</emphasis></emphasis></para>
  </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Communication Services</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Communications Services interconnect systems and mechanisms for the opaque transfer of selected data between or among access points, in accordance with agreed quality parameters and without change in the form or content of the data as sent and received.</emphasis></para>
    <para>Communications Services can be further defined as:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>Transmission and Transport Services</listitem>

	<listitem>Communications Access Services</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>In addition, standards and implementation practice must also be adhered to in the following area:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>Communications Equipment</listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <sect2>
	<title>Communications Equipment</title>
        <para>Although technically not part of the AMN, fundamental to the establishment of any federated communications service, there are a few equipment standards that must be adhered to. These are listed in Table 1 below.</para>
      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table1">
        <title>Table 1: Communications Equipment Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Connectivity between coalition networks (autonomous systems) Fibre</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Single-mode optical fibre (SMF) 9/125μm, ISO/IEC OS1, LC duplex single-mode connector.</para><para>IEEE 802.3z Gigabit Ethernet, 1000BASE-LX10, 1310nm</para>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>This interconnection is based on STANAG 5067 enhanced with a non-tactical connector and optional 1Gb/s Ethernet.</para><para> 
ST 5067 provides additional implementation, security and management guidance.</para><para>
Use 1Gb/s Ethernet over SMF.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
   </sect2>
	<sect2>
    <title>Transmission and Transport Services</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Transmission Services cover the physical layer (also referred to as media layer or air-interface in wireless/satellite (SATCOM) communications) supporting Transport Services, as well as Communications Access Services. Support for the latter is relevant to personal communications systems, in which the User Appliances directly connect to the transmission element without any transport elements in between.</emphasis></para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Transport Services provide resource-facing services, providing metro and wide-area connectivity to the Communications Access Services that operate at the edges of the network. In that role, Transport Services interact with the Transmission Services using them as the physical layer fabric supporting the transfer of data over a variety of transmission bearers as and where needed.</emphasis></para>
	<sect3>
	<title>Standards</title>
	<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table 2 should be adhered to.</para>
      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table2">
        <title>Table 2: Transmission and Transport Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Naming and addressing</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Classless Inter Domain Routing (IETF RFC 4632)</para>
		<para>Host Extensions for IP Multicasting (IETF RFC 1112)</para>
		<para>The Internet Multicast Address Allocation (IETF RFC 2908)</para>
		<para>IANA Guidelines for IPv4 Multicast Address Assignments (IETF RFC 3171)</para>
		<para>Administratively Scoped IP Multicast (IETF RFC 2365)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2:Basic connectivity between technical services.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>User Datagram Protocol (IETF Standard 6, RFC 768)</para>
		<para>Transmission Control Protocol (IETF Standard 7, RFC 793:1981 updated by RFC 3168:2001)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Max Transmission Unit (MTU) reduced to 1300 bytes, Max Segment Size (MSS) set to 1260 bytes in order to accommodate IP crypto tunnelling within autonomous systems</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
 	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>Although the implementation scope of AMN technically does not cover Transmission and Transport Services (see definition in REF(A) section 3.2) the TCN joining the AMN require guidance on options on how to provide communications within Theatre.</para>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing these services:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex A.1: Provision of Terrestrial Communications.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex A.2: Use of Deployable CIS (including SATCOM).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>With respect to creating the connection at the NIP the following Annex is provided:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex A.3: Connecting to the Network Interconnection Points (NIP).</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
	</sect3>
 	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	<title>Communications Access Services</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Transport Communications Access Services provide end-to-end connectivity of communications or computing devices. Communications Access Services can be interfaced directly to Transmission Services (e.g. in the case of personal communications systems) or to Transport Services, which in turn interact with Transmission Services for the actual physical transport. Communications Access Services correspond to customer-facing communications services. As such, they can also be referred to as Subscriber Services, or Customer-Edge (CE) Services.</emphasis></para>
	<para>With respect to the current implementation scope of AMN, the following Communications Access services apply:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Packet-Based Access Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Communications Access Information Assurance (IA) Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Communications Access Service Management Control (SMC) Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Multimedia Services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
	<sect3>
	<title>Standards</title>
	<para>To provide federated services, the standards listed Table 3 should be adhered to.</para>
	<table frame="all" id="v3t-table3">
        <title>Table 3: Communications Access Services Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Basic connectivity between technical services.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Internet Protocol (IETF RFCs 791/792, 919/922/950/1112/1812
<footnote><para>FMN: will also implement IETF RFC 2644. It is advisory that AMN also follows this.</para></footnote>
</para>
		<para>Internet Protocol version 6 (IPv6)  (IETF RFCs 2460:1998)
<footnote><para>FMN: will also implement IETF RFC 2474/3484/3810/4291/4443/4861/5095. If IPv6 is ever implemented for the AMN, many of these would be also advisable.</para></footnote>
</para>
		<para>QoS – AMN standard was constructed based on QENI – see Annex B.3 for details
<footnote><para>FMN: will implement QoS: IP QoS for the NII, [NC3A TN-1417]. Note for implementation: Utilize Quality of Service capabilities of the network according to TN-1417 maturity level QoS-1 (Diffserve, no military precedence on IP).</para></footnote>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>IP networking. Accommodate both IPv4 and IPv6 addressing
<footnote><para>Note that although IPv6 has always been part of the AMN Profile it has never been taken up. There has always been the intent to provide a tunnel of v6 over v4 or via a dual stack, should a TCN require it.</para></footnote>
</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><para>2:Connectivity between coalition networks (autonomous systems)</para><para>Fibre<footnote><para>FMN: A key improvement that the FMN will bring is the ability to create connectivity over a Time-division multiplexing (TDM) Wide Area Network (WAN). For this a suite of standards additional to those for a fibre based network has been drawn from TACOMs and demonstrated. The FMN Profile will include implementation notes and instructions for these.</para></footnote></para></entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Ethernet Address Resolution Protocol (IETF Standard 37. RFC 826) (for IPv4 only)</para>
<para>Border Gateway Protocol V4 (IETF RFC 1771, March 1995)
<footnote><para>FMN: Will implement IETF RFC 4271, 4760, 3392, 2545. FMN notes: BGP deployment guidance in RFC 1772 must be considered. (RFC 4271 obsoletes RFC 1771). BGP sessions must be authenticated, through a TCP message authentication code (MAC) using a one-way hash function (MD5), as described in RFC 4271.</para></footnote></para>
<para>BGP Communities Attribute (IETF RFC 1997, Aug 1996)</para>
<para>FMN footnote
<footnote><para>FMN: Will implement Neighbor Discovery for IP version 6 (IPv6) (IETF RFC 4861) (for IPv6 only)</para></footnote></para>
<para>Multicast Source Discovery Protocol (MSDP) (IETF RFC 3618, Oct 2003)</para>
<para>Protocol Independent Multicast Sparse Mode (PIM-SM) (IETF RFC 4601, Aug 2006)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Detailed Interface Control Document for “Connection Between CISAF network and TCN networks” [Thales ICD NIP Dec 2013]</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3:Provide communications security over the network above the Transport Layer</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Mandatory: Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2 (RFC 5246:2008)</para>
<para>Fading (to Dec 2011): Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol version 1.0 (RFC 2246:1999)
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	<title>Implementation of Packet-Based Access Services</title>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Transport Packet-based Access Services involve delivery or exchange of data (or digitised voice, video) encapsulated in IP packets. In the case of the AMN, IPv4 and IPv6 (if implemented) routed access services can be considered under this Service Category.</emphasis></para>
	<para>The NIP provides a network interconnection at the IP layer for the ISAF SECR3T environment making up the AMN. It serves 3 major purposes:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Intra autonomous system (AS) routing (routing of traffic between nations or between nations and NATO, where each nation is a BGP Autonomous System)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>QoS policy enforcement (to provide end-to-end QoS for the required services)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>IPSLA compliance verification (to verify end-to-end performance compliance)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex B.1: Numbering Registration [incl 5.2.5.4 from v2]</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex B.2: Sample Router Configuration Template</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex B.3: BGP and IP Multicast Routing [incl note about IP accelerators]</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex B.4: Quality of Service (QOS)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex B.5: Internet Protocol Service Level Agreement Monitoring [incl 5.2.4.5 from v2]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	<title>Implementation of Communications Access Information Assurance (IA) Services</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Communications Access Information Assurance (IA) Services provide a foundation to implement and enforce IA policies at the communications access level..</emphasis></para>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex C.1: Firewalls</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex C.2: Intrusion Detection Systems</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex C.3: Intrusion Prevention Systems</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	<title>Implementation of Communications Access Service Management Control (SMC) Services</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Communications Access Service Management and Control (SMC) Services provide the necessary means to implement and enforce SMC policies at the communications access level. Encompasses VTC Management Services, Demand Assigned Multiple Access (DAMA) Control Services and Call Management Services.</emphasis></para>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex D.1: Network Management</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex D.2: Incident Management</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex D.3: Performance Management</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex D.4: Access Control. BPS – make sure cite MN TCN back link policy</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	<title>Implementation of Multimedia Services</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Multimedia Access Services provide the interface with User-Facing Capabilities, as well as the adaptation (e.g. encoding and compression) of the media (e.g. voice, video, text) and the protocols employed for multimedia communication sessions (e.g. video-teleconferencing), for delivery and exchange over packet-based, frame-based, circuit-based, or digital (link)-based Communications Access Services.</emphasis></para>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex E.1: Voice/VoSIP/VTC Numbering Plans</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex E.2: Voice Services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

	</sect3>
      </sect2>
   </sect1>
	
	<sect1>
	<title>Core Enterprise Services</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Core Enterprise Services (CES) provide generic, domain independent, technical functionality that enables or facilitates the operation and use of Information Technology (IT) resources.</emphasis></para>
	<para>CES will be broken up further into:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Infrastructure Services (incl. Information Assurance (IA) services)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) Platform Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Enterprise Support Services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

	<sect2>
	<title>Infrastructure Services</title>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Infrastructure Services provide software resources required to host services in a distributed and federated environment. They include computing, storage and high-level networking capabilities that can be used as the foundation for data centre or cloud computing implementations.</emphasis></para>
	<sect3>
	<title>Standards</title>
	<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table 4 should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table4">
        <title>Table 4: Infrastructure Services Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry morerows="1">1: Infrastructure Foundation Services: Distributed Time Services: Time synchronization</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Mandatory: Network Time Protocol version 3 (NTPv3), dated March 1992. RFC 1305</para>
<para>The AMN Core must provide a time server directly connected to a stratum-0 device<footnote><para>For an FMN implementation, if TCN also provide an equivalent to the AMN Core (known in FMN terms as “Option A”), then the time service could also be provided over a network path to a stratum-1 time server on the TCN (Option A) network.</para></footnote>.</para>
<para>TCN connecting to the AMN Core must use the time service of the AMN Core.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>A stratum-1 time server is directly linked (not over a network path) to a reliable source of UTC time (Universal Time Coordinate) such as GPS, WWV, or CDMA transmissions through a modem connection, satellite, or radio.</para>
<para>The W32Time service on all Windows Domain Controllers is synchronizing time through the Domain hierarchy (NT5DS type).</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>To aid rapid post event reconstruction, ALL networked equipment and databases will be set to store and process time as Coordinated Universal Time (UTC). i.e. ZULU Time Zone should apply to the Mission [AMN TPT CES Sept 2011].</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Human interfaces may convert the time for display to the user as D* (i.e. Local) as required.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: Infrastructure Foundation Services: Domain Name Services: Naming and Addressing</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Domain Name System (IETF Standard 13, RFC 1034/RFC 1035)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Identification and addressing of objects on the network.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>RFC 1738, Uniform Resource Locators (URL), 20 December 1994</para>
<para>RFC 2396, Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI), Generic Syntax, August 1998 (updates RFC 1738)
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Namespaces within XML documents shall use unique URLs or URIs for the namespace designation.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4: Infrastructure IA Services:  Facilitate the access and authorization between FMN users and services.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Directory access and management service:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>version 3 of the Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAPv3), RFC 4510 and associated  LDAP Technical Specification (RFC 4511-4519)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>LDAP Interchange Format, RFC 2849</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>
<para>Authentication:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Kerberos version 5, RFC 1510</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>
<para>
Public Key Infrastructure:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Version 3 public-key certificates and Version 2 CRLs in accordance with ITU-T X.509v3. RFC2560,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NATO Public Key Infrastructure (NPKI) Certificate Policy (CertP) Rev2, AC/322D(2004)0024REV2</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RFC2560, x.509 Public Key Infrastructure Certificate</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>There are three options available to a Troop Contributing Nation (TCN) when joining their national network extension to the AMN:</para>
<para>1. Join the ISAF SECR3T AD forest on AMN Core</para>
<para>2. Join the AD forest of an existing AMN TCN</para>
<para>3. Create own AD forest for the new AMN TCN</para>
<para>(Option 1 and 2 should be considered by the prospective Joining TCN before Option 3).</para>
<para>Whilst LDAP is a vendor independent standard, in practice Microsoft Active Directory (AD) is a common product providing directory services on national and NATO owned Mission Network elements. AD provides additional services aside from LDAP like functionality.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5: Infrastructure Processing (Operating System) Services</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Operating Systems used on the AMN must be accredited by the respective Security Accreditation Authority.</para>
<para>As a minimum the Operating Systems should support the specifications for the above (Infrastructure IA Services).</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Note: Clients on the AMN Core and Option 1 TCN National Network Extensions are strongly advised to use Windows 7 Enterprise due to the mid-2014 End of Support provision by Microsoft for Windows XP. Win 7 Enterprise was selected due to the inclusion of AppLocker (remote enforcement of application control policies) and integration with Sharepoint 2010 and MS Office Professional Plus 2010.</para>
<para>Note: Windows 2008 R2 Standard Full Edition 64 bit is strongly advised for Domain Controllers. Note Service Pack SP1 should be installed</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6: Infrastructure Storage Services:  Database Replication Services</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>[To Do]</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Note required on Enterprise Infonic Replication</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex F.1: Time Synchonisation</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex F.2: DNS Synchonisation</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex F.3: Active Directory Options</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex F.4: PKI</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex F.5: AMN DC Server and Recommended Client Builds</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex F.6: Database Replication</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex F.7: Preventive Cyber Defence Services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

	</sect3>
	</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	<title>SOA Platform Services</title>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">SOA Platform Services provide a foundation to implement web-based services in a loosely coupled environment, where flexible and agile service orchestration is a requirement. They offer generic building blocks for SOA implementation (e.g. discovery, message busses, orchestration, information abstraction and access, etc.) and can be used as a capability integration platform in a heterogeneous service-provisioning ecosystem.</emphasis></para>
	<sect2>
	<title>Standards</title>
	<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table 5 should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table5">
        <title>Table 5: SoA Platform Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Web Platform Services</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Hypertext Transfer Protocol HTTP 1.1 (RFC 2616): 1999</para>
<para>TLS Protocol v1.0 (RFC2246)<footnote><para>FMN: Upgrading to TLS within HTTP 1.1 (RFC 2817)</para></footnote>.</para>
<para>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax (RFC 3938)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>HTTP shall be used as the transport protocol for information without 'need-to-know' caveats between all service providers and consumers.</para>
<para>HTTPS shall be used as the transport protocol between all service providers and consumers to ensure CONFIDENT1ALity requirements.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: Publishing information including text, multimedia, hyperlink features, scripting languages and style sheets on the network</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>HTML 4.01 (RFC2854:2000), HyperText Markup Language (HTML), W3C<footnote><para>FMN: Emerging (2014): HyperText Markup Language, Version 5 (HTML 5), W3C Candidate Recommendation, Dec 2012.</para></footnote></para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Providing a common style sheet language for describing presentation semantics (that is, the look and formatting) of documents written in markup languages like HTML.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Mandatory: Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), Level 2 revision 1 (CSS 2.1), W3C Recommendation, Sep 2009.</para>
<para>Emerging : Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), Level 3(CSS 3), W3C Recommendation,</para>
<para>Fading (until Dec 2011): CSS Level 1, Jan 1999.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4: General formatting of information for sharing or exchange.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Extensible Markup Language (XML), v1.0 3rd Edition XML Schema: Structures 1.0</para>
<para>XML Schema: Data types 1.0 XML Namespaces: W3C (REC-xmlnames-1999-01-14)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>XML shall be used for data exchange to satisfy those IERs within a FMN instance that are not addressed by a specific information exchange standard. XML Schemas and namespaces are required for all XML documents.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5: Providing web content or web feeds for syndication to web sites as well as directly to user agents.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Mandatory: Really Simple Syndication (RSS) 2.0 Specification</para>
<para>Emerging (by Dec 2011): Atom 1.0: Atom syndication format, Dec 2005 (RFC 4287) and Atom Publishing Protocol , Oct 2007 (RFC 5023)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6: Encoding of location as part of  web feeds</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Mandatory: GeoRSS Simple encoding.</para>
<para>Where GeoRSS Simple is not appropriate the OGC GeoRSS Geography Markup Language (GML) Application Profile shall be used</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>GeoRSS extensions should be used to describe location aspects within ATOM and RSS feeds.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>7: Message Security for web services</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>WS-Security: SOAP Message Security 1.1</para>
<para>XML Encryption Syntax and Processing (dtd. 10 December 2002)</para>
<para>XML Signature Syntax and Processing 1.0 (Second Edition)</para>
<para>WS-I Basic Security profile 1.1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Specifies how integrity and CONFIDENT1ALity can be enforced on messages and allows the communication of various security token formats, such as SAML, Kerberos, and X.509v3. Its main focus is the use of XML Sig nature and XML Encryption to provide end-to-end security.</para>
<para>Specifies a process for encrypting data and representing the result in XML. Referenced by WS-Security specification.</para>
<para>Specifies XML digital signature processing rules and syntax. Referenced by WS-Security specification.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>8: Security token format</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>SAML 2.0</para>
<para>Web Services Security: SAML Token Profile 1.1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Provides XML-based syntax to describe uses security tokens containing assertions to pass information about a principal (usually an end-user) between an identity provider and a web service.</para>
<para>Describes how to use SAML security tokens with WS-Security specification.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>9: Security token issuing</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>WS-Trust 1.4</para>
<para>WS-Federation 1.1</para>
<para>WS-Policy 1.5</para>
<para>and WS-Security Policy 1.3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Uses WS-Security base mechanisms and defines additional primitives and extensions for security token exchange to enable the issuance and dissemination of credentials within different trust domains.</para>
<para>Extends WS-Trust to allow federation of different security realms.</para>
<para>Used to describe what aspects of the federation framework are required/supported by federation participants and that this information is used to determine the appropriate communication options.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>10: Transforming XML documents into other XML documents</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>XSL Translation (XSLT 1.0)</para>
<para>Emerging  March  2013:  XSL Transformation (XSLT) 2.0, W3C Recommendation 23 Jan 2007</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Developer best practice for the translation of XML based documents into other formats or schemas.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>11: Configuration management of structured data standards, service descriptions and other structured metadata.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>ebXML v3.0: Electronic business XML Version 3.0,</para>
<para>Registry Information Model (ebRIM), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005,</para>
<para>Registry Services and Protocols (ebRS), OASIS Standard,</para>
<para>Universal Description, Discovery, and Integration Specification (UDDI v 2.0), OASIS Standard</para>
<para>Emerging (Dec  2011): UDDI v 3.0, OASIS Standard.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Used as foundation for setup, maintenance and interaction with a (AMN) Metadata Registry and Repository for sharing and configuration management of XML metadata. Also enables federation among metadata registries/ repositories.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>12: Exchanging structured information in a decentralized, distributed environment via web services</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>W3C SOAP 1.1, Simple Object Access Protocol v1.1 (SOAP)</para>
<para>Emerging (2014): SOAP 1.2,  2 May 2005.</para>
<para>Representational State Transfer (REST)</para>
<para>WSDL v1.1: Web Services Description Language (WSDL) 1.1, W3C Note, 15 March 2001.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>The preferred method for implementing web-services are SOAP, however, there are many use cases (mash-ups etc.) where a REST based interface is easier to implement and sufficient to meet the IERs.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>13: Secure exchange of data objects and documents across multiple security domains</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>The Draft X-Labels syntax definition is called the "NATO Profile for the XML CONFIDENT1ALity Label Syntax" and is based on version 1.0 of the RTG-031 proposed XML CONFIDENT1ALity label syntax, see "Sharing of information across communities of interest and across security domains with object level protection" below.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>14: Topic based publish / subscribe web services communication</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>WS-Notification 1.3 including:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>WS-Base Notification 1.3</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>WS-Brokered Notification 1.3</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>WS-Topics 1.3</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Enable topic based subscriptions for web service notifications, with extensible filter mechanism and support for message brokers.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>15: Providing transport-neutral mechanisms to address web services</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>WS-Addressing 1.0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Provides transport-neutral mechanisms to address Web services and messages which is crucial in providing end-to- message level security, reliable messaging or publish / subscribe based web services end.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>16: Reliable messaging for web services</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>WS-Reliable Messaging 1.2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Describes a protocol that allows messages to be transferred reliably between nodes implementing this protocol in the presence of software component, system, or network failures.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex G.1: Authoritative and Trusted Data Sources</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex G.2: Service Registration [TBC]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	<title>Enterprise Support Services</title>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Enterprise Support Services are a set of Community Of Interest (COI) independent services that must be available to all members within the AMN.  Enterprise Support Services facilitate other service and data providers on the federated networks by providing and managing underlying capabilities to facilitate collaboration and information management for end-users.</emphasis></para>
	<para>For the purposes of this Volume, Enterprise Support Services will be broken up further into:<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Unified Communication and Collaboration Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Information Management Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Geospatial Services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	<sect2>
	<title>Unified Communication and Collaboration Services</title>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Unified Communication and Collaboration Services provide users with a range of interoperable collaboration capabilities, based on standards that fulfill operational requirements. They will enable real-time situational updates to time-critical planning activities between coalition partners, communities of interest (e.g. the Intel community or the Logistics community), and other agencies. Levels of collaboration include awareness, shared information, coordination and joint product development.</emphasis></para>
	<para>Different use cases require different levels of protection of these communication and collaboration services. For voice or audio-based collaboration services, the AMN profile can provide interoperability standards for two different scenarios<footnote><para>FMN: Under the FMN profile, 3 scenarios are offered. The first being pure Voice over IP (VoIP) network services, i.e. conventional IP telephony. The choice of this over VoSIP being purely based on classification of the network.</para></footnote>:<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>A. Voice over Secure IP (VoSIP) network services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>B. Network agonistic Secure Voice Services (such as 3G, IP/4G, ISDN)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>
	<para>On AMN, VoSIP is mandatory.  If however network agnostic Secure Voice services are required in addition to VoSIP<footnote><para>The only scenario where this would apply would be in the case that crypto devices cannot be supplied, protected and managed on site and <emphasis role="underline">physical</emphasis> access to the AMN is hence not available at that location.</para></footnote>, then SCIP specifications as defined for audio-based collaboration services (end-to-end protected voice) over any network should be used<footnote><para>If SCIP is used, then access to the AMN can only be possible if a gateway for SCIP multi-conferencing and interconnection to VoSIP networks is provided. AMN. Additionally to achieve this there would need to be agreement to re-use a Key Management system that is already deployed in ISAF (for example that used for the OMLTs).</para></footnote>. [Note this has been included due to the emerging requirements regarding RSM]</para>
	<para>For text-based collaboration there is also a basic profile sufficient for operating this service with reduced protection requirements as well as an enhanced XMPP profile that includes additional security mechanisms.</para>
	<sect3>
	<title>Standards</title>
	<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table 6 should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table6">
        <title>Table 6: Unified Communication and Collaboration Services and Data Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Video-based Collaboration Services (VTC)</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Mandatory: VTCoIP: Signalling: ITU-T Recommendation H.323;</para> 
<para>Mandatory: Audio encoding: ITU-T Recommendation G.722.1c;</para> 
<para>Mandatory: Video encoding: ITU-T Recommendation H.263</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>AMN VTC over IP is based on a QoS-Enabled Net- work Infrastructure (QENI) using Diffserve.</para> 
<para>The AMN-Wide allowed interconnections are:</para> 
<para>A) Peer to Peer,</para> 
<para>B) Peer to MCU and</para> 
<para>C) Peer to MCU to MCU to Peer</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: Audio-based Collaboration Services</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>VoIP: SIP (IETF RFC 3261)<footnote><para>FMN: Also include RTP (IETF RFC 3550)</para></footnote></para> 
<para>Audio data compression Codec ITU-T Recommendation G.729 (01/07)  -  The  use  of  G.729 may require a license fee and/ or royalty fee - DiffServ, PHB and DSCP defined by IETF RFC 2474
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>VoSIP refers to non-protected voice service running on a classified IP network (as in the case of the AMN).</para> 
<para>ITU-T G.Imp729 (11/09)</para> 
<para>Voice Sampling Interval between Voice packets: 40ms</para> 
<para>RTP protocol ports 16384 and/or 16385</para> 
<para>See also detailed Interface Control Document for "Voice over Secure IP (VoSIP) Network Service" [THALES ICD 61935771-558 A Jul 2009].</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Audio-based Collaboration Services (end-to-end protected voice)</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Modem over IP (MoIP) according to ITU-T V.150.1 Minimum Essential Requirements</para> 
<para>Minimum Essential Requirements (MER) for V.150.1 recommendation: SCIP-216</para> 
<para>SCIP signalling plan: SCIP-210</para> 
<para>Interface requirements for SCIP devices to circuit switched networks: SCIP-214</para> 
<para>Interface requirements for SCIP devices to IP networks: SCIP-215</para> 
<para>Minimum Essential Requirements (MER) for V.150.1 recommendation: SCIP-216</para> 
<para>Requirements for SCIP: SCIP-220</para> 
<para>SCIP Minimum Implementation Profile (MIP): SCIP-221</para> 
<para>NATO interim cryptographic suite: SCIP-233 (NATO and coalition)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Secure voice services over any network.</para> 
<para>V.150.1 support must be end-to-end supported by unclassified voice network</para> 
<para>SCIP-214 only applies to gateways</para> 
<para>Note that SCIP-216 requires universal implementation.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4: Informal messaging services (e-mail)</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP) (RFC 1870:1995 and RFC 2821:2001)</para> 
<para>Simple Internet Messages (RFC 2822:2001).</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Emerging: RFC 5321:2008 which obsoletes: RFC 2821:2001</para> 
<para>Conditional: messages must be labelled in the message header field “Keywords” (RFC 2811) according to the following convention:</para> 
<para>[MMM] [CLASSIFICATION], Releasable to [MISSION]</para> 
<para>Where CLASSIFICATION is the classification {SECR3T, CONFIDENT1AL, RESTR1CTED, UNCLASSIFIED} and MMM is the alpha-3 country code e.g. DEU, GBR, as defined in Table 8.ID2 with the exception that NATO will be identified by the four letter acronym “NATO”.  The “releasable to” list shall include the short-name of the mission and may be extended to include other entities.</para> 
<para>Example:</para> 
<para>Keywords:  ITA UNCLASSIFI ED, Releasable to ISAF</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5: Content encapsulation within bodies of internet messages</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) specification (RFC 2045:1996, RFC 2046:1996, RFC 2047:1996, RFC 2049:1996, RFC 4288 :2005)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>10 MB max message size limit</para> 
<para>Minimum Content-Transfer-Encoding: 
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>7bit</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>base64</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>binary BINARYMIME SMTP extension [RFC 3030]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para> 
<para>Minimum set of media and content-types:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>text/plain [RFC1521]</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>text/enriched [RFC1896]</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>text/html [RFC1866]</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>multipart/mixed [RFC 2046]</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>multipart/signed</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6: text-based collaboration services<footnote><para>FMN: It is proposed that the FMN will also adopt these Mandatory and Enhanced XMPP profiles</para></footnote>
</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Mandatory: Basic XMPP profile (see 6.1)</para> 
<para>Recommended: Enhanced XMPP profile (see 6.2)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Near-real time text-based group collaboration capability for time critical reporting and decision making in military operations.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6.1: text-based collaboration services (basic XMPP profile)</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>IETF RFC 6120 Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): Core, March 2011 covering XML streams, SASL, TLS, stanza semantics</para> 
<para>IETF RFC 6121 Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP) extensions for: Instant Messaging and Presence.</para> 
<para>The following XMPP Extension Protocols shall also be supported:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>XEP-0004: Data Forms</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0030: Service Discovery, February 2007</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0045: Multi-User Chat (MUC), July 2008</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0049: Private XML Storage, March 2004</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0050: Ad Hoc Commands, June 2005</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0054: vCard Profiles,  March 2003</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0065: SOCKS5 Byte streams</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0078: Non-SASL Authentication (for support of older clients)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0091: Legacy Delayed Delivery, May 2009</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0092: Software Version, February 2007</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0096: File Transfer</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0114: Jabber Component Protocol, March 2005</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0115: Entity Capabilities</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0203: Delayed Delivery, September 2009</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0220: Server Dialback, December 2007</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0288: Bidirectional Server-to-Server Connections, October 2010</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
<para>RFC 6120 supersedes RFC 3920 and RFC 6121 XMPP IM supersedes RFC 3921</para> 
<para>Developers are also advised to consult the following RFCs:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>RFC 6122 XMPP ADDR XMPP address format</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RFC 3923 XMPP E2E End- to-end signing and object en cryption for XMPP</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RFC4854 XMPP URN. A Uniform Resource Name (URN) tree for use in XMPP extensions</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RFC 4979 XMPP ENUM IANA registration    of an Enumservice (see RFC 3761) for XMPP</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RFC 5122 XMPP URI A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) scheme for XMPP (this specification corrects several errors in RFC 4622)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6.2: text-based collaboration services (enhanced XMPP profile).</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>The enhanced profile requires compliance with the basic profile as defined above plus:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>XEP-0033: Extended Stanza Addressing</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0079: Advanced Message Processing</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0122: Data Forms Validation</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0199: XMPP Ping, June 2009</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0249: Direct MUC Invitation</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0258: Security Labels in XMPP, March 2009</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0289: Federated MUC for Constrained Environments, May 2012</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>XEP-0311: Fast Reconnect</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Developers are also advised to consult the following RFCs:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>RFC 6122: Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP): Address Format, March 2011</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RFC 6125: Representation and Verification of Domain-Based Application Service Identity within Internet Public Key Infrastructure Using X.509 (PKIX) Certificates in the Context of Transport Layer Security (TLS), March 2011</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RFC 3923: XMPP E2E End-to-end signing and object encryption for XMPP</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RFC 4854: XMPP URN A uniform Resource Name (URN) tree for use in XMPP</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RFC 4979: XMPP ENUM IANA registration of an Enum service (see RFC 3761) for XMPP</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RFC 5122: XMPP URI A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) schema for XMPP (this specification corrects several errors in RFC 4622)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex H.1: VTC Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex H.2: VoSIP Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex H.3: SCIP Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex H.4: SMTP Mail Routing</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex H.5: GAL Synchonisation</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex H.6: XMPP Text Based Chat</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	</sect3>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	<title>Information Management Services</title>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Information Management Services provide technical services "...to direct and support the handling of information throughout its life-cycle ensuring it becomes the right information in the right form and of adequate quality to satisfy the demands of an organization."  These services support organizations, groups, individuals and other technical services with capabilities to organize, store and retrieve information (in any format, structured or unstructured) through services and managed processes, governed by policies, directives, standards, profiles and guidelines.</emphasis></para>
	<sect3>
	<title>Standards</title>
	<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table 7 should be adhered to. Additionally all information should be labelled with the minimum metadata set listed in Table 8.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table7">
        <title>Table 7: Information Management Services and Data Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Enterprise Search Services:  Automated information resource discover, information extraction and interchange of metadata</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>ISO 15836:2009 also known as the Dublin Core Metadata Element Set</para> 
<para>TIDE Information Discovery (v2.3.0, Oct 2009)</para> 
<para>Emerging: TIDE Service Discovery (v.2.2.0 Oct 2008)</para> 
<para>Emerging: SPARQL Ver 1.1 (2009)</para> 
<para>Emerging: OWL Ver 2 (2009)</para> 
<para>Emerging (2014): OpenSearch 1.1 Draft 4.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>ISO 15836:2009 does not define implementation detail.</para> 
<para>This profile requires a subset of metadata with UTF8 character encoding as defined in the NATO Discovery Metadata Specification (NDMS).</para> 
<para>The technical implementation specifications are part of the TIDE Transformational Baseline v3.0, however, Query-by-Example (QBE), has been deprecated with the TIDE Information Discovery specs v2.3.0 and replaced by SPARQL.</para> 
<para>The TIDE community is evaluating OpenSearch for potential inclusion into the TIDE Information Discovery specifications.  On the AMN CORE a commercial product called FAST ESP is being used to generate search indexes. This product could act as an OpenSearch "slave", but re- quires adaptation to this Open Standard but only using HT-TP. For automated information discovery across the AMN, all potential information sources must provide this standard search interface in order to allow  tools like FAST ESP to discover relevant information</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: Enterprise Support Guard Services:  General definition of Security and CONFIDENT1ALity metadata</entry>
              <entry>
                <para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>NO-FFI 00961 (RTO spec on CONFIDENT1ALity labels);</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NO-FFI 00962 (RTO spec on metadata binding);</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NC3A TN-1455 (NATO profile of NO-FFI 00962);</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NC3A TN-1456 (NATO profile of NO-FFI 00961).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Services and applications shall implement object level labelling in order to support cross-domain information exchange using common enterprise Support Guard Services (e.g. Cross-Domain Solutions or Information Exchange Gateways)</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table8">
        <title>Table 8:  Minimum Metadata set</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="12*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="15*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">(Dublin Core) element name</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">XML element name</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Obligation category</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>title</entry>
              <entry>dc:title</entry>
              <entry>M</entry>
              <entry><para>A name given to the resource.</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>creator</entry>
              <entry>dc:creator</entry>
              <entry>M</entry>
              <entry><para>An entity (organization) primarily responsible for making the content of the resource.</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Date</entry>
              <entry>dc:date</entry>
              <entry>M</entry>
              <entry><para>A calendar date associated with an event in the life cycle of the resource. Typically, ‘date’ will be associated with the creation or availability of the resource. Implementation of the W3C profile of ISO 8601:2004 (W3CDTF profile) is recommended using the YYYY-MM-DD format.</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>subject</entry>
              <entry>dc:subject</entry>
              <entry>M</entry>
              <entry><para>The topic of the content of the resource.</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Keywords</entry>
              <entry>dc:keywords</entry>
              <entry>M</entry>
              <entry><para>Specific words denoting the context of the resource.</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Description</entry>
              <entry>dc:description</entry>
              <entry>C</entry>
              <entry><para>An account of the content of the resource. Description may include but is not limited to: an abstract, table of contents, reference to a graphical representation of content or a free-text account of the content.</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>identifier</entry>
              <entry>dc:identifier</entry>
              <entry>C</entry>
              <entry><para>An unambiguous reference (reference number) to the resource within a given context. An internal, external, and/or universal identification number for a data asset or resource.</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>coverage</entry>
              <entry>ows:BoundingBox</entry>
              <entry>C</entry>
              <entry><para>The spatial or temporal topic of the resource.</para>
<para>The spatial applicability of the resource specified by its geographic coordinates, or the jurisdiction (such as a named administrative entity as defined in ISO-3166-2) under which the resource is relevant.</para></entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex I.1: Federating Search [TBC]</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex I.2: Minimum Metadata Standard</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex I.3: Enterprise Portal Configuration</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	</sect3>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	<title>Geospatial Services</title>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Geospatial Services deliver network-based access to quality raster, vector and terrain data, available in varying degrees of format and complexity. Geospatial Services form a distinct class of information services through their unique requirements for collecting, converting, storing, retrieving, processing, analysing, creating, and displaying geographic data. The generic nature of Geospatial Services - "organizing information by location" - is interdisciplinary and not specific to any Community of Interest (COI) or application.</emphasis></para>
	<sect3>
	<title>Standards</title>
	<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table 9 should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table9">
        <title>Title string</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Service/Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Distribution of geospatial data as maps rendered in raster image formats.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>OGC 04-024 (ISO 19128:2005), Web Map Service (WMS) v.1.3  Fading (Dec 2012): OGC WMS v1.0.0, v1.1.0, and v1.1.1</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OGC 05-078r4, OpenGIS Styled Layer Descriptor Profile of the Web Map Service (SLD) v.1.1.0</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Emerging 2014: OGC 07-057r7, OpenGIS Web Map Tile Service Implementation Standard (WMTS) v.1.0.0</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>WMTS are to be provided as a complimentary service to WMS to ease access to users operating in bandwidth constraint environments. WMTS trades the flexibility of custom map rendering for the scalability possible by serving of static data (base maps) where the bounding box and scales have been constrained to discrete tiles which enables the use of standard network mechanisms for scalability such as distributed cache systems to cache images between the client and the server, reducing latency and bandwidth use.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: Distribution of geo feature (vector) data between applications</entry>
              <entry>
                <para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>OGC 04-094, Web Feature Service (WFS) v.1.1.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OGC 06-049r1, GML Simple Feature Profile (GML 3.1.1) v.1.0.0 Compliance Level 0</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OGC 04-095, Filter Encoding v.1.1</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Electronic interchange of geospatial data as coverage, that is, digital geospatial information representing space varying phenomena</entry>
              <entry>
                <para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>OGC 07-067r2, Web Coverage Service (WCS) v.1.1.1. Fading (Dec 2011): v1.0.0 and v1.1.0</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>
<para>Emerging (2014):
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>OGC 09-110r4, Web Coverage Service (WCS) v2.0</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Web Coverage Service v.1.1.1 is limited to describing and requesting grid (or "simple") coverage.</para>
<para>OGC Web Coverage Service (WCS) Standard Guidance Implementation Specification 1.0</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4: Catalogue services support the ability to publish and search collections of descriptive information (metadata) for geospatial data, services, and related information objects.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>OGC 07-110r4, CSW ebRIM Registry Service Part 1: ebRIM profile of CSW v.1.0.1</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>
<para>Recommended:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>OGC 07-006r1: Catalogue Service for the Web (CSW) v.2.0.2, SOAP message</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist></para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Catalogue Services will be supported by Core GIS FSD2 on the AMN Core.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5: Electronic format for medium resolution terrain evaluation data.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>U.S. Military Specification Digital Terrain Elevation Data (DTED)	level 0,1,2 MIL-PRF-89020B</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Used to support line-of-sight analyses, terrain profiling, 3D terrain visualization, mission planning/rehearsal, and modelling and simulation.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6: File based storage and exchange of digital geospatial mapping (raster) data where services based access is not possible</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>GeoTIFF format specification revision 1 v1.8.2, Dec 2000 (a public domain metadata standard embedding geo-referencing information within a TIFF revision 6.0 file)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OpenGIS GML in JPEG 2000 (ISO/IEC 15444-1 and 2) for Geographic Imagery Encoding Specification 1.0.0 (05-047r3).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Multi-resolution seamless image database (MrSid Generation 2)
<footnote><para>FMN: This is placed as Fading for the FMN in 2013</para></footnote>
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Enhanced Compressed Wavelet (ECW 3.3)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NSA Compressed ARC Digitized Raster Graphics (CADRG), MIL-C-89038, October 1994</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Raster product format (RPF), MIL-STD-2411, 6 Oct 1994</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>This is provided for legacy systems, implementers are encouraged to upgrade their systems to consume OGC Web Services.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>7: File based storage and exchange of non-topological geometry and attribute information or digital geospatial feature (vector) data</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>ESRI SHAPE files</para><para> 
Open Geospatial Consortium 07-147r2, Keyhole Markup Language (KML) 2.2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>ESRI SHP files are used by legacy systems and as file based interchange format. Implementers are encouraged to upgrade their systems based on OGC Web Services.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex J.1: Geospatial Services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	</sect3>
	</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	<title>Communities of Interest Services</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Communities of Interest (COI) Services support one or many collaborative groups of users with shared goals, interests, missions or business processes.</emphasis></para>
	<para>COI Service will be broken up further into:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>COI Enabling Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>COI Specific Services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
	<sect2>
	<title>Communities of Interest Enabling Services</title>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic"></emphasis>COI-Enabling Services provide COI-dependant functionality required by more than one communities of interest. They are similar to Enterprise Support Services in that they provide building blocks for domain-specific service development. The distinction between the two is that Enterprise Support Services provide generic COI-independent capabilities for the entire enterprise (e.g. collaboration and information management services) and COI-Enabling Services provide those COI-dependant services that are typically shared by a larger group of COIs (e.g. operational planning and situational awareness capabilities).</para>
	<para>For the purposes of this Volume, COI-Enabling Services will be broken up further into:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>General COI-Enabling Formats and Standards</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Situational Awareness Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Biometric Services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	<sect3>
	<title>General COI-Enabling Formats and Standards</title>
	<sect4>
	<title>Standards</title>
	<para>Common standards that apply to all COI Enabling Service are listed Table 10. These should be adhered to if federated services are to be achieved.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table10">
        <title>Table 10: General Data Format Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: General definition for the Representation of Dates and Times.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>ISO 8601:2004 - Data elements and interchange formats - Information interchange - Representation of dates and times</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>If not otherwise specified, implementation of the W3C profile of ISO 8601:2004 (W3CDTF profile) is mandatory.</para>
<para>Note: See also guidance on storage and use of time regarding the ZULU Time Zone given in Table 4.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: General definition of letter codes for Geographical Entities</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>STANAG 1059, Letter Codes for Geographical Entities (8th edition, 2005)<footnote><para>FMN: For FMN the following alpha-2/alpha-3 codes shall be used to identify international organizations and their sub-ordinated entities: NATO: “XN”/ “XXN”, European Union: “EU” / “XEU”, United Nations: “XU”/”XUN”.</para></footnote>.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Whenever possible, the ISO-3166 alpha-3 (three-letter codes) contained in STANAG 1059 should be used.</para>
<para>Alpha-3 codes “XXA”, “XXB”, “XXC”, “XXX” shall not be used to avoid potential conflicts with ISO/IEC 7501-1.</para>
<para>Codes “EEE” and “GER” are used as a deviation by ISAF Force Tracking System (IFTS) for EUPOL and Germany respectively.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: General definition of letter codes for identifying Nationality of a person</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>When STANAG 1059 3-letter codes are being used for identifying nationality, code extensions as defined in ISO/IEC 7501-1 such as XXA, XXB, XXC, XXX for special machine-readable passports are to be used.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>ISO/IEC 7501-1 for special machine-readable passports</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4: General definition of geospatial coverage areas in discovery metadata</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>World Geodetic System (WGS) 84, ISO 19115 and ISO 19136 (for point references)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>ISO 19139 provides encoding guidance for ISO 19115</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
	</sect4>
	<sect4>
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex K.1: [Nil to date]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	</sect4>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	<title>Situational Awareness Services</title>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Situational Awareness (SA) Services provide the situational knowledge required by a military commander to plan operations and exercise command and control. This is the result of the processing and presentation of information comprehending the operational environment - the status and dispositions of friendly, adversary, and non-aligned actors, as well as the impacts of physical, cultural, social, political, and economic factors on military operations.</emphasis>
</para>
	<sect4>
	<title>Standards</title>
	<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table 11 should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table11">
        <title>Table 11: Battlespace Management Interoperability Protocols and Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Expressing digital geographic annotation and visualization on, two-dimensional maps and three dimensional globes</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>TIDE Transformational Baseline Vers. 3.0 NATO Vector Graphics (NVG)</para>
<para>Mandatory: (NVG 1.5)<footnote><para>FMN: Emerging (2014): (NVG) v2.0</para></footnote></para>
<para>Fading (Dec 2011): NVG 1.4</para>
<para>Retired: NVG 0.3</para>
<para>Open Geospatial Consortium 07-147r2, Keyhole Markup Language (KML) 2.2</para>
<para>Open Geospatial Consortium 05-047r3, GML in JPEG 2000 for Geographic Imagery Encoding Specification 1.0.0,  (annotations and overlays)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>NVG shall be used as the standard Protocol and Data Format for encoding and sharing of information layers</para>
<para>NVG and KML are both XML based language schemas for expressing geographic annotations.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: General formatted message exchange</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>STANAG 5500 Ed.6:2010</para>
<para>AdatP-3 Concept of NATO Message Text Formatting System (CONFORMETS) ADatP-3(A) Change 1
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>ADatP-3(A) contains two different equivalent presentations of data: one as "classic" message or alternatively as XML-MTF instance.</para>
<para>A) Automated processing of XML-files in static facilities/systems is much easier and thus preferred for the exchange between national AMN extensions and the AMN Core.</para>
<para>B) At the tactical edge of the AMN the "classic" message format is the preferred option as this format is "leaner" and easier to transmit via tactical radio systems.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>3: Message formats for exchanging information in low bandwidth environment between systems enabled for processing Military Message Format</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>STANAG 7149 Ed. 4  NATO Message Catalogue APP-11(C)</para>
<para>Minimum set of messages supported by the AMN Core Network:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>INCIDENT REPORT (A078)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SARIR (J012)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>EVENTREP (J092)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>EODINCREP (J069)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>AIR SUPPORT REQUEST (F091)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>AIR TASKING ORDER (F058)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>AIRSPACE CONTROL ORDER (F011)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>PRESENCE REPORT (A009)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SITREP (J095)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>ENEMY CONTACT REP (A023)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>CASEVACREQ (A015)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>KILLBOX MESSAGE (F083)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>INCIDENTSPOTREP (J006)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>Emerging (from Dec 2012):
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>SALTATIC (A073)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>CASEVACREQ (A015)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>MEDEVAC MESSAGE (A012)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>FRIENDLY FORCE INFORMATION (J025) Note: This is the ADatP-3 representation of NFFI.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OPSITREP IRREGULAR ACTOR (A011)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>The following messages that are not compliant with STANAG 7149 Ed 4. could be accepted by the AMN Core Network:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>UXO IED REPORT 10LINER (UXOIED) (A075)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Joint Tactical Air Strike Request (JTAR) US DD Form 1972</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>ROZ Status / KILLBOX MESSAGE (F083)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>ENEMY CONTACT REP (A023)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SALUTE (Size, Activity, Location, Unit/Uniform, Time, Equipment)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>Change request proposals reflecting the requirements for those non-standard messages should be submitted within the configuration management process of ADatP-3 by those nations that are the primary originators of those messages.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>4: Exchanging information on Incident and Event information to support information exploitation.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>(A) NC3A JOCWatch Web Services Specification - Operational Incident Report (OIR) – 1.2, Sep 2011</para>
<para>Emerging (2014): Draft EVENTEXPLOITREP XML schema. Under development. Rationale: The coordination between NC3A and US on this work has been stalled due to lack of funding.</para>
<para>U.S.PM Battle Command SIGACT Schema<footnote><para>It should be noted that this schema is subject to release by the US Army</para></footnote>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para> </para>
		<para>This schema (EVENTEXPLOITREP) will be used to exchange rich and structured incident/ event information between C2 and Exploitation systems like JOCWatch and CIDNE. National capability developers are invited to contribute to the development of the final EVENTEXPLOITREP XML Schema<footnote><para>See http://tide.act.nato.int/tidepedia/index.php?title=TP_112:_Event_Exploitation_Reports_(EVENTEXPLOITREP)</para></footnote>.</para>
<para>This schema (SIGACT) is used via PASS, webservices and XMPP to exchange SIGACT information at Regional Command level and below.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>5: Exchange of digital Friendly Force Information such as positional tracking information amongst airborne and land-based tactical data systems and C2 systems.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>AC/322-D(2006)0066 Interim NFFI Standard for Interoperability of Force Tracking Systems</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>All positional information of friendly ground forces (e.g. ground forces of Troop Contributing Nations or commercial transport companies working in support of ISAF Forces) shall be as a minimum made available in a format that can be translated into the NFFI v1.3 format.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>6: Military Symbology interoperability</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>STANAG 2019, Ed.5:2008, Joint SymbologyAPP-6(B)<footnote><para>FMN: Emerging (2013): STANAG 2019, Ed.6:2011, Joint SmbologyAPP-6(C)</para></footnote></para>
                <para>MIL-STD-2525B (w/Change 2), Common Warfighting Symbology, Mar 2007<footnote><para>FMN: MIL-STD-2525C, Common Warfighting Symbology, Nov 2008</para></footnote></para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Note that the different standards are not fully compatible with each other and may require mapping services.  A translation service may need to be provided on the AMN Core Network (i.e. at the AMN Integration Core).</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	    <row>
              <entry>7: Digital exchange of semantically rich information about Battlespace Objects</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>MIP C2 Information Exchange data model (C2IEDM)  [note: STANAG 5523 was canceled]<footnote><para>FMN: Emerging (2014): MIP Joint Consultation, Command and Control Information Exchange Data Model v3.1.4</para></footnote></para>
<para>MIP Data Exchange Mechanism (DEM) Block 2<footnote><para>FMN: MIP Data Exchange Mechanism (DEM) Baseline 3.1</para></footnote></para>
<para>AMN MIP Implementation Profile (published in Annex A to NC3A AMN MIP Workshop Final Report). RD-3188</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>C2IEDM Business Rule F11.2 b is not applicable in the AMN scope. Implementations shall ensure that the use of CONTEXT-ASSOCIATION does not create circular references between CONTEXTs.</para>
<para>AMN members implementing MIP have agreed to use C2IEDM (MIP-Block 2) due to lack of fielded MIP-Block 3.1 systems by the Nations and the limited information exchange requirements of AMN Mission Threads (i.e. no requirement for Operational planning)<footnote><para>It should be noted that no further development is being pursued by the MIP community for MIP-Block 2. If AMN is to progress in line with direction of FMN, implementation needs to include MIP DEM Block 2.0 to 3.1 translation. If incorporated at the AMN Integration Core, translation of the information to other standards would also be possible.</para></footnote>.</para>
<para>Any addition or expansion of this data model or data dictionaries that is deemed to be of general interest shall be submitted as a change proposal within the con- figuration control process to be considered for inclusion in the next version of the specification</para>
<para>The AMN Integration Core uses Ground Tracks, Event Exploit Rep, Atom, KML, NVG and initial support for JC3IEDM as the basis for its canonical model schemas. Other Schemas of immediate interest to AMN include the US Publish and Subscribe Services (PASS) Schemas POSREP, SIGACT and GRAPHICS. Altogether allow the ingestion of Track, Unit, Object Associations (ORBAT/ TASKORG), Facilities, Control Features, Airspace Control measures, Routes<footnote><para>See also https://tide.act.nato.int/tidepedia/index.php?title=C2_Integration_Cononical_Modeling.</para></footnote> information and the transformation into formats that the AMN Integration Core canonical model support.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
		  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
	</sect4>
	<sect4>
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex L.1: Track Management Services</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex L.2: Information exchange via MIP</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Annex L.3: Information Exchange via the Integration Core</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	</sect4>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	<title>Biometric Services</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Biometrics services record measurable biological (anatomical and physiological) and behavioural characteristics of personnel for use by automated recognition systems. Biometric enabled systems typically provide distinct services for Data Collection and for Matching/Identification.</emphasis></para>	<sect4>
	<title>Standards</title>
	<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table 12 should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table12">
        <title>Table 12: Biometric Data and System Interoperability Protocols and Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Interchange of Fingerprint (Type 4 and 14) data</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000</para>
<para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007 Part 1</para>
<para>EBTS 1.2 (references ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000)</para>
<para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1 (references ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007)</para>
<para>DOD EBTS 2.0</para>
<para>ISO/IEC 19794-2:2005, part 2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2:Type 10 Facial</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>EFTS v7.0, EFTS v7.1</para>
<para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1</para>
<para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000, 1-2007 Part 1</para>
<para>EBTS   1.2   (references   EFTS v7.0)</para>
<para>DOD EBTS v2.0</para>
<para>ISO/IEC 19794-5 w/Amd1:2007, part 5</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3:Type 16 Iris</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000, 1-2007 Part 1</para>
<para>EBTS 1.2</para>
<para>ISO/IEC 19794-6</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4:Type 17 Iris</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007 Part 1</para>
<para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1 (ref AN- SI/NIST ITL 1-2007)</para>
<para>DOD EBTS v2.0</para>
<para>ISO/IEC 19794-6</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
	</sect4>
	<sect4>
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex M.1: [Nil]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	</sect4>
	</sect3>
	<sect2>
	<title>Communities of Interest Specific Services</title>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic"></emphasis>Community of Interest (COI)-Specific Services provide specific functionality as required by particular C3 user communities in support of NATO operations, exercises and routine activities. These COI-Specific Services were previously also referred to as "functional services" or "functional area services".</para>
	<para>For the purposes of this Volume and the AMN, Standards and Implementation Instructions are currently only required for:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Joint Intelligence, Surveillance and Reconnaissance (JISR or Joint ISR) Community of Interest (COI) Services.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	<sect3>
	<title>JISR COI Services</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Joint Intelligence, Surveillance and Reconnaissance (JISR or Joint ISR) Community of Interest (COI) Services provide unique computing and information services for intelligence support to operations. Intelligence Support is the set of military activities that are undertaken to receive commander's direction, proactively collect information, analyse it, produce useful predictive intelligence and disseminate it in a timely manner to those who need to know.</emphasis></para>
	<sect4>
	<title>Standards</title>
	<para>The NATO Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconnaissance Interoperability Architecture (NIIA) [AEDP-2, Ed.1:2005] provides the basis for the technical aspects of an architecture that provides interoperability between NATO nations' ISR systems. AEDP-2 provides the technical and management guidance for implementing the NIIA in ISR systems. These common standards are listed Table 13. These should be adhered to if federated services are to be achieved.</para>
      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table13">
        <title>Table 13: JISR Interoperability Protocols and Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Storing and exchanging of images and associated data</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>STANAG 4545, Ed. Amendment 1:2000, NATO Secondary Imagery Format (NSIF)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>AEDP-4, Ed. 1, NATO Secondary Imagery Format Implementation Guide, 15 Jun 07, NU</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2:Providing a standard software interface for searching and retrieving for ISR products.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>NATO Standard ISR Library Interface (NSILI)</para>
<para>Mandatory:  STANAG 4559, Ed. 3:2010 (starting Dec 2011).</para>
<para>Fading:  STANAG  4559,  Ed. 2:2007 (beginning July 2011)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>AEDP-5, Ed. 1, NATO Standard Imagery Library Interface Implementation Guide, TBS, NU</para>
<para>STANAG 4559, Ed.2 and Ed.3 are NOT compatible with each other (No backwards compatibility). The NATO provided CSD on the AMN Core network only implements Ed.3:2010).</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3:Exchange of ground moving target indicator radar data</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>NATO Ground Moving Target Indicator (GMTI) Format</para>
<para>Mandatory: STANAG 4607, Ed. 2:2007</para>
<para>Emerging: STANAG 4607, Ed.3:2010</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>AEDP-7, Ed. 1, NATO Ground Moving Target Indication (GMTI) Format Implementation Guide, TBS, NU</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4:Provision of common methods for exchanging of Motion Imagery (MI)across systems</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>NATO Digital Motion Imagery Standard</para>
<para>Mandatory: STANAG 4609, Ed. 2:2007</para>
<para>Emerging: STANAG 4609, Ed. 3:2009</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>AEDP-8, Ed. 2, Implementation Guide For STANAG 4609NDMI , June 2007, NU</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5:Exchange of unstructured data (documents, jpeg imagery)</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>IPIWIG V4 Metadata Specification:2009, Intelligence Projects Integration Working Group (IPIWG), Definition of metadata for unstructured Intelligence.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6: Providing a standard software interface for ex changing information about sensor planning, including information about capabilities of sensors, tasking of a sensors and status of sensor-planning requests.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Emerging: OGC 09-000: OGC Sensor Planning Service Implementation Standard v2.0, Mar 2011</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>For the AMN, Sensor Planning Service implementations shall adhere to the SOAP binding as defined in OGC 09-000.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
	</sect4>
	<sect4>
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex N.1: JISR Interoperability via CSD</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	</sect4>
	</sect3>
	</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	<title>User Facing Capabilities</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">User-Facing Capabilities express the requirements for the interaction between end users and all CIS Capabilities, in order to process Information Products in support of Business Processes. User-Facing Capabilities incorporate the User Appliances, as well as the User Applications that run on those appliances.</emphasis></para>
	<para>For the purposes of this Volume, only the standards for User Applications need to be cited.</para>
	<sect2>
	<title>User Applications</title>
	<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">User Applications, also known as application software, software applications, applications or apps, are computer software components designed to help a user perform singular or multiple related tasks and provide the logical interface between human and automated activities.</emphasis></para>
	<sect3>
	<title>Standards</title>
	<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table 14 should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table14">
        <title>Table 14: User Application Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Displaying content within web browsers.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>W3C Hypertext Markup Language HTML 4.0.1</para>
<para>W3C Extensible Hypertext Markup Language XHTML 1.0</para>
<para>W3C Cascading Style Sheets CSS 2.0</para>
<para>Browser plug-ins are not covered by a single specification.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>Applications must support the following browsers: Microsoft Internet Explorer v9.0 and newer, and Mozilla Firefox 12.0 and newer. When a supported browser is not true to the standard, choose to support the browser.</para>
<para>Some organizations or end-user devices do not allow the use of proprietary extensions such as Adobe Flash or Microsoft Silverlight. Those technologies shall be avoided.  Implementers should use open standard based solutions (HTML5 / CSS3) instead.</para>
<para>Some AMN members do not allow the use of ActiveX controls in the browser. Browser plug-ins will need to be approved by AMN Change Advisory Board (CAB).</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: Visualize common operational symbology within C4ISR systems in order to convey information about objects in the battlespace.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>STANAG 2019, Ed.5:2008, Joint SmbologyAPP-6(B)<footnote><para>FMN: Emerging (2013): STANAG 2019, Ed.6:2011, Joint SmbologyAPP-6(C)</para></footnote></para>
<para>MIL-STD-2525B (w/Change 2), Common Warfighting Symbology, Mar 2007<footnote><para>FMN: MIL-STD-2525C, Common Warfighting Symbology, Nov 2008</para></footnote></para>
<para>TIDE Transformational Baseline Vers. 3.0 NATO Vector Graphics (NVG)</para>
<para>Mandatory: (NVG 1.5)<footnote><para>FMN: Emerging (2014): (NVG) v2.0</para></footnote></para>
<para>Fading (Dec 2011): NVG 1.4</para>
<para>Retired: NVG 0.3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>All presentation service shall render tracks, tactical graphics, and MOOTW objects using this standard except in the case where the object being rendered is not covered in the standard. In these exceptional cases, additional symbols shall be defined as extensions of existing symbol standards and must be backwards compatible. These extensions shall be submitted as a request for change within the configuration management process to be considered for inclusion in the next version of the specification.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3:Reliable messaging over XMPP</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>XMPP Clients must implement the following XMPP Extension Protocols (XEP).</para>
<para>XEP-0184 - Message Delivery Receipts (whereby the sender of a message can request notification that it has been received by the intended recipient).</para>
<para>XEP 0202 - Entity Time (for communicating the local time of an entity)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>All XMPP Chat Clients used on the AMN shall implement these two protocol extensions {this section will be enhanced in the next version based on a detailed recently conducted requirements analysis}.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4:Collaborative generation of spreadsheets, charts, presentations and word processing documents</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>ECMA-376, Ed. 1: 2006 Office Open XML</para>
<para>Emerging (2013): Document description and processing languages ISO/IEC 29500:2008 (transitional).</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5:Document exchange, storage and archiving</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>ISO 19005-1:2005 - Document management -Electronic document file format for long-term preservation –Part 1: Use of PDF 1.4 (PDF/A-1)</para>
<para>Emerging (2014): ISO 19005: Document management -- Electronic document file format for long-term preservation -- Part 2: Use of ISO 32000-1 (PDF/A-2)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>See Operational Record Retention Schedule and AMN JMEI Exit Instructions (Vol3) for further details.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
	</sect3>
	<sect3>
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex O.1: [Nil]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	</sect3>
	</sect2>

	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	<title>Service Management and Control</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic">Service Management and Control (SMC) provides a collection of capabilities to coherently manage components in a federated service-enabled information technology infrastructure. SMC tools enable service providers to provide the desired quality of service as specified by the customer. In a federated environment such as the AMN, utilizing common process and data is a critical enabler to management of the network.</emphasis></para>
	<sect2>
	<title>Standards</title>
	<para>To provide federated services the standards listed in Table 15 should be adhered to.</para>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-table15">
        <title>Table 15: Service Management and Control Interoperability Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1: Provide Service Management within a FMN instance.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Mandatory: ITIL 2011 update / ISO/IEC 20000</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>See also AMN Service Management Framework CONOPS</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2: Provide the Control (Governance) required to efficiently and effectively control an  FMN instance.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Mandatory: Control Objectives for Information and related Technology (COBIT 5).</para>
<para>Optional: Frameworx (Business Process Framework (eTOM)) as required for Business Processes especially Customer Relationship Management activities</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>COBIT is based on established frameworks, such as the Software Engineering Institute’s Capability Maturity Model, ISO
9000, ITIL, and ISO 17799 (standard security framework, now ISO 27001).
</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3: Network management</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Simple Network Management Protocol Version 3 (SNMPv3)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4: SOA Platform SMC Services</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Web Services for Management:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>WS-Management Specification Version 1.0.0 (DSP0226), dated: 12 Feb 2008, Distributed Management Task Force</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>WS-Management CIM Binding Specification Version 1.0.0 (DSP0227), dated: 19 June 2009, Distributed Management Task Force</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>WS-Management provides a common way for systems to access and exchange management information across the IT infrastructure.</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5: Represent and share Configuration Items and details about the important attributes and relationships between them.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>CIM Schema version 2.29.0, dated 3 May 2011, Distributed Management Task Force</para>
<para>CMDB Federation Specification V1.0.1, dated 22 Apr 2010, Distributed Management Task Force
</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para></para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	<title>Implementation</title>
	<para>The following Annexes provide guidance on implementing services:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Annex O.1: Federation of TCN and NATO SMC Systems [TBC]</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
	</sect2>

	</sect1>

	<sect1>
	<title>Abbreviations</title>

	</sect1>


<!--
*****************************************************************
                   OLD TEXT FOLLOWS

Reuse this code as needed

<para><emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>: <emphasis role="italic"></emphasis></para>

<footnote><para></para></footnote>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para></para></listitem>
<listitem><para></para></listitem>
<listitem><para></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

      <table frame="all" id="v3t-id-string">
        <title>Title string</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:repeating purpose para</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>repeating Standard para</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>repeating Guidance para</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
	  </tbody>
         </tgroup>
	</table>

*****************************************************************  
-->
  
      
    <sect1>
      <title>References</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>[1] MC 245 Statement of Military Requirement for Interoperability
            between Automated Data Systems.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>[2] Allied Data Publication 34 (ADatP-34) NATO Interoperability 
            Standards and Profiles (NISP) STANAG 5524.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>[3] NATO C3 System Interoperability Policy, AC/322-D(2004)0039 dated 
            13 Sep 2004.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>[4] NATO C3 System Interoperability Directive, AC/322-D(2004)0040 
            dated 13 Sep 2004.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>  
</appendix>
