<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 3 - FMN SPIRAL 1.1 PROFILE
*****************************************************************  
-->

<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v3-fmn-spiral-1">
  <title>Federated Mission Networking Spiral 1.1 Standards Profile</title>
     <figure id="f3-fmn-logo">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/FMN_Logo_Color_With_Text_Side.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        </figure>

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This document defines the Standards Profile for Federated
    Mission Networking (FMN) Spiral 1. FMN Standards Profiles provide
    a suite of interoperability standards and other standardized
    profiles for interoperability of selected community of interest
    services, core services and communications services in a
    federation of mission networks. It places the required
    interoperability requirements, standards and specifications in
    context for FMN Affiliates.</para>
    
    <para>FMN Standards Profiles are generic specifications at a
    logical level. They allow for independent national technical
    service implementations, without the loss of essential
    interoperability aspects.</para>
    
    <para>FMN is founded on a service-oriented approach. The
    interoperability standards applicable to these services are
    identified and specified in line with the NATO C3 Taxonomy.</para>
<sect2>
<title>Disclaimer</title>
<para>The information in this document is derived from the Enterprise Mapping (EM) Wiki, a data analysis and enterprise architecture tool based on Semantic MediaWiki technology and hosted by the Technology and Human Factors (THF) Branch at Headquarters Supreme Allied Commander Transformation (HQ SACT).</para>
<para>This document is generated overnight in an automated process and stamped with a date on the cover page. Hence, a baselined version is not exclusively identified by a version marking and the date on the cover must be used for version control.</para>
</sect2>
    
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>The diagram below presents an overview of the profile structure.</para>

      <figure id="f3-fmn-profiles">
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/fmn-profile-structure.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        </figure>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
<title>FMN Spiral 1 Profile</title>  
<sect2>
  <title>Scope</title>

    <para>The Federated Mission Networking (FMN) Spiral 1 standards profile defines interface standards for the services that are required to deploy a Mission Network Elements (FMN capability option A). Mission Network Extensions (option B) and Hosted Users (option C) may not meet these minimum service and service interoperability requirements. Connectivity and service provision throughout the federation is regulated by hosting agreements between participants.</para>
    
   <para>FMN Spiral 1 refers to an FMN maturity level in which separate physical infrastructures exist per mission and per security classification level. This spiral is an evolution of the fielded baseline of the Afghanistan Mission Network (AMN). Notably, biometrics interoperability standards were removed and the network architecture has changed from a hub-and-spoke to a
meshed concept.</para>

   <para>Mission Network Extensions must be provided with their local area networks (including IP management) within the physical and cyber security boundaries of the hosting Mission Network Element. The services must function in a network environment that contains firewalls and various routing and filtering schemes; therefore, developers must use standards and well-known port specifications wherever possible, and document non-standard configurations as part of their service interface.</para>

  </sect2> 

  <sect2>
    <title>Interoperability</title>

    <para>In the context of Federated Mission Networking, the purpose of standardization is to enable interoperability in a multi-vendor, multi-network, multi-service environment. Technical interoperability must be an irrefutable and inseparable element in capability development and system implementation - without it, it is not possible to realize connections and service deliveries across the federation and hence, information sharing will not be achieved.</para>

    <para>Within NATO, interoperability is defined as "the ability to act together coherently, effectively and efficiently to achieve allied tactical, operational and strategic objectives". In the context of information exchange, interoperability means that a system, unit or forces of any service, nation can transmit data to and receive data from any other system, unit or forces of any service
or nation, and use the exchanged data to operate effectively together.</para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2>
    <title>Standards and Profiles</title>
    
    <para>For successful Federated Mission Networking, technical
    interface standards are critical enablers that have to be
    collectively followed and for which conformity by all
    participating members is important.</para>

    <para>Standards are aggregated in profiles. A standards profile is
    a set of standards for a particular purpose, covering certain
    services in the C3 taxonomy, with a guidance on implementation
    when and where needed. As profiles serve a particular purpose,
    they can be used in different environments, and therefore, they
    are not specific to a single overarching operational or technical
    concept. Profiles for Federated Mission Networking may and will be
    reused in other profiles.</para>

    <para>Generally, the scope of a profile in the EM Wiki is limited:
    it will focus on only a few services and a limited scope of
    functionality. Therefore, a full profile with a wider scope
    (ranging to an environment, a system or a concept) will have to
    consist of a selection of profiles, that together cover the full
    capability of that overarching profile. For organization of these
    standards and profiles, the overarching profile - in this case the
    FMN Spiral 1 Profile - is broken down in a hierarchical tree that
    forms a number of functional branches, ending in the leaves that
    are the profiles which contain the actual assignments of standards
    and their implementation guidance.</para>

    <para>In the profiles, interoperability standards fall into four
    obligation categories:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Mandatory - Mandatory interoperability standards must be met to enable Federated Mission Networking</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Conditional - Conditional interoperability standards must be present under certain specific circumstances</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Recommended - Recommended interoperability standards may be excluded for valid reasons in particular circumstances, but the full implications must be understood and carefully weighed</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Optional - Optional interoperability standards are truly optional</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Sources</title>
    
    <para>The interoperability standards profile in this document is derived from standards that are maintained by a selection of
standardization organizations and conformity and interoperability resources. Some of these are included in the NATO
Interoperability Standards and Profiles. Furthermore, standards are used from:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>International Organization for Standardization (ISO) standards</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>International Electrotechnical Commission (IEC) standards</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>International Telecommunication Union (ITU) Radiocommunication (R) Recommendations</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>International Telecommunication Union (ITU) Telecommunication (T) Recommendations</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) Requests for Comments (RFC)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) Recommendations</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Multilateral Interoperability Programme (MIP) standards</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Secure Communications Interoperability Profiles (SCIP)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP) Extension Protocols (XEP)</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Federated Communications and Networking Profile</title>

    <para>The Federated Communications and Networking Profile arranges
    standards profiles for the facilitation of the platform and
    communications infrastructure of federated mission
    networks.</para>

    <sect3>
       <title>Federated Communications Profile</title>

       <para>The Federated Communications Profile arranges standards profiles for the addressing, routing, forwarding, quality and
       security of IP traffic over federated mission networks.</para>
       
      <?dbmerge profile="fmn-fed-com"?>

    </sect3>


    <sect3>
      <title>Federated Networking Profile</title>

      <para>The Federated Networking Profile arranges standards
      profiles for the establish network logic above the
      communications layer of federated mission networks.</para>

      <?dbmerge profile="fmn-fed-net"?>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
    <title>Federated Human-to-Human Communications Profile</title>

    <para>The Federated Human-to-Human Communications Profile arranges
    standards profiles for the facilitation of information sharing and
    exchange on user platforms.</para>

    <sect3>
      <title>Federated Unified Collaboration Profile</title>

      <para>The Federated Unified Collaboration Profile arranges
      standards profiles for a range of interoperable collaboration
      capabilities to support real-time situational updates to
      time-critical planning activities between coalition partners,
      communities of interest and other participants. Levels of
      collaboration include awareness, shared information,
      coordination and joint product development.</para>

      <?dbmerge profile="fmn-uni-collab"?>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Federated Information Management Profile</title>

      <para>The Federated Information Management Profile arranges standards profiles for the handling of information throughout its
life-cycle and the support of capabilities to organize, store and retrieve information through services and managed processes,
governed by policies, directives, standards, profiles and guidelines.</para>

      <?dbmerge profile="fmn-fed-inf-mgnt"?>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Federated Web Hosting Profile</title>
      <para>The Federated Web Hosting Profile arranges standards profiles for the facilitation of web-based services in a loosely coupled
environment, where flexible and agile service orchestration is a requirement on the basis of a Service Oriented Architecture
(SOA).</para>
      <?dbmerge profile="fmn-fed-web-host"?>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  </sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Related Information</title>
<sect2>
<title>Standards</title>
<para>See https://tide.act.nato.int/tidepedia/index.php/FMN_Spiral_Specification_1.1</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
  
</appendix>
