<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 4 - A N N E X - D
*****************************************************************  
-->

<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v4-d">
    <title>The Afghanistan Mission Network (AMN) Profile of NATO Interoperability
      Standards</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Purpose</title>

    <para>NATO, through its interoperability directive, has recognized that widespread 
    interoperability is a key component in achieving effective and efficient operations.
    In many of the operations world-wide in which NATO nations are engaged, they 
    participate together with a wide variety of other organizations on the ground.
    Such organizations include coalition partners from non-NATO nations, Non-Governmental
    Organization (NGOs - e.g. Aid Agencies) and industrial partners. The NATO Interoperability 
    Standards and Profile (NISP) provides the necessary guidance and technical components
    to support project implementations and transition to NATO Network Enabled Capability
    (NNEC).</para>

<para>The figure below characterizes the information environment and various scenarios that exist for exchanging operational information.  This environment, although rich in participation and basic connectivity, lacks fully meshed interoperability at the services layer.  This diagram represents the AMN environment, and the starting point for future mission network for NATO-led operations.  It is presumed for the purposes of this document that the AMN Profile will only address capabilities between the AMN Core and national AMN extensions.</para>

<figure id="v4amnf1" float="0">
          <title>AMN Information Environment</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../figures/AMN-info-env.svg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        

    <para>The purpose of this document is to define an Interoperability Standards 
    Profile to support the Afghanistan Mission Network (AMN) and transition from 
    today's legacy systems to NNEC by defining a useful level of interoperability.</para>
    
    <para>This document will also serve as a resource for NATO C4ISR
    planners, to be used as a guide in achieving interoperability
    between NATO nations, coalition partners and NATO provided
    capabilities.  The AMN Profile is for use throughout the complete
    lifecycle of the ISAF mission.  The AMN Profile will enable Net
    Centric operations by enhancing collaboration across the entire
    operational environment across all levels of command.  Subsequent
    NATO led missions will benefit from the modular nature of the AMN
    Profile, which will allow for maximum reuse of established
    capabilities, while accommodating unique requirements and
    technology improvements.</para>
<para>Coalition Interoperability Assurance and Validation (CIAV) supports the AMN change management process by assessing proposed changes on the Coalition Test and Evaluation Environment (CTE2) replication of the AMN before they are deployed to the operational network.  In the CIAV, all functionalities and interactions can be assured before the upgrades are implemented.</para>

<para>Additional benefits to deployment and sustained operations include:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Speed of execution of operations,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Richer information environment,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>More dynamic information exchange between all members of the network,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Speedier standup of an NATO-led operation,</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Reach-back to feature rich information enterprise(s), and</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Elimination of hierarchical information flow.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Participating nations are encouraged to use this document as part of the planning process for coordination and establishment of connectivity and interoperability with respect to joint NATO-led operations.
</para>
    
    <para>This profile will be used in the implementation of NATO Common Funded Systems.
    Nations participating in AMN agree to use this profile at Network Interconnection 
    Points (NIPs) and at other Service Interoperability Points as applicable.</para>

	<para>Nations participationg in the AMN have agreed to comply with the AMN joining instructions. This profile is a technical document that changes more frequently than the joining instructions.</para>
    
    <para>NNEC Services must be able to function in a network environment containing
    firewalls and various routing and filtering schemes; therefore, developers must
    use standard and well-known ports wherever possible, and document non-standard
    ports as part of their service interface. Service developers must assume network
    behavior and performance consistent with the existing limits of these networks,
    taking bandwidth limitations and potentially unreliable networks into account.</para>
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Change Management</title>
    
    <para>Applying existing NATO standards or - in those areas where NATO STANAGS
    do not yet exist - International Standards are key for achieving interoperability
    in a federated environment. The dynamic nature of ISAF operations results in
    unforeseen information exchange requirements within and across ISAF. This might
    require the development and design of new data and metadata exchange formats 
    which are not part of current STANAGs and/or Standards. Those ad-hoc formats
    shall be developed in-line with existing NATO policies and guidelines so that
    they can be quickly transformed into standards (e.g. STANAGS) by the appropriate 
    NATO Bodies based on the NATO Bi-SC Data Strategy, the NATO NNEC Data Strategy, 
    and when appropriate, based on the APP-15 process.The AMN Profile is being maintained
    by the AMN Architecture Working Group; it is a living document and is expected 
    to be updated every six months.</para>
    
    <para>ADatP-34 defines four stages within the life-cycle of a standard: emerging,
    mandatory, fading and retired; in those situations where multiple stages are 
    mentioned the AMN Profile recommends dates by which the transition to the next
    stage is to be completed by all AMN members. If a nation decides to implement
    emerging standards it is her responsibility to maintain backwards compatibility
    to the mandatory standard.</para>
    
    <para>Any discrepancies discovered between different elements of this Profile,
    shall be resolved through a change proposal prepared by the responsible NATO
    body or an AMN member nation.</para>
    
    <para>AMN Profile change requests can only be submitted by NATO civil or military
    bodies or AMN member nations.</para>
    
    <para>The AMN Architecture Working Group will review updates to
    ADatP-34, the ISAF Baseline Architecture and AMN Profile change
    proposals and if required will produce a new version of the AMN
    Profile. The AMN profile of the NISP is reviewed by the AMN
    Architecture Working Group (AWG) on a quarterly basis and requests
    for formal adoption by the IP CaT are made by the AWG on a six
    monthly basis.</para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Service Management and Control (SMC) Processes</title>
    
      <table frame="all" id="v4t-SMC-Processes">
        <title>SMC Processes</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Provide Service Management within the AMN Core and between the Core and the TCN/Partners.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Mandatory: ITIL 2011 update /ISO/IEC 20000</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>See also AMN SMF CONOPS</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>SMC Governance</title>
    
      <table frame="all" id="v4t-SMC-Governance">
        <title>SMC Governance</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Provide the Control (Governance) required to efficiently and effectively control the AMN.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Mandatory: Control Objectives for Information and related Technology (COBIT 5).</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
		<para>COBIT is based on established frameworks, such as the Software Engineering Institute’s Capability Maturity Model,ISO 9000, ITIL, and ISO 17799 (standard security framework, now ISO 27001).</para>
	      </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>SMC Configuration Management Database (CMDB)</title>
    
      <table frame="all" id="v4t-SMC-CMDB">
        <title>SMC CMDB</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Represent and share Configuration Items and details about the important attributes and relationships between them.</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Emerging Dec 2013: CIM Schema version 2.29.0, dated 3 May 2011, Distributed Management Task Force</para>
                <para>Emerging Dec 2013: CMDB Federation Specification V1.0.1, dated 22 Apr 2010, Distributed Management Task Force</para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Communication and Network Services Standards</title>
    
      <table frame="all" id="v4t-Comms-andNetwork-Stds">
        <title>Communication and Network Services Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Basic connectivity between technical services.</entry>
              <entry>Internet Protocol (IETF Standard 5, September 1981. RFCs 
                791/950/919/922/792/1112)
                <para>Transmission Control Protocol (IETF Standard 7, RFC 793:1981
                  updated by 3168:2001)</para>
                <para>Internet Protocol, Version 6 (IPv6) (IETF RFC 2460:1998)</para>
                <para>Domain Name System (IETF Standard 13, RFC 1034/RFC 1035:1987)
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>IP networking. Accommodate both IPv4 and IPv6 addressing and
                Network Address Translation. Utilize Quality of Service capabilities
                of the network.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2:Connectivity between AMN Core network and TCN networks</entry>
              <entry>IEEE 802.3z Gigabit Ethernet (GbE)<para>
Border Gateway Protocol V4 (IET RFC 1771, March 1995)</para><para>
BGP Communities Attribute (IETF RFC 1997, August 1996)</para><para>
Multicast Source Discovery Protocol (MSDP) (IETF RFC 3618, October 2003)</para><para>
Protocol Independent Multicast - Sparse Mode (PIM-SM) (IETF RFC 4601, August 2006)</para></entry>
              <entry>Detailed Interface Control Document for "Connection Between CISAF network and TCN networks" (Thales Doc: F0057/62543313/558/-/I/EN), dated 24 Feb 2012
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3:Service transport protocol</entry>
              <entry>Hypertext Transfer Protocol - HTTP 1.1 (RFC 2616:1999)</entry>
              <entry>HTTP shall be used as the transport protocol for information 
                without 'need-to-know' caveats between all service providers and 
                consumers.
                <para>HTTPS shall be used as the transport protocol between all 
                  service providers and consumers to ensure confidentiality requirements.
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4:Provide communications security over the network above the 
                Transport Layer</entry>
              <entry>Mandatory: Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2 
                (RFC 5246:2008)
                <para>Fading (until Dec 2011): Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol
                  Version 1.0 (RFC 2246:1999)</para>
                <para>Retired: Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) Protocol, Version 3.0, 18 
                  Nov 1996</para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5:Voice communication</entry>
              <entry>VoIP: SIP RFC 3261
                <para>- Audio data compression Codec ITU-T Recommendation G.729 (01/07)
                  - The use of G.729 may require a license fee and/or royalty fee
                  - DiffServ,PHB and DSCP defined by IETF RFC 2474</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>- ITU-T G.Imp729 (11/09)
                <para>- Interval between Voice packets 40ms</para>
                <para>- RTP protocol ports 16384 and/or 16385</para>
                <para>- Detailed Interface Control Document for "Voice over Secure IP 
                  (VoSIP) Network Service" (Thales Doc: F0057/61935771/558/ICD VOSIP/A/EN; 
                  NATO RESTRICTED)</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6:Secure Network management</entry>
              <entry>Simple Network Management Protocol Version 3 (SNMPv3)</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>7:Facilitate the access and authorization between AMN users</entry>
              <entry>Directory service: LDAPv3, RFC 4510
                <para>Authentication: Kerberos version 5, RFC 1510</para></entry>
              <entry>The AMN OPT has identified three options available to a nation
                when joining their national network extension to the AMN:
                <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
                  <listitem><para>Join the ISAF SECRET AD forest on AMN Core</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Join the AD forest of an existing AMN TCN</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Create own AD forest for the new AMN TCN</para></listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>(Option 1 and 2 should be considered before option 3. Ref: 
                  AMN Systems engineering CONOPS dated 29 April 10).</para>
                <para>Whilst LDAP is a vendor independent standard, in practice 
                  Active Directory (AD) is the product providing directory services
                  on the AMN. AD provides additional services aside from LDAP like 
                  functionality.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>8:Time synchronisation on the AMN</entry>
              <entry>Mandatory: Network Time Protocol version 3 (NTPv3), dated March 1992. RFC 1305</entry>
              <entry>The W32Time service on all Windows DCs on the AMN Core is synchronizing time through the Domain hierarchy (NT5DS type).<para>POC: NCIA / Pierre Calvez</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>9:Video Collaboration</entry>
              <entry>Mandatory: Signalling - H.323, Audio - G.722.1c and Video - H.263</entry>
              <entry>AMN VTC over IP is based on a QoS-Enabled Network Infrastructure(QENI) using Diffserve. AMN Wide allowed interconnections are A) Peer to Peer, B) Peer to MCU and C) Peer to MCU to MCU to Peer<para>POC: NCIA / Pierre Calvez</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Infrastructure and Core Enterprise Services Standards</title>
    
      <table frame="all" id="v4t-CES-Stds">
        <title>Infrastructure and Core Enterprise Services Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:electronic mail (e-mail) transmission</entry>
              <entry>SMTP (RFC 1870:1995, 2821:2001), Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP)
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2:Publishing information including text, multimedia, hyperlink 
                features, scripting languages and style sheets on the network</entry>
              <entry>HTML 4.01(RFC2854:2000), HyperText Markup Language (HTML), W3C</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3:Providing a common style sheet language for describing presentation 
                semantics (that is, the look and formatting) of documents written
                in markup languages like HTML.</entry>
              <entry>Mandatory: Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), Level 2 revision 1 
                (CSS 2.1), W3C Recommendation, Sep 2009.
                <para>Emerging : Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), Level 3(CSS 2)</para>
                <para>Fading (until Dec 2011): CSS Level 1, Jan 1999.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4:Enable free text real time communication in combination with
                structured messages (data payload).</entry>
              <entry>IETF RFC 6120 XMPP CORE covering XML streams, SASL, TLS, stanza
                semantics and RFC 6121 extensions for basic instant messaging and 
                presence.
                <para>The following XMPP Extension Protocols shall be supported:</para>
                <para>XEP-0004: Data Forms</para>
                <para>XEP-0012: Last Activity</para>
                <para>XEP-0013: Flexible offline message retrieval</para>
                <para>XEP-0030: Service Discovery</para>
                <para>XEP-0045: Multi User Chat</para>
                <para>XEP-0060: Publish and Subscribe</para>
                <para>XEP-0082: XMPP Date and Time Profiles</para>
                <para>XEP-0128: Service Discovery Extensions</para>
                <para>XEP-0138: Stream Compression</para>
                <para>XEP-0033: Extended Stanza Addressing and multiple group chat service (emerging by Nov 11)</para>
                <para>XEP-0079: Advanced Message Processing to implement time-to-live (TTL) and reliability-in-delivery features or (emerging by Nov 11)</para>
                <para>XEP-0198: Stream Management for active management of an XML stream between two XMPP entities, including features for stanza acknowledgements and stream resumption. (emerging by Nov 11)</para>
		<para>The following XMPP Extension Protocols are optional:</para>
		<para>Emerging (Jan 2013): XEP-0106: JID Escaping</para>
		<para>Emerging (Jan 2013): XEP-0115: Entity Capabilities</para>
		<para>Emerging (Jan 2013): XEP-0122: Data Forms Validation</para>
		<para>Emerging (Jan 2013): XEP-0199: XMPP Ping</para>
		<para>Emerging (Jan 2013): XEP-0249: Direct MUC Invitation</para>
		<para>Emerging (Jan 2013): XEP-0289: Federated MUC</para>
		<para>Emerging (Jan 2013): XEP-0311: Fast Reconnect</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>RFC 6120 supersedes RFC 3920 and RFC 6121 XMPP IM supersedes
                RFC 3921
                <para>Developers are also advised to consult the following RFCs:
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem><para>RFC 6122 XMPP ADDR XMPP address format</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>RFC 3923 XMPP E2E End-to-end signing and object encryption for XMPP</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>RFC 4854 XMPP URN A Uniform Resource Name (URN) tree for use in XMPP extensions</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>RFC 4979 XMPP ENUM IANA registration of an Enumservice (see RFC 3761) for XMPP</para></listitem>
                    <listitem><para>RFC 5122 XMPP URI A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) scheme for XMPP (this specification corrects several errors in RFC 4622)</para></listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5:Providing web content or web feeds for syndication to web sites
                as well as directly to user agents.</entry>
              <entry>Mandatory: Really Simple Syndication (RSS) 2.0 Specification
                <para>Emerging (by Dec 2011): Atom 1.0: Atom syndication format, 
                  Dec 2005 (RFC 4287) and Atom Publishing Protocol , Oct 2007 (RFC 5023)
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6:Encoding of location as part of a web feeds</entry>
              <entry>Mandatory: GeoRSS Simple encoding.
                <para>Where GeoRSS Simple is not appropriate the OGC GeoRSS Geography 
                  Markup Language (GML) Application Profile shall be used</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>GeoRSS extensions should be used to describe location aspects
                within ATOM and RSS feeds.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>7:Message Security for web services</entry>
              <entry>WS-Security: SOAP Message Security 1.1
                <para>XML Encryption Syntax and Processing  (dtd. 10 December 2002)</para>
                <para>XML Signature Syntax and Processing 1.0 (Second Edition)</para>
		<para>WS-I Basic Security profile 1.1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Specifies how integrity and confidentiality can be enforced on 
                messages and allows the communication of various security token formats, 
                such as SAML, Kerberos, and X.509v3. Its main focus is the use of XML 
                Signature and XML Encryption to provide end-to-end security.
                <para>Specifies a process for encrypting data and representing the 
                  result in XML. Referenced by WS-Security specification.</para>
                <para>Specifies XML digital signature processing rules and syntax.
                  Referenced by WS-Security specification.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>8:Security token format</entry>
              <entry>SAML 2.0
                <para>Web Services Security: SAML Token Profile 1.1 </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Provides XML-based syntax to describe uses security tokens containing 
                assertions to pass information about a principal (usually an end-user) 
                between an identity provider and a web service.
                <para>Describes how to use SAML security tokens with WS-Security 
                  specification.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>9:Security token issuing</entry>
              <entry>WS-Trust 1.4
                <para>WS-Federation 1.1</para>
                <para>WS-Policy 1.5</para>
                <para>And WS-Security Policy 1.3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Uses WS-Security base mechanisms and defines additional primitives 
                and extensions for security token exchange to enable the issuance and 
                dissemination of credentials within different trust domains.
                <para>Extends WS-Trust to allow federation of different security realms.</para>
                <para>Used to describe what aspects of the federation framework are  
                  required/supported by federation participants and that this information 
                  is used to determine the appropriate communication options.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>9:General definition of data structure and the operations on data 
                stored in that structure</entry>
              <entry>SQL 3 (ISO/IEC 9075(-1 to - 14):2003), Definition of data structure 
                and the operations on data stored in that structure.</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>10:Public Key Infrastructure to support single sign-on</entry>
              <entry>Version 3 public-key certificates and Version 2 CRLs in accordance
                with ITU-T X.509v3
                <para>NATO Public Key Infrastructure (NPKI) Certificate Policy (CertP)
                  Rev2, AC/322-D(2004)0024REV2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    
      <para>Within the AMN architecture, new services must be designed around the 
        Request/Response, Publish/Subscribe, or Message Queue patterns. For the AMN 
        architecture, developers must:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>provide read or read/write services as appropriate
            </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>implement either synchronous or asynchronous services
            </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>include authentication as part of their service</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem><para>support dynamic bindings</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>The challenge is in re-using the existing data standards developed 
        under ADatP-3 in this new service environment.</para>
        
      <table frame="all" id="v4t-CES-Stds2">
        <title>Infrastructure and Core Enterprise Services Standards, Part 2</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Identification and addressing of objects on the network.</entry>
              <entry>RFC 1738, Uniform Resource Locators (URL), 20 December 1994
                RFC 2396, Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI), Generic Syntax, August 
                1998 (updates RFC 1738)
              </entry>
              <entry>Namespaces within XML documents shall use unique URLs or URIs
                for the namespace designation.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2:General formatting of information for sharing or exchange.</entry>
              <entry>Extensible Markup Language (XML), v1.0 3rd Edition XML Schema:
                Structures 1.0 XML Schema: Data types 1.0 XML Namespaces: W3C 
                (REC-xml-names-19990114)</entry>
              <entry>XML is required for data exchange to satisfy those IERs within
                the AMN that are not addressed by a specific information exchange 
                standard. XML Schemas and namespaces are required for all XML documents.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3:Transforming XML documents into other XML documents</entry>
              <entry><para>XSL Translation (XSLT 1.0)</para>
<para>Emerging March 2013: XSL Transformation (XSLT) 2.0</para></entry>
              <entry>Developer best practice for the translation of XML based documents 
                into other formats or schemas.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4:Specific, practical guidance for the development of web services,
                through constraints and clarifications to their base specifications.</entry>
              <entry>Web Services Interoperability Organization (WS-I) Basic Profile 
                1.1, Final Material, August 24, 2004; Note that this profile references
                several other standards associated with web services:
                <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
                  <listitem><para>SOAP, WSDL, UDDI</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Hypertext Transfer Protocol, HTTP v1.1</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>RFC2246 TLS Protocol v1.0</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>RFC2560, x.509 Public Key Infrastructure Certificate</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Emerging (2013):WS-I Basic Profile 1.2</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Emerging (2014):WS-I Basic Profile 2.0</para></listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>Conformance to this standards-set is required for all SOAP based
                services although WS-I Basic Profile mandates the use of UDDI 2.0 and TLS 1.0, the AMN Profile mandates TLS 1.2 and UDDI 3.0.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5:Configuration management of structured data standards, service 
                descriptions and other structured metadata.</entry>
              <entry>ebXML v3.0: Electronic business XML Version 3.0, Registry Information 
                Model (ebRIM), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005, Registry Services and 
                Protocols (ebRS), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005.</entry>
              <entry>Used as foundation for setup, maintenance and interaction with
                a (AMN/ISAF) Metadata Registry and Repository for sharing and configuration
                management of XML metadata. Also enables federation among metadata 
                registries/repositories.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6:Exchanging structured information in a decentralized, distributed
                environment via services</entry>
              <entry>W3C SOAP 1.1, Simple Object Access Protocol v1.1 (SOAP)
                <para>Representational State Transfer (REST)</para>
                <para>WSDL v1.1: Web Services Description Language (WSDL) 1.1, W3C 
                  Note, 15 March 2001.</para>
                <para>ebXML v3.0: Electronic business XML Version 3.0,Registry Information 
                  Model (ebRIM), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005,Registry Services and 
                  Protocols (ebRS), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005.</para>
                <para>Universal Description, Discovery, and Integration Specification
                  (UDDI v 2.0), OASIS Standard.</para>
                <para>Emerging (Dec 2011): UDDI v3.0</para>
                <para>Emerging (2014): SOAP 1.2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>The preferred method for implementing webservices are SOAP, 
                however, there are many use cases (mash-ups etc.) where a REST based 
                interface is easier to implement and sufficient to meet the IERs.
                <para>Used as foundation for setup, maintenance and interaction with
                  a (NATO) Metadata Registry and Repository for sharing and configuration
                  management of XML metadata. Also enables federation among metadata 
                  registries/repositories.</para>
                <para>AMN transition strategy to UDDI 3.0 needs to be developed
                  for 2011.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>7:Secure exchange of information across multiple security domains</entry>
              <entry>The Draft X-Labels syntax definition is called the "NATO Profile
                for the XML Confidentiality Label Syntax" and is based on version 
                1.0 of the RTG-031 proposed XML Confidentiality Label Syntax See 
                "Sharing of information across Communities of Interest and across 
                Security Domains with Object Level Protection" below.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>8:Topic based Publish / subscribe web services communication</entry>
              <entry>WS-Notification 1.3 including:
                <para>WS-Base Notification 1.3,</para>
                <para>WS-Brokered Notification 1.3,</para>
                <para>WS-Topics 1.3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Enable topic based subscriptions for web service notifications, 
                with extensible filter mechanism and support for message brokers.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>9:Providing transport-neutral mechanisms to address web services</entry>
              <entry>WS-Addressing  1.0</entry>
              <entry>Provides transport-neutral mechanisms to address Web services 
                and messages which is crucial in providing end-to-end message level 
                security, reliable messaging or publish / subscribe based web services.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>10:Reliable messaging for web services</entry>
              <entry>WS-Reliable Messaging 1.2</entry>
              <entry>Describes a protocol that allows messages to be transferred reliably 
                between nodes implementing this protocol in the presence of software 
                component, system, or network failures.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Community of Interest Services and Data Standards</title>
      
      <para>Many information exchange mechanisms between existing systems are built
      around complex and extensive military messaging standards, such as ADatP-3 
      CONFORMETS, U.S. Message Text Format (USMTF) and the Variable Message Format
      (VMF). The intent of this AMN interoperability profile is to specify the minimum
      subset of military message formats needed per service line.</para>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Community of Interest Data and System Interoperability</title>
      
      <table frame="all" id="v4tTech-services">
        <title>COI Interoperability</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:General formatted message exchange</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 5500 Ed.6:2010
                <para>AdatP-3 - Concept of NATO Message Text Formatting System (CONFORMETS) - ADatP-3(A) Change 1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>This change does not have any impact on existing implementations<para>ADatP-3(A) contains two different equivalent presentations of data: one as "classic" message or alternatively as XML-MTF instance.</para><para>
A) Automated processing of XML-files in static facilities/systems is much easier and thus preferred for the exchange between national AMN extensions and the AMN Core.</para><para> 
B) At the tactical edge of the AMN and the "classic" message format is the preferred option as this format is "leaner" and easier to transmit via tactical radio systems.</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2:Automated information resource discover, information extraction
                and interchange of metadata</entry>
              <entry>ISAF Minimum Metadata Implementation Policy, ISO 15836:2009 
                also known as the Dublin Core Metadata Element Set
                <para>TIDE Information Discovery (v2.3.0, Oct 2009)</para>
                <para>TIDE Service Discovery (v.2.2.0 Oct 2008)</para>
<para>Emerging (by Dec 2012): OpenSearch 1.1 Draft 4</para>
<para>Emerging 2013: SPARQL Ver 1.1 (2009)</para>
<para>Emerging 2013: OWL Ver 2 (2009)</para>
</entry>
              <entry>The policy defines a subset of the NATO Discovery Metadata
                Specification (NDMS) intended for information resource discovery.
                <para>ISO 15836:2009 does not define implementation detail.</para>
                <para>The technical implementation specifications are part of the 
                  TIDE Transformational Baseline v3.0, however, Query-by-Example (QBE), has been deprecated with the TIDE Information Discovery specs v2.3.0.</para>
<para>The TIDE community is evaluating OpenSearch for potential inclusion into the 
TIDE Information Discovery specifications. On the AMN CORE a commercial product called FAST ESP is being used to generate search indexes. This product could act as an OpenSearch "slave", but requires adaptation to this Open Standard but only using HTTP. CUR 1021, will request automated information discovery across the AMN for 2012. Therefore all potential information sources must provide this standard search interface in order to allow tools like FAST ESP to discover relevant information.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3:General definition for the Representation of Dates and Times.</entry>
              <entry>ISO 8601:2004, Representation of Dates and Times.</entry>
              <entry>If not otherwise specified, implementation of the W3C profile of ISO 8601:2004 is mandatory.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4:General definition of letter codes for Geographical Entities</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 1059, Letter Codes for Geographical Entities (9th edition, 2005)
              </entry>
              <entry>Whenever possible, the ISO-3166 three-letter codes contained in 
                STANAG 1059 should be used</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5:General definition of geospatial coverage areas in discovery metadata</entry>
              <entry>World Geodetic System (WGS) 84, ISO 19115 and ISO 19136 (for point 
                references)</entry>
              <entry>ISO 19139 provides encoding guidance for ISO 19115</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6:General definition of Security and Confidentiality metadata</entry>
              <entry>Emerging (Dec 2012):<para>
- NO-FFI 00961 (RTO spec on confidentiality labels);</para><para>
- NO-FFI 00962 (RTO spec on metadata binding);</para><para>
- NC3A TN-1455 (NATO profile of NO-FFI 00962);</para><para>
- NC3A TN-1456 (NATO profile of NO-FFI 00961).</para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>7:Asset/ consignment tracking</entry>
              <entry>The following two STANAGS require updating to reflect the IERs 
                identified in ISAF CUR 254.
                <para>STANAG 2185</para>
                <para>STANAG 2183</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Use for exchanging information with existing systems that process
                Asset and Consignment information.
                <para>Note that their evolution is foreseen to also regulate the 
                  civilian convoy information exchange</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Geospatial Interoperability</title>
  
      <table frame="all" id="v4Geospatial-interop">
        <title>Geospatial Interoperability</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Distribution of compiled mapping (raster) data between applications.</entry>
              <entry>OGC 04-024 (ISO 19128:2005), Web Map Service v.1.3
                <para>Fading (Dec 2012): v1.0.0, v1.1.0, and v1.1.1</para>
                <para>OGC 05-078r4, OpenGIS Styled Layer Descriptor Profile of the 
                  Web Map Service (SLD) v.1.1.0</para>
<para>OGC 07-057r7, OpenGIS Web Map Tile Service Implementation Standard (WMTS) v.1.0.0 Emerging: Dec 2013</para>
              </entry>
              <entry><para>WMTS are to be provided as a complimentary service to WMS to ease access to users operating in bandwidth constraint environments. WMTS trades the flexibility of custom map rendering for the scalability possible by serving of static data (base maps) where the bounding box and scales have been constrained to discrete tiles which enables the use of standard network mechanisms for scalability such as distributed cache systems to cache images between the client and the server, reducing latency and bandwidth use.</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2:Distribution of geo feature (vector) data between applications</entry>
              <entry>OGC 04-094, Web Feature Service (WFS) v.1.1.
                <para>OGC 06-049r1, GML Simple Feature Profil (GML 3.1.1) v.1.0.0 
                  Compliance Level 0</para>
                <para>OGC 04-095, Filter Encoding v.1.1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3:Electronic interchange of geospatial data as coverages, that is, 
                digital geospatial information representing space varying phenomena</entry>
              <entry>OGC 07-067r2, Web Coverage Service (WCS) v.1.1.1
                <para>Fading (Dec 2011): v1.0.0 and v1.1.0</para>
                <para>OGC Web Coverage Service (WCS) Standard Guidance Implementation 
                  Specification 1.0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Required for publishing coverage data.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4:Catalogue services support the ability to publish and search 
                collections of descriptive information (metadata) for geospatial 
                data, services, and related information objects.</entry>
              <entry>OGC 07-006r1: Catalogue Service for the Web (CSW) v.2.0.2, SOAP
                message
                <para>OGC 07-110r4, CSW-ebRIM Registry Service - Part 1: ebRIM profile
                  of CSW v.1.0.1</para></entry>
              <entry>Catalogue Services will be supported by Core GIS FSD2 on the 
                AMN Core.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5:Electronic format for medium resolution terrain evaluation data.</entry>
              <entry>U.S. Military Specification Digital Terrain Elevation Data (DTED)
                level 0,1,2 MIL-PRF-89020B</entry>
              <entry>Used to support line-of-sight analyses, terrain profiling, 3-D 
                terrain visualization, mission planning/rehearsal, and modeling and 
                simulation.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6:File based storage and exchange of digital geospatial mapping 
                (raster) data where services based access is not possible</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem><para>Geotiff (a public domain metadata standard embedding
                    georeferencing information within a TIFF 6.0 file</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>JPEG2000 (ISO/IEC 15444-1 and 2)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Multiresolution seamless image database (MrSid
                    Generation 2)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Enhanced Compressed Wavelet (ECW 3.3)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>NSA Compressed ARC Digitized Raster Graphics (CADRG)
                    </para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Raster product format (RPF)</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>This is provided for legacy systems, implementers are encouraged 
                to upgrade their systems to consume OGC Web Services.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>7:File based storage and exchange of non-topological geometry and 
                attribute information or digital geospatial feature (vector) data 
                where services based access is not possible</entry>
              <entry>ESRI SHAPE files
                <para>Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC), Keyhole Markup Language
                  (KML 2.2)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>This is provided for legacy systems, implementers are encouraged
                to upgrade their systems to provide/consume OGC Web Services.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>  
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Battlespace Management Interoperability</title>
    
      <table frame="all" id="v4battlespace-mgmt">
        <title>Battlespace Management Interoperability</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Digital exchange of semantically rich information about Battlespace
                Objects such as units, their structural composition, Plans and Orders 
                etc.</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 5523 – C2 Information Exchange model in conjunction with MIP Data Exchange Mechanism (DEM) Block 2 and the AMN MIP Implementation Profile (published in Annex A to NC3A RD-3188 - AMN MIP Workshop Final Report).</entry>
              <entry>C2IEDM Bussiness Rule F11.2 b is not applicable in the AMN scope. 
                Implementations shall ensure that the use of CONTEXT-ASSOCIATION does 
                not create circular references between CONTEXTs.Currently most AMN 
                members use C2IEDM (MIP-Block 2). 
                <para>Any addition or expansion of this data model or data dictionaries
                  that is deemed to be of general interest shall be submitted as a 
                  change proposal within the configuration control process to be 
                  considered for inclusion in the next version of the specification.
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2:Expressing digital geographic annotation and visualization on, 
                two-dimensional maps and three-dimensional globes</entry>
              <entry>TIDE Transformational Baseline Vers. 3-0, NATO Vector Graphics 
                (NVG)
                <para>Mandatory: NVG 1.5</para>
                <para>Fading (Dec 2011): NVG 1.4</para>
                <para>Retired: NVG 0.3 </para>
                <para>Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC), Keyhole Markup Language 
                  (KML 2.2)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>NVG shall be used as the standard Protocol and Data Format for 
                encoding and sharing of information layers between Situational Awareness 
                and C2 systems.
                <para>NVG and KML are both XML-based language schemas for expressing
                  geographic annotations.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3:Exchanging information on Significant Activities (SIGACTs) 
                in support of current operations</entry>
              <entry>U.S.PM Battle Command SIGACT Schema<footnote><para>Document currently 
                not included in NISP Vol.2 (ed.E), as it was not available from the 
                author.</para></footnote></entry>
              <entry>This schema is used via PASS, webservices and XMPP to exchange
                SIGACT information at Regional Command level and below.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4:Exchanging information on Incident and Event information to
                support information exploitation.</entry>
              <entry>Emerging (Jul 2011): Draft EVENTEXPLOITREP XML schema. Under 
                development. Rationale: The coordination between NC3A and US on this work has been stalled due to the lack of funding.</entry>
              <entry>This schema will be used to exchange rich and structured incident/
event information between C2 and Exploitation systems like JOCWatch and CIDNE. National capability developers are invited to contribute to the development of the final EVENTEXPLOITREP XML Schema<footnote><para>See http://tide.act.nato.int/tidepedia/index.php?title=TP_112:_Event_Exploitation_Reports_(EVENTEXPLOITREP)</para></footnote>
Until the EVENTEXPLOITREP XML Schema definition is finalised, it is recommended to use the current draft schema also known as OIR (Operational Incident Report).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5:Real time automated data exchange such as radar tracking information 
                among airborne and land-based tactical data systems beyond line of sight.
                <para>Message exchange Over Tactical Data Links</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>STANAG 5516, Ed.4:2008 - Tactical Data Exchange (Link 16)
                <para>STANAG 5511, Feb 28, 2006 - Tactical Data Exchange (Link 11/11B); 
                  see also US MIL-STD 6011</para>
                <para>STANAG 5616 Ed 4:2008 - Standards for Data Forwarding between 
                  Tactical Data Systems employing Link 11/11B, Link 16 and Link 22.
                  </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>AMN members shall follow the specifications for automatic data 
                exchange of tactical information with and among NATO tactical data 
                systems, using the data transmission Links designated as Link 11/11B 
                and Link 16.
                <para>Edition 5 of 5516 is ratified, implementation in ISAF needs
                  to be coordinated via the AMN OPT.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6:Exchange of digital Friendly Force Information such as positional 
                tracking information amongst airborne and land-based tactical data
                systems and C2 systems.</entry>
              <entry>AC/322-D(2006)0066 Interim NFFI Standard for Interoperability 
                of Force Tracking Systems</entry>
              <entry>All positional information of friendly ground forces (e.g. ground
                forces of Troop Contributing Nations or commercial transport companies 
                working in support of ISAF Forces) shall be as a minimum made available
                in a format that can be translated into the NFFI V1.3 format. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>7:Message formats for exchanging information in low bandwidth 
                environment between systems enabled for processing Military Message
                Format</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 7149 Ed. 4 - NATO Message Catalogue - APP-11(C)
<para>Minimum set of messages supported by AMN Core:</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem><para>INCIDENT REPORT (A078)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>SARIR (J012)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>EVENTREP (J092)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>EODINCREP (J069)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>AIR SUPPORT REQUEST (F091)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>AIR TASKING ORDER (F058)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>AIRSPACE CONTROL ORDER (F011)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>PRESENCE REPORT (A009)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>SITREP (J095)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>ENEMY CONTACT REP (A023)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>CASEVACREQ (A015)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>KILLBOX MESSAGE (F083)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>INCIDENTSPOTREP (J006)</para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
		<para>Emerging Dec 2012</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem><para>SALTATIC (A073)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>CASEVACREQ (A015)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>MEDEVAC MESSAGE (A012)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>FRIENDLY FORCE INFORMATION (J025) is the ADatP-3 representation of NFFI</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>OPSITREP IRREGULAR ACTOR (A011)</para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
</entry>
              <entry>The following messages that are not compliant with STANAG 7149 
                Ed 4. will be accepted by the AMN Core:
              <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem><para>UXO IED REPORT 10-LINER (UXOIED) (A075)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Joint Tactical Air Strike Request (JTAR) - US DD Form 1972</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>ROZ Status / KILLBOX MESSAGE (F083)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>SALUTE (Size, Activity, Location, Unit/Uniform, Time, Equipment)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>ENEMY CONTACT REP (A023)</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
<para>Change request proposals reflecting the requirements for those non-standard messages should be submitted within the configuration management process of ADatP-3 by those nations that are the primary originators of those messages.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>8:Military Symbology interoperability</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 2019, Ed.5:2008, Joint Smbology- APP-6(B)
                <para>U.S. MIL-STD 2525 B Change 2, Common Warfighting Symbology</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Note that both standards are not fully compatible with each other.
                A translation service may need to be provided at the AMN integration core.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>9:Providing a standard software interface for exchanging information about sensor planning, including information about capabilities of sensors, tasking of a sensors and status of sensor planning requests.</entry>
              <entry>Emerging (July 2012): OGC 09-000: OGC Sensor Planning Service Implementation Standard V.2.0, dated 2011-03-28</entry>
              <entry>For the AMN, Sensor Planning Service implementations shall adhere to the SOAP binding as defined in OGC 09-000.</entry>
            </row>

          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Joint Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconaissance Interoperability</title>
      
      <para>AEDP-2, Ed.1:2005- NATO Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconnaissance 
        Interoperability Architecture (NIIA). The NIIA provides the basis for the
        technical aspects of an architecture that provides interoperability between 
        NATO nations' ISR systems. AEDP-2 provides the technical and management guidance
        for implementing the NIIA in ISR systems.</para>
        
      <table frame="all" id="v4joint-isrt">
        <title>Joint Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconaissance Interoperability</title> 
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Storing and exchanging of images and associated data</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 4545, Ed. Amendment 1:2000, NATO Secondary Imagery Format (NSIF)
              </entry>
              <entry>AEDP-4, Ed. 1, NATO Secondary Imagery Format Implementation 
                Guide, 15 Jun 07, NU</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2:Providing a standard software interface for searching and retrieving 
                for ISR products.</entry>
              <entry>NATO Standard ISR Library Interface (NSILI)
                <para>Mandatory: STANAG 4559, Ed. 3:2010 (starting Dec 2011)</para>
                <para>Fading: STANAG 4559, Ed. 2:2007 (beginning July 2011)</para></entry>
              <entry>AEDP-5, Ed. 1, NATO Standard Imagery Library Interface Implementation
                Guide, TBS, NU<para>STANAG 4559,Ed.2 and Ed.3 are NOT compatible with each other (No backwards compatibility). The CSD on the AMN Core only implements Ed.3:2010).</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3:Exchange of ground moving target indicator radar data</entry>
              <entry>NATO Ground Moving Target Indicator (GMTI) Format
                <para>Mandatory: STANAG 4607, Ed. 2:2007</para>
                <para>Emerging (Dec 2012): STANAG 4607, Ed.3:2010</para></entry>
              <entry>AEDP-7, Ed. 1, NATO Ground Moving Target Indication (GMTI) Format
                Implementation Guide, TBS, NU</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4:Provision of common methods for exchanging of Motion Imagery 
                (MI)across systems</entry>
              <entry>NATO Digital Motion Imagery Standard
                <para>Mandatory: STANAG 4609, Ed. 2:2007</para>
                <para>Emerging (Dec 2011): STANAG 4609, Ed. 3:2009</para></entry>
              <entry>AEDP-8, Ed. 2, Implementation Guide For STANAG 4609-NDMI , 
                Jun 07, NU</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5:Exchange of unstructured data (documents, jpeg imagery)</entry>
              <entry>IPIWIG V4 Metadata Specification:2009, Intelligence Projects 
                Integration Working Group (IPIWG), Definition of metadata for unstructured
                Intelligence.<footnote><para>Document currently not included in NISP Vol.2
                (ed.E), as it was not available from the author.</para></footnote></entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Biometrics Data and System Interoperability</title>
      
      <para>Biometrics is a general term used alternatively to describe a characteristic 
      or a process. As a characteristic, a biometric is a measurable biological 
      (anatomical and physiological) and behavioral characteristic that can be used
      for automated recognition. As a process, a biometric is an automated method 
      of recognizing an individual based on measurable biological (anatomical and
      physiological) and behavioral characteristics.</para>
      
      <table frame="all" id="v4t-biometrics">
        <title>Biometrics Data and System Interoperability</title> 
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Interchange of Fingerprint (Type 4 and 14) data</entry>
              <entry>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000
                <para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007 Part 1</para>
                <para>EBTS 1.2 (references ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000)</para>
                <para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1 (references ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007)</para>
                <para>DOD EBTS 2.0</para>
                <para>ISO/IEC 19794-2:2005, part 2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2:Type 10 Facial</entry>
              <entry>EFTS v7.0, EFTS v7.1
                <para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1</para>
                <para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000, 1-2007 Part 1</para>
                <para>EBTS 1.2 (references EFTS v7.0)DOD EBTS v2.0</para>
                <para>ISO/IEC 19794-5 w/ Amd 1:2007, part 5</para></entry>
              <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3:Type 16 Iris</entry>
              <entry>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000, 1-2007 Part 1
                <para>EBTS 1.2</para>
                <para>ISO/IEC 19794-6</para></entry>
              <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4:Type 17 Iris</entry>
              <entry>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007 Part 1
                <para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1 (ref ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007)</para>
                <para>DOD EBTS v2.0</para>
                <para>ISO/IEC 19794-6</para></entry>
              <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
   
    <sect1>
      <title>User Interface Capabilities/Applications</title>
      
      <para>User Applications, also known as application software, software applications, applications or apps, are computer software components designed to help a user perform singular or multiple related tasks and provide the logical interface between human and automated activities.</para>
      
      <table frame="all" id="v4t-userinterface">
        <title>User Interface Capabilities/Applications</title> 
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID:Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>1:Displaying content within web browsers.</entry>
              <entry>W3C Hypertext Markup Language HTML 4.0.1
                <para>W3C Extensible Hypertext Markup Language XHTML 1.0</para>
                <para>W3C Cascading Style Sheets CSS 2.0</para></entry>
              <entry>Applications must support the following browsers: Microsoft 
                Internet Explorerv7.0 and newer, and Mozilla Firefox3.0 and newer.
                When a supported browser is not true to the standard, choose to support
                the browser</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>2:Browser plug-ins.</entry>
              <entry>Browser plug-ins are not covered by a single specification.</entry>
              <entry>Some AMN members do not allow the use of ActiveX controls in
                the browser. Browser plug-ins do need to be approved by AMN CAB.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>3:Visualize common operational symbology within C4ISR systems 
                in order to convey information about objects in the battlespace.</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 2019, Ed.5:2008, Joint Symbology- APP-6(B)
                <para>U.S. MIL-STD 2525 B Change 2, Common Warfighting Symbology</para>
                <para>TIDE Transformational Baseline Vers. 3-0, NATO Vector Graphics 
                  (NVG)</para>
                <para>Mandatory: NVG 1.5</para>
                <para>Fading (Dec 2011): NVG 1.4</para>
                <para>Retired: NVG 0.3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>All presentation service shall render tracks, tactical graphics,
                and MOOTW objects using this standard except in the case where the
                object being rendered is not covered in the standard. In these exceptional
                cases, additional symbols shall be defined as extensions of existing 
                symbols and must be backwards compatible. These extensions shall be
                submitted as a change proposal within the configuration control process
                to be considered for inclusion in the next version of the specification.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>4:Reliable messaging over XMPP</entry>
              <entry>XMPP Clients must implement the following XMPP protocol extensions
                <para>XEP-0184 for message receipts, whereby the sender of a message 
                  can request notification that it has been received by the intended
                  recipient, and XEP 0202 for communicating the local time of an entity.
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>All XMPP Chat Clients used on the AMN shall implement these 
                two protocol extensions.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>5:Collaborative generation of spreadsheets, charts, presentations
                and word processing documents</entry>
              <entry>ECMA-376, Ed. 1: 2006 Office Open XML
                <para>Emerging (Dec 2012): Document description and processing languages
                  ISO/IEC 29500:2008 (transitional)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>6:Document exchange, storage and archiving</entry>
              <entry>Document management -- Electronic document file format for 
                long-term preservation --ISO 19005-1:2005 Part 1: Use of PDF 1.4 
                (PDF/A-1)</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
      
    <sect1>
      <title>References</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>[1] MC 245 Statement of Military Requirement for Interoperability
            between Automated Data Systems.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>[2] Allied Data Publication 34 (ADatP-34) NATO Interoperability 
            Standards and Profiles (NISP) STANAG 5524.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>[3] NATO C3 System Interoperability Policy, AC/322-D(2004)0039 dated 
            13 Sep 2004.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>[4] NATO C3 System Interoperability Directive, AC/322-D(2004)0040 
            dated 13 Sep 2004.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>  
</appendix>
