<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 5 -   A N N E X - A
*****************************************************************  
-->
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v5a-a">
  <title>STANAG Transformation Framework</title>

  <para>This annex describes the STANAG Transformation Framework (STF) included in the NISP.</para>

  <table frame="all">
    <title>Article Metadata</title>

    <tgroup cols="2">
      <colspec colwidth="40*"/>

      <colspec colwidth="60*"/>

      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>Project name:</entry>

          <entry>Interoperability &amp; Standardization (ACT Sponsor: Troy Turner)</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>Topic:</entry>

          <entry>STANAG Transformation Framework (STF)</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>Area of Validity:</entry>

          <entry>Common framework and methodology to transform textual STANAGs into XML</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>Original Author:</entry>

          <entry>Dario Cadamuro</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>Original Author:</entry>

          <entry>Jelle van Zeijl</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>Original Author:</entry>

          <entry>Mimi Nguyen</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>Maintained by:</entry>

          <entry>NCI Agency CapDev</entry>
        </row>

        <row>
          <entry>Version:</entry>

          <entry>v1.0</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>

  <sect1 id="one-introduction">
    <title id="one-introduction-title">Introduction</title>

    <sect2 id="one-dot-one-background">
      <title id="one-dot-one-background-title">Background</title>

      <para>NATO captures the definition of processes, procedures, terms, and conditions for common
      military or technical procedures or equipment between member countries using a Standardization
      Agreement (STANAGs).</para>

      <para>The NATO Standardization Agency (NSA) and Consultation, Command and Control Board (C3B)
      with Capability Panels (CaPs) and Capability Teams (CaTs) develop and maintain STANAGs under
      configuration management within NATO.</para>

      <para>STANAGs form the basis for enabling technical interoperability between a wide variety of
      Communication and Information Systems (CIS). In particular, information exchange STANAGs are
      used to standardize the protocols and data formats which regulate the information exchange
      between various CISs. Within the NATO APP-15 such types of STANAGs are called Information
      Exchange Specifications (IES). In this document, STANAG shall be read as a STANAG related to
      an IES within NATO.</para>

      <para>STANAGs constantly evolve in line with the evolution of NATO roles and derived
      requirements. The evolution implies the enhancement, modification and reduction of their
      contents. NATO has identified several gaps and areas for improvement within the current
      STANAGs that require action to ensure current and continual interoperability among forces and
      to enable the information sharing in a seamless infrastructure.</para>

      <para>As NATO and Nations are evolving to achieve the vision of the NATO Network-Enabled
      Capability (NNEC) , it has been realized and agreed that the NNEC data strategy goals involve
      making data Visible, Accessible, Understandable and Interoperable. In order to support these
      goals, traditional text-based information exchange STANAGs need to evolve into an unambiguous,
      machine-interpretable format, such as the extensible mark-up language (XML).</para>

      <para>A common framework and methodology to transform textual STANAGs into XML have been
      developed and are presented here as the STANAG Transformation Framework (STF) set of design
      rules.</para>

      <para>With the application of the STF, NATO and Nations are provided a mechanism to start
      tackling the data strategy vision and facilitating the improvement of current and future
      STANAG development efforts.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="one-dot-two-scope">
      <title id="one-dot-two-scope-title">Scope</title>

      <para>The scope of the analysis is to introduce a common framework, the STF, and associated
      design rules and methodology to transform textual STANAGs into XML to support the NNEC data
      strategy goals to make data Visible, Accessible, Understandable and Interoperable in an NNEC,
      service-oriented architecture (SOA) based, environment.</para>

      <para>The STF set of design rules also aims to assist in the development of current and future
      STANAGs within NATO. The STF, design rules and methodology are applicable to all information
      exchange STANAGs related to technical interoperability between systems and services.</para>

      <para>Although it may be applicable to all types of information exchanges, it does not aim to
      regulate the development of standards used outside of NATO.</para>

      <para>The STF is not intended to be used for transforming STANAGs that are unrelated to
      information exchange (e.g. STANAG 2832 - Restrictions for the Transport of Military Equipment
      by Rail on European Railways).</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="one-dot-three-abbreviations-and-definitions">
      <title id="one-dot-three-abbreviations-and-definitions-title">Abbreviations and
      Definitions</title>

      <para>In this section abbreviations and concepts used in the analysis report are
      listed.</para>

      <table frame="all">
        <title><emphasis role="bold">Abbreviations</emphasis></title>

        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="20*"/>

          <colspec colwidth="80*"/>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>APP</entry>

              <entry>Allied Procedural Publication</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>AST</entry>

              <entry>Asset Tracking</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>C3B</entry>

              <entry>Consultation, Command and Control Board</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>CaP</entry>

              <entry>Capability Panel</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>CaT</entry>

              <entry>Capability Team</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>CIS</entry>

              <entry>Communication and Information System</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>COI</entry>

              <entry>Community of Interest</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>FFT</entry>

              <entry>Friendly Force Tracking</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>IES</entry>

              <entry>Information Exchange Specification</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>NATO</entry>

              <entry>North Atlantic Treaty Organisation</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>NMRR</entry>

              <entry>NATO Metadata Registry &amp; Repository</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>NNEC</entry>

              <entry>NATO Network Enabled Capability</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>NSA</entry>

              <entry>NATO Standardization Agency</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>SOA</entry>

              <entry>Service-oriented architecture</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>STANAG</entry>

              <entry>NATO Standardization Agreement</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>STF</entry>

              <entry>STANAG Transformation Framework</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>TDL</entry>

              <entry>Tactical Data Link</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>V&amp;V</entry>

              <entry>Verification &amp; Validation</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>XML</entry>

              <entry>Extensible Mark-up Language</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="two-executive-summary">
    <title id="two-executive-summary-title">Executive Summary</title>

    <para>STANAGs regulate the information exchange between systems and services and form the basis
    for technical interoperability. These STANAGs are under configuration management within NATO and
    are evolving in line with the evolution of NATO roles and derived requirements.</para>

    <para>Gaps in current STANAGs related to this evolution and areas for improvement of the STANAGs
    have been identified. These include lack of support for NNEC Data Strategy requirements, a lack
    in the ability to verify and validate (V&amp;V) the quality of the STANAG content and
    implementation, and the need for resource optimization required for the management and
    maintenance of the STANAGs. The STANAG Transformation Framework (STF) set of design rules is
    based on a proven solution to the identified problems related to the contents, the quality and
    the resources required for the management of the STANAG that are regulating the information
    exchange within NATO.</para>

    <para>The STF set of design rules provides a methodology to apply STF in order to transform
    traditional human-readable textual representation of the STANAGs into equivalent
    machine-readable representations to support NNEC goals of making data Visible, Accessible,
    Understandable and Interoperable.</para>

    <para>The STF has been successfully applied to various STANAGs related to and tested within
    different Communities of Interest (COIs). In particular, STF design rules have been applied to
    the Tactical Data Link (TDL), the Asset Tracking (AST), Joint Intelligence, Surveillance and
    Reconnaissance (JISR) and the Friendly Force Tracking (FFT) communities within NATO.</para>

    <para>Viewed from a common perspective, the STF design rules have been shown to address problems
    that occur over and over again within different contexts. This has demonstrated its usefulness,
    applicability, reliability and trustworthiness as a means to develop and transform STANAGs that
    regulate the information exchange within NATO. Also as organisations and nations convert STANAGs
    to XML to meet their own systems requirements, the STF sets out the design rules to enable this
    process, thus providing standardization and ensuring interoperability of our systems.</para>

    <para>The NATO Standardization Agency (NSA) and Consultation, Command and Control Board (C3B)
    with Capability Panels (CaPs) and Capability Teams (CaTs) develop and maintain STANAGs under
    configuration management within NATO. As these bodies develop or maintain STANAGs, it is highly
    recommended that they apply the STF as needed based on the context of the problem they are
    trying to solve.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="three-recommendations">
    <title id="three-recommendations-title">Recommendations</title>

    <para>The identified recommendations based upon the findings of the analysis are listed
    below:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>NATO and Nations to mandate the usage of the STF set of design rules to develop new
        information exchange STANAGs and to transform existing STANAGs into equivalent
        machine-readable and machine-interpretable representations to support the NNEC Data Strategy
        goals.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In order to make this feasible, the following is the recommended Way Ahead:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Develop a roadmap and development plan detailing the sequencing and prioritisation of
        activities related to the transformation of existing STANAGs.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Develop a NATO stakeholder plan to define which bodies within NATO shall apply the STF
        set of design rules.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Establish a NATO Metadata Registry and Repository that is configuration managed, to
        store the STF set of XML artefacts as well as the XML artefacts produced by applying the
        STF.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Establish the STF namespace to maintain the XML artefacts that are part of the STF set
        of design rules under configuration management and shareable within NATO.</para>

        <para>There is a need to continue active and constructive interaction between NATO, Nations
        and Industry, leading towards the definition of a roadmap for the transformation and
        maturity of information exchange STANAGs. As the NSA and C3B develop or maintain STANAGs, it
        is highly recommended that they apply the STF.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="four-document-information">
    <title id="four-document-information-title">Document Information</title>

    <sect2 id="four-dot-one-document-revision-information">
      <title id="four-dot-one-document-revision-information-title">Document Revision
      Information</title>

      <para><table frame="all">
          <title>Document Revision Information</title>

          <tgroup cols="4">
            <colspec colwidth="20*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="20*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="40*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="20*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Date</entry>

                <entry>Issue</entry>

                <entry>Description</entry>

                <entry>Author</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>2012/05/31</entry>

                <entry>First version</entry>

                <entry>STANAG Transformation Framework (STF) Design Rules. Analysis report</entry>

                <entry>NCI Agency</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="four-dot-two-document-survey">
      <title id="four-dot-two-document-survey-title">Document Survey</title>

      <sect3 id="four-dot-two-dot-one-enclosures">
        <title id="four-dot-two-dot-one-enclosures-title">Enclosures</title>

        <para>The enclosed documents listed in the table below form the STF Set of XML artefacts and
        are provided here for the reader's reference. The authoritative versions of these STF XML
        artefacts are available electronically via the interim NATO Metadata Registry &amp;
        Repository (NMRR) within the STF Namespace.</para>

        <para><table frame="all">
            <title>Enclosures</title>

            <tgroup cols="3">
              <colspec colwidth="40*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="28*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="32*"/>

              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Document ID</entry>

                  <entry>Date of publication</entry>

                  <entry>Issue number / version</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>STF-common.xsd</entry>

                  <entry>31 August 2012</entry>

                  <entry>1.0</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>STF-security.xsd</entry>

                  <entry>31 August 2012</entry>

                  <entry>1.0</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>DataElementDictionary-Base.xsd</entry>

                  <entry>31 August 2012</entry>

                  <entry>1.0</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>DataElementDictionary-Codelists.xsd</entry>

                  <entry>31 August 2012</entry>

                  <entry>1.0</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>DataElementDictionary-BitBased.xsd</entry>

                  <entry>31 August 2012</entry>

                  <entry>1.0</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>DataElementDictionary-TextBased.xsd</entry>

                  <entry>31 August 2012</entry>

                  <entry>1.0</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>MessageStructure-Base.xsd</entry>

                  <entry>31 August 2012</entry>

                  <entry>1.0</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>MessageStructure-Codelists.xsd</entry>

                  <entry>31 August 2012</entry>

                  <entry>1.0</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>MessageStructure-BitBased.xsd</entry>

                  <entry>31 August 2012</entry>

                  <entry>1.0</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>MessageStructure-TextBased.xsd</entry>

                  <entry>31 August 2012</entry>

                  <entry>1.0</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="four-dot-two-dot-two-government-documents">
        <title id="four-dot-two-dot-two-government-documents-title">Government Documents</title>

        <para><table frame="all">
            <title><emphasis role="bold">Government documents</emphasis></title>

            <tgroup cols="3">
              <colspec colwidth="34*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Document ID</entry>

                  <entry>Date of publication</entry>

                  <entry>Issue number / version</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>TBD</entry>

                  <entry/>

                  <entry/>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="four-dot-two-dot-three-references">
        <title id="four-dot-two-dot-three-references-title">References</title>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>References</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colwidth="80*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="10*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="10*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Document ID</entry>

                <entry>Date of publication</entry>

                <entry>Issue number / version</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry id="REF-APP15">[APP15] NATO Consultation, Command and Control Board (NC3B)
                Information Services Sub-Committee (ISSC), ANNEX 1 to EAPC(AC/322-SC/5)N(2009)0001,
                APP-15 (Allied Procedural Publication) NATO Information Exchange Requirement
                Specification Process, (NATO/EAPC Unclassified)</entry>

                <entry>November 2008</entry>

                <entry>Original</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-NNEC-FS">[NNEC-FS] NATO Network Enabled Capability Feasibility Study
                (NNEC FS)</entry>

                <entry>October 2005</entry>

                <entry>2.0</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-NNEC-DS">[NNEC-DS] NATO Network Enabled Capability (NNEC) Data
                Strategy</entry>

                <entry>January 2005</entry>

                <entry>1.1</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-IST-088">[RTO-IST-088] RTO-LS-IST-088 - Interoperability Enhancement
                via Standards Transformation</entry>

                <entry>November 2009</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-MP-IST-01">[MP-IST-01] Street, M.D, "Software Defined Radio to Enable
                NNEC: Technical Challenges and Opportunities for NATO", MP-IST-01, pp 7 (NATO
                Unclassified)</entry>

                <entry>April 2008</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-W3C-XML">[W3C-XML] Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0, W3C
                Recommendation http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/REC-xml-20081126</entry>

                <entry>26 November 2008</entry>

                <entry>Fifth Edition</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-OSI">[ISO/OSI] International Organization for Standardization and
                International Electrotechnical Commission (ISO/IEC 7498-1:1994(E), "Information
                technology " Open Systems Interconnection " Basic Reference model: The Basic
                Model"</entry>

                <entry>November 1994</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-W3C-SWA">[W3C-SWA] World Wide Web Consortium (on-line),"W3C Semantic
                Web Activity", at http://www.w3.org/2001/sw/</entry>

                <entry>17-09-2009, viewed 2 October 2009</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-ISOIEC11179">[ISO/IEC11179] International Organization for
                Standardization and International Electrotechnical Commission (ISO/IEC 11179-1:2004,
                "Information technology - Metadata registries (MDR)"</entry>

                <entry>2004</entry>

                <entry>Edition 2</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-BISC-C2">[BiSC-C2] Bi-SC Secure C2 Data Strategy v1.0 (BI-SC Secure
                C2 Data Strategy (3805/SPTCIS/CFOISM/2010/82-270734)</entry>

                <entry>27 July 2010</entry>

                <entry>1.0</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-NAC-INFOSEC">[NAC-INFOSEC] AC/322-WP(2004)0006(INV), "INFOSEC
                Technical and Implementation Guidance for Electronic labeling of NATO Information",
                North Atlantic Council, Brussels, Belgium (NATO Unclassified)</entry>

                <entry>2 February 2004</entry>

                <entry>Working paper</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-RTO-XML-2008">[RTO-XML-2008] RTO RTG-031/IST-068-2008 "XML In
                Cross-Domain Security Solutions: XML Security labeling proposal, 2008", NATO
                Research and Technology Organization, Paris, FR, (NATO Unclassified))</entry>

                <entry>November 2008</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-RTO-XML-2009">[RTO-XML-2009] RTO RTG-031/IST-068-2009, "XML
                Confidentiality Label Syntax - A Proposal for a NATO Specification", NATO Research
                and Technology Organization, A. Eggen, R. Haakseth, Norwegian Defence Research
                Establishment (NFFI), A. Thümmel (NC3A) (NATO Unclassified)</entry>

                <entry>April 15, 2009</entry>

                <entry>Draft Version 0.3, Not published</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-xTDL">[xTDL] EAPC(AC322-SC5-WG1)N(2009)0008 - xTDL Framework Document
                Original Distribution</entry>

                <entry>May 2009</entry>

                <entry>Original</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-NC3A-TN1391">[NC3A-TN-1391] NATO Consultation, Command and Control
                Agency (NC3A) Technical Note 1391, "Tactical Information Sharing, Improved Sharing
                via Standards Development and Validation", D. Cadamuro, J. van Zeijl, R. van
                Klaveren, N. Kol, A.C. Dinc, L. Fallani, M. van Nierop, M. van Schouwen, NC3A, The
                Hague, Netherlands (NATO Unclassified)</entry>

                <entry/>

                <entry>Draft</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-NC3A-TN1311">[NC3A-TN-1311] NATO Consultation, Command and Control
                Agency (NC3A) Technical Note 1311, "Administrative NATO Metadata Registry and
                Repository (NMRR) User Requirements", D. Cadamuro, N. Kol, NC3A, The Hague,
                Netherlands, (NATO Unclassified)</entry>

                <entry>December 2008</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-NC3A-TN1312">[NC3A-TN-1312] NATO Consultation, Command and Control
                Agency (NC3A) Technical Note 1312, "Administrative NATO Metadata Registry and
                Repository (NMRR) Functional Requirements", D. Cadamuro, N. Kol, NC3A, The Hague,
                Netherlands (NATO Unclassified)</entry>

                <entry>December 2008</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-NC3A-TN1313">[NC3A-TN-1313] NATO Consultation, Command and Control
                Agency (NC3A) Technical Note 1313, "Administrative NATO Metadata Registry and
                Repository (NMRR) Architecture and Design", D. Cadamuro, N. Kol, NC3A, The Hague,
                Netherlands (NATO Unclassified)</entry>

                <entry>December 2008</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-NC3A-TN1367">[NC3A-TN-1367] NATO Consultation, Command and Control
                Agency (NC3A) Technical Note 1367, "Operational NATO Metadata Registry and
                Repository (NMRR) System Requirements Specification (SRS)", D. Cadamuro, N. Kol, R.
                van der Lingen, M. van Schouwen, H. van Woudenberg, NC3A, The Hague, Netherlands
                (NATO Unclassified).</entry>

                <entry/>

                <entry>Draft</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-NC3A-TN1368">[NC3A-TN-1368] NATO Consultation, Command and Control
                Agency (NC3A) Technical Note 1368, "Operational NATO Metadata Registry and
                Repository (NMRR) Feasibility Overview", D. Cadamuro, N. Kol, R. van der Lingen, M.
                van Schouwen, H. van Woudenberg, NC3A, The Hague, Netherlands (NATO
                Unclassified)</entry>

                <entry>December 2008</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-NC3A-TN1369">[NC3A-TN-1369] NATO Consultation, Command and Control
                Agency (NC3A) Technical Note 1369, "Operational NATO Metadata Registry and
                Repository (NMRR) Interface Control Document", D. Cadamuro, N. Kol, R. van der
                Lingen, M. van Schouwen, H. van Woudenberg, NC3A, The Hague, Netherlands (NATO
                Unclassified)</entry>

                <entry>December 2008</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-RTO-EN-IST-088">[RTO-EN-IST-088] RTO-EN-IST-088,"NATO Metadata
                Registry and Repository: Core Service for XML", D. Cadamuro, N. Kol and R. van
                Klaveren (NATO Unclassified)</entry>

                <entry>October 2009</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-NC3A-TN1254">[NC3A-TN-1254] NATO Consultation, Command and Control
                Agency (NC3A) Technical Note 1254, "Standardization and the Power of Metadata", D.
                Cadamuro, N. Kol, NC3A, The Hague, Netherlands(NATO Unclassified)</entry>

                <entry>December 2008</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-NC3A-NU-CCS-ADP-2008-331">[NC3A-NU/CCS/ADP/2008/331] NATO
                Consultation, Command and Control Agency CD-ROM NU/CCS/ADP/2008/331, "Link-16
                ALTBMD-MRS Interoperability Matrix for Command and Control/Battle
                Management/Communications Ballistic Missile Defence Systems (BMDS) Interface Control
                Document (ICD)", D. Cadamuro, NC3A, The Hague, Netherlands (NATO
                Confidential)</entry>

                <entry>April 2008</entry>

                <entry>Version 1.0</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry id="REF-BiSC-DLMS">[BiSC-DLMS] AC322-N0638 - Bi-Strategic Commands Data Link
                Migration Strategy (Bi-SC DLMS)</entry>

                <entry>11 December 2000</entry>

                <entry>Original</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="five-analysis">
    <title id="five-analysis-title">Analysis</title>

    <para>In this chapter, the STF set of design rules is introduced by first providing the context
    and the problem it is addressing. Following, the solution and derived consequences are
    described. Finally, the limitations, the deviations and examples are presented.</para>

    <sect2 id="five-dot-one-context">
      <title id="five-dot-one-context-title">Context</title>

      <para>As NATO and Nations are evolving to achieve the vision of the NATO Network-Enabled
      Capability (NNEC), there are four basic challenges which have to be addressed in order to
      achieve the NNEC requirements that "<emphasis>data, information and services be visible,
      accessible, understandable and trusted across the networked environment for all authorized
      users, whether anticipated or unanticipated.</emphasis>" Each of these challenges build on top
      of each other - as one challenge is solved, the next becomes relevant as the new challenge to
      be addressed.</para>

      <figure id="v5a-f1">
        <title>Requirement for Data, Information and Services (derived from NNEC Data
        Strategy)</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/NNEC_Data_Strategy_Goals.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>As depicted in <xref linkend="v5a-f1"/>, these challenges are addressed by six key
      strategy goals, known as the NNEC Data Strategy goals, of making data Visible, Accessible,
      Coherent, Interoperable, and Assured, and their related actions/solution approaches. These
      solution approaches deal with data and information exchanges across a networked environment,
      and in particular a Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) environment, and thus require
      standardization of the protocols and data formats to ensure interoperability within the NATO
      context. As stated in <xref linkend="one-dot-one-background"/>, these standardizations are
      captured by NATO as information exchange STANAGs.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="five-dot-two-problem-areas-and-opportunities">
      <title id="five-dot-two-problem-areas-and-opportunities-title">Problem areas and
      opportunities</title>

      <para>Essentially, NATO has identified several gaps and areas for improvement within the
      current STANAGs that require action to ensure an appropriate interoperability among forces and
      to enable the information sharing in a seamless infrastructure.</para>

      <para>In general, the identified problems are related to the following areas:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Lack of ability to efficiently and accurately perform Verification and Validation
          (V&amp;V) on the quality of the contents and implementations of the STANAGs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Limited resources available for the management and maintenance of the
          STANAGs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Lack of support to address specific needs to support the NNEC Data Strategy
          goals.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>No agreed or standardized approach to the conversion of STANAGS to XML (design
          rules, methodology).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In particular, STANAGs have to be matured in the following aspects, based on the NNEC
      requirements and their identified gaps:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Security matters related both to information exchange security within the same
          security domain and cross security domains.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Operational cross-domain addressing harmonization of the information being exchanged
          across-COIs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Open/common architecture framework to describe the enterprise and the common/core
          services.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Service Oriented Architecture enabling seamless sharing of information.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Supporting object uniqueness and coherent object identification within a particular
          COI and among other COIs.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The above mentioned areas are further described in the following sections.</para>

      <sect3 id="five-dot-two-dot-one-sect">
        <title id="five-dot-two-dot-one-title">Lack of automated support for V&amp;V of STANAG
        content &amp; implementation quality</title>

        <para>Current STANAGs are text-based documents often composed of many pages (e.g. STANAG
        5516 consists of more than 8000 pages). These STANAGs are mainly manually written in text
        using a natural communication language like English, leaving room for (mis-)interpretations
        and ambiguous definitions (see e.g. standards ambiguity in [MP-IST-01]). To remove the
        possibility of misinterpretation and ambiguity, verification and validation of the quality
        and integrity of the STANAG content is required and needs to be supported in an automated
        way. The text-based representations of the STANAG do not allow this to happen in an
        efficient and effective manner.</para>

        <para>In fact, due to the current status quo, many STANAG standards and implementations
        may:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Contain unnecessary errors, since an automated integrity check cannot occur with a
            STANAG described in a natural language.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Contain inconsistencies when sections of a STANAG are updated as there is no
            automated means to check and cue updates that are required for other linked sections of
            the STANAG.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Be difficult to browse through without clickable hyperlinks, especially for very
            large and complex standards.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Contain duplications and inconsistencies between the definitions of the same data
            elements across multiple STANAGs.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Have vague or incomplete definitions of important concepts related to information
            exchanges, such as data bearers.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Be subject to restriction from proprietary rights aspects.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>As STANAGs are currently open to different interpretations, this allows inconsistent
        implementation of the standards which could lead to interoperability issues when fielded.
        There is a need for a framework and methodology that supports the transformation of
        traditional text-based STANAGs into an unambiguous, machine-interpretable format in order to
        support the automated V&amp;V of STANAG content and implementation quality.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="five-dot-two-dot-two-sect">
        <title id="five-dot-two-dot-two-title">Limited resources available for STANAG configuration
        management (CM)</title>

        <para>The traditional approach for STANAG definition and maintenance is that a NATO body "
        in many cases a NATO working group " is responsible for the definition and maintenance of
        the STANAG based on a well defined process. There currently are limited resources available
        for the management and maintenance of current STANAGs. In this era where defence budgets are
        generally in decline with little, if any, prospect for significant improvements, there
        exists a need to optimize resources to improve the efficiency and effectiveness of the
        management and maintenance of existing STANAGs and the development of new ones.</para>

        <para>The current approach for STANAG configuration management and maintenance is a very
        manual-intensive, stove-piped process that:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Results in a tedious and lengthy ratification process.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Does not leverage on new technologies and methodologies which would support
            automatic or semi-automatic verification and validation of the STANAG change proposal
            content, and assessment of impacts and dependencies before implementation.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Is not designed to optimize resources via the reuse of common definitions to
            support data harmonization, while increasing quality of the data content.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Allows duplications and inconsistencies in the definition of the same data
            elements between multiple STANAGs as there is no automated way to cross-check the
            definitions.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Once current STANAGs are transformed into a machine-readable and machine-interpretable
        format, automated tools could be developed to help optimize the limited available resources
        in order to support the management and maintenance of STANAGs. It will also increase the
        efficiency in the development of new STANAGs as it supports the discovery, reuse and
        harmonization of common definitions across the various Communities of Interest (COIs)
        responsible for STANAG development.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="five-dot-two-dot-three-sect">
        <title id="five-dot-two-dot-three-title">Unaddressed shortcomings of current STANAGs</title>

        <para>The need for making data Visible, Accessible, Understandable and Interoperable in an
        NNEC (SOA) environment is not fully addressed in current STANAGs.</para>

        <para>Current STANAGs typically:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Have missing definitions of important concepts related to information exchanges,
            such as data bearers.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Do not define how to share information in a Service Oriented Architecture (SOA)
            environment outside its legacy information exchange stovepipe.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Are not sufficiently mature to support information exchange within a SOA.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Do not support or address several necessary requirements such as cross COI and
            cross-security domain information sharing.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Do not support object uniqueness and coherent object identification within and
            between COIs.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>A structured, layered approach that identifies and captures the gaps and addresses the
        shortcomings of existing STANAGs in fulfilling the NNEC Data Strategy goals is needed to
        guide the transformation of existing STANAGs to support information exchange in a SOA
        environment. It will also assist in future STANAG development to ensure these gaps are
        addressed at STANAG inception and development rather than costlier and time-consuming
        changes after the fact.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="five-dot-three-sect">
      <title id="five-dot-three-title">Solution Introduction</title>

      <para>In this section, the solution for addressing the identified problem areas and
      opportunities captured in <xref linkend="five-dot-two-problem-areas-and-opportunities"/>, the
      STANAG Transformation Framework (STF), and its associated layered concepts are introduced. In
      the following <xref linkend="five-dot-four-stf-layers-and-definition"/>, the Framework and
      layers are presented, with an analogy and description per layer that defines the purpose for
      each layer. Following, in <xref linkend="five-dot-five-stf-design-rules-and-methodology"/>,
      the associated design rules, the methodology, a description of the associated XML Schema
      Definitions and an XML sample are provided for each layer of the STF. These provide guidance
      to the end users on how the STF design rules and methodology could be applied to transform
      existing STANAGs or develop new STANAGs in a layered approach and as machine-interpretable
      STANAG definition.</para>

      <sect3 id="five-dot-three-dot-one-sect">
        <title id="five-dot-three-dot-one-title">STANAG Transformation Framework (STF)
        Background</title>

        <para>As part of the multi-year standards transformation effort, NCI Agency (formerly NC3A)
        developed, under sponsorship of ACT, the STANAG Transformation Framework (STF) to address
        the identified problem areas and opportunities captured in <xref
        linkend="five-dot-two-problem-areas-and-opportunities"/>. The STF concepts were first
        introduced in the RTO sponsored Lecture Series on Interoperability in November 2009
        [RTO-IST-088], and has been further enhanced in detail here. The STF is a framework, a set
        of design rules and a methodology for transforming traditional text-based information
        exchange STANAGs into an unambiguous, machine-interpretable XML format and providing a
        layered approach in addressing the needs for maturing the information exchange STANAGs in
        the areas identified.</para>

        <para>The standards transformation concept transforms and augments standards by moving
        towards a more modular composition of the standards differentiating messages structure, data
        element dictionary, information exchange business rules and other aspects. To fulfil the
        emerging NNEC requirements, the current standards will be augmented with additional
        specifications, such as security cross-domain information exchange definitions.</para>

        <para>Moreover, the transformation of current standards towards machine-interpretable
        standards is foreseen as part of the standards transformation concept. The expanding
        exploration and application of XML into the realm of information exchange is viewed as a
        major step in support of NNEC. An evolving framework for capturing information exchange
        specifications in XML is a key element in advancing this technology. As that framework
        matures it is imperative that it adopts a model which fully supports all types of
        information exchanges, i.e. binary-, text- and XML-based formats. This will improve quality,
        maintainability and integrity of the standards and therefore contribute to the NNEC
        Networking and Information Infrastructure (NII) by improving interoperability.</para>

        <para>A common framework and methodology applicable to all STANAGs, which are related to the
        technical interoperability between systems/services, was developed. The combination of the
        two will allow the NNEC Data Strategy goals to be addressed and they will facilitate the
        implementation of it from a standardization perspective.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="five-dot-three-dot-two-sect">
        <title id="five-dot-three-dot-two-title">Concepts</title>

        <para>Below a number of concepts specific to the STF set of design rules are
        described.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Layered approach:</emphasis> The purpose of each layer is to
            offer services to its neighboring layers, avoiding those layers from being affected from
            changes in the internal details of their neighboring layers, and from how the offered
            services are implemented. The linkages between different layers, is regulated by
            specific interfaces. The principles used in internetworking can be taken as analogy. As
            a consequence, layers can also be reused or interchanged.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Interface:</emphasis>The place where two different systems
            interact, normally in accordance with an agreed contract.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Human Readable:</emphasis>A human-readable medium or
            human-readable format is a representation of data or information that can be naturally
            read by humans. In computing, human-readable data is often encoded as ASCII or Unicode
            text, rather than presented in a binary representation. This can also refer to the
            shorter names or strings that are easier to comprehend or remember rather than the
            longer, more complex syntax notations, such as some URL strings.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Machine Readable:</emphasis> A machine-readable format or
            medium of data primarily designed for reading by electronic, mechanical or optical
            devices, or computers. For example, the binary representation of data used by computers,
            the UPC barcodes for scanners, or the URL strings.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Machine Interpretable:</emphasis> More than just being
            readable by machines, machine interpretable data or format contains structured content
            that can be processed and "understood" by machines.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Bit-based:</emphasis> the information is encoded in a binary
            representation to optimise bandwidth usage, e.g. Link16 or VMF. This representation is
            generally not easily human readable.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Structured Text-based:</emphasis> the information is
            represented as textual values and the structure of the message is governed by other
            means e.g. line-based and slash delimited like for MTF and OTH-Gold. This representation
            is typically human and machine readable, but may not be easily machine
            interpretable.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">XML-based:</emphasis> the information is represented as
            textual values and the structure is governed by an XML Schema Definition (XSD) in line
            with the [W3C-XML], e.g. MTF-XML or NFFI. This representation is highly machine-readable
            and machine-interpretable.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="five-dot-four-stf-layers-and-definition">
      <title id="five-dot-four-stf-layers-and-definition-title">STF Layers and Definition</title>

      <para>Leveraging the successful application of the layered approach similarly to that of the
      ISO OSI reference model, the STF is defined using a layered approach to identify and capture
      the different areas of the information exchange STANAGs that should be specified in order to
      support various levels of interoperability. The STF layers have been identified based on the
      analysis of current Information Exchange Requirements and Specifications and emerging
      requirements for information sharing. The STF defines clear interfaces between the layers,
      supported by machine-interpretable XML specifications, design rules and a methodology to apply
      them, in order to support the identification, capture and reuse of specifications within those
      layers to support information exchange interoperability.</para>

      <para>The logical view depicted in <xref linkend="v5a-f2"/> provides an overview of the
      identified STF layers necessary to ensure appropriate data and information
      dissemination.</para>

      <figure id="v5a-f2">
        <title>Layers of the STANAG Transformation Framework</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_Layers.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>As can be seen, the STF defines five stacked horizontal layers and three vertical
      layers.</para>

      <para>The application of the STF layers towards STANAG transformation is based on the intended
      use and need to support interoperable information exchange within different domains.</para>

      <para>The horizontal STF layers could be considered Mandatory; their specifications are needed
      to support interoperable information exchange within a domain. However, a particular system
      implementation might not need to provide all functionalities described within the STANAG--the
      functionalities might be implemented by various systems, each playing a different role within
      the functional scenario. Therefore, the deployment or implementation of a system might cover
      only a subset of the layers to cover their needs and roles. This way the minimum
      implementation requirements for each system to achieve interoperability within a functional
      scenario must specify the requirement to implement parts of each layers to fulfil a specific
      role in a functional scenario.</para>

      <para>On the other hand, the vertical layers could be considered Optional specifications based
      on the intended use and functional scenario. In particular, if it is determined that there is
      a need to support the exchange of information across different security domains, then the
      specifications to support that information exchange has to be captured at the Security
      Cross-Domain layer. If it is envisioned that there is a need to support the exchange of
      information utilizing web services, then the Web Services specifications have to be captured
      using the Web Services layer. Finally, if it is deemed necessary to support the exchange
      of information across operational domains, it is necessary to map and specify how that
      information exchange will occur between those domains using the Operational Cross-Domain
      layer.</para>

      <para>The horizontal layers leverage concepts that can be loosely mapped to the <ulink
      url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iso_osi">ISO OSI 7-layer model</ulink>, <ulink
      url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tcp/ip">TCP/IP stack</ulink> and <ulink
      url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communication_protocol">communication protocol</ulink>
      specifications.</para>

      <para>The first two horizontal layers, "Data bearer" and "Routing", deal with physically and
      logistically "how" the information exchange is occuring between two systems. These two layers
      can be mapped to the lower 5 layers of the OSI model or the lower 2 levels of the TCP/IP
      stack, namely the Physical and Data Link layers, and the Network, Transport and Session
      layers. These deal with getting the data between any two or more systems that need to
      interoperate with each other.</para>

      <para>The top three horizontal layers defines "what" is being exchanged and the "rules" for
      exchanging those messages between two or more systems. These layers map loosely to the data
      defintion, data syntax, data semantics and data synchronization concepts used to define
      communication protocols at the Application layer of the OSI and TCP/IP stack.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The "Data Element Dictionary" and "Message Structure" define the data representation
          and syntax of the information exchange which define the context of the information
          exchange.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The "TX + RX rules/business rules", focuses on the semantics and synchronization of
          the data exchange, which defines how to send, receive and interpret the messages so that
          they make "sense", defining the rules that determine whether the data is
          meaningful.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The STF has been defined in such a way that the layers are generic and applicable to all
      types of information exchanges. The machine-interpretable XML specifications provide, where
      required, support for the different types of exchanges by defining a specific adapter of the
      XML Schema Definition (XSD). In the case of XML-based information exchanges the STF will
      leverage on the existence of a compliant XSD governing the information exchanges augmented
      with further required information.</para>

      <para>The following sections will describe each of these layers starting with an analogy to
      compare the relevant aspects of automated information exchange with a scenario everyone will
      be familiar with: natural language communication.</para>

      <sect3 id="data-bearer">
        <title id="data-bearer-title">Data Bearer</title>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="right" fileref="../figures/STF_Data_Bearer.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <sect4 id="analogy">
          <title id="analogy-title">Analogy</title>

          <para><emphasis>The information exchange via a language can be achieved in different ways.
          The usage of the verbal communication is probably the preferred communication media,
          either directly in a local discussion or via a transport medium like a phone.
          Nevertheless, language can also be used to exchange information via textual media (either
          electronic or paper-based), television and chat.</emphasis></para>

          <figure id="v5a-f3">
            <title>SatCom, Radio, Newspaper, Internet communication bearer</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/Satcom-Internet.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="definition-of-data-bearer-layer">
          <title id="definition-of-data-bearer-layer-title">Definition of Data Bearer layer</title>

          <para>The data bearer information is composed of the information in the lower 2 layers of
          the ISO OSI models, which are the physical and data link layers of the OSI network
          architecture.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Physical Layer defines the electrical and physical specifications for devices.
              In particular, it defines the relationship between a device and a physical
              medium.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Data Link Layer provides the functional and procedural means to transfer data
              between network entities and to detect and possibly correct errors that may occur in
              the Physical Layer.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The description within a STANAG of the possible data bearers used within the
          interfaces is essential to achieve interoperability between system and services.</para>

          <para>In case multiple data bearers can be used for information exchange, all of them have
          to be described here, including a rationale why the information exchange node should
          choose one or the other data bearer in specific situations.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="five-dot-four-dot-two-routing-op-horizontal-layer-cp">
        <title id="five-dot-four-dot-two-routing-op-horizontal-layer-cp-title">Routing (Horizontal
        Layer)</title>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="right" fileref="../figures/STF_Routing.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-two-dot-one-analogy">
          <title id="five-dot-four-dot-two-dot-one-analogy-title">Analogy</title>

          <para><emphasis>The distribution of information via language is addressed to a specific
          audience and thus does not occur unconditionally and to everyone. A conversation occurs
          only in between the participants of the conversation. The chat can be addressed one-on-one
          or to multiple chat participants, whereas the distribution of the newspaper occurs on a
          subscription basis.</emphasis></para>

          <figure id="v5a-f4">
            <title>Britain's first Official Post Card, the first commercial telephone
            switchboard</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/Postcard-Switchboard.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-two-dot-two-definition-of-routing-layer">
          <title id="five-dot-four-dot-two-dot-two-definition-of-routing-layer-title">Definition of
          Routing layer</title>

          <para>The Routing layer overlaps with the 3rd, 4th and 5th layers of the OSI reference
          model for network communication, which is typically referred to as the Network, Transport
          &amp; Session layers.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Network Layer provides the functional and procedural means of transferring
              variable length data sequences from a source to a destination via one or more
              networks, while maintaining the quality of service requested by the Transport Layer.
              The Network Layer performs network routing functions, and might also perform
              fragmentation and reassembly, and report delivery errors.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Transport Layer provides transparent transfer of data between end users,
              providing reliable data transfer services to the upper layers. This Layer controls the
              reliability of a given link through flow control, segmentation/desegmentation, and
              error control. This Layer can be thought of as a transport mechanism, e.g., a vehicle
              with the responsibility to make sure that its contents (passengers/goods) reach their
              destination.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Session Layer controls the dialogues (connections) between computers. It
              establishes, manages and terminates the connections between the local and remote
              application. It provides for full-duplex, half-duplex, or simplex operation, and
              establishes checkpointing, adjournment, termination, and restart procedures.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The routing of the information dissemination between two or more parties needs to be
          explicitly captured within STANAGs.</para>

          <para>Current technology defines the routing of information in heterogeneous ways, which
          tend not to be interoperable. A lack in specifying the routing mechanism will lead to
          interoperability issues. In case multiple routing algorithms can be used for information
          exchange, all of them have to be described within the STANAG, including a rationale why
          the information exchange node should choose one or the other routing mechanism in specific
          situations.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="five-dot-four-dot-three-data-element-dictionary-op-horizontal-layer-cp">
        <title
        id="five-dot-four-dot-three-data-element-dictionary-op-horizontal-layer-cp-title">Data
        Element Dictionary (Horizontal Layer)</title>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="right" fileref="../figures/STF_DED.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-three-dot-one-analogy">
          <title id="five-dot-four-dot-three-dot-one-analogy-title">Analogy</title>

          <para><emphasis>The definitions of words within a language are captured in a dictionary,
          where each word can have one or multiple meanings in that language. Sometimes the meaning
          is explicitly stated in the dictionary, in other cases, the meaning of the word is
          associated with non-verbal communication or tonality of pronunciation. The meaning
          expressed by a word within a certain language, can be expressed by multiple words within
          the same language and in other languages.</emphasis></para>

          <figure id="v5a-f5">
            <title>Data Element Dictionary</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/DataElementDictionary.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-three-dot-two-definition-of-data-element-dictionary-layer">
          <title
          id="five-dot-four-dot-three-dot-two-definition-of-data-element-dictionary-layer-title">Definition
          of Data Element Dictionary layer</title>

          <para>Within an information exchange STANAG, a data element is the atomic unit of data
          that has a precise meaning and precise semantics for that domain. Such a data element can
          be stored or exchanged among computer systems. The catalogue containing all Data Elements
          within a certain domain is called a Data Element Dictionary (DED) for that domain.</para>

          <para>It has to be stressed that proper and clear <ulink
          url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_element_definition">data element
          definitions</ulink> are critical for external users of any data system, since a good
          definition can ease the process of data element harmonization, where one set of data
          elements are mapped into another set of data elements.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="five-dot-four-dot-four-message-structure-op-horizontal-layer-cp">
        <title id="five-dot-four-dot-four-message-structure-op-horizontal-layer-cp-title">Message
        Structure (Horizontal Layer)</title>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="right" fileref="../figures/STF_Message_Structure.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-four-dot-one-analogy">
          <title id="five-dot-four-dot-four-dot-one-analogy-title">Analogy</title>

          <para><emphasis>Providing words in a non-structured way will pass only very limited
          information. Every communication language defines the grammar to construct sentences and
          therefore disseminate the information in an understandable way, to whoever knows the words
          and the language grammar. The human is capable of interpreting, assuming and correcting
          grammar mistakes, and thus understanding the information even if not completely properly
          structured.</emphasis></para>

          <figure id="v5a-f6">
            <title>Message Structure</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/MessageStructure.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-four-dot-two-definition-of-message-structure-layer">
          <title
          id="five-dot-four-dot-four-dot-two-definition-of-message-structure-layer-title">Definition
          of Message Structure layer</title>

          <para>To ensure interoperability between systems, it is essential that the data exchange
          is conforming to specific syntax rules. This syntax is called the message structure, which
          defines:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>A packaging of one or multiple levels of data elements into logical and/or
              functional groups, and;</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The sequencing of data elements within each functional and/or logical
              group.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>A proper structure will enable the association of data elements with each other, in
          order to support the binding of data to certain functional or logical objects. For
          example, the exchange of an altitude without context expresses less information than the
          exchange of an altitude related to a certain object. By using multiple level packaging,
          information about multiple objects, or even sub-objects, might be exchanged within one
          message.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="five-dot-four-dot-five-business-rules-op-horizontal-layer-cp">
        <title id="five-dot-four-dot-five-business-rules-op-horizontal-layer-cp-title">Business
        Rules (Horizontal Layer)</title>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="right" fileref="../figures/STF_Business_Rules.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-five-dot-one-analogy">
          <title id="five-dot-four-dot-five-dot-one-analogy-title">Analogy</title>

          <para><emphasis>"The Grammar of Ornament", a "new geographical and historical grammar"
          (London, 1764) and "Augustus as Ruler of Rome" summarize the explicit and implicit aspects
          of a dialogue. Knowing the available words and the valid sentences (see grammar of the
          language) that can be formed using these words, does not imply the capability to
          participate in dialogue. A dialogue follows explicit and implicit rules; if a question is
          asked, a related answer is expected, if a statement is made, a related statement or
          follow-up is expected.</emphasis></para>

          <figure id="v5a-f7">
            <title>Implicit and explicit parts of a dialogue</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/SymbolsGrammerGesture.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-five-dot-two-definition-of-business-rules-layer">
          <title
          id="five-dot-four-dot-five-dot-two-definition-of-business-rules-layer-title">Definition of
          Business Rules layer</title>

          <para>While the Message Structure and Data Element Definition (DED) provide the more
          static description of the way messages are constructed and how data elements are coded,
          the business rules / transmission reception rules aspect of the standard is defined as
          what behaviour a system should follow when handling the messages, the interaction with an
          operator or with the underlying system (e.g. its sensors' output). The business rules /
          transmission reception rules describe the dynamics of an automated message handling
          system.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="five-dot-four-dot-six-security-cross-dash-domain-op-vertical-layer-cp">
        <title
        id="five-dot-four-dot-six-security-cross-dash-domain-op-vertical-layer-cp-title">Security
        Cross-Domain (Vertical Layer)</title>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="right" fileref="../figures/STF_Security.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-six-dot-one-analogy">
          <title id="five-dot-four-dot-six-dot-one-analogy-title">Analogy</title>

          <para><emphasis>The human tailors the type of information he provides to the audience and
          to the context, withholding information that is not releasable to (a part of) that
          audience or in that specific context.</emphasis></para>

          <para><emphasis>In a conversation a party can put explicit constraints on the further
          distribution of provided information. The judgement, whether or not to share information
          is based on specific rules (e.g. need-to-know principle, personal in confidence
          attributes) but also on perception.</emphasis></para>

          <figure id="v5a-f8">
            <title>Past, Current and future security mechanisms</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/GuardShoeLock.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-six-dot-two-definition-of-security-cross-dash-domain-layer">
          <title
          id="five-dot-four-dot-six-dot-two-definition-of-security-cross-dash-domain-layer-title">Definition
          of Security Cross-Domain layer</title>

          <para>The Security Cross Domain takes into account recommendations provided in Bi-SC
          Secure C2 Data Strategy with security requirements aspects being subdivided into two
          categories:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Requirements for information exchange within the classification at the same
              level (important if connected to unsecure networks like the Internet), and</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Requirements for the security cross-domain functionalities.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The latter can be omitted in case only a single security domain is involved.</para>

          <para>For security requirements within a homogeneous security domain, the security aspects
          might contain:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Information on security related protocols / services (HTTPS).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Information on data source authentication and authorisation.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>For cross-domain security, the aspects might contain;</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Appropriate security labeling (in-line with NATO standards [NAC-INFOSEC] and
              recommendations [RTO-XML-2008] [RTO-XML-2009]) including the specification of what
              information should be considered classified (at what level) and what information
              should be considered unclassified</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Possible rules for sanitization of data, defining the manner to downscale the
              classification of information, e.g. information might be classified during a certain
              operation or exercise, but unclassified after the operation finished. Sanitization
              rules should be used to define this.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Information integrity: If information is labeled with the purpose to exchange
              it cross-security domain, the boundary device should be able to verify that the
              information has been labeled by a trusted device, and that nobody tampered with the
              label or the data in between the labeler and the boundary device (e.g. Public Key
              Identifier (PKI).</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="five-dot-four-dot-seven-web-services-op-vertical-layer-cp">
        <title id="five-dot-four-dot-seven-web-services-op-vertical-layer-cp-title">Web Services
        (Vertical Layer)</title>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="right" fileref="../figures/STF_Web_Services.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-seven-dot-one-analogy">
          <title id="five-dot-four-dot-seven-dot-one-analogy-title">Analogy</title>

          <para><emphasis>The presence and the wellness of a person, imply that the person is in the
          position to provide the information in his hands. In addition to being aware of the
          presence of a person, one should also recognize the person (knowing the person) and know
          for example his profession or the type of information he can provide, in order to collect
          useful information from that person. Moreover, a person can attend a meeting for multiple
          purposes: learn (listening only), actively contribute (active dialogue) or provide
          information (giving a presentation).</emphasis></para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-seven-dot-two-definition-of-web-services-layer">
          <title
          id="five-dot-four-dot-seven-dot-two-definition-of-web-services-layer-title">Definition of
          Web Services layer</title>

          <para>The web services specification chapter will mainly be used when the information
          exchange can take place via web-services. The web-services description will contain at
          least the following components: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Information exchange scenarios for the Service Oriented Architecture
                information exchange (containing information on whether data will be pulled or
                pushed, using mechanisms like publish-subscribe, request-response, etc.).</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>A detailed description of the web-services interface, defining the methods
                that can be called, arguments to be provided and answers to be expected. This part
                might refer to schemas and WSDL file.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The Service Metadata specification, which will contain the description of the
                services based on a set of metadata containing useful information for all COIs, to
                enable the discovery of the information providers.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="five-dot-four-dot-eight-operational-cross-dash-domain-op-vertical-layer-cp">
        <title
        id="five-dot-four-dot-eight-operational-cross-dash-domain-op-vertical-layer-cp-title">Operational
        Cross-Domain (Vertical Layer)</title>

        <informalfigure>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="right" fileref="../figures/STF_Operational.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </informalfigure>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-eight-dot-one-analogy">
          <title id="five-dot-four-dot-eight-dot-one-analogy-title">Analogy</title>

          <para><emphasis>Within the usage of a common language such as English, different users
          will develop their own vocabulary and associated specific meaning to words related to
          their core business. If a patient with a basic knowledge meets a doctor and the doctor
          does not adapt his vocabulary (medical terminology) to the daily vocabulary, the patient
          will not really understand what the doctor says. Sometimes the patient might have the
          perception to understand the doctor since he has a vague idea of the meaning of medical
          terms, but for sure he will not grasp the details. Moreover, a person visiting a foreign
          country needs a translator to help him communicate with the local people in case he does
          not speak the local language. Unfortunately, in most of the translations, a loss of
          information and meaning will occur.</emphasis></para>

          <figure id="v5a-f9">
            <title>Human Association between different information</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/Brain.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="five-dot-four-dot-eight-dot-two-definition-of-operational-cross-dash-domain-layer">
          <title
          id="five-dot-four-dot-eight-dot-two-definition-of-operational-cross-dash-domain-layer-title">Definition
          of Operational Cross-Domain layer</title>

          <para>Many information exchange STANAGs are normally developed with usage limited to one
          specific Community of Interest (COI), leading to the development of ad-hoc vocabularies to
          fulfil their immediate requirements. The data elements definitions are specifically
          oriented to the COI with direct impact on quality within the COI specific network and
          interoperability with other COI specific systems, with little to no consideration of
          existing STANAGs within or between other COIs.</para>

          <para>This typically results in a lack of interoperability both within the COI (because of
          the availability of multiple COI specific standards) and between COIs.</para>

          <para>The Operational Cross-Domain layer is provided to capture those information exchange
          specifications between COIs or STANAGs at the necessary levels as identified in the
          horizontal layers.</para>

          <para>For example, the data elements defined within two COIs' information exchange
          specifications could be fully overlapping, disjointed or partially overlapping. It is
          essential to associate these data elements and their relationships based on the context
          and content of the information exchange in order to achieve interoperability between the
          COIs. The mapping and harmonization of semantically the same data elements and the
          association of similar data elements has to be captured.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="five-dot-five-stf-design-rules-and-methodology">
      <title id="five-dot-five-stf-design-rules-and-methodology-title">STF Design Rules &amp;
      Methodology</title>

      <para>In this section, for each layer of the STF, the design rules are provided together with
      a description of the supporting XML Schema Definition with examples, followed by the
      methodology of applying the design rules and utilizing the XML Schema Definition.</para>

      <para>For STF Version 1.0, the STF Design Rules &amp; Methodology section is scoped to the
      following:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data Element Dictionary (DED):</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Bit-based</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Structured text-based</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Message Structure (MS):</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Bit-based, Fixed-length</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For plans for the STF Design Rules, please consult <xref
      linkend="future-plans"/>.</para>

      <sect3 id="stf-holistic-process">
        <title id="stf-holistic-process-title">STF Holistic Process</title>

        <para>The definition, application and V&amp;V of the STF layers, design rules and
        methodology is an on-going process that is handled by the iterative process captured in
        <xref linkend="v5a-f10"/>. This is a Holistic Process that can be applied to the STF itself
        as well as for the application of the STF in transforming textual IESs into XML. There are
        explicit points identified for feedback to the STF and IER/IES Stakeholders for possible
        improvements of their products.</para>

        <para>For STF Version 1.0, the STF Holistic Process is depicted below. It is anticipated
        that this Process will be expanded for future versions as additional STF layers are matured
        and provided. For example, once the Business Rules layer has been expanded upon, an
        additional step will have to be added to cover that layer.</para>

        <figure id="v5a-f10">
          <title>STF - Holistic Process</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_Holistic_Process.svg" scalefit="1"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The STF Holistic Process is detailed in the rigorous steps below: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Map IER/IES needs to STF Layers.</emphasis> Analyze the
              IERs with regards to the STF layers to identify the need for specifications at those
              layers (i.e. if there is a requirement to exchange the Information Product via Web
              Services, then a specification for the Web Services STF layer would be necessary).
              Based on these needs, identify existing Standards (IESs) that could fulfill those
              needs. With the STF layered approach, one may find that the same IESs can be reused to
              fulfil multiple types of IERs as well as find that there will be missing IESs that
              need to be developed to fill gaps in the STF layers for that IER. The findings can be
              analysed and corrective actions can be taken by the appropriate stakeholders. In
              particular, possible outcomes of this step could include the following: <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Identified STF gaps where no STF Layer captures IER/IES needs, which
                    should be captured and forwarded to the STF Stakeholders for the possible
                    opportunity to <emphasis role="bold">Improve the STF</emphasis>.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Identified IES gaps where no Standards could be found for a particular
                    layer, which should be captured for submission to the appropriate IER/IES
                    Stakeholders for analysis. Results could be the possible opportunity to
                    <emphasis role="bold">Improve current Standards</emphasis> with the adoption of
                    existing IESs to close the gap or lead to the development of new IESs.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Identified IESs to fulfil each identified STF Layer needed to fulfil IER.
                    For the IESs that specify the format and message structures of the information
                    exchange, <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                          <para><emphasis role="bold">Produce XML representation of DED and MS based
                          on STF.</emphasis> Apply the STF XML schemas at the DED and MS Layers to
                          capture the valid data elements that can be exchanged as part of the
                          information exchange, the order in which they can occur, and constraints
                          on certain aspects of these message exchanges in XML representations.
                          Outcomes of this step could include the following: <itemizedlist>
                              <listitem>
                                <para>Identified problems/gaps within the STF XML schemas for
                                sufficiently capturing the information exchange DED and MS, which
                                should be captured and forwarded to the STF Stakeholders for the
                                possible opportunity to <emphasis role="bold">Improve the
                                STF</emphasis>.</para>
                              </listitem>

                              <listitem>
                                <para>Identified problems within the textual IESs, which should be
                                captured as Possible Errata for submission to the appropriate
                                IER/IES Stakeholders for the possible opportunity to <emphasis
                                role="bold">Improve the Standards</emphasis>.</para>
                              </listitem>

                              <listitem>
                                <para>XML files of transformed Standards. Once the Standards have
                                been transformed into XML, the XML files have to be V&amp;V'd to
                                ensure they properly capture the existing IES. Using existing XML
                                Technology and Tools, one is able to perform the following V&amp;V
                                steps on the resultant XML files: <itemizedlist>
                                    <listitem>
                                      <para><emphasis role="bold">Automatic Conversion to Human-Readable
                                      Formats.</emphasis> Automatically produce the equivalent
                                      human-readable documents from the XML files to be provided to the
                                      IES Stakeholders to be analyzed for correctness. Results of this
                                      could be exploited to <emphasis role="bold">Improve the
                                      Standards</emphasis>.</para>
                                    </listitem>
                                  </itemizedlist></para>
                              </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist></para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist></para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="data-bearer-design-rules-and-methodology">
        <title id="data-bearer-design-rules-and-methodology-title">Data Bearer Design Rules &amp;
        Methodology</title>

        <para>Not yet addressed within the current version of the STF.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="routing-design-rules-and-methodology">
        <title id="routing-design-rules-and-methodology-title">Routing Design Rules &amp;
        Methodology</title>

        <para>Not yet addressed within the current version of the STF.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="data-element-dictionary-layer-design-rules-and-methodology">
        <title id="data-element-dictionary-layer-design-rules-and-methodology-title">Data Element
        Dictionary Layer Design Rules &amp; Methodology</title>

        <para>The purpose of the Data Element Dictionary layer is to capture the data elements, or
        vocabulary, of the Information Exchange STANAG.</para>

        <para>In general, there are different types of Information Exchanges that can occur which
        can be categorized based on the way the data being exchanged between systems is represented.
        In particular, within the STF, the following three types have been identified-- bit-based,
        text based and XML-based, the last being a highly-structured text based information
        exchange.</para>

        <para>The STF Data Element Dictionary layer has been defined in such a way that it is
        applicable to all types of information exchanges. The machine-interpretable STF-related XML
        specifications provide, where required, support for the different types of exchanges by
        defining a specific adapter of the XML Schema Definition.</para>

        <sect4 id="ded-concepts">
          <title id="ded-concepts-title">DED Concepts</title>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">ISO/IEC 11179 Data Modelling</emphasis></para>

          <para>As considered by ISO/IEC 11179, there are three main relationships related to
          semantic theory and the basic principles of data modelling that should be addressed when
          identifying, defining and grouping data elements. These are the following:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Between generic and more specific concepts (e.g. "Altitude" vs. "Altitude in 25
              FT increments above MSL")</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Between a concept and its terminology (e.g. "Location" vs "Position")</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Between a concept and its usage/context (e.g. "Latitude" + "target" = "Latitude
              of target")</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Within STF, the first two relationships are captured within the Data Element
          Dictionary layer. The third relationship can be captured either in the Data Element
          Dictionary or in the Message Structure layer (see below).</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">Usage vs. Context</emphasis></para>

          <para>In Merriam-Webster online dictionary, the word <ulink
          url="http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/context">context</ulink> can refer to two
          slightly different, but related meanings:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>the parts of a discourse that surround a word or passage and can throw light on
              its meaning</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>the interrelated conditions in which something exists or occurs : environment,
              setting</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Within STF, the context, or the third data modelling relationship, can be captured
          either explicitly as a different Data Element or implicitly as a data field within the
          Message Structure layer. The reason for this is that, often, the specific meaning of a
          Data Element could be provided by how it is being used (i.e. Latitude of target vs
          Latitude of shooter). However, the context could also describe the environment in which
          the data element exists (i.e. Latitude is a data field within the Target Position
          Message). This could be considered a different usage, hence a different Data Element, but
          not necessarily so.</para>

          <para>Furthermore, the type of Information Exchange may have impact on the way the Data
          Element Concept and Data Elements are defined as e.g. the different representations of
          bit-based Information Exchanges might be considered different uses.</para>

          <para>For the purpose of the STF and to support reuse and data harmonization, it is highly
          recommended that the end user captures the context relationship within the Message
          Structure layer rather than as an explicit data element.</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Element Concept/Data Elements</emphasis></para>

          <para>These are two related concepts within the STF Data Element Dictionary layer that
          capture the first two relationships. The <emphasis role="bold">Data Element
          Concept</emphasis> maps to the generic, "conceptual" concept while the <emphasis
          role="bold">Data Elements</emphasis> map to the more specific, "concrete" concepts. In
          particular, the Data Elements in the STF DED are organised based on a thesauri, in support
          of the Data Coherence goal of the NNEC Data Strategy, whereby the Data Element Concepts
          group together semantically equivalent data elements that might be represented within a
          STANAG using different terminology and/or granularity. Different possible instantiations
          of a Data Element Concept are described with the use of one or more Data Elements.</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold"> Data Element </emphasis></para>

          <para>A Data Element captures a specific concept with a specific representation, and
          possibly with a specific usage. It is the atomic unit of data that has a precise meaning
          and precise semantics for that domain. Such a data element can be stored or exchanged
          between computer systems.</para>

          <para>Some important Data Element properties:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Data Elements are instantiated in the context of a message as a Data Field (see
              further 5.5.4) in the Message Structure layer.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>As defined, Data Elements are atomic units of data, and therefore are
              unstructured (e.g. non-complex types). To capture parent-child relationships, data
              elements should be instantiated as data fields within a Word of a Message
              Structure.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Data Elements provide the information on how to handle and interpret the value
              as exchanged, i.e. how to decode the value as transmitted to something meaningful for
              computers or humans and how to encode such meaningful value to the representation for
              transmission. This is similar to the "serialization" concept in information
              systems.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>For example, the exchange representation might be some binary or string
                  value, for which the meaningful value might be the altitude in meters or the
                  country name.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The coding information of a Data Element can specify a mapping between exchanged
              values and the real values, e.g. mapping the text value NL to The Netherlands for a
              text-based Information Exchange or mapping the numerical value 3 to FRIEND for a
              binary Information Exchange.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>For numerical Data Elements, the specification can include a conversion method
              from the exchanged representation to the meaningful value, e.g. a binary value might
              indicate the altitude in multiples of 10 meters.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Additional information is captured on the meaning of the Data Element, e.g. in
              the case of numerical values which unit the value has (degrees, data miles, meters,
              etc) and which type (integer or floating point number, boolean, etc).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>In the situation where the coding of a Data Element depends on the value of
              another Data Element, the DED provides a construct called a CodingSwitch | Coding
              Switch. The Coding Switch construct allows to capture explicitly which other Data
              Element (actually, the instantiated Data Field version) should be inspected and
              depending on its value how the first Data Element should be decoded/encoded. For
              example, a Scale Indicator Data Element might control that the Altitude Data Element
              is reporting the altitude in multiples of 100 or 500 feet increments. This construct
              is especially used in the binary information exchanges for space optimization.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Within the STF, a <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_element">data
          element</ulink> is composed of and defined by:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>An identification including the <ulink
              url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_element_name">data element name</ulink> and a
              unique identifier:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The name given to the data element within the context of the STANAG, not
                  necessarily unique although recommended.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The unique identifier is used to uniquely refer to the Data Element within
                  the context of the STANAG.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>A clear <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_element_definition">data
              element definition</ulink>:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>A human readable phrase or sentence associated with the data element within
                  a data dictionary that describes the meaning or semantics of a data
                  element.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>One or more <ulink
              url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representation_term">representation
              terms</ulink>:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>A word, or a combination of words, that semantically represent the data type
                  (value domain) of a data element.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Optional enumerated values:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>System of valid symbols that substitute for longer values <ulink
                  url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ISO/IEC_11179">ISO/IEC 11179</ulink>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>An optional list of synonyms to data elements in other STANAGs or Metadata
              Registries:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Data elements that are considered semantically equivalent for the purposes
                  of information retrieval.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Optionally, additional metadata depending on the type of information
              exchange.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>It has to be stressed that proper and clear <ulink
          url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_element_definition">data element
          definitions</ulink> are critical for external users of any data system, since a good
          definition can ease the process of data element harmonization, where one set of data
          elements are mapped into another set of data elements.</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Element Concept</emphasis></para>

          <para>The Data Element Concept is the agreed upon term for a generic concept used to
          represet a set of common data elements.</para>

          <para>Within the STF, a data element concept is identified by:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The Name given to the Data Element Concept within the context of the STANAG, not
              necessarily unique although recommended</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The Data Element Concept Identifier, which is the unique identifier used to
              refer to the Data Element Concept within the context of the STANAG.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Element Dictionary</emphasis></para>

          <para>A collection of data element concepts and associated data elements that are used to
          specify the message exchange. Within STF, the XML file containing all Data Elements within
          a certain domain is called a Data Element Dictionary (DED) for that domain.</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Element Concept/Data Element Identification
          (DECI/DEI)</emphasis></para>

          <para>To promote reuse, to ease harmonization and to provide meaning to the data elements,
          it is necessary to be able to uniquely identify each Data Element in an explict and
          unambigious way. Each Data Element Concept is identified by a numerical ID, <emphasis
          role="bold">data element concept identifier (deci)</emphasis>, unique within the
          particular dictionary and each Data Element is identified by a numerical ID, <emphasis
          role="bold">data element identifier (dei)</emphasis>, unique within a Data Element
          Concept.</para>

          <para>The combination of the DECI/DEI values is used to uniquely reference a particular
          Data Element. This approach can be easily mapped on that used by various other communities
          to reference Data Elements, for example:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>the MTF community uses the FFIRN/FUD (Field Format Index Reference Number/Field
              Use Designator)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>the TDL community uses the DFI/DUI (Data Field Identifier/Data Use
              Identifier)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Element Concept/Data Element Examples</emphasis></para>

          <para>The following table provides some examples of Data Element Concepts and Data
          Elements.</para>

          <table frame="all">
            <title>Examples of Data Element Concepts and Data Elements</title>

            <tgroup cols="2">
              <colspec colwidth="40*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="60*"/>

              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Data Element Concept</entry>

                  <entry>Data Elements</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Altitude</entry>

                  <entry>Altitude in 25 FT increments, Altitude in 100 FT increments</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Heading</entry>

                  <entry>Wind direction, Course</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Latitude</entry>

                  <entry>Latitude (accurate in 0.04 minutes), Latitude (accurate in 0.005
                  minutes)</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Platform</entry>

                  <entry>Air platform, Surface platform, Subsurface platform, Land platform, Space
                  platform</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="data-element-dictionary-logical-model">
          <title id="data-element-dictionary-logical-model-title">Data Element Dictionary Logical
          Model</title>

          <para>This logical model shows the relationship between these concepts to support the
          definition of a generic data element dictionary to be used for information exchanges. The
          attributes shown in the classes denote relevant information that needs to be captured on
          the classes or indicate a relationship between classes (e.g. dei).</para>

          <figure id="v5a-f11">
            <title>Data Element Dictionary Logical Model</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_Data_Element_Dictionary_Logical_Model.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>The Data Element Dictionary XML Schemas are derived from this logical model, fully
          elaborated to include all components (elements and attributes) that are required to model
          the generic data element dictionaries for all types of information exchanges.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="known-limitations">
          <title id="known-limitations-title">Known Limitations</title>

          <para>There are some known shortcomings in Version 1.0 of the STF Data Element Dictionary
          XML Schemas and Logical Model in supporting all types of information exchanges. These are
          described here:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The logic behind a Formula is not represented in machine-interpretable XML and
              is therefore still open for interpretation by developers etc. Alternatives are
              defining standard Formulas (stored in a catalogue) which can be referenced from the
              data elements. The standard Formula can use XML elements to describe e.g. simple
              mathematical operations (e.g. multiplication with a certain factor). More complex
              operations (e.g. for positional information like latitude and longitude) will require
              more work or maybe even external references.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The Unit of a DataElement is defined as a simple string (e.g. "METER", "SECOND",
              "DATAMILE") without any restriction or coupling to external standards. Whenever there
              is a standard defining such unit there should be a way to link to that.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>These are being considered although not yet planned for the next version of the STF
          Design Rules.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="ded-design-rules">
          <title id="ded-design-rules-title">DED Design Rules</title>

          <para>Based on the type of information exchange and data representation of the Data
          Elements, a specific adapter (extension) of the common Data Element Dictionary XML Schema
          (DataElementDictionary-*.xsd) shall be used to capture the Data Elements in an XML
          representation to fulfil the Data Element Dictionary layer of the STF.</para>

          <figure id="v5a-f12">
            <title>Data Element Dictionary</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/Data_Element_Dictionary.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>Below are the design rules with the methodology on how to apply them to create the
          STANAG-specific XML file that captures the data element dictionary for a particular
          information exchange:</para>

          <para>Rule 1: The DataElementDictionary-BitBased.xsd shall be applied in case the
          Information Exchange is bit-based, e.g. GMTI, Link16, DIS.</para>

          <para>Rule 2: The DataElementDictionary-TextBased.xsd shall be applied in case the
          Information Exchange is based on structured text, e.g. MTF.</para>

          <para>Rule 3: (Future work) - The DataElementDictionary-XMLBased.xsd shall be applied in case the
          Information Exchange is based on XML. <emphasis>This XSD is not provided within the
          current version of the STF.</emphasis></para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="methodology-for-data-element-dictionary-definition">
          <title id="methodology-for-data-element-dictionary-definition-title">Methodology for Data
          Element Dictionary definition</title>

          <para>Step 0: Based on the process in place for defining the IES, like [APP-15], decide on
          the required type of message exchange being bit-based, text-based or XML-based.</para>

          <para>Step 1: Data Elements Guidance|Identify all Data Elements, being the atomic units of
          data required for the information exchange.</para>

          <para>As you are identifying your Data Elements, start to group similar data elements
          together that share the same functional concept, but have different representation or
          view. For instance 'Latitude Degrees Minutes Seconds' and 'Latitude Decimal Degrees' both
          share the same concept 'Latitude', but are expressed by using different data
          representation types.</para>

          <para>Step 2: For each Data Element, define the following:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Identification:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Typically the name of the data element as defined in the STANAG, e.g.
                  "latitude" from NFFI or "Country Code" from APP-6A. If the STANAG defines similar
                  data element concepts with the same formats, but use different "labels" or "names"
                  for them, such as "Identification" vs. "ID", they should be defined using the same
                  data element.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Assign a Data Element Concept Identifier (number) and a Data Element
                  Identifier (number), consulting the custodian for guidance.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Data element definition:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Text that describes the meaning or semantics from the data element, e.g.
                  "Angular distance north or south of the earth's equator measured in decimal
                  degrees WGS-84" or "Identifies the country with which a symbol is
                  associated"</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Representation terms:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Semantically represents the data element covering the data type and, if
                  applicable, the unit, e.g. for a latitude specify double as type and decimal
                  degrees as unit, or specify for Country Code string as a type and no specified
                  unit.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Enumerated values:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The list of mappings between symbols and their meaning, if
                  applicable.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Synonyms:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Identify data elements within other STANAGs or meta data registries that are
                  interchangeable in the context without changing the truth value of the proposition
                  in which they are embedded</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Step 3: If defining a new Data Element, verify whether an existing Data Element can
          be reused by consulting the preferred data element within the meta-data registry (see
          Data Elements Guidance| Data Harmonization).</para>

          <para>Step 4: Depending on the type of information exchange, additionally define the
          following:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>For bit-based information exchange:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify the length in bits of the Data Element for exchange</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>For numerical data elements, specify the used bit-coding which captures how
                  a value is represented in binary, in particular relevant for signed numbers (e.g.
                  unsigned, twos-complement, ...).</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>For text-based information exchange:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify the character set allowed for exchange, e.g. only "alphanumeric and
                  dash" and/or a regular expression specifying what values are allowed</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Specify the minimum and/or maximum length in characters, e.g. 10-30</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>For XML-based information exchange:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>It is supposed that an XSD is defined within the STANAG that defines the XML
                  data elements. If this is not the case, first define this XSD.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>With respect to the data element dictionary, map every Data Element Concept
                  to the corresponding XML element in the XSD.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>More specific steps will be provided in STF version 2.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Step 5: Once the data elements have been defined create the XML document
          representing the DED for the STANAG. For that, apply the respective XML Schema as
          prescribed by the design rules to populate with the information identified above.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="description-of-the-ded-xml-schema-definitions">
          <title id="description-of-the-ded-xml-schema-definitions-title">Description of the DED XML
          Schema Definitions</title>

          <para>The following sections describe the XML Schema definitions used to capture the Data
          Element Dictionary.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="base-dataelementdictionary-xml-schema">
          <title id="base-dataelementdictionary-xml-schema-title">Base DataElementDictionary XML
          Schema</title>

          <para>The base DataElementDictionary XML Schema provides the common elements used for
          capturing the Data Elements. These common elements are depicted in <xref
          linkend="v5a-f13"/> followed by a short description.</para>

          <figure id="v5a-f13">
            <title>Structure for Data Element Dictionary XML Schema</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_DataElementDictionary_structure.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">DataElementDictionary:</emphasis> Denotes the top level
              element containing the Data Element Dictionary for the specific Information Exchange
              as defined in the BaselineInfo element.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">BaselineInfo:</emphasis> Contains the meta-data for this
              STANAG like its title, identifier, version, security markings, etc. and is further
              described below.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">DataElementConcept:</emphasis> Describes a Data Element
              Concept which includes a single concept and is the generic representation of the Data
              Elements grouped under it.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">DataElement:</emphasis> Describes a Data Element, which is
              a representative of the corresponding Data Element Concept. It is further described in
              the section below.</para>

              <para>The example below depicts the top-level elements of the XML instance document of
              the Data Element Dictionary for STANAG 5516 showing the root element, the
              BaselineInfo details (explained in the next section) and one of the
              DataElementConcepts.</para>

              <figure id="v5a-f14">
                <title>Example of Data Element Dictionary XML instance for Link 16</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_DataElementDictionary_example_link16.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="baselineinfo-xml-schema">
          <title id="baselineinfo-xml-schema-title">BaselineInfo XML Schema</title>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">BaselineInfo</emphasis> element is further detailed in
          <xref linkend="v5a-f15"/> followed by a short description of its main elements.</para>

          <figure id="v5a-f15">
            <title>Structure for BaselineInfo XML Schema</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_BaselineInfo_structure.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Title</emphasis>: Provides the name given to the STANAG as
              Configuration Item (CI). Enables the user to find the CI with a particular title or
              carry out more accurate searches. The title is commonly used as the key point of
              reference in the list of search results. Examples are "TACTICAL DATA EXCHANGE - LINK
              16" and "NATO IMPLEMENTATION CODES AND RULES".</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">AlternativeTitle</emphasis>: Provides any form of the
              title used as a substitute or alternative to the formal title of the Configuration
              Item (CI). Examples are "Link16 spec" and "NICR".</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Identifier</emphasis>: Provides an unambiguous reference
              to the STANAG as Configuration Item (CI) within the context of specific community. An
              internal, external, and/or universal identification number for a data asset or
              resource. Examples are "STANAG 5516", "ADatP-31" and "NICR T/1".</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">BaselineVersion</emphasis>: Provides the edition or
              version of the STANAG as Configuration Item. Examples are "edition 5" and "edition 6,
              first draft".</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Version</emphasis>: Provides the internal version number
              of the instance document.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Component</emphasis>: Identifies the STF component of the
              specification that this instance document contains. This element explicitly indicates
              what is implied by the root element to support discovery. Examples are
              "MessageStructure" and "DataElementDictionary".</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Security</emphasis>: Contains the security markings for
              the instance document (i.e. the specification) and is further described in the next
              section.</para>

              <para>See the section above on the Base DataElementDictionary for an example of the
              usage of the BaselineInfo element.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="security-xml-schema">
          <title>Security XML Schema</title>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Security</emphasis> element provides specific Information
          Assurance (IA) metadata for data objects; supports typical existing security labels to
          express policy, classification and category attributes. It is depicted in <xref
          linkend="v5a-f16"/> followed by a short description of its main elements.</para>

          <figure id="v5a-f16">
            <title>Structure for Security XML Schema</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_Security_structure.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">PolicyIdentifier</emphasis>: Identifies the nation or
              organization responsible for creating, maintaining, and implementing the security
              policy to be applied to the information. The security policy is understood as a set of
              rules for protecting information against unauthorized discloser, while maintaining
              authorized access, and preventing loss of unauthorized modification. The policy bodies
              of different security domains must agree on a common understanding of the handling
              requirements for information of a particular sensitivity. After the understanding
              exists, mappings from one security policy to another can be created (see Reference
              EAPC(AC/322-SC/5)N(2006)0008). For example, NATO, NATO/EAPC, NATO/PFP, NATO/EU,
              NATO/RUSSIA, NATO/UKRAINE. National use includes: USA, FRA, GBR, NLD, etc.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Classification</emphasis>: Provides security markings that
              indicate the sensitivity level of the information (see Reference :
              EAPC(AC/322-SC/5)N(2006)0008). Examples as defined in AC/322-D(2004)0021 and in
              "Guidance on the use of metadata element descriptions for use in NDMS" are UNMARKED,
              UNCLASSIFIED, RESTRICTED, CONFIDENTIAL, SECRET, and COSMIC TOP SECRET.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Category</emphasis>: Provides an indication of an
              additional, specific sensitivity, or a dissemination control, or an informational
              marking on which no automated access control is performed (see Reference :
              EAPC(AC/322-SC/5)N(2006)0008). Special category designator include ATOMAL, CRYPTO,
              SIOP, SIOP ESI. Dissemination Limitation Markings include EXCLUSIVE, INTELLIGENCE,
              LOGISTICS, OPERATIONS. Release categories include RELEASABLE TO, RELEASABLE FOR (e.g.
              RELEASABLE TO ISAF or RELEASABLE FOR INTERNET TRANSMISSION). Administrative markings
              include MANAGEMENT, STAFF, PERSONAL, MEDICAL, COMMERCIAL.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">type</emphasis> (attribute for Category): Can be one of
              permissive, restrictive or informational.</para>

              <para>See the section above on the Base DataElementDictionary for an example of the
              usage of the Security element.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="dataelement-xml-schema">
          <title>DataElement XML Schema</title>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">DataElement</emphasis> XML element describes a Data
          Element, which is a representative of the corresponding Data Element Concept. It denotes
          the actual Data Element and contains the Data Items (DIs) used to compose the Data
          Element. The combination of a Data Element Concept Identifier (deci) and a Data Element
          Identifier (dei) uniquely defines a Data Element. The <emphasis
          role="bold">DataElement</emphasis> XML element is depicted in <xref linkend="v5a-f17"/>
          followed by a short description of its main elements.</para>

          <figure id="v5a-f17">
            <title>Structure for Data Element XML Schema</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_DataElement_structure.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">DataElementName:</emphasis> Provides the name of this Data
              Element.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">dei</emphasis> (attribute of DataElement): Specifies the
              Data Element Identifier, which needs to be unique within the parent Data Element
              Concept.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">type</emphasis> (attribute of DataElement): Provides a
              mechanism to differentiate between types of Data Elements, for example data elements
              used as spare, disused ones, required for the structure of a message, or holding
              actual data. The following values are currently supported by STF: <informaltable
                  frame="all">
                  <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colwidth="50*"/>

                    <colspec colwidth="50*"/>

                    <thead>
                      <row>
                        <entry>DataElement type</entry>

                        <entry>Meaning</entry>
                      </row>
                    </thead>

                    <tbody>
                      <row>
                        <entry>spare</entry>

                        <entry>Indicates this Data Element denotes a spare; a data element that, on
                        transmissions, will be encoded as zero and shall not be processed upon
                        receipt. Messages shall not be discarded upon receipt of non-zero spare
                        fields.</entry>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <entry>disused</entry>

                        <entry>Indicates this Data Element denotes a disused element which are spare
                        fields that previously had a valid meaning. When transmitted, Disused fields
                        shall be encoded as 0 and shall not be processed upon receipt. Messages
                        shall not be discarded upon receipt of a nonzero Disused field.</entry>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <entry>structure</entry>

                        <entry>Indicates this Data Element is used to define the structure of a
                        message or word. This includes Data Elements that define which message or
                        word is handled (e.g. for the message label) or Data Elements that act
                        purely as a structure switch and do not itself represent any
                        information.</entry>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <entry>data</entry>

                        <entry>Indicates this Data Element is carying real (tactical) data.</entry>
                      </row>
                    </tbody>
                  </tgroup>
                </informaltable></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">DataElementExplanation:</emphasis> Provides an explanation
              of how to use this Data Element</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">ShortName:</emphasis> Provides a short version of the
              DataElementName, which can be used to refer to the DataElement. It is aimed to make
              this ShortName unique over all Data Elements, but this cannot be guaranteed at this
              time.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Security:</emphasis> Provides the ability to provide
              additional security markings for the DataElement. If none is specified it takes the
              security markings from the BaselineInfo.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Remark:</emphasis> Provides an optional remark for this
              Data Element specification.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Unit:</emphasis> Specifies the measurement unit for this
              Data Element, e.g. Meters, Degrees, Feet. The possible units are specific for a STANAG
              although preferably units should be used that are defined in standards. If no unit is
              specified, the value is without unit which is true for all pure enumerations. If the
              coding for this Data Element utilizes a CodingSwitch (i.e. the coding depends on the
              value of another Data Field), the unit can be different for different coding variants.
              In that case the Unit should be specified within the CodingSwitch.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">ValueType:</emphasis> Specifies the specific type of value
              that is represented, e.g. Double, Integer or Enumeration. The current list of types
              can be extended if required. If the coding for this Data Element utilizes a
              CodingSwitch (i.e. the coding depends on the value of another Data Field), the value
              type can also be different for different coding variants. In that case the ValueType
              should be specified within the CodingSwitch.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Formula:</emphasis> Specifies the Formula needed to decode
              the decimal value to a meaningful value of a Data Element</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">CodingSwitch:</emphasis> Defines a decoding switch
              indicating that, based on the value of the referenced DataField, this DataElement
              needs to be decoded in a certain way. E.g. the referenced DataElement specifies that
              this DataElement needs to be interpreted as an altitude in either 1 meter, 10 meters
              or 100 meters increment.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Enum:</emphasis> Defines a mapping from the exchanged
              value in a message to its meaning. Mappings can be provided to text (e.g. the reported
              numerical value 3 means FRIEND, or the reported textual value SV means Surface
              Vessel), or to the real, meaningful value (e.g. reporting the binary latitude as a
              double). In case the mapping to a meaningful value is provided, normally not all
              possible values are enumerated but instead the mapping from a range of binary values
              to a range of meaningful values (e.g. "0 through 2047" maps to "0 through 511 3/4 data
              miles"). The enumeration element provides information to encode and decode the
              exchanged value to a meaningful value for processing or to present as human-readable
              information. The CodingSwitch and Enum elements are further detailed below.</para>

              <para>The example below depicts two examples of the representation of a Data Element,
              one for a bit-based Data Element from STANAG 5516 and one for a text-based Data
              Element from STANAG 5500.</para>

              <figure id="v5a-f18">
                <title>Example of DataElement XML instance for Link 16</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_DataElement_example_link16.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>

              <para>The above example demonstrates how the various elements can be used for a
              bit-based data element that represent a numerical value (see ValueType element). Note
              that the Formula that produces the meaningful value for this Data Element only is
              valid for a specific range of the raw value. The remaining values (so 11..14 and 15)
              are only valid as enumerations.</para>

              <para>The logic of the actual formula is not covered by the STF yet, although a
              limited number of formulas can be defined, each with its own explicit semantics. In
              this case, the LinearExpressionIntegerFormula will produce a meaningful value by
              taking two parameters, offset and factor, and applying the formula: meaningful-value =
              exchanged-value * factor + offset The definition of the formulas is under discussion
              and will be considered for the next version of the STF.</para>

              <figure id="v5a-f19">
                <title>Example of DataElement XML instance for ADatP-3</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_DataElement_example_formets.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>

              <para>The above example demonstrates the use of the Enum elements for pure mappings,
              in this case for a text-based format. For the first Data Element, the exchanged value
              of JAN is decoded as JANUARY, while for the second Data Element, the values are
              encoded as numbers starting with 01 for JANUARY.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="dataelement-enum-xml-schema">
          <title>DataElement Enum XML Schema</title>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Enum</emphasis> XML element defines a mapping from the
          actual value as exchanged in a message to its meaning. It is depicted in <xref
          linkend="v5a-f20"/> followed by a short description of its main elements.</para>

          <figure id="v5a-f20">
            <title>Structure for Enum XML Schema</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_DataElement_Enum_structure.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>The XML Schema does not cover the aspect of the exchanged value as this mapping
          depends on the type of exchange (bit-based vs. text-based) and therefore the way to
          describe the exchanged value is type specific and is described in the respective
          sections.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">type</emphasis> (attribute): Provides a mechanism to
              differentiate between types of Data Items, i.e. values, to further support automated
              interpretation. Currently the following types are supported: <informaltable
                  frame="all">
                  <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colwidth="50*"/>

                    <colspec colwidth="50*"/>

                    <thead>
                      <row>
                        <entry>Enum type</entry>

                        <entry>Meaning</entry>
                      </row>
                    </thead>

                    <tbody>
                      <row>
                        <entry>disused</entry>

                        <entry>Indicates a Data Item value that was previously named but is no
                        longer valid. A DISUSED value cannot be renamed without determining if
                        coordinated implementation is required.</entry>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <entry>undefined</entry>

                        <entry>Indicates a term used to describe a code that has no value currently
                        assigned but may have a value assigned in the future. (This occurs in
                        logically coded Data Elements in which all the Data Items in the Data
                        Element do not have assigned values.)</entry>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <entry>illegal</entry>

                        <entry>Indicates a term used to describe a code that is not a permissible
                        entry into the tactical data system(s) supporting the interface, e.g., a 9
                        bit Data Element called HEADING that has legal values of 0 through 359
                        representing degrees has illegal values of 360 through 511.</entry>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <entry>no statement</entry>

                        <entry>Indicates no information on this Data Element is being transmitted.
                        (This does not necessarily indicate that the originator does not have the
                        information.)</entry>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <entry>unknown</entry>

                        <entry>Indicates other values available for this Data Element have not been
                        determined by the originator.</entry>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <entry>to be determined</entry>

                        <entry>Indicates that Data Item design is incomplete. (Data Items and codes
                        will be specified at a later time.)</entry>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <entry>data</entry>

                        <entry>Indicates actual data.</entry>
                      </row>

                      <row>
                        <entry>reserved</entry>

                        <entry>Indicates that this value is reserved for future use.</entry>
                      </row>
                    </tbody>
                  </tgroup>
                </informaltable></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">DataItem</emphasis>: Provides the description and/or
              decoded value of this enumeration.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Explanation</emphasis>: Provides an additional explanation
              for this Data Item only when necessary for amplification.</para>

              <para>See the DataElement example above for examples on Enums, both for bit-based and
              for text-based information exchanges.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="dataelement-codingswitch-xml-schema">
          <title>DataElement CodingSwitch XML Schema</title>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">CodingSwitch</emphasis> XML element provides a way to
          specify that the encoding/decoding of a DataElement depends on the value of another
          DataElement. For example, an Altitude DataElement has a value of 5 which means an actual
          altitude of either 5 meter or 50 meter, indicated by the value of an Altitude Scale
          Indicator DataElement. Such a construct is typically used within bit-based information
          exchanges for space efficiency. Note that the <emphasis
          role="bold">CodingSwitch</emphasis> can be nested for the situation where the coding is
          dependent on multiple data elements.</para>

          <para>The CodingSwitch XML element is depicted in <xref linkend="v5a-f21"/> followed by a
          short description of its main elements.</para>

          <figure id="v5a-f21">
            <title>Structure for CodingSwitch XML Schema</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_DataElement_CodingSwitch_structure.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">deci</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">dei</emphasis>:
              Indicates the Data Element Concept Identifier (deci) and Data Element Identifier (dei)
              of the referenced, controlling DataField in the message context whose value is used to
              switch on.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">When</emphasis>: Encapsulates a specific coding for the
              DataElement. The enclosed Case element(s) indicate for which value(s) of the
              referenced DataField this coding should be chosen.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Otherwise</emphasis>: Encapsulates a specific coding for
              the DataElement which is chosen if none of the When branches is selected.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Case</emphasis>: Defines for which value a specific coding
              applies. This is either indicated with a single value or a range of values, the
              specifics of which are defined in the type-specific XSD (i.e. bit-based or
              text-based).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Unit</emphasis>, <emphasis
              role="bold">ValueType</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Formula</emphasis>, <emphasis
              role="bold">Enum</emphasis>: as defined for the DataElement. Their presence within the
              CodingSwitch will overrule any definition provided at a higher level in the
              DataElement.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>

          <para>The example below for the DEPTH Data Element of STANAG 5516 demonstrates the use of
          a CodingSwitch where the actual depth is depending of the value of another DataElement
          that is indicating the multiplication factor.</para>

          <programlisting>
  <xi:include href="program-fragment.txt" parse="text" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
</programlisting>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="bit-dash-based-data-element-dictionary-xml-schema">
          <title>Bit-based Data Element Dictionary XML Schema</title>

          <para>The XML Schema for BitBased Data Element Dictionary extends the base Data Element
          Dictionary XML Schema with the additional information required to capture bit-based Data
          Elements. In particular, it adds the following:</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Length</emphasis> element to the DataElement element
              expressed in number of bits</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">BitCoding</emphasis> element to the DataElement element
              indicating how numerical values are encoded. Possible values are unsigned,
              onesComplement, twosComplement, modifiedTwosComplement, and signMagnitude.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">BitCode</emphasis> element as sub-element of the Enum
              element. Holds the actual numerical value which can be mapped to its meaning held in
              DataItem.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">BitCodeRange</emphasis> element as sub-element of the Enum
              element. Similar to the BitCode element but provides a range of actual values
              instead.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>

          <para>The examples shown before demonstrate the use of these additional elements.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="structured-text-dash-based-data-element-dictionary-xml-schema">
          <title>Structured Text-based Data Element Dictionary XML Schema</title>

          <para>The XML Schema for text-based Data Element Dictionary extends the base Data Element
          Dictionary XML Schema with the additional information required to capture text-based Data
          Elements. In particular, it adds the following:</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">CharacterSet</emphasis> attribute to the DataElement
              element indicating which characters are allowed in the actual value, e.g. only
              uppercase alphabetical characters, or only digits. If unspecified, any character is
              allowed although e.g. for Field or Word separation, specific messages might be
              excluded.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">RegularExpression</emphasis> attribute to the DataElement
              element indicating alone or in addition to the CharacterSet the restriction on the
              actual value of the DataElement by specifying a regular expression, e.g.
              "[0-9]{3,6}[A-Z]" indicating 3 to 6 digits followed by one uppercase alphabetical
              character.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">MinimumLength</emphasis> and <emphasis
              role="bold">MaximumLength</emphasis> attributes to the DataElement element indicating
              the minimum and maximum allowed length of the actual value. If unspecified,
              MinimumLength is interpreted as 0 and MaximumLength as unbounded, although the message
              or transport might impose a maximum.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">StringCode</emphasis> element as sub-element of the Enum
              element. Holds the actual textual value which can be mapped to its meaning held in
              DataItem.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>

          <para>The examples shown before demonstrate the use of these additional elements.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="xml-dash-based-data-element-dictionary-xml-schema">
          <title>XML-based Data Element Dictionary XML Schema</title>

          <para>Not yet addressed within the current version of the STF.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="message-structure-layer-design-rules-and-methodology">
        <title>Message Structure Layer Design Rules &amp; Methodology</title>

        <sect4 id="message-structure-concepts">
          <title>Message Structure Concepts</title>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Field</emphasis>: The instantiation or use of a data
              element.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Word</emphasis>: A structured collection, or container, of
              one or more data fields used to report on a specific aspect. <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>For example, in ADatP-3, within the OWNSITREP message, the LOCATION set
                    provides the Geographic Location of the unit and the LOCAMPN set provides
                    Location Amplification, while in Link-16, within the J3.1 message, the J3.1I
                    word reports on the basic information for an emergency point and J3.1C1 provides
                    the IFF/SIF codes.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Message</emphasis>: A structured collection of one
                    or more words to report a particular set of information.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>For example, the ADatP-3 OWNSITREP message for reporting information
                    regarding own and subordinate units can contain nested sets including the
                    LOCATION and LOCAMPN sets, while the Link-16 J3.2 message for reporting (the
                    state of) an air track can contain the J3.2I, J3.2E0, and J3.2C1 words.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">StructureSwitch</emphasis>: Similar to the concept
                    of a "switch" statement in computer programming, a StructureSwitch is a
                    "conditional construct" that is used as a way to select between alternative data
                    sets within a message structure. It allows for building message structures where
                    the value of a data field defines which following data field(s) are included in
                    the message. StructureSwitches can be nested to support multiple levels of data
                    set selection.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Within the TDL and JISR community, this would be considered as overlaid
                    sets of data fields, where the value of another, referenced data field, defines
                    which set is present in a word. For example, if in the Link-16 J7.0 message the
                    environment/category data field indicates AIR then the word contains the Air
                    Platform and the Air Platform Activity data fields, while for the GMTI format,
                    if the Segment Type data field specifies Mission Segment the following data is
                    containing the data fields like Mission Plan and Flight Plan.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Element Dictionary</emphasis>: The collection
                    of all Data Elements used in the Messages specified by this information exchange
                    STANAG.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="message-structure-logical-model">
          <title>Message Structure Logical Model</title>

          <para>This logical model shows the relationship between these concepts to support the
          definition of a generic information exchange message structure. The attributes shown in
          the classes denote relevant information that needs to be captured on the classes or
          indicate a relationship between classes (e.g. dui).</para>

          <figure id="v5a-f22">
            <title>Message Structure Logical Model</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_Message_Structure_Logical_Model.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>The Message Structure XML Schemas are derived from this logical model, fully
          elaborated to include all components (elements and attributes) that are required to model
          the generic message structures for all types of information exchanges.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="known-limitations2">
          <title>Known Limitations</title>

          <para>There are some known shortcomings in Version 1.0 of the STF Message Structure XML
          Schemas and Logical Model in supporting all types of information exchange message
          structures. These are described here:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Information exchange specifications sometimes do not specify a container-like
              construct such as the "word" concept defined here. Instead, they define messages as a
              flat collection of data elements.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Messages with a more complex structure cannot be represented with the current
              Message / Word / DataField structure. For example, VMF or the encapsulating protocol
              for Link 22 messages require more nesting support, such as nesting Words within other
              Word containers, to get "Sets", "Segments", etc.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The current structure does not yet support information exchange specifications
              that define messages of variable length by including optional contents (e.g. VMF,
              GMTI, DIS, ASTERIX), but will be enhanced to serve this purpose.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Further details need to be captured in XML on how the data is serialised, e.g.
              big-endian vs. little-endian, bit-order, character coding.</para>

              <para>These are being considered, and extensions, such as the ability to have nested
              Word elements, to the current model to address these limitations will be provided in
              Version 2.0 of the STF Design Rules.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="message-structure-design-rules">
          <title>Message Structure Design Rules</title>

          <para>Based on the type of information exchange specified by the IES, a specific adapter
          (extension) of the common STF Message Structure XML Schema (STFMessageStructure-*.xsd)
          shall be used to capture the Message Structures supporting that information exchange in an
          XML representation to fulfil the Message Structure layer of the STF, as depicted in <xref
          linkend="v5a-f23"/>.</para>

          <figure id="v5a-f23">
            <title>Message Structure with adapters</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/MS_with_adapters.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>Below are the design rules with the methodology on how to apply them to create the
          XML file to capture the message structures for a particular information exchange:</para>

          <para>Rule 1: The MessageStructure-BitBasedFixedLength.xsd shall be applied in case the
          Information Exchange is bit-based and the Message Structure type defines messages of fixed
          length, i.e. no presence of optional contents and use of filler bits.</para>

          <para>Rule 2: (Future work) -The MessageStructure-BitBasedVariableLength.xsd shall be applied in
          case the Information Exchange is bit-based and the Message Structure type defines messages
          of variable length, i.e. presence of optional contents.</para>

          <para><emphasis>This XSD is not provided within the current version of the
          STF.</emphasis></para>

          <para>Rule 3: The MessageStructure-TextBased.xsd shall be applied in case the Information
          Exchange is text-based and the Message Structure type is non-XML.</para>

          <para>Rule 4: (Future work) - The MessageStructure-XMLBased.xsd shall be applied in case the
          Information Exchange is based on XML. This will capture the Container Elements for each
          message. The message structure itself is provided by the XSD as defined in the STANAG. The
          MessageStructure-XMLBased.xsd defines the mapping between the STF Container Elements and
          the corresponding XSD constructs (e.g. xsd:group, xsd:sequence). <emphasis>This XSD is not
          provided within the current version of the STF.</emphasis></para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="methodology-for-message-structure-definition">
          <title>Methodology for Message Structure Definition</title>

          <para>Step 1: Determine which type of message exchange (bit-based fixed length, bit-based
          variable length, text-based or XML-based). Based on this, determine the correct STF XML
          artefact to use and the XML namespace to use for the MS XML instance document that will be
          created to define the information exchange message structures. Bit-based, text-based and
          XML-based types each have their own XML namespace.</para>

          <para>Step 2: Identify all messages to be exchanged.</para>

          <para>Step 3: For each message, identify the grouping constructs. Depending on the format,
          terms like word, group, set, container, segment, PDU, etc. may be used.</para>

          <para>Step 4: For all identified grouping constructs, determine how they should be mapped
          to the 'Word' abstract concept in the STF MS XML Schema. The mapping does not need to be
          one-to-one. For example, extra words may be added if they are necessary to group repeated
          fields even though the specification of the format does not group them.</para>

          <para>Step 5: For each message, determine the data fields that make up the message using
          data elements captured within the STANAG-specific DED XML from <xref
          linkend="data-element-dictionary-layer-design-rules-and-methodology"/>.</para>

          <para>Step 5a: If there is a need within a particular message for a StructureSwitch, then
          for each "switch" pattern, determine the conditions that control the switch.</para>

          <para>Step 6: Identify all properties of the messages, groupings (words) and data fields,
          such as DECI and DEI number, name, title, purpose, remarks, start bits if appropriate,
          fixed and value.</para>

          <para>Step 7: Create the XML instance document representing the MS, according to the
          appropriate XML Schema selected in Step 1.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="description-of-the-message-structure-xml-schema-definitions">
          <title>Description of the Message Structure XML Schema Definitions</title>

          <para>The following sections describe the XML Schema definitions used to capture the
          Message Structure.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="base-message-structure-xml-schema">
          <title>Base Message Structure XML Schema</title>

          <para>The base Message Structure XML Schema provides the common elements used for
          capturing the Message Structure. These common elements are depicted in <xref
          linkend="v5a-f24"/> followed by a short description.</para>

          <figure id="v5a-f24">
            <title>Root level MessageStructure XML Schema Definition</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_MessageStructure_structure.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">MessageStructure:</emphasis> Denotes the top level element
              containing the definition of the structure of the messages for a specific STANAG as
              defined in the BaselineInfo element.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">BaselineInfo:</emphasis> See the section on BaselineInfo
              XML Schema within the description of the DED XML Schema Definitions</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Message:</emphasis> Defines the structure information for
              a particular Message. A Message has some metadata (like a Name and Title) and consists
              of Word elements.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Word:</emphasis> Defines the possible Words that are
              defined for this Message which acts as a container for the actual DataFields. The
              presence or order of the Words within an exchanged Message is not prescribed
              here.</para>

              <para>The Word element is further detailed in the section below followed by a short
              description of its main elements.</para>

              <para>The example in <xref linkend="v5a-f25"/> depicts the top-level elements of the
              XML instance document of the Message Structure for STANAG 5516 showing the root
              element, the BaselineInfo details (explained before) and one of the Messages.</para>

              <figure id="v5a-f25">
                <title>Word XML Schema</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_MessageStructure_example_link16.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="word-xml-schema">
          <title>Word XML Schema</title>

          <para>The structure of the <emphasis role="bold">Word</emphasis> element is shown in <xref
          linkend="v5a-f26"/> followed by a short description of its main elements.</para>

          <figure id="v5a-f26">
            <title>Word within the Generic Message Structure XML Schema Definition</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_MessageStructure_Word_structure.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis> (attribute): Specifies the name of the
              Word including specific characters and/or spaces.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">WordTitle</emphasis>: Specifies the title of the
              Word.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">DataField</emphasis>: Describes a DataField within a Word
              holding the actual data. A DataField refers to a Data Element via the deci and dei.
              The order of the DataFields within a Word is relevant. Optionally a DataField can have
              a fixed value.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">StructureSwitch</emphasis>: Defines a "conditional
              construct" that is used as a way to select between alternative data sets within a
              message structure. Based on the value of the referenced DataField one of a set of
              DataFields is expected. E.g. depending on the value of DataField 'Environment
              Category' (Air, Ground, Surface, etc), either the 'Air platform', 'Ground platform',
              'Surface platform', etc. DataField is present. The StructureSwitch element is built
              from one or more 'When' entries and an optional 'Otherwise' entry each holding one or
              more DataFields and/or nested StructureSwitch elements.</para>

              <para>The figures below depict examples of the representation of a bit-based Word from
              STANAG 5516 and a text-based Message and 2 Words for OTH Gold.</para>

              <figure id="v5a-f27">
                <title>Example of Word XML instance for Link 16</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_MessageStructure_Word_example_link16.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>

              <figure id="v5a-f28">
                <title>Example of Message and 2 Words XML instance for OTH Gold</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_MessageStructure_Message_example_otg.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="structureswitch-xml-schema">
          <title>StructureSwitch XML Schema</title>

          <para>The structure of the <emphasis role="bold">StructureSwitch</emphasis> element is
          shown in <xref linkend="v5a-f29"/> followed by a short description of its main
          elements.</para>

          <figure id="v5a-f29">
            <title>StructureSwitch XML Schema Definition</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_MessageStructure_StructureSwitch_structure.svg"/>
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">deci</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">dei</emphasis>
              (attributes): Indicate the deci and dei numbers of the referenced DataField that is
              the base of the StructureSwitch. Based on the value of te referenced DataField one of
              the When blocks applies or alternatively the Otherwise.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">When</emphasis>: Defines an alternative set of one or more
              DataField(s) or nested StructureSwitch(es). The enclosed Case element(s) indicate for
              which value(s) of the referenced DataField this set should be chosen..</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Otherwise</emphasis>: Defines the alternative set of one
              or more DataField(s) or nested StructureSwitch(es) in case none of the preceding When
              elements was applied (i.e. none of the indicated Case elements).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Case</emphasis>: Specifies the value for the referenced
              DataField for which the enclosing When element is selected and therefore the following
              DataField(s) and/or nested StructureSwitch(es). The value is either indicated with a
              single value or a range of values, the specifics of which are defined in the
              type-specific XSD (i.e. bit-based or text-based). Note that a When element can contain
              multiple Case elements to be able to specify that this When applies for all the
              specified values.</para>

              <para>The example below depicts an example of the representation of a StructureSwitch
              from STANAG 5516. The example specifies that after DataField 758/004, different
              DataFields can occur depending on the value of the DataField 385/003. If its value is
              0, then the DataField will be 376/007, while if the value is 1, the DataField will be
              376/001. Taking the definitions of these DataElements from STANAG 5516 into
              account, this means that the EXERCISE INDICATOR field controls whether the field is
              interpreted as either the IDENTITY field or the IDENTITY AMPLIFYING DESCRIPTOR.</para>

              <figure id="v5a-f30">
                <title>Bit-based Message Structure XML Schema</title>

                <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF_-_MessageStructure_StructureSwitch_example_link16.svg"/>
                  </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </figure>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="bit-dash-based-message-structure-xml-schema">
          <title>Bit-based Message Structure XML Schema</title>

          <para>The XML Schema for BitBased Message Structure extends the base Message Structure XML
          Schema with the additional information required to capture bit-based Message Structures.
          In particular, it adds the following:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">startBit</emphasis> attribute to the DataField element
              expressed as offset in number of bits from 0.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Optional <emphasis role="bold">value</emphasis> attribute to the DataField
              element for holding the fixed value as an unsigned decimal.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Decimal <emphasis role="bold">value</emphasis> attribute of the Case element
              within the StructureSwitch.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The examples shown before demonstrate the use of these additional elements.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="structured-text-dash-based-message-structure-xml-schema">
          <title>Structured text-based Message Structure XML Schema</title>

          <para>The XML Schema for Structured Text-based messages extends the base Message Structure
          XML Schema with the additional information required to capture text-based Message
          Structures. In particular, it adds the following:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Optional <emphasis role="bold">value</emphasis> attribute to the DataField
              element for holding the fixed value as a string.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>String <emphasis role="bold">value</emphasis> attribute of the Case element
              within the StructureSwitch.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Optional <emphasis role="bold">presence</emphasis> attribute to the DataField
              element to indicate whether an actual value is optional or mandatory.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The examples shown before demonstrate the use of these additional elements.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="xml-dash-based-message-structure-xml-schema">
          <title>XML-based Message Structure XML Schema</title>

          <para>Not yet addressed within the current version of the STF.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="business-rules-design-rules-and-methodology">
        <title>Business Rules Design Rules &amp; Methodology</title>

        <para>Not yet addressed within the current version of the STF.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="security-cross-dash-domain-design-rules-and-methodology">
        <title>Security Cross-Domain Design Rules &amp; Methodology</title>

        <para>Not yet addressed within the current version of the STF.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="web-services-design-rules-and-methodology">
        <title>Web Services Design Rules &amp; Methodology</title>

        <para>Not yet addressed within the current version of the STF.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="operational-cross-dash-domain-design-rules-and-methodology">
        <title>Operational Cross-Domain Design Rules &amp; Methodology</title>

        <para>Not yet addressed within the current version of the STF.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="five-dot-six-consequences-sect">
      <title>Consequences</title>

      <para>To fulfil the information exchange requirements from a mid and a long term view it is
      essential to plan the implementation of the guidance from a holistic approach. This means the
      approach needs to achieve improvements which are both efficient and effective. The approach
      should be modular to enable to reuse, while a spiral approach will allow for continual
      learning and improvement. The following key success factors for the STANAG transformation need
      to be considered.</para>

      <sect3 id="efficiency">
        <title id="efficiency-title">Efficiency</title>

        <para>The process of STANAG transformation should result in an improved efficiency from
        multiple perspectives. One of the main aspects of efficiency is to enhance the cost
        effectiveness by reducing manual labour. The reduction of manual labour will also provide an
        advantage by reducing time in STANAG development and maintenance. In particular, this will:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Lead towards faster implementation of Change Proposals (CP) to the
              STANAG.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Facilitate the discovery of ambiguities via automatic verification of both the
              STANAG and the CPs.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Cause a reduction in the need for the manual labour-intensive actions
              (validation, implementation, etc.).</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="effectiveness">
        <title id="effectiveness-title">Effectiveness</title>

        <para>The process of transforming the STANAG towards machine readable STANAGs will increase
        effectiveness: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>By enabling common interpretation of the standards via the non-ambiguous machine
              interpretable STANAGs.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Via the enabling of automated standard validation, in order to find possible
              errors at an earlier stage.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>In the semi-automatic system implementation that are facilitated via the
              creation of machine interpretable STANAGs. This will reduce the human errors in the
              system implementation of the STANAGs and thus lead to better implementations.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>In facilitating the semi-automatic validation of system implementation in order
              to find system failures at an earlier stage. This validation is supported by the
              STANAGs being machine readable.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>By providing the possibility to generate system documentation in a
              semi-automated way, based on the machine interpretable STANAG. Allowing the system
              documentation and system implementation to be always in line for the STANAG
              implementation part.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>In data harmonization by aligning the machine interpretable STANAG to the
              Guidance for XML Naming and Design (GXND) and therefore enabling the registration in
              the NATO Metadata registry and Repository (NMRR) for data element harmonization and
              vocabulary management.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="modularity">
        <title id="modularity-title">Modularity</title>

        <para>The STANAG transformation process aims to result into a modular machine interpretable
        STANAG, which will provide the following advantages compared to the current STANAGs:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Different modules within the STANAG can be reused within other STANAGs.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The components must be derived from the requirements of the different scenarios.
            Nevertheless, after the transformation of the STANAG, it can be applied based on the
            context. E.g. if no security context is needed, the security layer can be either not
            implemented or disabled in specific situations</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Using the modular approach in the STANAG and addressing all different aspects will
            make the STANAG ready to fulfil unforeseen requirements.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="spiral-development">
        <title id="spiral-development-title">Spiral development</title>

        <para>The Spiral development will enable the COI to achieve tangible results by adopting
        early technologies and concepts and learn from their application. This will provide
        operational and administrative benefits since the first deliverable and lessons learned and
        feedback can be retrofitted to the administrative community.</para>

        <para>All consequences of implementing and not implementing a solution whether direct or
        indirect, wanted or unwanted shall be documented to the extent possible. Consequences for at
        least the following areas shall be regarded: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Time</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Cost</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Capabilities</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Security</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Interoperability</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Usability</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Flexibility</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Procedures</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="benefits-of-the-layered-approach">
        <title id="benefits-of-the-layered-approach-title">Benefits of the layered approach</title>

        <para>The use of the layered approach is a wide-spread and well-known concept that has been
        used for years and successful application can be found in the OSI reference model for
        communication protocols and semantic web interoperability. The adoption of this layered
        approach introduces multiple benefits:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Interoperability: Currently, solutions based on the standards attempt to provide
            the overall capability embedded in a single system due to the complexity and unclear
            separation between the different functional areas addressed by the STANAG. The ability
            to verify separate functionalities addressed by the current standards is minimal due to
            their unclear and tangled definitions. By untangling these functionalities and
            presenting them within a layered approach, the different functionalities can be verified
            layer by layer independently. This improves the quality of the standard and therefore
            contributes to overall interoperability.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Scalability: The means to accommodate unforeseen new requirements is enhanced by
            the application of the layered approach to the STANAG. A new layer can be introduced
            leveraging on the other layers in a controlled way, e.g. based on emerging
            requirements.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Flexibility: Each layer describes a specific functionality, where layers can be
            stacked on top of each other. When a specific functionality is not needed (e.g. Security
            cross-domain) for a specific deployment or system role, this approach allows clear
            identification of the parts of the STANAG that do not have to be implemented.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Maintainability: Without using a layered approach, identifying the impact of a
            change in one part of the STANAG to the other parts of the STANAG is often a challenge.
            Making changes to one of the layers in a layered approach will affect the other layers
            in a more controlled and traceable manner.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Therefore, the modular approach as adopted within the information exchange STANAG
        framework allows for maximum reuse of the STANAG layers and a more clear distinction between
        the different functionalities addressed within the STANAG.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="consequences-of-implementing-the-solution">
        <title id="consequences-of-implementing-the-solution-title">Consequences of implementing the
        solution</title>

        <para>Current and future operations require and will require interoperability at all levels:
        from machine-to-machine, to human-to-human via all the transformation steps from data to
        information. The essential pre-requisite is standardization and well-defined and error-free
        standards, which are machine-interpretable for ease of implementation and with no
        opportunity for mis-interpretation. Using the traditional approach to standardization will
        continue to produce standards that are difficult to maintain and often contain errors,
        entail long delays before ratification, are ambiguous, and therefore result in
        non-interoperable systems. The new approach proposed in this document applies to five areas:
        The application of the layered approach, the configuration management of the standards, the
        development of systems, the actual interoperability, and the enhanced operational usage in
        the future. The benefits provided in each of these areas are further addressed in the
        following sections.</para>

        <sect4 id="stanag-configuration-management-enhancements">
          <title id="stanag-configuration-management-enhancements-title">STANAG Configuration
          Management enhancements</title>

          <para>The current configuration management (CM) of the various STANAGs is handled by their
          respective custodians (e.g. Defence Information Systems Agency (DISA) for STANAG 5516)
          using different proprietary tools and methodologies. The process of creating a new STANAG
          baseline is largely a manual task where changes to the STANAG text are applied to the
          proper sections; some of the text is maintained in a database as structured data (e.g. the
          Message Structure and Data Element Dictionary), others are maintained as a collection of
          plain text (e.g. the body text or the transmit and receive rules). Linkage between one
          baseline of a STANAG and a previous one is difficult. Furthermore, various STANAGs need to
          maintain consistency between them, e.g., those defining different Data Links and those
          that define the conversions between them, or STANAGs and standards which define common
          elements (e.g. positional definitions or identities (STANAG 1241)).</para>

          <para>The CM process could leverage on the possibilities introduced by the representation
          of STANAGs in a machine-interpretable format which is structured and well-defined. Several
          enhancements are foreseen to the CM process:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>More explicit specification of the components that make up a Configuration Item
              (CI) which makes these components easier to be discovered and referenced from other
              areas.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Automated support for creating a new baseline based on the availability in a
              machine-interpretable format of both the previous baseline and the changes to be
              applied.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Easier tracking of changes to the elements that make up the CI with all relevant
              aspects like what, when, why and who.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The machine-interpretable format of the STANAG can then be used to automatically
          generate the required STANAG documentation. The quality of this documentation will be
          greatly improved because of the resulting consistency in internal structure and phrasing,
          possible different views on the structure, fully hyperlinked to ease navigation, and
          support for different output formats (e.g. HTML, PDF, and Word). To support these
          enhancements, the improved standard would provide ways to create references on several
          levels that can be used:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Internally in a baseline, e.g., from the message structure to a data element or
              from the processing actions to a specific message.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>From one baseline to previous ones, e.g. to trace changes to elements.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>To other baselines of related standards, e.g., to data elements in a common or
              related standard (e.g. variable message format (VMF) and Link-22 reuse data elements
              from Link-16)).</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Using these references, the internal and external integrity of the standard can then
          be validated resulting in increased quality of the produced baseline.</para>

          <para>The actual changes in an information exchange standard are often part of a Change
          Proposal (CP) process. CPs are developed and then submitted by Nations and Strategic
          Commands (SC) represented in the body responsible for the CM of the STANAG in order to
          modify parts of the STANAGs. CPs could correct errors in the STANAGs or could introduce
          changes in order to implement new capabilities. As soon as agreement has been reached the
          CP and supplement sections will be embedded in the next edition of the STANAG.</para>

          <para>This process could be greatly improved by having both CPs and STANAGs in a
          structured, well-defined, unambiguous, and machine-interpretable format [NC3A-TN-1391],
          resulting in the following benefits</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Automated verification of impact and integrity constraints of the CP even before
              submission</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Automated update of the STANAG based on the agreed CP, including automated
              referential integrity handling</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Automated verification of changes to interoperability matrices as a result of
              the CP before agreement</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Possibility to register the changed Information Exchange Specification in the
              NMRR in machine interpretable format for implementation</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Several of the aforementioned baseline management activities are supported by the
          NATO Metadata Registry and Repository (NMRR), which is an NNEC core service for
          registration, discovery and configuration management of machine-interpretable artefacts.
          More information on the administrative aspects of the NMRR can be found in [NC3A-TN-1311]
          [NC3A-TN-1312] [NC3A-TN-1313] [RTO-EN-IST-088]. Besides being visible and accessible to
          human users, the artefacts registered in the NMRR will also be available to automated
          clients via a service interface. Due to the machine-interpretable format, services can
          make use of these artefacts and be notified of changes, thus enabling various advanced use
          cases. More information on these so-called `operational' aspects of the NMRR can be found
          in [NC3A-TN-1367] [NC3A-TN-1368] [NC3A-TN-1369].</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="stanag-implementation-and-system-development-enhancement">
          <title id="stanag-implementation-and-system-development-enhancement-title">STANAG
          Implementation &amp; System development enhancement</title>

          <para>A structured, well-defined, machine-interpretable standard can be used in various
          ways. Generation of human readable documentation is one of the most self-evident ones,
          which could also provide more capabilities than the current human readable standard by
          using the information provided by the structure. But because of the machine-interpretable
          aspect of the new specification, it's strength is most prominent when it is used as the
          base for the implementing system's logic i.e., using the specification to generate the
          system's implementation. In traditional systems, humans read the standard and implement
          the desired functionality. This is manual work to a large extent without real support for
          automation. Often engineers will convert certain aspects of the standard to some sort of
          structured information but each group is basically reinventing the wheel. Furthermore,
          besides being time-consuming and error-prone, it also requires the human to interpret
          thousands of pages of text, not always in their native language, while keeping track of
          the intrinsic linkage between the various sections of the standard. Undoubtedly each
          company or agency will have developed their own ways of tracking the quality of their work
          with linkage back to the specification which is a huge effort and therefore represents
          concrete value and is therefore not easily shared among companies or agencies.</para>

          <para>Transforming the specification so it can be interpreted by a machine would mean a
          huge reduction of human interpretation. This can be achieved by defining only a limited
          and well-defined vocabulary instead of the many ways a natural language can be used to
          express, e.g., the logic of a system. Different ways of expressing the same thing might be
          pleasant while reading a novel but will trigger an engineer's brain to wonder whether the
          different wording might indicate a different behaviour. This is even more applicable when
          the language at hand is not the engineer's native language.</para>

          <para>The reduction of human interpretation will have two aspects:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The level of interpretation will be reduced because of the limited and
              well-defined vocabulary: just a limited set of constructs needs to be defined with
              great accuracy and because there is only a limited set, it will be easier to
              understand.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The amount of interpretation will be reduced because, once the vocabulary is
              understood, the whole standard is basically about applying those constructs in a
              well-defined and repetitive way. That is obviously something a machine is aimed
              at.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>When automatically generating systems, ruling out most of the human interpretation
          together with the increased power and quality of the specification, will have several
          positive effects on the resulting product:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Shorter time between specification and implementation: as the standard is now
              machine-interpretable there is no need to read through all the changes and then find
              and update the relevant code. In the best case it would be a push-on-a-button to
              create an updated system ready for testing.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Cost reduction: shorter time to implement an updated system has a direct impact
              on the costs. But furthermore, by generating parts of the system the time spent in
              testing can be reduced because mainly the generation process needs to be validated to
              produce the correct output.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Fewer errors: The machine-interpretable aspect means far less human
              interpretation is required and because of the automatic generation of part of the
              system less manual work needs to be performed. Both contribute to fewer errors in the
              final implementation of the system.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Improved interoperability: Using an unambiguous specification to produce an
              implementation of higher quality will increase the level of interoperability between
              systems. More on this subject is covered in the next section.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Test support: The specification can also be used during the test and validation
              phases of a system, e.g., to generate automatically test code and scenarios.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Obtaining all these benefits will obviously take time to mature but system
          development will be greatly enhanced resulting in better information exchange systems and
          increased interoperability which will further examined in the following section.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="interoperability-enhancement">
          <title id="interoperability-enhancement-title">Interoperability enhancement</title>

          <para>Assessment, verification and validation of the interoperability among platforms is
          essential in order to achieve situational awareness according to the NNEC Data Strategy.
          This is especially true in a NATO environment where various nations are collaborating with
          their own national systems, often developed by different companies and with different
          requirements. Interoperability shall be verified during various stages of the system's
          life, each of which can leverage on the machine-interpretable standard.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="paper-based-interoperability-assessment">
          <title id="paper-based-interoperability-assessment-title">Paper based interoperability
          assessment</title>

          <para>Originally, a paper-based interoperability assessment involved manually comparing
          documents against each other; the system's requirements document (SRD) or the interface
          control document (ICD) against the standard. By capturing the SRD and the ICD in XML in a
          similar manner to that foreseen for the TDL standard itself, automatic assessment of
          interoperability against the standard or another system can be easily achieved. This has a
          direct positive effect on both the quality of the comparison as well as the time it takes.
          The paper-based interoperability assessment between the SRD and the standard can be
          performed even before the system is actually built, reducing the costs associated with
          later changes. An example of such an interoperability assessment via machine interpretable
          versions of both the reference document and the ICD can be found in
          [REF-NC3A-NU/CCS/ADP/2008/331].</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="system-development">
          <title id="system-development-title">System development</title>

          <para>Using the machine-interpretable standard to generate major parts of an
          implementation system, as explained in the previous section, will positively affect the
          level of interoperability between these systems. The level of interpretation is reduced
          because of the well-defined constructs and the limited number of constructs, while the
          amount of interpretation is reduced because of applying these constructs consistently over
          the whole standard. Furthermore, if a system interprets a certain construct in a
          non-standard way (i.e. a bug), this would affect all situations where it is applied which
          therefore increases the chance of discovering this during tests.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="interoperability-testing">
          <title id="interoperability-testing-title">Interoperability testing</title>

          <para>By using the machine-interpretable specification, not only can the system itself,
          but also test and analyzer tools can be generated to a large extent. The specification
          will contain all the information like the supported messages, their structure and the
          protocol for the message exchange. These tools can then be used to rigorously test systems
          against the standard, both in a one-on-one test and for analyzing the interaction between
          different systems.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="harmonization-of-standards">
          <title id="harmonization-of-standards-title">harmonization of standards</title>

          <para>The introduction of machine-interpretable standards will significantly increase the
          interoperability between systems whose implementation has been derived from the same
          standard; it will eliminate the need for ad-hoc interfaces and translation of data
          structures. To ensure interoperability between the systems based on different standards
          from different COIs, COIs should harmonize their information exchanges and establish
          common agreed upon operational cross-domain specifications. In the past, this process was
          often tedious for various reasons, but it is foreseen that this process can be facilitated
          by the application of the STF and the availability of the future NMRR capability to store
          and manage those specifications. More information about standardization, the power of
          metadata, such as the machine-interpretable standards, and the role of the NMRR, can be
          found in [NC3A-TN-1254] [RTO-EN-IST-088].</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="consequences-of-not-implementing-the-solution">
        <title id="consequences-of-not-implementing-the-solution-title">Consequences of not
        implementing the solution</title>

        <para>The STF can be applied in several ways:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The STF Layered Framework is used to identify gaps in the IERs and IESs with
            respect to the NNEC Data Strategy goals.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The STF Layers are used to structure the evolution and development of IESs.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The STF Design Rules and XML artefacts are used to transform existing textual IES
            related to the message formats (DED and MS) into XML representations</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>If the STF is not applied in the evolution and development of IERs and IESs, there is
        a high risk that the following will occur:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>IERs and IESs will be insufficiently specified, as developers may forget to
            consider certain aspects such as security cross-domain and operational cross-domain
            considerations.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>IESs transformed into XML may not have sufficient information to support data
            harmonization, reuse and semantic interoperability</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>If a common framework is not used to transform the way NATO develops STANAGs for
        information exchange, it would be difficult to realize the NNEC Data Strategy goals and
        reach interoperability in the NNEC environment.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="five-dot-seven-limitations">
      <title id="five-dot-seven-limitations-title">Limitations</title>

      <para>Limitations imposed by the Design Rule or limited conformance to applied standard shall
      be described in this section.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="deviations">
      <title id="deviations-title">Deviations</title>

      <para>There has been cases where IESs for DED and MS have been transformed or captured into
      XML, but not in-line with the STF XML Schemas for those layers.</para>

      <para>If the STF Design Rules and STF XML Schemas are not applied to transform existing
      message formats into XML, there is a chance that the following deficiencies may occur:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The data element specifications may lack enough detail to support data
          harmonization.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Incompatible implementations of frameworks are negating the benefits of a common
          framework for different message formats.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Incompatible specifications will make operational cross-domain harder or impossible.
          <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>For example, when applying STF to the forwarding from format A to format B,
                every data element from either can be referenced with a consistent and unambiguous
                triple of Format, deci and dei. This results in a specification for forwarding which
                is much simpler than taking different specification domain in account.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Re-inventing the Wheel: Wasted investment of time and resources to define
                solutions that are already existing, thought-through, tested, and accepted.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="examples">
      <title id="examples-title">Examples</title>

      <para>Examples of applying the design rules are provided within the Design Rules &amp;
      Methodology section for each STF layer.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="six-relations-to-other-products">
    <title id="six-relations-to-other-products-title">Relations to other products</title>

    <sect2 id="six-dot-one-dependencies">
      <title id="six-dot-one-dependencies-title">Dependencies</title>

      <para>The STF Design Rule have the following dependencies from other products.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The STF XML artefacts are registered within the NMRR within the STF
          namespace.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>XML artefacts created by applying the STF design rule shall be registered within the
          NMRR.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The STF XML artefacts in the NMRR shall be used to automatically validate the XML
          artefact created by applying the STF design rule.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The DED XML artefacts can be used for data harmonization.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="six-dot-two-impacts">
      <title id="six-dot-two-impacts-title">Impacts</title>

      <para>The STF Design Rules impact the evolution and development of STANAGs related to
      information exchanges. The following table provides an initial list of STANAGs that have been
      identified so far that should be transformed and improved by appling this design rule. This
      list is by no means exhaustive and should be expanded as more information exchange STANAGs are
      identified and used by the NATO community.</para>

      <table frame="all">
        <title>Impacted STANAGs</title>

        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="34*"/>

          <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

          <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Document ID</entry>

              <entry>Date of publication</entry>

              <entry>Issue number / version</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 5500]: NATO Standardization Agreement 5500, "Concept of NATO
              Message Text Formatting System (CONFORMETS) - ADatP-3", NATO Standardization Agency,
              Brussels, Belgium (NATO Unclassified).</entry>

              <entry>25 October 2006</entry>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 5501]: NATO Standardization Agreement 5501, Digital Data Link "
              Link 1 (Point-to-Point)", NATO Standardization Agency, Brussels, Belgium (NATO
              Unclassified).</entry>

              <entry>28 February 2006</entry>

              <entry>4th Edition</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 5511]: NATO Standardization Agreement 5511, "Tactical Data
              Exchange " Link 11/11B", NATO Standardization Agency, Brussels, Belgium (NATO
              Unclassified).</entry>

              <entry>28 February 2006</entry>

              <entry>5th Edition</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 5516]: NATO Standardization Agreement 5516, "Tactical Data
              Exchange " Link 16", NATO Standardization Agency, Brussels, Belgium (NATO
              Unclassified).</entry>

              <entry>10 May 2006</entry>

              <entry>5th Edition</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 5518]: NATO STANAG 5518</entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 5519]: NATO STANAG 5519</entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 5522]: NATO Standardization Agreement 5522, "Tactical Data Link "
              Link 22", NATO Standardization Agency, Brussels, Belgium (NATO Unclassified).</entry>

              <entry>24 September 2004</entry>

              <entry>2nd Edition</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 5527]: NATO STANAG 5527</entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 5601]: NATO Standardization Agreement 5601, "Standards for
              Interface of Data Links 1, 11, 11B and 14"</entry>

              <entry>28 August 2006</entry>

              <entry>3rd Edition</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 5616]: NATO Standardization Agreement 5616, "Standards for Data
              Forwarding between Tactical Data. Systems Employing Digital Data Link 11/11B and
              Tactical Data System Employing Link 16"</entry>

              <entry>09 March 2006</entry>

              <entry>3rd Edition</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 2183]: NATO STANAG 2183</entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 2185]: NATO STANAG 2185</entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 4607]: NATO STANAG 4607</entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry/>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>[NATO STANAG 4609]: NATO STANAG 4609</entry>

              <entry/>

              <entry/>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="six-dot-three-interferences">
      <title id="six-dot-three-interferences-title">Interferences</title>

      <para><emphasis>Describe the interference of the Design Rule with other
      products.</emphasis></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="six-dot-four-replacement">
      <title id="six-dot-four-replacement-title">Replacement</title>

      <para><emphasis>List what is replaced and why.</emphasis></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="six-dot-five-change-request-op-cr-cp-slash-improvements">
      <title id="six-dot-five-change-request-op-cr-cp-slash-improvements-title">Change Request
      (CR)/Improvements</title>

      <para>As this is version 1.0 of the STF Design Rules, no change requests are yet
      submitted.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="v-and-v-op-verification-and-validation-cp">
    <title id="v-and-v-op-verification-and-validation-cp-title">V&amp;V (Verification and
    Validation)</title>

    <sect2 id="verification-and-validation-of-stf">
      <title id="verification-and-validation-of-stf-title">Verification and Validation of
      STF</title>

      <para>Verification and validation together can be defined as a process of reviewing, testing
      and inspecting the STF components to determine that the STF components produces the expected
      results based on the expressed requirements.</para>

      <para>V&amp;V is an on-going process that occurs in several phases with the involvement of
      NATO and National Stakeholders in multiple venues. The decision to involve external
      stakeholders at the early stages of the validation process proved to be a success by having
      obtained buy-in and active contributions from several NATO and National Stakeholders.</para>

      <para>As the STF is developed based on the spiral incremental approach, the verification and
      validation process is repeated several times for each component of the STF.</para>

      <figure id="v5a-f31">
        <title>STF V&amp;V Process Overview</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/STF-VandV-Process_Overview.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>STF V&amp;V Process Overview depicts the overarching process adopted for the
      verification and validation.</para>

      <para>As usual, two questions normally asked when dealing with V&amp;V are the
      following:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Validation: Are you building the right thing?</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Verification: Are you building it right?</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In order to address the first question, the STF product--which includes the layered
      framework, design rules, XML artefacts and methodology--addresses the requirements expressed
      by ACT based on the NNEC Data Strategy. In particular, there are requirements to make data
      Visible, Accessible, Coherent, Assured, Interoperable and Managed Effectively. It is
      recognized that in order to achieve these goals, many technical and procedural improvements
      have to be made in the way NATO specifies and manages their Standardization Agreements
      (STANAGs). The STF is being developed to facilitate both types of improvements by providing a
      means for transforming and capturing the information exchange STANAGs into a
      machine-interpretable format, such as XML, to support the NNEC Data Strategy goals.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>In particular, the Validation question will be answered by showing that:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The STF layered framework itself is necessary and sufficient to capture the
              minimum aspects of STANAG specifications in order to support interoperable information
              exchanges. For example, these should include being able to account for the
              following:</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Different data element definitions (bit-based, text-based,
                  XML-based),</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Different message types (fixed vs. variable length; XML-formatted vs.
                  structured text),</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Different transport requirements (TCP/IP, UHF, UDP, etc.),</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Different business rules (transmit/receive rules, transactions, business
                  processes, etc.)</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Different information exchange domain requirements (security,
                  cross-operational, enterprises, etc.)</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The STF design rules and methodology provide a common framework to transform
              information exchange specifications into XML, a machine-interpretable format, to
              support reuse, harmonization and semantic interoperability.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In order to address the second question, the STF product is continuously being shared
      with stakeholders to ensure the STF is designed to deliver all functionality. There is a
      constant feedback to the STF and IER/IES Stakeholders, and the STF is continuously reviewed
      with walkthroughs and inspection meetings to evaluate the conceptual layers, XML artefacts,
      design rules and methodology.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verification can be addressed by showing that if one applies the STF one is able
          to:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Transform relevant sections of existing information exchange STANAGs into
              machine-interpretable representations to support the NNEC data strategy</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Apply it to identify and capture all necessary aspects of information exchange
              specifications within current STANAGs</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Either reuse existing specifications or develop new ones to fill in any gaps,
              such as missing or insufficient specification for the data bearer/routing levels, in a
              machine-interpretable format</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Capture and harmonize data elements in a common way to support reuse, data
              sharing and interoperable information exchanges across communities of interest</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Specify message structures and business rules in a common way to readily support
              semantic interoperability</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This STF V&amp;V process fits into the overarching #STF_Holistic_Process | STF Holistic
      Process, where the STF is being applied to various Case Studies within different communities
      to transform relevant aspects of their information exchange STANAGs into XML to get the
      necessary feedback to verify, validate and mature the STF. In this section, these V&amp;V case
      studies are discussed with a particular emphasis on answering the V&amp;V questions posed
      above.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="stf-v-and-v-case-studies">
      <title id="stf-v-and-v-case-studies-title">STF V&amp;V Case Studies</title>

      <para>The STF has been applied to various communities of interest including the Asset Tracking
      (AST), Friendly Force Tracking (FFT), Joint Intelligence, Surveillance and Reconnaissance
      (JISR) and Tactical Data Link (TDL) communities of interest (COIs).</para>

      <para>Below is a table that summarizes how the STF has been applied to the various COIs to
      identify, transform and/or develop relevant STANAGs/Standards to support interoperable
      information exchanges within those communities.</para>

      <para><table frame="all">
          <title>STF Applied</title>

          <tgroup cols="4">
            <colspec colwidth="25*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="25*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="25*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="25*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>COI</entry>

                <entry>STANAG/Standard</entry>

                <entry>Applicable STF Layers</entry>

                <entry>Information Exchange Aspects</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry morerows="2">Asset Tracking</entry>

                <entry>5500 [APP-11 (MTF, XML-MTF)]</entry>

                <entry>DED, MS</entry>

                <entry>Text-based and XML-based</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>2183 (AAITP-6)</entry>

                <entry>Data bearer, Routing, Security cross-domain, Web services</entry>

                <entry>Draft labeling, SMTP</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>2185 (AAITP-4)</entry>

                <entry>Business Rules</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry morerows="1">FFT</entry>

                <entry>5500 [APP-11 (MTF, XML-MTF)]</entry>

                <entry>DED, MS</entry>

                <entry>Text-based and XML-based</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>5527</entry>

                <entry>Security Cross-Domain, Web Services, Operational Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>Draft XML Schemas, Draft service specification (SIP-3)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry morerows="1" valign="top">JISR</entry>

                <entry>4607 (GMTIF)</entry>

                <entry>DED, MS</entry>

                <entry>Bit-based (variable-length)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>4609 ([KLV only])</entry>

                <entry>MS, DED, Routing, Data Bearer</entry>

                <entry>CODEC Formats (e.g. MPEG2, H.264, KLV), Bit-based Data Streams (Video, Audio,
                Metadata), MPEG-2 Transport Stream</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry morerows="6" valign="top">TDL</entry>

                <entry>5501 (Link 1)</entry>

                <entry>DED, MS</entry>

                <entry>Bit-based (fixed)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>5516 (Link 16)</entry>

                <entry>DED, MS</entry>

                <entry>Bit-based (fixed)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>5518 (JREAP)</entry>

                <entry>Data bearer, Routing, DED, MS</entry>

                <entry>Bit-based (variable-length)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>5519 (VMF)</entry>

                <entry>DED, MS</entry>

                <entry>Bit-based (variable-length)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>5522 (Link 22)</entry>

                <entry>DED, MS</entry>

                <entry>Bit-based (fixed-length)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>5601</entry>

                <entry>Operational Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>Forwarding rules between Link1 and Link11/11B</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>5616</entry>

                <entry>Operational Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>Forwarding rules between Link16 and Link11/11B</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="v-and-v-in-the-asset-tracking-coi">
      <title id="v-and-v-in-the-asset-tracking-coi-title">V&amp;V in the Asset Tracking COI</title>

      <para>In support of NATO Overarching Architecture 3.1 (OA 3.1) NOV-3 Operational Information
      Requirement for exchanging Prioritized Critical Assets List (IP632), the Asset Tracking (AST)
      COI used the AAP-51A (Asset Tracking Business Process Model) to derive NOV-3 Information
      Requirements specific to tracking of consignments, transport packages and personnel. The STF
      was applied from the onset to assist in analyzing and identifying the information exchange
      requirements in support of these Asset Tracking-specific Information Requirements.</para>

      <sect3 id="stf-analysis-asset-tracking">
        <title id="stf-analysis-asset-tracking-title">STF Analysis: Asset Tracking</title>

        <para>Based on this analysis, it was determined that the relevant IESs were STANAG 5500
        (ADatP-3 XML-MTF format), STANAG 7149 (NATO Message Catalogue APP-11), STANAG 2183 (AAITP-6)
        and STANAG 2185 (AAITP-4).</para>

        <para>In particular, it was determined that the structure of messages and the data elements
        contained within them were to be specified according to STANAG 5500 ADatP-3 following the
        XML-MTF format, and to be included within the STANAG 7149 Allied Procedural Publication 11
        (APP-11), NATO Message Catalogue. The ASTWG developed the corresponding AST-XML-MTF message
        set, and are to be published later in 2012 with a new edition of APP-11.</para>

        <para>The STF layers were applied to evolve the AAITP-6 and AAITP-4 specifications to ensure
        that the data bearing, routing and business rules layers were also covered. In particular,
        standards for the routing and means of bearing the actual messages appear in AAITP-6 (STANAG
        2183) and the business rules are captured in AAITP-4 (STANAG-2185).</para>

        <para>The Table captures this mapping to illustrate which layers of the STF are covered by
        which IES specifications.</para>

        <para><table frame="all">
            <title>Asset Tracking Information Exchange Requirement (IER) Analysis</title>

            <tgroup cols="3">
              <colspec colwidth="34*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Required NOV-3 Information Product</entry>

                  <entry>Derived Information Product Requirement(s)</entry>

                  <entry>Domain(s)</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Prioritized Critical Asset List (IP632), Joint Prioritized Critical Asset
                  List (IP634)</entry>

                  <entry>Asset Tracking data</entry>

                  <entry>Logistics, Security (NATO/Nations)</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>

        <para><table frame="all">
            <title>STF Holistic Process to Asset Tracking Analysis</title>

            <tgroup cols="3">
              <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="34*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

              <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*"/>

              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry align="center" nameend="c3" namest="c1">STF Holistic Process &lt;--&gt;
                  Asset Tracking</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>STF Layers mapped to IER</entry>

                  <entry>IES/Specs per Layer</entry>

                  <entry>STF Information Exchange Aspects</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Security Cross-Domain</entry>

                  <entry>AAITP-6/STANAG 2183</entry>

                  <entry>labeling</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Business Rules</entry>

                  <entry>AAITP-4/STANAG 2185 <emphasis>(plain English statements, not machine
                  readable XML&gt;</emphasis></entry>

                  <entry>NOT XML</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Message Structure</entry>

                  <entry>part of APP-11 message catalogue (STANAG 7149), ADatP-3 XML-MTF covered by
                  STANAG 5500</entry>

                  <entry>XML-based</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Data Element Dictionary</entry>

                  <entry>part of APP-11 message catalogue (STANAG 7149), ADatP-3 XML-MTF covered by
                  STANAG 5500</entry>

                  <entry>Text-based</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Routing</entry>

                  <entry morerows="1">defined in AAITP-6</entry>

                  <entry morerows="1">SMTP</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Data Bearer</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Web Services</entry>

                  <entry>AAITP-6 <emphasis>(guidance is provided, but a specification does not
                  exist, yet)</emphasis></entry>

                  <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Operational Cross-Domain</entry>

                  <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                  <entry>NOT APPLICABLE</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="asset-tracking-conclusions">
        <title id="asset-tracking-conclusions-title">Asset Tracking Conclusions</title>

        <para>As highlighted in the table, comparative analysis between the STF Layers and the Asset
        Tracking information exchange requirements highlighted the lack or incomplete definition
        related to the following: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Business Rules are currently formulated in plain English statements, and are not
              (yet) captured in machine readable XML</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>WS (a Web Services guidance is provided but a specification is scheduled for
              next edition)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Cross-COI Information Exchange</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="stf-overall-v-and-v-conclusions-asset-tracking">
        <title id="stf-overall-v-and-v-conclusions-asset-tracking-title">STF Overall V&amp;V
        Conclusions: Asset Tracking</title>

        <para>The V&amp;V of the STF Layers as applied to the AST COI did show that the layers
        provided the necessary components to analyze the information exchange requirements for Asset
        Tracking messages, and helped to identify gaps in the existing specifications to support
        that information exchange.</para>

        <para>The V&amp;V of the STF design rules, XML artefacts and methodology showed that it was
        able to be applied in the development of two new information exchange STANAGs (2183 and
        2185) in support of supporting the Asset Tracking information exchange requirements.</para>

        <para>Currently, the AST-XML-MTF messages and data elements have been captured in XML
        in-line with the STANAG 5500 XML-MTF Schemas, but not in-line with the STF XML Schemas. The
        capture of XML-based DED and MS are out-of-scope of STF Version 1.0, but the need for this
        has already been identified and captured within the STF Design Rules. It is envisioned that
        this will be provided in STF Version 2.0.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="v-and-v-in-the-friendly-force-tracking-op-fft-cp-coi">
      <title id="v-and-v-in-the-friendly-force-tracking-op-fft-cp-coi-title">V&amp;V in the Friendly
      Force Tracking (FFT) COI</title>

      <para>The FFT COI initiated a transformation of the specifications related to FFT information
      exchange: currently the NFFI "D" Document, STANAG-5527 and STANAG 5500 are the relevant
      documents for this COI.</para>

      <sect3 id="stf-analysis-fft-phase-one--op-nffi-and-quotd-and-quot-document-cp">
        <title id="stf-analysis-fft-phase-one--op-nffi-and-quotd-and-quot-document-cp-title">STF
        Analysis: FFT Phase 1 (NFFI "D" Document)</title>

        <para>In the initial analysis of FFT information exchange, it was determined that the only
        specification available at the time was the NFFI "D" Document. This document was a C3B
        "Decision" Document that is meant to capture the NFFI format, which is the basic message
        format used to support FFT.</para>

        <para><table frame="all">
            <title>FFT Information Exchange Requirement (IER) Analysis</title>

            <tgroup cols="3">
              <colspec colwidth="34*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Required NOV-3 Information Product</entry>

                  <entry>Derived Information Product Requirement(s)</entry>

                  <entry>Domain(s)</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Order Of Battle - Land Forces (IP478), Own Land Forces Situation Report
                  (IP482)</entry>

                  <entry>FFT data</entry>

                  <entry>Land, Operational Cross-Domain (Joint, Air, Maritime)</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>

        <para><table frame="all">
            <title>STF Holistic Process to FFT Phase 1 Analysis</title>

            <tgroup cols="3">
              <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="34*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

              <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*"/>

              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry align="center" nameend="c3" namest="c1">STF Holistic Process &lt;--&gt; FFT
                  Phase 1: NFFI "D" Document</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>STF Layers mapped to IER</entry>

                  <entry>IES/Specs per Layer</entry>

                  <entry>STF Information Exchange Aspects</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Security Cross-Domain</entry>

                  <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                  <entry/>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Business Rules</entry>

                  <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                  <entry/>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Message Structure</entry>

                  <entry>AC/322-D(2006)0066 - Interim NFFI Standard for Interoperability of
                  FTS</entry>

                  <entry>XML-based</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Data Element Dictionary</entry>

                  <entry>AC/322-D(2006)0066 - Interim NFFI Standard for Interoperability of
                  FTS</entry>

                  <entry>XML-based</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Routing</entry>

                  <entry morerows="1">NFFI "D" Document</entry>

                  <entry morerows="1">TCP and UDP as defined in IP-1 and IP-2</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Data Bearer</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Web Services</entry>

                  <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                  <entry/>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Operational Cross-Domain</entry>

                  <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                  <entry/>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table></para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold"> STF Conclusion: NFFI </emphasis></para>

        <para>A comparative analysis between the STF Layers and the NFFI "D" Document highlighted
        the lack of specifications related to the:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Business Rules</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Web Services</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Security Cross Domain</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Cross-COI Information Exchange</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>These gaps were brought to the attention of the Stakeholders. It was eventually
        decided to not use the NFFI "D" Document for the message definitions, but rather move along
        a different path and to align with the XML-MTF format, as agreed in STANAG 5500. Also, it
        was decided to develop a new STANAG, STANAG 5527, in-line with the STF so that the gaps
        could be filled.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="stf-analysis-fft-phase-two--op-stanag-five-five-two-seven-cp">
        <title id="stf-analysis-fft-phase-two--op-stanag-five-five-two-seven-cp-title">STF Analysis:
        FFT Phase 2 (STANAG 5527)</title>

        <para>Based on the decisions based on the STF Conclusions of Phase 1, in Phase 2 NATO began
        to capture the FFT-related messages in-line with STANAG 5500, with these new messages to be
        made available in the APP-11 NATO Message Catalogue. Effort was also undertaken to use the
        STF layered framework as a basis for developing the specification to support the FFT
        information exchange in STANAG 5527, where the specification for each layer is captured in
        different sections on the STANAG.</para>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>STF Holistic Process to FFT Phase 2 Analysis</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="34*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center" nameend="c3" namest="c1">STF Holistic Process &lt;--&gt; FFT
                Phase 2</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>STF Layers mapped to IER</entry>

                <entry>IES/Specs per Layer</entry>

                <entry>STF Information Exchange Aspects</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Security Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 5527: Security Cross-Domain XML Schemas</entry>

                <entry>Draft XML Schema used to capture the security Labeling and Sanitizing</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Business Rules</entry>

                <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                <entry/>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Message Structure</entry>

                <entry>part of APP-11 message catalogue (STANAG 7149), ADatP-3 XML-MTF covered by
                STANAG 5500</entry>

                <entry>XML-based</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data Element Dictionary</entry>

                <entry>part of APP-11 message catalogue (STANAG 7149), ADatP-3 XML-MTF covered by
                STANAG 5500</entry>

                <entry>XML-based</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Routing</entry>

                <entry morerows="1">STANAG 5527</entry>

                <entry morerows="1">Interface Profiles: IP-1 (TCP) and IP-2 (UDP)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data Bearer</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Web Services</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 5527: Web Services Specification</entry>

                <entry>Draft version of the SIP-3</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Operational Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 5527: Cross-COI XML Schemas</entry>

                <entry>Draft Schemas used to capture mapping details for allowing data transfer
                between differing standards (i.e. NFFI to FFI MTF and NFFI to OTH-Gold)</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="stf-overall-v-and-v-conclusions-fft">
        <title>STF Overall V&amp;V Conclusions: FFT</title>

        <para>The V&amp;V of the STF layers did show that the layers provided the necessary
        components to analyze the information exchange requirements for FFT, and helped to identify
        gaps in the existing specifications to support that information exchange.</para>

        <para>The V&amp;V of the STF design rules, XML artefacts and methodology showed that it was
        able to be applied in the development of a new information exchange STANAG 5527 in support
        of supporting the FFT information exchange requirements.</para>

        <para>Overall, the V&amp;V of the STF showed that <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The STF layered approach helped to identify gaps in the existing specifications
              to support that information exchange for FFT</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The STF supported the reuse of existing specifications: <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>In the DED and MS layers: STANAG 5500 and STANAG 7149</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>In the Transport/Data Bearer layers: IP-1 (TCP) and IP-2 (UDP)</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>The STF supported the development of a new information exchange format:
                    STANAG 5527</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="v-and-v-in-the-jisr-coi">
      <title>V&amp;V in the JISR COI</title>

      <para>Within the JISR-community, there is a multi-national R&amp;D group, called the Multi-INT
      All-Source Joint Intelligence, Surveillance and Reconnaissance Coalition (MAJIIC2), that
      focuses on developing the standards, technologies, processes and policies to support the
      interoperability and integration of Intelligence, Surveillance, Target Acquisition and
      Reconnaissance (ISTAR) systems within a networked enabled enterprise. Within this enterprise,
      there is a need to disseminate many different types of ISTAR data products, including, but not
      limited to, raw and exploited Ground Moving Target Indicator (GMTI), Synthetic Aperture Radar
      (SAR) and Electro-Optical(EO)/Thermal Imaging (TI) imagery/motion imagery, weapon locating
      information, Electronic Support Measures (ESM), etc. These different data products may be
      disseminated via different transport mechanisms (broadcasted on LAN, multicast on WAN,
      streaming video, still imagery files, tactical data links, via NATO Standard ISR Library
      Interface servers, etc.) based on the needs and requirements of the end users and functional
      scenario.</para>

      <para>As an initial case study, the STF was applied to two of the JISR information exchange
      requirements, namely GMTI and motion imagery, with the goal to be able to support
      interoperability testing and validation of these types of information exchanges.</para>

      <sect3 id="gmti">
        <title id="gmti-title">GMTI</title>

        <para>GMTI is used within the JISR community to detect and report on ground moving targets
        in support of the NOV-3 Operational Information Requirement to exchange Moving Target
        Indicator Exploitation Reports (IP660).</para>

        <para>At the time of the analysis, the relevant documents to specify the information
        exchange of GMTI were the NATO Ground Moving Target Indicator Format (STANAG 4607), NATO
        STANAG 4607 Implementation Guide (AEDP-7) and the MAJIIC2 STANAG 4607 Implementation Guides
        (MAJIIC2 IG)</para>

        <sect4 id="stf-analysis-gmti-information-exchange">
          <title>STF Analysis: GMTI Information Exchange</title>

          <para>Following the STF Holistic Process, the STF layers were used as a guidance to
          analyze the information exchange requirements for GMTI and to map the contents of the
          existing IES documents onto the STF layers to help identify possible gaps within the
          existing specifications.</para>

          <para>These are shown below:</para>

          <table frame="all">
            <title>GMTI Information Exchange Requirement (IER) Analysis</title>

            <tgroup cols="3">
              <colspec colwidth="34*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Required NOV-3 Information Product</entry>

                  <entry>Derived Information Product Requirement(s)</entry>

                  <entry>Domain(s)</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Moving Target Indicator Exploitation Report (IP660)</entry>

                  <entry>Ground Moving Target Indicator (GMTI) data</entry>

                  <entry>JISR, Security (NATO/Nations)</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>

          <table frame="all">
            <title>STF Holistic Process to GMTI Analysis</title>

            <tgroup cols="3">
              <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="34*"/>

              <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

              <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*"/>

              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry align="center" nameend="c3" namest="c1">STF Holistic Process &lt;--&gt;
                  GMTI</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>STF Layers mapped to IER</entry>

                  <entry>IES/Specs per Layer</entry>

                  <entry>STF Information Exchange Aspects</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>Security Cross-Domain</entry>

                  <entry>STANAG 4607: Appendix A (for DED, MS &amp; allowable values)<emphasis>Note:
                  same specification repeated in AEDP-7: Appendix B</emphasis> <emphasis>Not
                  captured in XML</emphasis></entry>

                  <entry>NOT APPLICABLE</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Business Rules</entry>

                  <entry>AEDP-7, MAJIIC2 IG</entry>

                  <entry>NOT APPLICABLE</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Message Structure</entry>

                  <entry>STANAG 4607</entry>

                  <entry>Variable-length</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Data Element Dictionary</entry>

                  <entry>STANAG 4607</entry>

                  <entry>Bit-based</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Routing</entry>

                  <entry morerows="1">AEDP-7, MAJIIC2 IG<emphasis>(Guidance, but no
                  specifications)</emphasis></entry>

                  <entry morerows="1">Embedded within other ISR formats (e.g. STANAG 4545, STANAG
                  7023) <para>Disseminated via STANAG 4559 </para><para> Distributed via UDP
                  broadcast</para></entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Data Bearer</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Web Services</entry>

                  <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                  <entry>NOT APPLICABLE</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>Operational Cross-Domain</entry>

                  <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                  <entry>NOT APPLICABLE</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="gmti-conclusions">
          <title>GMTI Conclusions</title>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>STANAG 4607 specifies the GMTI format</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The STF DED and MS XML artefacts were sufficient and were applied to capture
                  the Data Element Dictionary and Message Structure of the GMTI information
                  exchange, as specified within the STANAG 4607 document.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>STANAG 4607 discusses Data Transmission only with respect to how to handle the
              messages. There are no sections in this document discussing how to physically transmit
              the GMTI data.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The MAJIIC2 STANAG 4607 Implementation Guide was developed by the MAJIIC
                  community for standardizing how GMTI data would be shared amongst the MAJIIC
                  participants. They selected a transport mechanism (UDP Broadcast), which is
                  <emphasis role="bold">not</emphasis> mentioned within any of the other
                  Standardized documents.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>AEDP-7 provides an Appendix discussing various options for physically
                  sharing the GMTI data. However, there are no specific guidance provided on which
                  are the preferred way, as advised by the STF to provide.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The MAJIIC2 community is currently transforming their way of business to be
              interoperable within an NNEC environment. Also, they have identified the need for
              sharing GMTI between various security domains, across different operational domains
              and via web services.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>These are identified as Gaps within the STF layers, but are out-of-scope for
                  this V&amp;V assessment.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="stf-applied-conclusions-gmti">
          <title>STF Applied Conclusions: GMTI</title>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>STANAG 4607 (GMTI Format) Edition 2 was successfully transformed into XML using
              the STF design rules &amp; methodology at the DED and MS layers.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The content of the STANAG 4607 Implementation Guides were analyzed and
              successfully mapped to the STF layers.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Gap: Although various Data Bearer/Routing options were identified within the
              relevant documents, it was not specified when or how to use each option.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Also, it should be noted that the "UDP broadcast" option was chosen by the
                  MAJIIC community as their GMTI transport mechanism and specified within their
                  Implementation Guide, but this was not provided as an option within the NATO
                  STANAG 4607 or AEDP-7 documents. Therefore, implementations within the MAJIIC
                  community may be interoperable with each other, but might not be interoperable
                  with external communities.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Recommendation: Improve specification and explicitly capture data bearer/routing
              requirements within STANAG for interoperable GMTI information exchange.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="stf-v-and-v-conclusions-gmti">
          <title>STF V&amp;V Conclusions: GMTI</title>

          <para>The STF layers do provide the coverage needed to identify the GMTI information
          exchange requirements that are needed to support interoperability.</para>

          <para>The V&amp;V of STF Design Rules &amp; methodology at the DED and MS layers showed
          that it was sufficient to transform STANAG 4607 (GMTI Format) Edition 2 into XML using the
          STF XML artefacts.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="motion-imagery-op-mi-cp">
        <title id="motion-imagery-op-mi-cp-title">Motion Imagery (MI)</title>

        <para>With MI, the relevant standard is STANAG 4609, which is aimed at promoting
        interoperability of present and future motion imagery systems within and among NATO nations.
        Similar to GMTI, MI system implementers have to rely on various implementation guides, the
        NATO Motion Imagery (MI) STANAG 4609 Implementation Guide (AEDP-8) and the MAJIIC2 STANG
        4609 Implementation Guides, in particular, in order to achieve interoperable
        implementations. There is also a MAJIIC2 Business Rules document available that provides
        details on motion imagery information exchange interaction requirements, especially with
        respect on how to utilize the Coalition Shared Data servers.</para>

        <para>In general, digital MI is composed of two major components, the Data Stream; and the
        Format. The Data Stream may actually be a set of "elementary" streams such as video, audio,
        metadata, and subtitles. Each stream type is processed by a specific encoder/decoder
        (CODEC). The Format is the protocol for transporting the streams through networks or in
        files. In STANAG-4609, formats available for MPEG2 are Elementary Stream (ES), Program
        Stream (PS), and Transport Stream (TS). PS and TS formats are capable of carrying multiple
        synchronized streams.</para>

        <para>We have mapped the content of those implementation guides to the STF horizontal layers
        in the table below.</para>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>Motion Imagery Information Exchange Requirement (IER) Analysis</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colwidth="34*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Required NOV-3 Information Product</entry>

                <entry>Derived Information Product Requirement(s)</entry>

                <entry>Domain(s)</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Video Product (IP653)</entry>

                <entry>Full motion video streams, Video clips, Video-on-demand streams (STANAG
                4609)</entry>

                <entry>JISR, Security Cross-Domain</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>STF Holistic Process to Motion Imagery Analysis</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="34*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center" nameend="c3" namest="c1">STF Holistic Process &lt;--&gt;
                Motion Imagery</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>STF Layers mapped to IER</entry>

                <entry>IES/Specs per Layer</entry>

                <entry>STF Information Exchange Aspects</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Security Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 4609</entry>

                <entry>NOT APPLICABLE</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Business Rules</entry>

                <entry>AEDP-8, MAJIIC2 STANAG 4609 Implementation Guide, MAJIIC2 Business
                Rules</entry>

                <entry>NOT APPLICABLE</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Message Structure</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 4609 (references SMPTE RP 210; MISB Standard 0801)</entry>

                <entry>CODEC Formats (e.g. MPEG2, H.264, KLV)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data Element Dictionary</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 4609</entry>

                <entry>Bit-based Data Streams (video, audio, metadata "elementary" streams)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Routing</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 4609</entry>

                <entry>MPEG2 Transport Stream (TS), MPEG2 Program Stream (PS)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data Bearer</entry>

                <entry>MAJIIC2 STANAG 4609 Implementation Guide, MAJIIC2 Business Rules</entry>

                <entry>UDP, RTP/RTSP, TCP, HTTP/HTTPS</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Web Services</entry>

                <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                <entry>NOT APPLICABLE</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Operational Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                <entry>NOT APPLICABLE</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <sect4 id="mi-conclusions">
          <title id="mi-conclusions-title">MI Conclusions</title>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>STANAG 4609 DED and MS</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The STF DED and MS XML artefacts were able to capture the Data Element
                  Dictionary and Message Structure of the KLV "metadata" elementary stream in
                  XML.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>The STF DED and MS XML artefacts were not used to capture the DED and MS of
                  the other "elementary" data streams, such as the video and audio. These were
                  considered out-of-scope of this case study.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>STANAG 4609 discusses Routing via the MPEG2 Transport Stream and Program Stream.
              These are slightly different formats for transmitting and storing motion imagery. This
              could lead to interoperability issues between participants if they do not have the
              correct implementations to handle both formats.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The MAJIIC2 STANAG 4609 Implementation Guide was developed by the MAJIIC
                  community for standardizing how MI data would be shared amongst the MAJIIC
                  participants. Within this community, it has been agreed to implement the MPEG2-TS.
                  Although interoperability would be achieved within the MAJIIC community,
                  interoperability with other STANAG 4609 implementers could not be
                  guaranteed.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>STANAG 4609 does not prescribe how to physically transport the video
              streams--there are many options as listed in the table, such as UDP, HTTP/HTTPS,
              RTP/RTSP, etc. It is left up to the end users to decide how to do so. This can lead to
              non-interoperable implementations of the STANAG.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The MAJIIC2 community has chosen to use MPEG2-TS over UDP, which is very
                  lossy. They are investigating possibly using RTP/RTSP.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The MAJIIC2 community is currently transforming their way of business to be
              interoperable within an NNEC environment. Also, they have identified the need for
              sharing MI across different operational domains and via web services.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>These have been identified as Gaps within the STF layers, but are
                  out-of-scope for this V&amp;V assessment.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="stf-v-and-v-conclusions-mi">
          <title>STF V&amp;V Conclusions: MI</title>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Following the STF, it is recommended that the STANAG is improved to provide
              explicit guidance on which routing and data bearer options should be chosen based to
              support interoperable solutions.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The question arose on whether the STF would or should be applicable for
              capturing the video and audio elementary streams of the STANAG 4609 specification in
              XML.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>At first glance, it does not seem that STF would be applicable as Motion
                  Imagery is a <emphasis role="bold"> unidirectional </emphasis> data transfer from
                  a source to a client. It has been stated that STF should be applied only to
                  information exchange, and specifically message exchange, specifications.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>As MI has no "information exchange" per se, as an information exchange is
                  defined as being a <emphasis role="bold"> bidirectional </emphasis> transmission
                  of data, and is not based on "message exchanges", it would seem like STF would not
                  be applicable.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>However, further analysis and work would need to be done to determine how
                  applicable the STF could be for capturing the specification to ensure
                  interoperable processing of the full data stream.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>In fact, this is a good case study to use to further elaborate and mature the
              other layers of the STF so that we get a clearer definition of what it means to
              transform this type of specification into XML.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="v-and-v-in-the-tdl-coi">
      <title id="v-and-v-in-the-tdl-coi-title">V&amp;V in the TDL COI</title>

      <para>The STF has been applied within the TDL CaT via tasking to the TDL CaT in XML Syndicate
      (TDLXMLS) to enable the transformation of TDL-specific STANAGs into XML. As one of the first
      applications of the STF, it provided a great forum to mature the concepts and ideas captured
      within the framework.</para>

      <para>The application of the STF concept to transform the TDL standards into XML was seen as
      the appropriate way to go to "preclude the continued independent development of unique
      solutions for each TDL standard." In particular the following were the standards of
      interest:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>STANAG 5501 (Link 1)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>STANAG 5511 (Link 11/11B)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>STANAG 5516 (Link 16)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>STANAG 5518 (JREAP) - under ratification</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>STANAG 5519 (VMF) - under ratification</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>STANAG 5522 (Link 22)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>STANAG 5601 (Data Forwarding between Link 1, 11, 11B and 14)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>STANAG 5616 (Data Forwarding between Link 11/11B and 16)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The STF's layered approach easily lent itself to the TDLXMLS's goals by providing a
      framework whereby the various components, e.g. data element dictionary, message structure,
      business rules, which characterizes a typical TDL information exchange could be separated out,
      harmonized and common parts reused. The TDLXMLS developed a framework in line with the STF,
      focusing on those layers applicable to the current STANAGs (see <xref linkend="v5a-f32"/>
      below) while a harmonization phase needs to take place to address all STF layers.</para>

      <figure id="v5a-f32">
        <title>xTDL Framework</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/XTDL_Framework.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <sect3 id="link-one-six">
        <title id="link-one-six-title">Link 16</title>

        <para>The work of the TDLXMLS focused on STANAG 5516, while
        keeping the generic aspect into account when applying the methodology on the other
        STANAGs.</para>

        <para>The STF was applied to capture the following aspects of the information
        exchanges:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Data Element Dictionary</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Message Structure</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Transmit/Receive Rules (TDL Processing)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Minimum Implementation (MIN IMP)/Implementation Requirements (IMP REQ)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Cross-STANAG mapping (Data Forwarding)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Business Rules</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Results have been achieved so far for the Data Element Dictionary and Message
        Structure with on-going effort to capture the TDL Processing in the form of the Transactions
        as defined by STANAG 5516. The structure of these Transactions offer a generic approach
        to model the overall message exchange between systems which is believed to be applicable to
        other information exchanges as well.</para>

        <para>To fulfill the STF Operational Cross-COI layer, the Data Forwarding as defined in
        STANAG 5616 between Link 11/11B and Link-16 Systems is used. This is on-going effort and
        will also result in feedback to the STF.</para>

        <para>The STF Data Bearer and Routing layers are, for Link 16, addressed in several ways.
        Traditionally, Link-16 uses radio frequency (RF) to exchange its J-messages within
        line-of-sight, although emerging technologies, such as IP and UHF SATCOM, provide the means
        to pass Link 16 data over long-haul protocols beyond line-of-sight. The traditional RF
        mechanism is defined in the MIDS standard while the JREAP (Joint Range Extension Application
        Protocol) standard (STANAG 5518) governs the IP and SATCOM transport. In particular, the
        JREAP standard defines its own message set and data elements to define the transport level
        protocol for the exchange of Link 16 J-messages. The JREAP messages and data elements are
        captured via the STF XML Schemas as well, requiring additional support in the XML Schema to
        indicate the nesting of Link 16 messages withing the JREAP messages. This enhancement will
        be retrofitted in the STF XML Schema in version 2. Worthwhile to note is that some of the
        Link 16 Data Elements are reused within the JREAP DED. Capturing the specific business rules
        of JREAP is a further action which have to support and tie in with the overall Link 16
        business rules.</para>

        <para>Additionally, the Link-16 Implementation Requirements have been captured in XML with a
        corresponding XML Schema which will need to be retrofitted in the STF as currently no
        generic STF XML Schema is provided yet.</para>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>Link 16 Information Exchange Requirement (IER) Analysis</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colwidth="34*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Required NOV-3 Information Product</entry>

                <entry>Derived Information Product Requirement(s)</entry>

                <entry>Domain(s)</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Various incl. Recognized Air Picture (IP82), Joint Target List (IP44),
                Electronic Warfare Mission Summary (IP326), Target Track Report (IP575), Engagement
                Of Hostile Aircraft Report (IP302)</entry>

                <entry>Tactical Data Exchange - Link 16 (STANAG 5516)</entry>

                <entry>TDL, Operational Cross-Domain (Joint, Land, Air, Maritime, JISR), Security
                Cross-Domain</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>STF Holistic Process to Link 16 Analysis</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="34*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center" nameend="c3" namest="c1">STF Holistic Process &lt;--&gt; Link
                16</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>STF Layers mapped to IER</entry>

                <entry>IES/Specs per Layer</entry>

                <entry>STF Information Exchange Aspects</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Security Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                <entry>MISSING</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Business Rules</entry>

                <entry morerows="2">STANAG 5516</entry>

                <entry>Transactions including Receive/Transmit Tables, Database Records</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Message Structure</entry>

                <entry>Fixed length messages</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data Element Dictionary</entry>

                <entry>Bit-based</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Routing</entry>

                <entry morerows="1">STANAG 5518 Joint Range Extension Application Protocol (JREAP),
                or STANAG 4175 VOL I: Technical Characteristics of the Multifunctional Information
                Distribution System (MIDS)</entry>

                <entry>Depends on transmission media. <para>Options include JREAP (see table below)
                for non-LOS or RF for LOS</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data Bearer</entry>

                <entry>IP-based (UDP or TCP), or RF</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Web Services</entry>

                <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                <entry>MISSING</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Operational Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 5616</entry>

                <entry>Message and Field forwarding rules between Link 11/11B and Link 16</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>STF Holistic Process to JREAP Analysis</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="34*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry nameend="c3" namest="c1">STF Holistic Process &lt;--&gt; JREAP</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>STF Layers mapped to IER</entry>

                <entry>IES/Specs per Layer</entry>

                <entry>STF Information Exchange Aspects</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Security Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                <entry>MISSING</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Business Rules</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 5518</entry>

                <entry>Not clearly defined; missing guidance on how to handle JREAP management
                messages (such as, Should management messages be forwarded? How should they be
                processed? How to avoid circular forwarding? etc.)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Message Structure</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 5518</entry>

                <entry>Variable length messages</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data Element Dictionary</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 5518: APPENDIX D DATA ELEMENT DICTIONARY</entry>

                <entry>Bit-based</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Routing</entry>

                <entry morerows="1">Appendix A- Half-Duplex Announced Token Passing
                Protocol<para>Appendix B Full-Duplex, Synchronous Or Asynchronous Point-To-Point
                Connection Protocol</para><para> Appendix C Encapsulation Over Internet Protocol
                (IP)</para></entry>

                <entry morerows="1">Depends on Transmission Media: see applicable Appendix</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data Bearer</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Web Services</entry>

                <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                <entry>MISSING</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Operational Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 5518</entry>

                <entry>Forwarding rules between tactical networks in English; needs to be specified
                in XML</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <sect4 id="conclusions-of-stf-applied-to-link-dash-one-six">
          <title id="conclusions-of-stf-applied-to-link-dash-one-six-title">Conclusions of STF
          applied to Link-16</title>

          <para>Capturing the specification of STANAG 5516 in XML has resulted in various relevant
          results:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>By applying an automated conversion from the Word-based STANAG, many errors have
              been found ranging from simple typos or layout inconsistencies to wrong references or
              missing definitions. These have been captured and provided to the TDL CaT for
              consideration for a DLCP.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>As various editions have been captured, an additional mechanism was available to
              verify the differences between subsequent versions.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>JREAP is an application-layer protocol &amp; message that enables transmitting
              Link-16 over IP. Therefore, STF can and was also applied to capture the information
              exchange requirements for that protocol.</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The STF was applicable for capturing the DED and MS of JREAP in XML.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>It was discovered that within the JREAP specification, STANAG 5518, there
                  were no clear guidance on the roles and responsibilities of JRE Processors for
                  forwarding management messages between JRE Processors networks. There are
                  references to Relay flags, but no explicit business rules for sending and
                  receiving management messages necessary for JREAP network management. This needs
                  to be captured and provided to the JREAP Custodians for consideration.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Neither STANAG 5516 nor STANAG 5518 provides any specifications or
                  discussions on Security or Web Services. These need to be remedied in order to
                  support the NNEC data strategy goals.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="link-two-two">
        <title id="link-two-two-title">Link 22</title>

        <para>Link 22 is being developed by the NATO Improved Link Eleven (NILE) Program. The goals
        of the development of Link 22 included the replacement of Link 11, complementing Link 16 and
        improvement of the Allied interoperability. As such, the Link 22 Data Elements and the
        Message Structure reuses many of the Link 16 ones contributing to increased standardization
        and interoperability.</para>

        <para>The Link 22 tactical messages and its data elements have been captured using the same
        XML Schemas as for Link 16. This provided the opportunity to perform an automatic
        comparision between the two resulting in a number of differences. Both the XML documents and
        the outcome of the comparison have been provided to the NILE community. Additional work on
        the messages and data elements used in the transport layer have been captured by NCI
        Agency-CapDev.</para>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>Link 16 Information Exchange Requirement (IER) Analysis</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colwidth="34*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Required NOV-3 Information Product</entry>

                <entry>Derived Information Product Requirement(s)</entry>

                <entry>Domain(s)</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Various incl. Recognized Maritime Picture (IP84), Maritime Intelligence
                Report/Summary (IP387/388), Electronic Warfare Mission Summary (IP326), Target Track
                Report (IP575), Merchant Shipping Situation Report (IP396)</entry>

                <entry>Tactical Data Exchange - Link 22(STANAG 5522)</entry>

                <entry>TDL, Operational Cross-Domain (Joint, Land, Air, Maritime, JISR), Security
                Cross-Domain</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>STF Holistic Process to Link 22 Analysis</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="34*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center" nameend="c3" namest="c1">STF Holistic Process &lt;--&gt; Link
                22</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>STF Layers mapped to IER</entry>

                <entry>IES/Specs per Layer</entry>

                <entry>STF Information Exchange Aspects</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Security Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                <entry>MISSING</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Business Rules</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 5522</entry>

                <entry>Not captured as STANAG does not provide transactions (yet) in same format as
                for Link 16</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Message Structure</entry>

                <entry morerows="1">STANAG 5522</entry>

                <entry>Fixed length messages</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data Element Dictionary</entry>

                <entry>Bit-based</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Routing</entry>

                <entry morerows="1">STANAG 4175 VOL I: Technical Characteristics of the
                Multifunctional Information Distribution System (MIDS)</entry>

                <entry morerows="1">RF for LOS</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data Bearer</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Web Services</entry>

                <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                <entry>MISSING</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Operational Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>non-NATO MIL-STD 6020</entry>

                <entry>Data Forwarding between Link 22 and Link 16 not captured as not yet covered
                in STANAG 5616</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <sect4 id="conclusions-on-stf-applied-to-link-dash-two-two">
          <title id="conclusions-on-stf-applied-to-link-dash-two-two-title">Conclusions on STF
          applied to Link-22</title>

          <para>Using the XML representation of both the Data Element Dictionary and the Message
          Structure, for both Link-16 and Link-22, comparisons have been carried out by NCI Agency
          to verify that Link-16 Data Elements reused for Link-22 are indeed defined identically.
          Likewise for the Link-22 FJ-messages, which should be an equivalent version of the Link-16
          J-message (with only 1 specific DataField prepended). Differences between the two have
          been analysed and reported to the NILE-PO.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="link-one">
        <title id="link-one-title">Link 1</title>

        <para>Link 1 is a point-to-point, duplex, non-encrypted, digital NATO Tactical Data Link
        (TDL) Standard for the automatic exchange of Track and Strobe data, combined with link and
        data management messages. It's governed by STANAG 5501 which mainly describes the various
        messages (S-series) and data elements. The S-series messages are bit-based, fixed length and
        can be easily captured in the STF XML Schemas. This has actually been done by NCI Agency to
        demonstrate the usage of the STF on other TDLs.</para>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>Link 1 Information Exchange Requirement (IER) Analysis</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colwidth="34*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Required NOV-3 Information Product</entry>

                <entry>Derived Information Product Requirement(s)</entry>

                <entry>Domain(s)</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Recognized Air Picture (IP82)</entry>

                <entry>Tactical Data Exchange - Link 1 (STANAG 5501)</entry>

                <entry>TDL</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>STF Holistic Process to Link 1 Analysis</title>

          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="34*"/>

            <colspec colwidth="33*"/>

            <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="33*"/>

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center" nameend="c3" namest="c1">STF Holistic Process &lt;--&gt; Link
                1</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>STF Layers mapped to IER</entry>

                <entry>IES/Specs per Layer</entry>

                <entry>STF Information Exchange Aspects</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Security Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                <entry>MISSING</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Business Rules</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 5501, ADatP-31</entry>

                <entry>Not captured as STANAG nor ADatP-31 provide full business rules, specifically
                not in same format as for Link 16 (transactions)</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Message Structure</entry>

                <entry morerows="1">STANAG 5501</entry>

                <entry>Fixed-length messages</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data Element Dictionary</entry>

                <entry>Bit-based</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Routing</entry>

                <entry morerows="1">RS-232, STANAG 5501</entry>

                <entry morerows="1">Communication is serial (RS-232) with Link-1 specifics described
                in STANAG 5501</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data Bearer</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Web Services</entry>

                <entry>NOT DEFINED</entry>

                <entry>MISSING</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Operational Cross-Domain</entry>

                <entry>STANAG 5601 (Data Forwarding between Link 1 and Link 11/11B)</entry>

                <entry>Not captured; STANAG does not contain full forwarding logic, e.g. message
                mapping</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <sect4 id="conclusions-on-stf-applied-to-link-dash-one">
          <title id="conclusions-on-stf-applied-to-link-dash-one-title">Conclusions on STF applied
          to Link-1</title>

          <para>Applying the STF to Link-1 demonstrated the following: <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>because of its simplicity, Link-1 was an easy information exchange to
                capture.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>capturing the layers that are actually covered by the STANAG 5501 turned out
                to be straightforward.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>it clearly highlighted layers that are not covered by any STANAG.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>even though some layers are covered in a STANAG, it also highlighted that
                these are lacking specific aspects ir not detailed enough (so requiring
                interpretation).</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="vmf">
        <title id="vmf-title">VMF</title>

        <para>Variable Message Format (VMF) provides a message catalogue of K-series messages
        described in STANAG 5519 which is the covering STANAG (to be ratified) for MIL-STD 6017.
        Together with a header message (described in MIL-STD 2045-47001) and bearer (MIL-STD
        188-220) it constitutes a tactical data link. From an STF perspective, this is an
        interesting format as it clearly separated the STF layers in different standards: one for
        the message catalogue (DED and Message Structure layers), one for the header (Routing layer)
        and one for the bearer (Bearer layer). Furthermore, by nature the messages or a variable
        length, requiring the STF XML Schemas to support also these types of messages.</para>

        <para>Even though the current STF version 1.0 does not cater for variable length messages,
        some experimentation have been done by NCI Agency to extend the XML schemas in preparation
        of version 2.0. Initially, the various Data Elements of VMF have been captured which has
        shown to be possible and result in XML instance documents that could be used for
        documentation purposes and verifications. Because of the nature of the structure of VMF
        messages, the XML Schema will require extensions to allow for optional DataField and Group
        of DataFields, and for repetitions of a DataField and a Group of DataFields. This will be
        added, taking backwards compatibility into account, to the XML Schemas for STF version
        2.0.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="v-and-v-for-other-information-exchanges-and-cois">
      <title id="v-and-v-for-other-information-exchanges-and-cois-title">V&amp;V for other
      information exchanges and COIs</title>

      <para>The STF, and in particular the DED and Message Structure schemas have been applied to
      several other information exchanges as detailed in the following sections.</para>

      <sect3 id="over-dash-the-dash-horizon-targeting-gold">
        <title id="over-dash-the-dash-horizon-targeting-gold-title">Over-the-horizon Targeting
        Gold</title>

        <para>Over-the-horizon Targeting Gold (OTH-Gold) is a text-based message format, mainly used
        in the maritime domain. It provides for a message set similar in structure and syntax to
        ADatP-11 Message Text Format (MTF) messages, with slant-delimited fields making up
        line-based Sets that are grouped into Messages. It's governed by the "Operational
        Specification for Over-the-horizon Targeting Gold" published by USA Navy Center for Tactical
        Systems Interoperability.</para>

        <para>The STF XML Schemas governing text-based information exchanges have been used to
        capture the Data Element Dictionary and Message Structure of OTH-Gold, although it's not a
        NATO STANAG. This demonstrated the following: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>STF can be successfully applied to OTH-Gold for capturing the DED and MS.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>OTH-Gold uses a nesting structure with one Set amplifying the previous. The
              OTH-Gold Message Structure STF representation can be enhanced to also indicate this
              nesting aspect. This is foreseen in the next version of the STF.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The OTH-Gold specification does not provide unique identifiers for its Data
              Elements. An initial approach has been taken to assign the DECI and DEI numbers
              although further harmonization is still required.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="methods">
    <title id="methods-title">Methods</title>

    <para>Please refer to the STF Holistic Process for the process for defining, applying and
    performing V&amp;V of the STF. This Process is applicable both for V&amp;V of the STF itself as
    well as for the V&amp;V of the STF artefacts produced by the application of the STF Design
    Rules.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="tools">
    <title id="tools-title">Tools</title>

    <para>NCI Agency exploited the capability to semi-automatically generate code to create tools to
    help validate the XML files in support of Interoperability Testing. In particular, the
    SMACQ/O-ANT tool suite is available that can be used to monitor the information exchange and to
    report on its compliance to the relevant Standards.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="outstanding-questions">
    <title id="outstanding-questions-title">Outstanding questions</title>

    <para>Not yet addressed within the current version of the STF.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="miscellaneous">
    <title id="miscellaneous-title">Miscellaneous</title>

    <para>Not yet addressed within the current version of the STF.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="future-plans">
    <title id="future-plans-title">Future Plans</title>

    <para>Work on the STF will continue with capturing further the missing aspects of current STF
    layers and adding the Design Rules and Methodology for additional layers including the XML
    Schemas to support it. The following is a planned list of items to work on:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data Element Dictionary and Message Structure for XML-Based information
          exchanges</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Message Structure for Variable-length Bit-based information exchanges</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Security Cross-domain Layer</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </sect1>
</appendix>
