<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
             Vol 4 -   A N N E X - H - CEMN profile

*****************************************************************  
-->

<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>

<appendix id="v4-h">
  <title>The Combined Endeavor Mission Network (CEMN) Profile of NATO Interoperability
    Standards</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Purpose</title>

    <blockquote><attribution>USEUCOM J6</attribution>
    <para>COMBINED ENDEAVOR (CE) is a Joint Chiefs of
    Staff (JCS) directed exercise consisting of a series of C4 related
    interoperability conferences and an exercise planned among NATO,
    NATO members, PfP nations and other organizations/formations
    within the NATO/PfP and invited nations framework who have their
    own C4 equipment. It follows a multiyear, collaborative process in
    an interactive, team-building environment with representatives
    from participating nations and organizations to design and execute
    an annual interoperability exercise</para></blockquote>

    <blockquote><attribution>USEUCOM J6</attribution>
    <para>For CE13, a Future Mission Network (FMN)
    management approach and real world Afghanistan Mission Network
    (AMN) experiences will be used to Plan, Govern, and Execute
    CE13. This will migrate CE from a multinational interoperability
    exercise to a mission focused coalition operation. All CE13 goals
    will be consistent with having NATO as a mission Partner as well
    as a mission Lead. EUCOM’s goal is to transform CE into an
    enduring multinational FMN trial event to improve the Speed and
    Effectiveness of ourselves and our partners in conducting
    coalition operations</para></blockquote>

    <para>NATO, through its interoperability directive, has recognized that widespread
      interoperability is a key component in achieving effective and efficient
      operations. In many of the operations world-wide in which NATO nations
      are engaged, they participate together with a wide variety of other organizations
      on the ground. Such organizations include coalition partners from non-NATO
      nations, Non-Governmental Organization (NGOs - e.g. Aid Agencies) and
      industrial partners. The NATO Interoperability Standards and Profile (NISP)
      provides the necessary guidance and technical components to support project
      implementations, exercises and transition to NATO Network Enabled Capability
      (NNEC).
    </para>
    <para>The figure
      <xref linkend="CEMN-Information-Environment" endterm="CEMN-Information-Environment-title"/>
      characterizes the information environment and various
      scenarios that exist for exchanging operational information. This environment,
      although rich in participation and basic connectivity, lacks fully meshed
      interoperability at the services layer. This diagram represents the CEMN
      environment, and the starting point for nations and NATO to plan for participation
      in Combined Endeavor 13. Future CE exercises will submit updates to this
      Annex as appropriate. It is presumed for the purposes of this document
      that the CEMN Profile will only address capabilities between the CEMN
      Core and national extensions.
    </para>
    <figure id="CEMN-Information-Environment" float="0">
      <title id="CEMN-Information-Environment-title">CEMN Information Environment</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="../figures/CEMN_Information_Environment.svg" format="SVG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>The purpose of this document is to define an Interoperability Standards
      Profile to support Combined Endeavor and transition from today's legacy
      systems to a federated networked environment by defining a useful level
      of interoperability.
    </para>
    <para>This document will also serve as a resource for NATO and national C4ISR
      planners, to be used as a guide in achieving interoperability among NATO
      nations, coalition partners and NATO provided capabilities who participate
      in Combined Endeavor. The CEMN Profile is for use throughout the complete
      lifecycle of the Future Mission Network framework as exercised by Combined
      Endeavor. The CEMN Profile will enable Net Centric operations by enhancing
      collaboration across the entire operational environment across all levels
      of command. Subsequent missions involving NATO and NATO nations will benefit
      from the modular nature of the CEMN Profile, which will allow for maximum
      reuse of established capabilities, while accommodating unique requirements
      and technology improvements.
    </para>
    <para>Additional benefits to deployment and sustained operations include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Speed of execution of operations,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Richer information environment,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>More dynamic information exchange between all members of the network,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Speedier standup of an NATO-led operation,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Reach-back to feature rich information enterprise(s), and</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Elimination of hierarchical information flow.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Participating nations are encouraged to use this document as part of the
      planning process for coordination and establishment of connectivity and
      interoperability with respect to joint/coalition NATO-led operations.
    </para>
    <para>Nations participating in CEMN agree to use this profile at Network Interconnection
      Points (NIPs) and at other Service Interoperability Points as applicable.
    </para>
    <para>Net-enabled Services must be able to function in a network environment
      containing firewalls and various routing and filtering schemes; therefore,
      developers must use standard and well-known ports wherever possible, and
      document non-standard ports as part of their service interface. Service
      developers must assume network behavior and performance consistent with
      the existing limits of these networks, taking bandwidth limitations and
      potentially unreliable networks into account.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Change Management</title>
    <para>Applying existing NATO standards or - in those areas where NATO STANAGS
      do not yet exist - International Standards are key for achieving interoperability
      in a federated environment. The dynamic nature of future operations results
      in unforeseen information exchange requirements within and across the
      supporting force. This might require the development and design of new
      Joining, Membership and Exiting Instructions (JMEI) for systems/capabilities
      within Combined Endeavor which do not exist. Since CE will not have a
      ‘formal’ body for Change management like the Coalition Interoperability
      Assurance and Validation (CIAV) Working Group, changes will most likely
      be part of CE Planning Conferences and/or execution schedule. CE will
      not develop new data exchange formats and leave that to other venues such
      as ACT led CWIX. JMEI shall be evaluated and developed in-line with existing
      NATO policies and guidelines so that they can be quickly transformed into
      standards (e.g. STANAGS) by the appropriate NATO Bodies based on the NATO
      Bi-SC Data Strategy, the NATO NNEC Data Strategy, and when appropriate,
      based on the APP-15 process. The CEMN Profile is maintained by the CEMN
      CJ6 Working Group and is expected to be upgraded every 12 months.
    </para>
    <para>ADatP-34 defines four stages within the life-cycle of a standard: emerging,
      mandatory, fading and retired; in those situations where multiple stages
      are mentioned, the CEMN Profile recommends dates by which the transition
      to the next stage is to be completed by all CEMN members. If a nation
      decides to implement emerging standards it is her responsibility to maintain
      backwards compatibility to the mandatory standard.
    </para>
    <para>Any discrepancies discovered between different elements of this Profile,
      shall be resolved through a change proposal prepared by the responsible
      NATO body or a CEMN member nation.
    </para>
    <para>CEMN Profile change requests can only be submitted by NATO civil or military
      bodies or CEMN member nations.
    </para>
    <para>The CEMN CJ6 Working Group will review updates to ADatP-34 and CEMN Profile
      change proposals and if required will produce a new version of the CEMN
      Profile. The CEMN profile of the NISP is reviewed by the CEMN CJ6 Working
      Group on a annual basis and requests for formal adoption by the Interoperability
      Profile Capability Team (IP CaT) are made by the WG on an annual basis.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Communication and Network Services Standards</title>
    <table>
      <title>Communication and Network Services Standards</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colwidth="30*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <thead valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry>Basic connectivity between technical services.</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Internet Protocol (IETF Standard 5, September 1981. RFCs 791/950/919/922/792/1112)</para>
              <para>Transmission Control Protocol IETF Standard 7, RFC 793:1981 updated by 3168:2001)</para>
              <para>Internet Protocol, Version 6 (IPv6) (IETF RFC 2460:1998)</para>
              <para>Domain Name System (IETF Standard 13, RFC 1034/RFC 1035:1987)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>IP networking. Accommodate both IPv4 and IPv6 addressing and Network Address
              Translation. Utilize Quality of Service capabilities of the network.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Connectivity between CEMN Core network and TCN networks</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>IEEE 802.3z Gigabit Ethernet (GbE)</para>
              <para>Border Gateway Protocol V4 (IETF RFC 1771, March 1995)</para>
              <para>BGP Communities Attribute (IETF RFC 1997, August 1996)</para>
              <para>Multicast Source Discovery Protocol (MSDP) (IETF RFC 3618, October 2003)</para>
              <para>Protocol Independent Multicast - Sparse Mode (PIM-SM) (IETF RFC 4601, August 2006)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>National Interconnection Point (NIP) as defined in the CE JMEI Technical
              Appendix 4.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Service transport protocol</entry>
            <entry>Hypertext Transfer Protocol - HTTP 1.1 (RFC 2616:1999)</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>HTTP shall be used as the transport protocol for information without 'need-to-know'
              caveats between all service providers and consumers.</para>
              <para>HTTPS shall be used as the transport protocol between all service providers and consumers
              to ensure confidentiality requirements.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Provide communications security over the network above the Transport Layer</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Mandatory: Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2 (RFC 5246:2008)</para>
              <para>Fading (until Dec 2011): Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.0
              (RFC 2246:1999)</para>
              <para>Retired: Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) Protocol, Version 3.0, 18 Nov 1996</para>
            </entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Voice communication</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>VoIP: SIP RFC 3261</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Audio data compression Codec ITU-T Recommendation G.729 (01/07)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>The use of G.729 may require a license fee and/ or royalty fee</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>DiffServ,PHB and DSCP defined by IETF RFC 2474</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>ITU-T G.Imp729 (11/09)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Interval between Voice packets 40ms</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>RTP protocol ports 16384 and/ or 16385</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Detailed Interface Control Document
                    for "Voice over Secure IP (VoSIP) Network Service" (C)</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Secure Network management</entry>
            <entry>Simple Network Management Protocol Version 3 (SNMPv3)</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Facilitate the access and au thorization between CEMN users</entry>
            <entry>Directory service: LDAPv3, RFC 4510</entry>
            <entry>Addressed by specific JMEI that facilitates network federation.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry></entry>
            <entry>Authentication: Kerberos version 5, RFC 1510</entry>
            <entry>LDAP is a vendor independent standard, in practice Active Directory (AD)
              is the most used product providing directory services on the CEMN. AD
              provides additional services aside from LDAP like functionality. The new
              Active Directory Federation Services 2.0 are likely to be used in future.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Infrastructure and Core Enterprise Services Standards</title>
    <table>
      <title>Infrastructure and Core Enterprise Services Standards</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colwidth="30*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <thead valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry>electronic mail (e-mail) transmission</entry>
            <entry>SMTP (RFC 1870:1995, 2821:2001), Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP)</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Publishing information including text, multimedia, hyperlink features,
              scripting languages and style sheets on the network</entry>
            <entry>HTML 4.01(RFC2854:2000), HyperText Markup Language (HTML), W3C</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Providing a common style sheet language for describing presentation semantics
              (that is, the look and formatting) of documents written in markup languages
              like HTML.</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Mandatory: Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), Level 2 revision 1 (CSS 2.1),
                W3C Recommendation, Sep 2009.</para>
              <para>Emerging : Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), Level 3(CSS 2)</para>
              <para>Fading (until Dec 2011): CSS Level 1, Jan 1999.</para>
            </entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Enable free text real time communication in combination with structured
              messages (data payload).</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>IETF RFC 6120 XMPP CORE covering XML streams, SASL, TLS, stanza semantics
                and RFC 6121 extensions for basic instant messaging and presence.</para>
              <para>The following XMPP Extension Protocols shall be supported:</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>XEP-0004: Data Forms</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>XEP-0012: Last Activity</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>XEP-0013: Flexible offline message retrieval</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>XEP-0030: Service Discovery</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>XEP-0045: Multi User Chat</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>XEP-0060: Publish and Subscribe</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>XEP-0082: XMPP Date and Time Profiles</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>XEP-0128: Service Discovery Extensions</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>XEP-0138: Stream Compression</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>XEP-0033: Extended Stanza Addressing and multiple group chat service
                    (emerging by Nov 11)</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>RFC 6120 supersedes RFC 3920 and RFC 6121 XMPP IM supersedes RFC 3921</para>
              <para>Developers are also advised to consult the following RFCs:</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>RFC 6122 XMPP ADDR XMPP address format</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>RFC 3923 XMPP E2E End- to-end signing and object encryption for XMPP</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>RFC 4854 XMPP URN A Uniform Resource Name (URN) tree for use in XMPP extensions</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>RFC 4979 XMPP ENUM IANA registration of an Enumservice (see RFC 3761) for XMPP</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>RFC 5122 XMPP URI A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) scheme for XMPP (this
                    specification corrects several errors in RFC 4622)</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry></entry>
            <entry>
              <para>XEP-0079: Advanced Message Processing to implement time-to-live (TTL)
              and reliability-in-delivery features or (emerging by Nov 11)</para>
              <para>XEP-0198: Stream Management for active management of an XML stream between two XMPP
              entities, including features for stanza acknowledgements and stream resumption.
              (emerging by Nov 11)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Providing web content or web feeds for syndication to web sites as well
              as directly to user agents.</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Mandatory: Really Simple Syndication (RSS) 2.0 Specification</para>
              <para>Emerging (by Dec 2011): Atom 1.0: Atom syndication format, Dec 2005 (RFC 4287)
                and Atom Publishing Protocol , Oct 2007 (RFC 5023)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Encoding of location as part of a web feeds</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Mandatory: GeoRSS Simple encoding.</para>
              <para>Where GeoRSS Simple is not appropriate
                the OGC GeoRSS Geography Markup Language (GML) Application Profile shall
                be used</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>GeoRSS extensions should be used to describe location aspects within ATOM
              and RSS feeds.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Message Security for web services</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>WS-Security: SOAP Message Security 1.1</para>
              <para>XML Encryption Syntax and Processing (dtd. 10 December 2002)</para>
              <para>XML Signature Syntax and Processing 1.0 (Second Edition)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Specifies how integrity and confidentiality can be enforced on messages
                and allows the communication of various security token formats, such as
                SAML, Kerberos, and X.509. Its main focus is the use of XML Signature
                and XML Encryption to provide end-to-end security.</para>
              <para>Specifies a process
              for encrypting data and representing the result in XML. Referenced by
              WS-Security specification.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry></entry>
            <entry></entry>
            <entry>Specifies XML digital signature processing rules and syntax. Referenced
              by WS-Security specification.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Security token format</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>SAML 2.0</para>
              <para>Web Services Security: SAML Token Profile 1.1</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Provides XML-based syntax to describe uses security tokens containing
                assertions to pass information about a principal (usually an end-user)
                between an identity provider and a web service.</para>
              <para>Describes how to use
                SAML security tokens with WS-Security specification.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Security token issuing</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>WS-Trust 1.4</para>
              <para>WS-Federation 1.1</para>
              <para>WS-Policy 1.5</para>
              <para>And WS-Security Policy 1.3</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Uses WS-Security base mechanisms and defines additional primitives and
                extensions for security token exchange to enable the issuance and dissemination
                of credentials within different trust domains.</para>
              <para>Extends WS-Trust to allow federation of different security realms.</para>
              <para>Used to describe what aspects
                of the federation framework are required/supported by federation participants
                and that this information is used to determine the appropriate communication
                options.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>General definition of data structure and the operations on data stored
              in that structure</entry>
            <entry>SQL 3 (ISO/IEC 9075(-1 to - 14):2003), Definition of data structure and
              the operations on data stored in that structure.</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Public Key Infrastructure to support SSL and single sign-on</entry>
            <entry>Version 3 public-key certificates and Version 2 CRLs in accordance with
              ITU-T X.509</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry></entry>
            <entry>NATO Public Key Infra-structure (NPKI) Certificate Policy (CertP) Rev2,
              AC/322- D(2004)0024REV2</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para>The CEMN architecture is intended to operate on fielded or near-fielded
      systems within the purview of the partner nations. Where new services
      must be created, they must be designed around the Request/Response, Publish/Subscribe,
      or Message Queue patterns. However, the intent is not to have CE as a
      development environment but rather use CE as a validation exercise to
      confirm interoperability with other systems/nations.
    </para>
    <para>New development must (in addition to forwarding back through developmental
      channels):
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>provide read or read/write services as appropriate</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>implement either synchronous or asynchronous services</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>include authentication as part of their service</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>support dynamic bindings</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The challenge is in re-using the existing data standards developed under
      ADatP-3 in this new service environment.
    </para>
    <table>
      <title>Infrastructure and Core Enterprise Services Standards, Part 2</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colwidth="30*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <thead valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry>Identification and addressing of objects on the network.</entry>
            <entry>RFC 1738, Uniform Resource Locators (URL), 20 December 1994 RFC 2396,
              Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI), Generic Syntax, August 1998 (updates
              RFC 1738)</entry>
            <entry>Namespaces within XML documents shall use unique URLs or URIs for the
              namespace designation.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>General formatting of information for sharing or exchange.</entry>
            <entry>Extensible Markup Language (XML), v1.0 3rd Edition XML Schema: Structures
              1.0 XML Schema: Data types 1.0 XML Namespaces: W3C (REC-xml-names-19990114)</entry>
            <entry>XML is required for data exchange to satisfy those IERs within the CEMN
              that are not addressed by a specific information exchange standard. XML
              Schemas and namespaces are required for all XML documents.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Transforming XML documents into other XML documents</entry>
            <entry>XSL Translation (XSLT 1.0)</entry>
            <entry>Developer best practice for the translation of XML based documents into
              other formats or schemas.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Specific, practical guidance for the development of web services, through
              constraints and clarifications to their base specifications.</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Web Services Interoperability Organization (WS-I) Basic Profile 1.1, Final
              Material, August 24, 2004; Note that this profile references several other
              standards associated with web services:</para>
              <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>SOAP, WSDL, UDDI</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Hypertext Transfer Protocol, HTTP v1.1</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>RFC2246 TLS Protocol v1.0</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>RFC2560, x.509 Public Key Infrastructure Certificate</para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist>
            </entry>
            <entry>Conformance to this standards-set is required for all SOAP based services.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Configuration management of structured data standards, service descriptions
              and other structured metadata.</entry>
            <entry>ebXML v3.0: Electronic business XML Version 3.0, Registry Information
              Model (ebRIM), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005, Registry Services and Protocols
              (ebRS), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005.</entry>
            <entry>Used as foundation for setup, maintenance and interaction with a Metadata
              Registry and Repository for sharing and configuration management of XML
              metadata. Also enables federation among metadata registries/repositories.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Exchanging structured information in a decentralized, distributed environment
              via services</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>W3C SOAP 1.1, Simple Object Access Protocol v1.1 (SOAP) Representational
              State Transfer (REST)</para>
              <para>WSDL v1.1: Web Services Description Language (WSDL)
                1.1, W3C Note, 15 March 2001.</para>
              <para>ebXML v3.0: Electronic business XML Version
                3.0,Registry Information Model (ebRIM), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005,Registry
                Services and Protocols (ebRS), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005.</para>
              <para>Universal Description, Discovery, and Integration Specification (UDDI v 2.0), OASIS
              Standard, April 2003.</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The preferred method for implementing webservices are SOAP, however, there
                are many use cases (mash-ups etc.) where a REST based interface is easier
                to implement and sufficient to meet the IERs.</para>
              <para>Used as foundation for
                setup, maintenance and interaction with a (NATO) Metadata Registry and
                Repository for sharing and configuration management of XML metadata. Also
                enables federation among metadata registries/repositories.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry></entry>
            <entry>Emerging (Dec 2011): UDDI v3.0</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Secure exchange of information across multiple security domains</entry>
            <entry>The Draft X-Labels syntax definition is called the "NATO Profile for the
              XML Confidentiality Label Syntax" and is based on version 1.0 of the RTG-031
              proposed XML Confidentiality Label Syntax See "Sharing of information
              across Communities of Interest and across Security Domains with Object
              Level Protection" below.</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Topic based Publish / subscribe web services communication</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>WS-Notification 1.3 including:</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>WS-Base Notification 1.3</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>WS-Brokered Notification 1.3</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>WS-Topics 1.3</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </entry>
            <entry>Enable topic based subscriptions for web service notifications, with extensible
              filter mechanism and support for message brokers.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Providing transport-neutral mechanisms to address web services</entry>
            <entry>WS-Addressing 1.0</entry>
            <entry>Provides transport-neutral mechanisms to address Web services and messages
              which is crucial in providing end-to-end message level security, reliable
              messaging or publish / subscribe based web services.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Reliable messaging for web services</entry>
            <entry>WS-Reliable Messaging 1.2</entry>
            <entry>Describes a protocol that allows messages to be transferred reliably between
              nodes implementing this protocol in the presence of software component,
              system, or network failures.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Community of Interest Services and Data Standards</title>
    <para>Many information exchange mechanisms between existing systems are built
      around complex and extensive military messaging standards, such as ADatP-3
      CONFORMETS, U.S. Message Text Format (USMTF) and the Variable Message
      Format (VMF). The intent of this CEMN interoperability profile is to specify
      the minimum subset of military message formats needed per service line.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Community of Interest Data and System Interoperability</title>
    <table>
      <title>COI Interoperability</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colwidth="30*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <thead valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry>General formatted message exchange</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>STANAG 5500 Ed.6:2009</para>
              <para>AdatP-3 - Concept of NATO Message Text Formatting
              System (CONFORMETS) - ADatP-3(A)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>ADatP-3(A) contains two different equivalent presentations of data: one
                as "classic" message or alternatively as XML-MTF instance.</para>
              <para>A) Automated
                processing of XML-files in static facilities/systems is much easier and
                thus preferred for the exchange between national CEMN extensions and the
                CEMN Core.</para>
              <para>B) At the tactical edge of the CEMN and the "classic" message
                format is the preferred option as this format is "leaner" and easier to
                transmit via tactical radio systems.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Automated information resource discover, information extraction and interchange
              of metadata</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>ISAF Minimum Metadata Implementation Policy, ISO 15836:2009 also known
                as the Dublin Core Metadata Element Set</para>
              <para>TIDE Information Discovery (v2.3.0, Oct 2009)</para>
              <para>TIDE Service Discovery (v.2.2.0 Oct 2008)</para>
              <para>Emerging (by Dec 2012): OpenSearch 1.1 Draft 4</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The policy defines a subset of the NATO Discovery Metadata Specification
                (NDMS) intended for information resource discovery.</para>
              <para>ISO 15836:2009 does not define implementation detail.</para>
              <para>The technical implementation specifications are part of the
                TIDE Transformational Baseline v3.0.</para>
              <para>The TIDE community is evaluating OpenSearch for potential inclusion
                into the TIDE Information Discovery specifications.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>General definition for the Representation of Dates and Times.</entry>
            <entry>ISO 8601:2004, Representation of Dates and Times.</entry>
            <entry>If not otherwise specified, implementation of the W3C profile of ISO 8601:2004
              is mandatory.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>General definition of letter codes for Geographical Entities</entry>
            <entry>STANAG 1059, Letter Codes for Geographical Entities (9th edition, 2005)</entry>
            <entry>Whenever possible, the ISO-3166 three-letter codes contained in STANAG
              1059 should be used</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>General definition of geospatial coverage areas in discovery metadata</entry>
            <entry>World Geodetic System (WGS) 84, ISO 19115 and ISO 19136 (for point references)</entry>
            <entry>ISO 19139 provides encoding guidance for ISO 19115</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>General definition of Security and Confidentiality metadata</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Emerging (Dec 2012):</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>NO-FFI 00961 (RTO spec on confidentiality labels);</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>NO-FFI 00962 (RTO spec on metadata binding);</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>NC3A TN-1455 (NATO profile of NO-FFI 00962);</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>NC3A TN-1456 (NATO profile of NO-FFI 00961).</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Asset/ consignment tracking</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The following two STANAGS require updating to reflect the IERs identified
                in ISAF CUR 254.</para>
              <para>STANAG 2185</para>
              <para>STANAG 2183</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Use for exchanging information with existing systems that process Asset
                and Consignment information.</para>
              <para>Note that their evolution is foreseen to
                also regulate the civilian convoy information exchange</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Geospatial Interoperability</title>
    <table>
      <title>Geospatial Interoperability</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colwidth="30*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <thead valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry>Distribution of compiled mapping (raster) data between applications.</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>OGC 04-024 (ISO 19128:2005), Web Map Service v.1.3</para>
              <para>Fading (Dec 2012): v1.0.0, v1.1.0, and v1.1.1</para>
              <para>OGC 05-078r4, OpenGIS Styled Layer Descriptor Profile of the
                Web Map Service (SLD) v.1.1.0</para>
              <para>OGC XXX, Web Map Tiling Service v.1.3 Emerging: Dec 2012</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>WMTS are to be provided as a complimentary service to WMS to ease access
              to users operating in bandwidth constraint environments. WMTS trades the
              flexibility of custom map rendering for the scalability possible by serving
              of static data (base maps) where the bounding box and scales have been
              constrained to discrete tiles which enables the use of standard network
              mechanisms for scalability such as distributed cache systems to cache
              images between the client and the server, reducing latency and bandwidth
              use.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Distribution of geo feature (vector) data between applications</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>OGC 04-094, Web Feature Service (WFS) v.1.1.</para>
              <para>OGC 06-049r1, GML Simple Feature Profil (GML 3.1.1) v.1.0.0
                Compliance Level 0</para>
              <para>OGC 04-095, Filter Encoding v.1.1</para>
            </entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Electronic interchange of geospatial data as coverages, that is, digital
              geospatial information representing space varying phenomena</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>OGC 07-067r2, Web Coverage Service (WCS) v.1.1.1</para>
              <para>Fading (Dec 2011): v1.0.0 and v1.1.0</para>
              <para>OGC Web Coverage Service (WCS) Standard Guidance Implementation
                Specification 1.0</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>Required for publishing coverage data.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Catalogue services support the ability to publish and search collections
              of descriptive information (metadata) for geospatial data, services, and
              related information objects.</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>OGC 07-006r1: Catalogue Service for the Web (CSW) v.2.0.2, SOAP message</para>
              <para>OGC 07-110r4, CSW-ebRIM Registry Service - Part 1:
                ebRIM profile of CSW v.1.0.1</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>Catalogue Services will be defined during CE planning events.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Electronic format for medium resolution terrain evaluation data.</entry>
            <entry>U.S. Military Specification Digital Terrain Elevation Data (DTED) level
              0,1,2 MIL- PRF-89020B</entry>
            <entry>Used to support line-of-sight analyses, terrain profiling, 3- D terrain
              visualization, mission planning/rehearsal, and modeling and simulation.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>File based storage and exchange of digital geospatial mapping (raster)
              data where services based access is not possible</entry>
            <entry>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Geotiff (a public domain metadata standard embedding georeferencing
                    information within a TIFF 6.0 file</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>JPEG2000 (ISO/IEC 15444-1 and 2)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Multiresolution seamless image database (MrSid Generation 2)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Enhanced Compressed Wavelet (ECW 3.3)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>NSA Compressed ARC Digitized Raster Graphics (CADRG)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Raster product format (RPF)</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </entry>
            <entry>This is provided for legacy systems, implementers are encouraged to upgrade
              their systems to consume OGC Web Services.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>File based storage and exchange of non-topological geometry and attribute
              information or digital geospatial feature (vector) data where services
              based access is not possible</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>ESRI SHAPE files</para>
              <para>Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC), Keyhole Markup Language
                (KML 2.2)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>This is provided for legacy systems, implementers are encouraged to upgrade
              their systems to provide/consume OGC Web Services.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Battlespace Management Interoperability</title>
    <table>
      <title>Battlespace Management Interoperability</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colwidth="30*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <thead valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry>Digital exchange of semantically rich information about Battlespace Objects
              such as units, their structural composition, Plans and Orders etc.</entry>
            <entry>STANAG 5523 – C2 Information Exchange model in conjunction with MIP Data
              Exchange Mechanism (DEM) Block 2/3/3.1</entry>
            <entry>Interoperability between MIP Block 2/3/3.1 is on going.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Expressing digital geographic annotation and visualization on, two-dimensional
              maps and three- dimensional globes</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>TIDE Transformational Baseline Vers. 3-0, NATO Vector Graphics (NVG)</para>
              <para>Mandatory: NVG 1.5</para>
              <para>Fading (Dec 2011): NVG 1.4</para>
              <para>Retired: NVG 0.3</para>
              <para>Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC), Keyhole Markup Language (KML 2.2)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>NVG shall be used as the standard Protocol and Data Format for encoding
                and sharing of information layers between Situational Awareness and C2
                systems.</para>
              <para>NVG and KML are both XML- based language schemas for expressing
                geographic annotations.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Exchanging information on Significant Activities (SIGACTs) in support
              of current operations</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>U.S.PM Battle Command</para>
              <para>SIGACT Schema<footnote><para>Document currently not included in NISP Vol.2 (ed. E),
                as it was not available from the author.</para></footnote></para>
            </entry>
            <entry>This schema is used via PASS, webservices and XMPP to exchange SIGACT
              information at Regional Command level and below.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Real time automated data exchange such as radar tracking information among
                airborne and land- based tactical data systems beyond line of sight.</para>
              <para>Message exchange Over Tactical Data Links</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>STANAG 5516, Ed.4:2008 - Tactical Data Exchange (Link 16)</para>
              <para>STANAG 5511, Feb 28, 2006 - Tactical Data Exchange (Link 11/11B);
                see also US MIL-STD 6011</para>
              <para>STANAG 5616 Ed 4:2008 - Standards for Data Forwarding between Tactical
                Data Systems employing Link 11/11B, Link 16 and Link 22.</para>
              <para>STANAG 5616 Ed 4:2008 - Standards for Data Forwarding between Tactical
                Data Systems employing Link 11/11B, Link 16 and Link 22.</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>CEMN members shall follow the specifications for automatic data exchange
              of tactical information with and among NATO tactical data systems, using
              the data transmission Links designated as Link 11/11B and Link 16.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Exchange of digital Friendly Force Information such as positional tracking
              information amongst airborne and land-based tactical data systems and
              C2 systems.</entry>
            <entry>AC/322-D(2006)0066 Interim NFFI Standard for Interoperability of Force
              Tracking Systems</entry>
            <entry>All positional information of friendly ground forces (e.g. ground forces
              of Troop Contributing Nations or commercial transport companies working
              in support of ISAF Forces) shall be as a minimum made available in a format
              that can be translated into the NFFI V1.3 format.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Message formats for exchanging information in low bandwidth environment
              between systems enabled for processing Military Message Format</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>STANAG 7149 Ed. 4 - NATO Message Catalogue - APP-11(C)</para>
              <para>Minimum set of messages supported by CEMN Core:</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>INCIDENT REPORT (A078)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>SARIR (J012)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>EVENTREP (J092)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>EODINCREP (J069)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>AIR SUPPORT REQUEST (F091)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>AIR TASKING ORDER (F058)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>AIRSPACE CONTROL ORDER (F011)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>PRESENCE REPORT (A009)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>SITREP (J095)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>ENEMY CONTACT REP (A023)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>CASEVACREQ (A015)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>KILLBOX MESSAGE (F083)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>INCIDENTSPOTREP (J006)</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
              <para>Emerging Dec 2012</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>SALTATIC (A073)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>CASEVACREQ (A015)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>MEDEVAC MESSAGE (A012)</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </entry>
            <entry>Assumption is that CE will use standard message formats.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Military Symbology interoperability</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>STANAG 2019, Ed.5:2008, Joint Symbology- APP-6(B)</para>
              <para>U.S. MIL-STD 2525 B Change 2, Common Warfighting Symbology</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>Note that both standards are not fully compatible with each other. A translation
              service may need to be provided at the CEMN integration core.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Providing a standard software interface for exchanging information about
              sensor planning, including information about capabilities of sensors,
              tasking of a sensors and status of sensor planning requests.</entry>
            <entry>Emerging (July 2012): OGC 09-000: OGC Sensor Planning Service Implementation
              Standard V.2.0, dated 2011-03-28</entry>
            <entry>For the CEMN, Sensor Planning Service implementations shall adhere to
              the SOAP binding as defined in OGC 09-000.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Joint Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconaissance (JISR) Interoperability</title>
    <para>AEDP-2, Ed.1:2005- NATO Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconnaissance
      Interoperability Architecture (NIIA). The NIIA provides the basis for
      the technical aspects of an architecture that provides interoperability
      between NATO nations' ISR systems. AEDP-2 provides the technical and management
      guidance for implementing the NIIA in ISR systems.
    </para>
    <table>
      <title>Joint Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconnaissance Interoperability</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colwidth="30*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <thead valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry>Storing and exchanging of images and associated data</entry>
            <entry>STANAG 4545, Ed. Amendment 1:2000, NATO Secondary Imagery Format (NSIF)</entry>
            <entry>AEDP-4, Ed. 1, NATO Secondary Imagery Format Implementation Guide, 15
              Jun 07, NU</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Providing a standard software interface for searching and retrieving for
              ISR products.</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>NATO Standard ISR Library Interface (NSILI)</para>
              <para>Mandatory: STANAG 4559, Ed. 3:2010 (starting Dec 2011)</para>
              <para>Fading: STANAG 4559, Ed. 2:2007 (beginning July 2011)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>AEDP-5, Ed. 1, NATO Standard Imagery Library Interface Implementation
                Guide, TBS, NU</para>
              <para>STANAG 4559,Ed.2 and Ed.3 are NOT compatible with each
                other (No backwards compatibility).</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Exchange of ground moving target indicator radar data</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>NATO Ground Moving Target Indicator (GMTI) Format</para>
              <para>Mandatory: STANAG 4607, Ed. 2:2007</para>
              <para>Emerging (Dec 2012): STANAG 4607, Ed.3:2010</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>AEDP-7, Ed. 1, NATO Ground Moving Target Indication (GMTI) Format Implementation
              Guide, TBS, NU</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Provision of common methods for exchanging of Motion Imagery (MI)across
              systems</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>NATO Digital Motion Imagery Standard</para>
              <para>Mandatory: STANAG 4609, Ed. 2:2007</para>
              <para>Emerging (Dec 2011): STANAG 4609, Ed. 3:2009</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>AEDP-8, Ed. 2, Implementation Guide For STANAG 4609- NDMI , Jun 07, NU</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Exchange of unstructured data (documents, jpeg imagery)</entry>
            <entry>IPIWIG V4 Metadata Specification:2009, Intelligence Projects Integration
              Working Group (IPIWG), Definition of metadata for unstructured Intelligence.
              <footnote><para>Document currently not included in NISP Vol.2 (ed. E), as it
              was not available from the author.</para></footnote>
            </entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Biometrics Data and System Interoperability (if used)</title>
    <para>Biometrics is a general term used alternatively to describe a characteristic
      or a process. As a characteristic, a biometric is a measurable biological
      (anatomical and physiological) and behavioral characteristic that can
      be used for automated recognition. As a process, a biometric is an automated
      method of recognizing an individual based on measurable biological (anatomical
      and physiological) and behavioral characteristics.
    </para>
    <table>
      <title>Biometrics Data and System Interoperability</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colwidth="30*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <thead valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Interchange of Fingerprint</para>
              <para>(Type 4 and 14) data</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000</para>
              <para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007 Part&nbsp;1</para>
              <para>EBTS 1.2 (references ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry></entry>
            <entry>
              <para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1 (references ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007) DOD EBTS 2.0</para>
              <para>ISO/IEC 19794-2:2005, part&nbsp;2</para>
            </entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Type 10 Facial</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>EFTS v7.0, EFTS v7.1</para>
              <para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1</para>
              <para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000, 1-2007 Part&nbsp;1</para>
              <para>EBTS 1.2 (references EFTS v7.0)DOD EBTS v2.0</para>
              <para>ISO/IEC 19794-5 w/ Amd 1:2007, part&nbsp;5</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Type 16 Iris</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000, 1-2007 Part&nbsp;1</para>
              <para>EBTS 1.2</para>
              <para>ISO/IEC 19794-6</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Type 17 Iris</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007 Part 1</para>
              <para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1 (ref ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007)</para>
              <para>DOD EBTS v2.0</para>
              <para>ISO/IEC 19794-6</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>User Interface Capabilities/Applications</title>
    <para>User Applications, also known as application software, software applications,
      applications or apps, are computer software components designed to help
      a user perform singular or multiple related tasks and provide the logical
      interface between human and automated activities.
    </para>
    <table>
      <title>User Interface Capabilities/Applications</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colwidth="30*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <colspec colwidth="35*" />
        <thead valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis></entry>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis></entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="top">
          <row>
            <entry>Displaying content within web browsers.</entry>
            <entry>W3C Hypertext Markup Language HTML 4.0.1</entry>
            <entry>Applications must support the following browsers: Microsoft</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry></entry>
            <entry>
              <para>W3C Extensible Hypertext Markup Language XHTML 1.0</para>
              <para>W3C Cascading Style Sheets CSS 2.0</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>Internet Explorer v7.0 and newer, and Mozilla Firefox 3.0 and newer. When
              a supported browser is not true to the standard, choose to support the
              browser</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Browser plug-ins.</entry>
            <entry>Browser plug-ins are not covered by a single specification.</entry>
            <entry>Some CEMN members do not allow the use of ActiveX controls in the browser.
              Use of browser plug-ins should be minimized.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Visualize common operational symbology within C4ISR systems in order to
              convey information about objects in the battlespace.</entry>
            <entry>
              <para>STANAG 2019, Ed.5:2008, Joint Symbology- APP-6(B)</para>
              <para>U.S. MIL-STD 2525 B Change 2, Common Warfighting Symbology</para>
              <para>TIDE Transformational Baseline Vers. 3-0, NATO Vector Graphics (NVG)</para>
              <para>Mandatory: NVG 1.5</para>
              <para>Fading (Dec 2011): NVG 1.4</para>
              <para>Retired: NVG 0.3</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>All presentation service shall render tracks, tactical graphics, and MOOTW
              objects using this standard except in the case where the object being
              rendered is not covered in the standard. In these exceptional cases, additional
              symbols shall be defined as extensions of existing symbols and must be
              backwards compatible. These extensions shall be submitted as a change
              proposal within the configuration control process to be considered for
              inclusion in the next version of the specification.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Reliable messaging over XMPP</entry>
            <entry>XMPP Clients must implement the following XMPP protocol extensions XEP-0184
              for message receipts, whereby the sender of a message can request notification
              that it has been received by the intended recipient, and XEP 0202 for
              communicating the local time of an entity.</entry>
            <entry>All XMPP Chat Clients used on the CEMN shall implement these two protocol
              extensions.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Collaborative generation of spreadsheets, charts, presentations and word
              processing documents</entry>
            <entry>ECMA-376, Ed. 1: 2006 Office Open XML</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry></entry>
            <entry>Emerging (Dec 2012): Document description and processing languages ISO/IEC
              29500:2008 (transitional)</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Document exchange, storage and archiving</entry>
            <entry>Document management -- Electronic document file format for long-term preservation
              –ISO 19005-1:2005 Part 1: Use of PDF 1.4 (PDF/A-1)</entry>
            <entry></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>References</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>[1] MC 245 Statement of Military Requirement for Interoperability between
          Automated Data Systems.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[2] Allied Data Publication 34 (ADatP-34) NATO Interoperability Standards
          and Profiles (NISP) STANAG 5524.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[3] NATO C3 System Interoperability Policy, AC/322-D(2004)0039 dated 13
          Sep 2004.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>[4] NATO C3 System Interoperability Directive, AC/322-D(2004)0040 dated
          13 Sep 2004.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
</appendix>
