<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 4 - A N N E X - D
*****************************************************************  
-->

<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v4-d">
    <title>The Afghanistan Mission Network (AMN) Profile of NATO Interoperability
      Standards</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Purpose</title>

    <para>NATO, through its interoperability directive, has recognized that widespread 
    interoperability is a key component in achieving effective and efficient operations.
    In many of the operations world-wide in which NATO nations are engaged, they 
    participate together with a wide variety of other organizations on the ground.
    Such organizations include coalition partners from non-NATO nations, Non-Governmental
    Organization (NGOs - e.g. Aid Agencies) and industrial partners. The NATO Interoperability 
    Standards and Profile (NISP) provides the necessary guidance and technical components
    to support project implementations and transition to NATO Network Enabled Capability
    (NNEC).</para>

    <para>The purpose of this document is to define an Interoperability Standards 
    Profile to support the Afghanistan Mission Network (AMN) and transition from 
    today's legacy systems to NNEC be defining a basic level of system interoperability 
    in order to enhance the exchange of information within and across the AMN. To
    support the goal of widespread interoperability the AMN Profile defines a minimum
    profile of services and standards for Technical Interfaces <footnote><para>Technical 
    Interfaces - specify interfaces and interactions between components and sub-systems,
    including the possible use of security mechanisms to protect stored data and 
    data transferred between systems; and specify the architecture and operation
    of systems in order to identify the standards that are needed to support multi-national,
    multi-vendor systems and their applications.</para></footnote>, Data Interchange Standards
    <footnote><para>Data Interchange Formats - specify the content, meaning, and representation
    of formats for the interchange of data, and specify notation and transfer formats
    that provide platform independence and separation of transfer syntax from content
    definition.</para></footnote> and Application Profile Standards<footnote><para>Application
    Profile Standards - specify one or more base standards and standardized profiles, 
    and where applicable, the identification of chosen classes, conforming subsets, 
    options, and parameters of those base standards or standardized profiles necessary
    to accomplish a particular function.</para></footnote> that are sufficient to provide
    a useful level of interoperability. The AMN Profile is structured along the new
    NNEC Framework developed by Allied Command Transformation and NC3A.</para>
    
    <para>The AMN Profile focuses primarily on the upper two OSI layers and assumes 
    that all participants are using IP v4 packet-switched, routed networks (at least 
    at least to their network boundaries). Interoperability will be supported through
    Network Interconnection Points (NIPs) between component networks and systems 
    providing a limited set of automated information exchange C2 information including
    but not limited to: Chat / Instant Messaging, E-mail with attachments, Web publishing/access,
    File transfer, VTC and Voice over IP telephony.</para>
    
    <para>This profile will be used in the implementation of NATO Common Funded Systems.
    Nations participating in AMN agree to use this profile at Network Interconnection 
    Points (NIPs) and at other Service Interoperability Points as applicable.</para>
    
    <para>NNEC Services must be able to function in a network environment containing
    firewalls and various routing and filtering schemes; therefore, developers must
    use standard and well-known ports wherever possible, and document non-standard
    ports as part of their service interface. Service developers must assume network
    behavior and performance consistent with the existing limits of these networks,
    taking bandwidth limitations and potentially unreliable networks into account.</para>
    
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Change Management</title>
    
    <para>Applying existing NATO standards or - in those areas where NATO STANAGS
    do not yet exist - International Standards are key for achieving interoperability
    in a federated environment. The dynamic nature of ISAF operations results in
    unforeseen information exchange requirements within and across ISAF. This might
    require the development and design of new data and metadata exchange formats 
    which are not part of current STANAGs and/or Standards. Those ad-hoc formats
    shall be developed in-line with existing NATO policies and guidelines so that
    they can be quickly transformed into standards (e.g. STANAGS) by the appropriate 
    NATO Bodies based on the NATO Bi-SC Data Strategy, the NATO NNEC Data Strategy, 
    and when appropriate, based on the APP-15 process.The AMN Profile is being maintained
    by the AMN Architecture Working Group; it is a living document and is expected 
    to be updated every six months.</para>
    
    <para>ADatP-34 defines four stages within the life-cycle of a standard: emerging,
    mandatory, fading and retired; in those situations where multiple stages are 
    mentioned the AMN Profile recommends dates by which the transition to the next
    stage is to be completed by all AMN members. If a nation decides to implement
    emerging standards it is her responsibility to maintain backwards compatibility
    to the mandatory standard.</para>
    
    <para>Any discrepancies discovered between different elements of this Profile,
    shall be resolved through a change proposal prepared by the responsible NATO
    body or an AMN member nation.</para>
    
    <para>AMN Profile change requests can only be submitted by NATO civil or military
    bodies or AMN member nations.</para>
    
    <para>The AMN Architecture Working Group will review updates to ADatP-34, the
    ISAF Baseline Architecture and AMN Profile change proposals and if required will
    produce a new version of the AMN Profile. The updated AMN Profile will be submitted
    by the AMN Architecture Working Group to the NATO Open Standards Working Group 
    (NOSWG) for publication under ADatP-34.</para>
    
    <para>The AMN profile v.0.5 was changed by the AMN WG during the NOSWG Meeting
    in December 2010: Voice communications are now based on SIP (instead of H.323),
    the Figure on the AMN Service Structure was removed and for the usage of C2IEDM 
    Bussiness Rule F11.2 b was excluded.</para>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Communication and Network Services Standards</title>
    
      <table frame="all" id="v4t-Comms-andNetwork-Stds">
        <title>Communication and Network Services Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Basic connectivity between technical services.</entry>
              <entry>Internet Protocol (IETF Standard 5, September 1981. RFCs 
                791/950/919/922/792/1112)
                <para>Transmission Control Protocol (IETF Standard 7, RFC 793:1981
                  updated by 3168:2001)</para>
                <para>Internet Protocol, Version 6 (IPv6) (IETF RFC 2460:1998)</para>
                <para>Domain Name System (IETF Standard 13, RFC 1034/RFC 1035:1987)
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>IP networking. Accommodate both IPv4 and IPv6 addressing and
                Network Address Translation. Utilize Quality of Service capabilities
                of the network.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Service transport protocol</entry>
              <entry>Hypertext Transfer Protocol - HTTP 1.1 (RFC 2616:1999)</entry>
              <entry>HTTP shall be used as the transport protocol for information 
                without 'need-to-know' caveats between all service providers and 
                consumers.
                <para>HTTPS shall be used as the transport protocol between all 
                  service providers and consumers to ensure confidentiality requirements.
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Provide communications security over the network above the 
                Transport Layer</entry>
              <entry>Mandatory: Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.2 
                (RFC 5246:2008)
                <para>Fading (until Dec 2011): Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol
                  Version 1.0 (RFC 2246:1999)</para>
                <para>Retired: Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) Protocol, Version 3.0, 18 
                  Nov 1996</para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Voice communication</entry>
              <entry>VoIP: SIP RFC 3261</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Secure Network management</entry>
              <entry>Simple Network Management Protocol Version 3 (SNMPv3)</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Facilitation of secure, flexible, jam resistant information 
                transfer in real time among dispersed and mobile units</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 4175 Ed.4:2009 - Technical Characteristics of the Multifunctional
                Information Distribution System (MIDS).</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 4175 provides a detailed technical specification for MIDS 
                terminals and is the governing document for MIDS terminal design 
                and TDL network architecture.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Facilitate the access and authorization between AMN users</entry>
              <entry>Directory service: LDAPv3, RFC 4510
                <para>Authentication: Kerberos version 5, RFC 1510</para></entry>
              <entry>The AMN OPT has identified three options available to a nation
                when joining their national network extension to the AMN:
                <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
                  <listitem><para>Join ISAF Secret Forest</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Join CX-I Forest</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Create standalone TCN forest</para></listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>(Option 1 and 2 should be considered before option 3. Ref: 
                  AMN Systems engineering CONOPS dated 29 April 10).</para>
                <para>Whilst LDAP is a vendor independent standard, in practice 
                  Active Directory (AD) is the product providing directory services
                  on the AMN. AD provides additional services aside from LDAP like 
                  functionality. The new Active Directory Federation Services 2.0
                  are likely to be used in future to better support Option 3 above.
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Infrastructure and Core Enterprise Services Standards</title>
    
      <table frame="all" id="v4t-CES-Stds">
        <title>Infrastructure and Core Enterprise Services Standards</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>electronic mail (e-mail) transmission</entry>
              <entry>SMTP (RFC 1870:1995, 2821:2001), Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP)
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Publishing information including text, multimedia, hyperlink 
                features, scripting languages and style sheets on the network</entry>
              <entry>HTML 4.01(RFC2854:2000), HyperText Markup Language (HTML), W3C</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Providing a common style sheet language for describing presentation 
                semantics (that is, the look and formatting) of documents written
                in markup languages like HTML.</entry>
              <entry>Mandatory: Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), Level 2 revision 1 
                (CSS 2.1), W3C Recommendation, Sep 2009.
                <para>Emerging : Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), Level 3(CSS 2)</para>
                <para>Fading (until Dec 2011): CSS Level 1, Jan 1999.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Enable free text real time communication in combination with
                structured messages (data payload).</entry>
              <entry>IETF RFC 3920:2004 - 3923:2004, Extensible Messaging and Presence 
                Protocol (XMPP) - An open technology for real-time communication.
                <para>The following XMPP Extension Protocols shall be supported:
                </para>
                <para>XEP-0004: Data Forms</para>
                <para>XEP-0012: Last Activity</para>
                <para>XEP-0013: Flexible offline message retrieval</para>
                <para>XEP-0030: Service Discovery</para>
                <para>XEP-0045: Multi User Chat</para>
                <para>XEP-0060: Publish and Subscribe</para>
                <para>XEP-0082: XMPP Date and Time Profiles</para>
                <para>XEP-0128: Service Discovery Extensions</para>
                <para>XEP-0138: Stream Compression</para>
                <para>XEP-0163: Personal Eventing Protocol</para></entry>
              <entry>RFC 3920 and RFC 3921 are currently being revised to correct
                errors, clarify matters that were underspecified, and incorporate
                feedback based on implementation and deployment experience gained 
                since RFC 3920 and RFC 3921 were published in 2004.
                <para>Developers are also advised to consult rfc3920bis and rfc3921bis,
                  which provide the most up-to-date and accurate description the 
                  core XMPP protocols.</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Providing web content or web feeds for syndication to web sites
                as well as directly to user agents.</entry>
              <entry>Mandatory: Really Simple Syndication (RSS) 2.0 Specification
                <para>Emerging (by Dec 2011): Atom 1.0: Atom syndication format, 
                  Dec 2005 (RFC 4287) and Atom Publishing Protocol , Oct 2007 (RFC 5023)
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Encoding of location as part of a web feeds</entry>
              <entry>Mandatory: GeoRSS Simple encoding.
                <para>Where GeoRSS Simple is not appropriate the OGC GeoRSS Geography 
                  Markup Language (GML) Application Profile shall be used</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>GeoRSS extensions should be used to describe location aspects
                within ATOM and RSS feeds.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Sharing identity information in order to identify which users 
                are trusted and what types of credentials can be securely accepted 
                to enable secure sharing of information in a federated environment.</entry>
              <entry>WS-* family of data Web services.
                <para>WS* family of Open Standards provide a foundation for delivering 
                  complete, interoperable federated identity and security capabilities
                  which include:</para>
                <para>WS-Security</para>
                <para>WS-Security (WSS) describes how to attach security tokens,
                  including binary security tokens such as X.509 certificates and
                  Kerberos tickets, to SOAP messages.</para>
                <para>WS-Federation</para>
                <para>WS-Federation specification identifies two sources of identity
                  and authentication requests across trust realms: active requestors, 
                  such as SOAP-enabled applications, and passive requestors, which 
                  are defined as HTTP browsers capable of supporting broadly supported
                  HTTP, for example, HTTP 1.1.</para>
                <para>XACML</para>
                <para>Extensible Access Control Markup Language (XACML) is an Organization
                  for the Advancement of Structured Information Systems (OASIS) standard 
                  that describes both a policy language and an access control decision
                  request/response language (both written in XML).</para>
                <para>SAML</para>
                <para>Security Assertions Markup Language (SAML) is an XML-based 
                  framework for communicating user authentication, entitlement, and
                  attribute information. As its name suggests, SAML allows business 
                  entities to make assertions regarding the identity, attributes,
                  and entitlements of a subject (an entity that is often a human user)
                  to other entities, such as a partner company or another enterprise
                  application.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>NATO and TCNs shall use federated access and identity management
                tools and applications which comply with the Open WS * standards when 
                they want to provide access to and share information with other coalition
                partners.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>General definition of data structure and the operations on data 
                stored in that structure</entry>
              <entry>SQL 3 (ISO/IEC 9075(-1 to - 14):2003), Definition of data structure 
                and the operations on data stored in that structure.</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Public Key Infrastructure to support SSL and single sign-on</entry>
              <entry>Version 3 public-key certificates and Version 2 CRLs in accordance
                with ITU-T X.509
                <para>NATO Public Key Infrastructure (NPKI) Certificate Policy (CertP)
                  Rev2, AC/322-D(2004)0024REV2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    
      <para>Within the AMN architecture, new services must be designed around the 
        Request/Response, Publish/Subscribe, or Message Queue patterns. For the AMN 
        architecture, developers must:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>provide read or read/write services as appropriate
            </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>implement either synchronous or asynchronous services
            </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>include authentication as part of their service</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem><para>support dynamic bindings</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>The challenge is in re-using the existing data standards developed 
        under ADatP-3 in this new service environment.</para>
        
      <table frame="all" id="v4t-CES-Stds2">
        <title>Infrastructure and Core Enterprise Services Standards, Part2</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Identification and addressing of objects on the network.</entry>
              <entry>RFC 1738, Uniform Resource Locators (URL), 20 December 1994
                RFC 2396, Uniform Resource Identifiers (URI), Generic Syntax, August 
                1998 (updates RFC 1738)
              </entry>
              <entry>Namespaces within XML documents shall use unique URLs or URIs
                for the namespace designation.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>General formatting of information for sharing or exchange.</entry>
              <entry>Extensible Markup Language (XML), v1.0 3rd Edition XML Schema:
                Structures 1.0 XML Schema: Data types 1.0 XML Namespaces: W3C 
                (REC-xml-names-19990114)</entry>
              <entry>XML is required for data exchange to satisfy those IERs within
                the AMN that are not addressed by a specific information exchange 
                standard. XML Schemas and namespaces are required for all XML documents.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Transforming XML documents into other XML documents</entry>
              <entry>XSL Translation (XSLT 1.0)</entry>
              <entry>Developer best practice for the translation of XML based documents 
                into other formats or schemas.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Specific, practical guidance for the development of web services,
                through constraints and clarifications to their base specifications.</entry>
              <entry>Web Services Interoperability Organization (WS-I) Basic Profile 
                1.1, Final Material, August 24, 2004; Note that this profile references
                several other standards associated with web services:
                <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
                  <listitem><para>SOAP, WSDL, UDDI</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Hypertext Transfer Protocol, HTTP v1.1</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>RFC2246 TLS Protocol v1.0</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>RFC2560, x.509 Public Key Infrastructure Certificate</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>Conformance to this standards-set is required for all SOAP based
                services.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Configuration management of structured data standards, service 
                descriptions and other structured metadata.</entry>
              <entry>ebXML v3.0: Electronic business XML Version 3.0, Registry Information 
                Model (ebRIM), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005, Registry Services and 
                Protocols (ebRS), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005.</entry>
              <entry>Used as foundation for setup, maintenance and interaction with
                a (AMN/ISAF) Metadata Registry and Repository for sharing and configuration
                management of XML metadata. Also enables federation among metadata 
                registries/repositories.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Exchanging structured information in a decentralized, distributed
                environment via services</entry>
              <entry>W3C SOAP 1.1, Simple Object Access Protocol v1.1 (SOAP)
                <para>Representational State Transfer (REST)</para>
                <para>WSDL v1.1: Web Services Description Language (WSDL) 1.1, W3C 
                  Note, 15 March 2001.</para>
                <para>ebXML v3.0: Electronic business XML Version 3.0,Registry Information 
                  Model (ebRIM), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005,Registry Services and 
                  Protocols (ebRS), OASIS Standard, 2 May 2005.</para>
                <para>Universal Description, Discovery, and Integration Specification
                  (UDDI v 2.0), OASIS Standard, April 2003.</para>
                <para>Emerging (Dec 2011): UDDI v3.0.4</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>The preferred method for implementing webservices are SOAP, 
                however, there are many use cases (mash-ups etc.) where a REST based 
                interface is easier to implement and sufficient to meet the IERs.
                <para>Used as foundation for setup, maintenance and interaction with
                  a (NATO) Metadata Registry and Repository for sharing and configuration
                  management of XML metadata. Also enables federation among metadata 
                  registries/repositories.</para>
                <para>AMN transition strategy to UDDI 3.0.4 needs to be developed
                  for 2011.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Secure exchange of information across multiple security domains</entry>
              <entry>The Draft X-Labels syntax definition is called the "NATO Profile
                for the XML Confidentiality Label Syntax" and is based on version 
                1.0 of the RTG-031 proposed XML Confidentiality Label Syntax See 
                "Sharing of information across Communities of Interest and across 
                Security Domains with Object Level Protection" below.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Community of Interest Services and Data Standards</title>
      
      <para>Many information exchange mechanisms between existing systems are built
      around complex and extensive military messaging standards, such as ADatP-3 
      CONFORMETS, U.S. Message Text Format (USMTF) and the Variable Message Format
      (VMF). The intent of this AMN interoperability profile is to specify the minimum
      subset of military message formats needed per service line.</para>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Community of Interest Data and System Interoperability</title>
      
      <table frame="all" id="v4tTech-services">
        <title>COI Interoperability</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>General formatted message exchange</entry>
              <entry>AdatP-3 - Concept of NATO Message Text Formatting System (CONFORMETS)
                and NATO Message Text Formatting System (FORMETS)
                <para>Mandatory: STANAG 5500 Ed.6:2009</para>
                <para>Emerging (Dec 2012): STANAG 5500 Ed.7:2010</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Use for exchanging information with existing systems that process 
                MTF messages.
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem><para>Observation Report</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Position Report</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>SITREP</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Air Support Request: ADatP-3 BL 11Future F091</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>Any addition or expansion of MTF messages or data dictionaries 
                  shall be developed in XML-MTF (9-liner MEDEVAC request, 15 -liner, 
                  SALTA reports etc.). All those extensions shall be submitted as 
                  a change proposal within the configuration control process to be 
                  considered for inclusion in the next version of the specification.
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Automated information resource discover, information extraction
                and interchange of metadata</entry>
              <entry>ISAF Minimum Metadata Implementation Policy, ISO 15836:2009 
                also known as the Dublin Core Metadata Element Set
                <para>TIDE Information Discovery (v2.3.0, Oct 2009)</para>
                <para>TIDE Service Discovery (v.2.2.0 Oct 2008)</para></entry>
              <entry>The policy defines a subset of the NATO Discovery Metadata
                Specification (NDMS) intended for information resource discovery.
                <para>ISO 15836:2009 does not define implementation detail.</para>
                <para>The technical implementation specifications are part of the 
                  TIDE Transformational Baseline v3.0.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>General definition for the Representation of Dates and Times.</entry>
              <entry>ISO 8601:2004, Representation of Dates and Times.</entry>
              <entry>If not otherwise specified, this format shall be used for representing 
                Dates and Time values.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>General definition of letter codes for Geographical Entities</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 1059, Letter Codes for Geographical Entities (9th edition, 2005)
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>General definition of geospatial coverage areas in discovery metadata</entry>
              <entry>World Geodetic System (WGS) 84, ISO 19115 and ISO 19136 (for point 
                references)</entry>
              <entry>ISO 19139 provides encoding guidance for ISO 19115</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>General definition of Security and Confidentiality metadata</entry>
              <entry>Community Security Requirements Statement For The Afghan Mission 
                Network, Version 1.1, 2 June 2010.
                <para>(See also ISAF Minimum Metadata Implementation Policy, Amendment
                  A: Metadata Encoding Guidance for the ISAF Minimum Metadata Standard 
                  and STANAG 1059 (9th edition, 2005)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>All system and programme managers have to plan to implement 
                these new standards in their individual area of responsibility. See 
                NATO Profile for the XML Confidentiality Label Syntax and NATO Profile
                for the Binding of Metadata to Data Objects for implementation detail.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Sharing of information across Communities of Interest and across 
                Security Domains with Object Level Protection</entry>
              <entry>Emerging (Dec 2012): XML Confidentiality Label Syntax Version 1.0 
                of the RTG-031 proposed XML Confidentiality Label Syntax (FFI Publication).
                <para>NATO Profile for the XML Confidentiality Label Syntax (NC3A 
                  RD-2903).</para>
                <para>Binding of Metadata to Data Objects Version 1.0 of the RTG-031 
                  proposed Binding of Metadata to Data Objects (FFI Publication).
                  </para>
                <para>NATO Profile for the Binding of Metadata to Data Objects 
                  (NC3A RD-2977).</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Emerging: The XML-Labeling and Binding specifications are published 
                as annexes to the final report of RTO Task Group IST-068/RTG-031 on
                &ldquo;XML in Cross-Domain Security Solutions&rdquo;. They are also available as 
                separate publication by the Norwegian Forsvarets forskningsinstitutt 
                (FFI)
                <para>For use within NATO specific NATO profiles of these specifications 
                  must be used. These are available as NC3A Reference Documents</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Asset/ consignment tracking</entry>
              <entry>The following two STANAGS require updating to reflect the IERs 
                identified in ISAF CUR 254.
                <para>STANAG 2185</para>
                <para>STANAG 2183</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Use for exchanging information with existing systems that process
                Asset and Consignment information.
                <para>Note that their evolution is foreseen to also regulate the 
                  civilian convoy information exchange</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Geospatial Interoperability</title>
  
      <table frame="all" id="v4Geospatial-interop">
        <title>Geospatial Interoperability</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Distribution of compiled mapping (raster) data between applications.</entry>
              <entry>OGC 04-024 (ISO 19128:2005), Web Map Service v.1.3
                <para>Fading (Dec 2012): v1.0.0, v1.1.0, and v1.1.1</para>
                <para>OGC 05-078r4, OpenGIS Styled Layer Descriptor Profile of the 
                  Web Map Service (SLD) v.1.1.0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Distribution of geo feature (vector) data between applications</entry>
              <entry>OGC 04-094, Web Feature Service (WFS) v.1.1.
                <para>OGC 06-049r1, GML Simple Feature Profil (GML 3.1.1) v.1.0.0 
                  Compliance Level 0</para>
                <para>OGC 04-095, Filter Encoding v.1.1</para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Electronic interchange of geospatial data as coverages, that is, 
                digital geospatial information representing space varying phenomena</entry>
              <entry>OGC 07-067r2, Web Coverage Service (WCS) v.1.1.1
                <para>Fading (Dec 2011): v1.0.0 and v1.1.0</para>
                <para>OGC Web Coverage Service (WCS) Standard Guidance Implementation 
                  Specification 1.0</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Required for publishing coverage data.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Catalogue services support the ability to publish and search 
                collections of descriptive information (metadata) for geospatial 
                data, services, and related information objects.</entry>
              <entry>OGC 07-006r1: Catalogue Service for the Web (CSW) v.2.0.2, SOAP
                message
                <para>OGC 07-110r4, CSW-ebRIM Registry Service - Part 1: ebRIM profile
                  of CSW v.1.0.1</para></entry>
              <entry>Catalogue Services will be supported by Core GIS FSD2 on the 
                AMN Core.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Electronic format for medium resolution terrain evaluation data.</entry>
              <entry>U.S. Military Specification Digital Terrain Elevation Data (DTED)
                level 0,1,2 MIL-PRF-89020B</entry>
              <entry>Used to support line-of-sight analyses, terrain profiling, 3-D 
                terrain visualization, mission planning/rehearsal, and modeling and 
                simulation.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>File based storage and exchange of digital geospatial mapping 
                (raster) data where services based access is not possible</entry>
              <entry>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem><para>Geotiff (a public domain metadata standard embedding
                    georeferencing information within a TIFF 6.0 file</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>JPEG2000 (ISO/IEC 15444-1 and 2)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Multiresolution seamless image database (MrSid
                    Generation 2)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Enhanced Compressed Wavelet (ECW 3.3)</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>NSA Compressed ARC Digitized Raster Graphics (CADRG)
                    </para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Raster product format (RPF)</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry>This is provided for legacy systems, implementers are encouraged 
                to upgrade their systems to consume OGC Web Services.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>File based storage and exchange of non-topological geometry and 
                attribute information or digital geospatial feature (vector) data 
                where services based access is not possible</entry>
              <entry>ESRI SHAPE files
                <para>Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC), Keyhole Markup Language
                  (KML 2.2)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>This is provided for legacy systems, implementers are encouraged
                to upgrade their systems to provide/consume OGC Web Services.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>  
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Battlespace Management Interoperability</title>
    
      <table frame="all" id="v4battlespace-mgmt">
        <title>Battlespace Management Interoperability</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Digital exchange of semantically rich information about Battlespace
                Objects such as units, their structural composition, Plans and Orders 
                etc.</entry>
              <entry>Mandatory: C2 Information Exchange Data Model (C2IEDM) and Data
                Exchange Mechanism (DEM)
                <para>Emerging (Dec 2011): STANAG 5525, Ed. 1:2007 - Joint C3 Information
                  Exchange Data Model (JC3IEDM)</para>
                <para>STANAG 5523 - C2 Information Exchange model</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>C2IEDM Bussiness Rule F11.2 b is not applicable in the AMN scope. 
                Implementations shall ensure that the use of CONTEXT-ASSOCIATION does 
                not create circular references between CONTEXTs.Currently most AMN 
                members use C2IEDM (MIP-Block 2). 
                <para>In 2011 the implementation of the STANAG (MIP Block 3) must 
                  be planned.</para>
                <para>Any addition or expansion of this data model or data dictionaries
                  that is deemed to be of general interest shall be submitted as a 
                  change proposal within the configuration control process to be 
                  considered for inclusion in the next version of the specification.
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Expressing digital geographic annotation and visualization on, 
                two-dimensional maps and three-dimensional globes</entry>
              <entry>TIDE Transformational Baseline Vers. 3-0, NATO Vector Graphics 
                (NVG)
                <para>Mandatory: NVG 1.5</para>
                <para>Fading (Dec 2011): NVG 1.4</para>
                <para>Retired: NVG 0.3 </para>
                <para>Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC), Keyhole Markup Language 
                  (KML 2.2)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>NVG shall be used as the standard Protocol and Data Format for 
                encoding and sharing of information layers between Situational Awareness 
                and C2 systems.
                <para>NVG and KML are both XML-based language schemas for expressing
                  geographic annotations.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Exchanging information on Significant Activities (SIGACTs) 
                in support of current operations</entry>
              <entry>U.S.PM Battle Command SIGACT Schema<footnote><para>Document currently 
                not included in NISP Vol.2 (ed.E), as it was not available from the 
                author.</para></footnote></entry>
              <entry>This schema is used via PASS, webservices and XMPP to exchange
                SIGACT information at Regional Command level and below.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Exchanging information on Incident and Event information to
                support information exploitation.</entry>
              <entry>Emerging (Jul 2011): Draft EVENTEXPLOITREP XML schema. Under 
                development between US PM Battle Command, US CENTCOM CCJ2 (CIDNE) 
                and NC3A.<footnote><para>Document currently not included in NISP Vol.2
                (ed.E), as it was not available from the author.</para></footnote></entry>
              <entry>This schema is used to exchange rich and structured incident/event 
                information between C2 and Exploitation systems (JOCWatch, CIDNE).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Real time automated data exchange such as radar tracking information 
                among airborne and land-based tactical data systems beyond line of sight.
                <para>Message exchange Over Tactical Data Links</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>STANAG 5516, Ed.4:2008 - Tactical Data Exchange (Link 16)
                <para>STANAG 5511, Feb 28, 2006 - Tactical Data Exchange (Link 11/11B); 
                  see also US MIL-STD 6011</para>
                <para>STANAG 5616 Ed 4:2008 - Standards for Data Forwarding between 
                  Tactical Data Systems employing Link 11/11B, Link 16 and Link 22.
                  </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>AMN members shall follow the specifications for automatic data 
                exchange of tactical information with and among NATO tactical data 
                systems, using the data transmission Links designated as Link 11/11B 
                and Link 16.
                <para>Edition 5 of 5516 is ratified, implementation in ISAF needs
                  to be coordinated via the AMN OPT.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Exchange of digital Friendly Force Information such as positional 
                tracking information amongst airborne and land-based tactical data
                systems and C2 systems.</entry>
              <entry>The Draft STANAG 5527 published under a D-Document and is not 
                expected to be ratified. However, NFFI v1.3 will continue to be 
                used as the Standard to exchange positional information on friendly
                forces for the foreseeable future within the AMN.</entry>
              <entry>All positional information of friendly ground forces (e.g. ground
                forces of Troop Contributing Nations or commercial transport companies 
                working in support of ISAF Forces) shall be as a minimum made available
                in a format that can be translated into the NFFI V1.3 format. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Message formats for exchanging information in low bandwidth 
                environment between systems enabled for processing Military Message
                Format</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 7149 -NATO Message Catalogue (NMC)(APP-11)
                <para>AdatP-3(Baseline 11C , F and 13) - Concept of NATO Message
                  Text Formatting System (CONFORMETS) and STANAG 5500 Ed.6:2009 
                  NATO Message Text Formatting System (FORMETS)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Minimum set of messages:
              <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem><para>Air Tasking Order</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Air Control Order</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Incident Spot Rep</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Overlay</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>Entity Data</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Military Symbology interoperability</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 2019, Ed.5:2008, Joint Smbology- APP-6(B)
                <para>U.S. MIL-STD 2525 B Change 2, Common Warfighting Symbology</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Note that both standards are not fully compatible with each other.
                A translation service may need to be provided at the AMN integration core.
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Joint Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconaissance Interoperability</title>
      
      <para>AEDP-2, Ed.1:2005- NATO Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconnaissance 
        Interoperability Architecture (NIIA). The NIIA provides the basis for the
        technical aspects of an architecture that provides interoperability between 
        NATO nations' ISR systems. AEDP-2 provides the technical and management guidance
        for implementing the NIIA in ISR systems.</para>
        
      <table frame="all" id="v4joint-isrt">
        <title>Joint Intelligence, Surveillance, and Reconaissance Interoperability</title> 
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Storing and exchanging of images and associated data</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 4545, Ed. Amendment 1:2000, NATO Secondary Imagery Format (NSIF)
              </entry>
              <entry>AEDP-4, Ed. 1, NATO Secondary Imagery Format Implementation 
                Guide, 15 Jun 07, NU</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Providing a standard software interface for searching and retrieving 
                for ISR products.</entry>
              <entry>NATO Standard ISR Library Interface (NSILI)
                <para>Mandatory: STANAG 4559, Ed. 2:2007</para>
                <para>Emerging (Jul 2013): STANAG 4559, Ed. 3:2010</para></entry>
              <entry>AEDP-5, Ed. 1, NATO Standard Imagery Library Interface Implementation
                Guide, TBS, NU
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Exchange of ground moving target indicator radar data</entry>
              <entry>NATO Ground Moving Target Indicator (GMTI) Format
                <para>Mandatory: STANAG 4607, Ed. 2:2007</para>
                <para>Emerging (Dec 2012): STANAG 4607, Ed.3:2010</para></entry>
              <entry>AEDP-7, Ed. 1, NATO Ground Moving Target Indication (GMTI) Format
                Implementation Guide, TBS, NU</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Provision of common methods for exchanging of Motion Imagery 
                (MI)across systems</entry>
              <entry>NATO Digital Motion Imagery Standard
                <para>Mandatory: STANAG 4609, Ed. 2:2007</para>
                <para>Emerging (Dec 2011): STANAG 4609, Ed. 3:2009</para></entry>
              <entry>AEDP-8, Ed. 2, Implementation Guide For STANAG 4609-NDMI , 
                Jun 07, NU</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Exchange of unstructured data (documents, jpeg imagery)</entry>
              <entry>IPIWIG V4 Metadata Specification:2009, Intelligence Projects 
                Integration Working Group (IPIWG), Definition of metadata for unstructured
                Intelligence.<footnote><para>Document currently not included in NISP Vol.2
                (ed.E), as it was not available from the author.</para></footnote></entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
      <title>Biometrics Data and System Interoperability</title>
      
      <para>Biometrics is a general term used alternatively to describe a characteristic 
      or a process. As a characteristic, a biometric is a measurable biological 
      (anatomical and physiological) and behavioral characteristic that can be used
      for automated recognition. As a process, a biometric is an automated method 
      of recognizing an individual based on measurable biological (anatomical and
      physiological) and behavioral characteristics.</para>
      
      <table frame="all" id="v4t-biometrics">
        <title>Biometrics Data and System Interoperability</title> 
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Interchange of Fingerprint (Type 4 and 14) data</entry>
              <entry>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000
                <para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007 Part 1</para>
                <para>EBTS 1.2 (references ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000)</para>
                <para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1 (references ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007)</para>
                <para>DOD EBTS 2.0</para>
                <para>ISO/IEC 19794-2:2005, part 2</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Type 10 Facial</entry>
              <entry>EFTS v7.0, EFTS v7.1
                <para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1</para>
                <para>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000, 1-2007 Part 1</para>
                <para>EBTS 1.2 (references EFTS v7.0)DOD EBTS v2.0</para>
                <para>ISO/IEC 19794-5 w/ Amd 1:2007, part 5</para></entry>
              <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Type 16 Iris</entry>
              <entry>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2000, 1-2007 Part 1
                <para>EBTS 1.2</para>
                <para>ISO/IEC 19794-6</para></entry>
              <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Type 17 Iris</entry>
              <entry>ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007 Part 1
                <para>FBI EBTS v8.0/v8.1 (ref ANSI/NIST ITL 1-2007)</para>
                <para>DOD EBTS v2.0</para>
                <para>ISO/IEC 19794-6</para></entry>
              <entry>Use of the ISO standard over national standards is preferred.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
   
    <sect1>
      <title>User Interface Capabilities/Applications</title>
      
      <para>User Applications, also known as application software, software applications, applications or apps, are computer software components designed to help a user perform singular or multiple related tasks and provide the logical interface between human and automated activities.</para>
      
      <table frame="all" id="v4t-userinterface">
        <title>User Interface Capabilities/Applications</title> 
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="30*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colwidth="35*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Standard</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Guidance</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Displaying content within web browsers.</entry>
              <entry>W3C Hypertext Markup Language HTML 4.0.1
                <para>W3C Extensible Hypertext Markup Language XHTML 1.0</para>
                <para>W3C Cascading Style Sheets CSS 2.0</para></entry>
              <entry>Applications must support the following browsers: Microsoft 
                Internet Explorerv7.0 and newer, and Mozilla Firefox3.0 and newer.
                When a supported browser is not true to the standard, choose to support
                the browser</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Browser plug-ins.</entry>
              <entry>Browser plug-ins are not covered by a single specification.</entry>
              <entry>Some AMN members do not allow the use of ActiveX controls in
                the browser. Browser plug-ins do need to be approved by AMN CAB.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Visualize common operational symbology within C4ISR systems 
                in order to convey information about objects in the battlespace.</entry>
              <entry>STANAG 2019, Ed.5:2008, Joint Symbology- APP-6(B)
                <para>U.S. MIL-STD 2525 B Change 2, Common Warfighting Symbology</para>
                <para>TIDE Transformational Baseline Vers. 3-0, NATO Vector Graphics 
                  (NVG)</para>
                <para>Mandatory: NVG 1.5</para>
                <para>Fading (Dec 2011): NVG 1.4</para>
                <para>Retired: NVG 0.3</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>All presentation service shall render tracks, tactical graphics,
                and MOOTW objects using this standard except in the case where the
                object being rendered is not covered in the standard. In these exceptional
                cases, additional symbols shall be defined as extensions of existing 
                symbols and must be backwards compatible. These extensions shall be
                submitted as a change proposal within the configuration control process
                to be considered for inclusion in the next version of the specification.
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Reliable messaging over XMPP</entry>
              <entry>XMPP Clients must implement the following XMPP protocol extensions
                <para>XEP-0184 for message receipts, whereby the sender of a message 
                  can request notification that it has been received by the intended
                  recipient, and XEP 0202 for communicating the local time of an entity.
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>All XMPP Chat Clients used on the AMN shall implement these 
                two protocol extensions.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Collaborative generation of spreadsheets, charts, presentations
                and word processing documents</entry>
              <entry>ECMA-376, Ed. 1: 2006 Office Open XML
                <para>Emerging (Dec 2012): Document description and processing languages
                  ISO/IEC 29500:2008 (transitional)</para>
              </entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Document exchange, storage and archiving</entry>
              <entry>Document management -- Electronic document file format for 
                long-term preservation --ISO 19005-1:2005 Part 1: Use of PDF 1.4 
                (PDF/A-1)</entry>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
      
    <sect1>
      <title>References</title>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>[1] MC 245 Statement of Military Requirement for Interoperability
            between Automated Data Systems.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>[2] Allied Data Publication 34 (ADatP-34) NATO Interoperability 
            Standards and Profiles (NISP) STANAG 5524.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>[3] NATO C3 System Interoperability Policy, AC/322-D(2004)0039 dated 
            13 Sep 2004.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>[4] NATO C3 System Interoperability Directive, AC/322-D(2004)0040 
            dated 13 Sep 2004.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>  
</appendix>
