<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                   Vol 5 - A P P E N D I X - A 
 ***************************************************************** 
-->

<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v5a-rdsi-A">
    <title>NISP Rationale Document - Supplementary Information</title>

    <sect1 id="rdsi-A-1-int">
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>This annex provides additional explanatory material in support of
      the standards assessment in the Rationale Document.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rdsi-A-2-ent">
      <title>Enterprise-level data management</title>

      <para>For inter-nation interoperability purposes, it is only necessary
      to standardise the definitions of information exchanged between systems
      in different nations and, even then, it is sufficient to standardise
      external schema representations only.</para>

      <para>There are other reasons why more extensive standardisation of data
      might be advantageous (e.g. application portability) and these concerns
      are relevant to NCF systems.</para>

      <para>To support unanticipated exchanges of information (for which
      provision was not made at design time), it would clearly be beneficial
      if the format and meaning of that data had been agreed in advance.
      However, such universal standardisation is highly costly and its
      benefits are at best difficult to quantify (and at worst might never
      materialise). Speculative standardisation also has the disadvantage
      (demonstrated repeatedly by previous 'open' computing initiatives) that
      the standards produced are seldom usable; by its very nature the process
      for production of such standards is pre-emptive and therefore unable to
      take into account specific requirements. Subsequent failure to adopt
      those standards leads to their being undermined and eventually displaced
      altogether by de facto substitutes.</para>

      <para>Nevertheless, the increasingly unpredictable nature of military
      operations, together with changing concepts of operations demanding
      increased interchange of data from the strategic to tactical levels,
      suggests that local interchange agreements (e.g. within a nation,
      bilateral between systems) will become increasingly unsustainable.
      Emphasis will need to shift towards NATO-wide agreements, encapsulated
      within the NISP.</para>

      <para>These issues, and the wider role of data management within NATO
      must be reviewed. The eventual scope and form of the NISP will therefore
      be influenced by this work.</para>

      <para>It has been suggested in some quarters that object-based
      approaches providing data encapsulation ('data hiding') can obviate the
      need for the widespread data standardisation to support remote data
      access, and thus that any other approach to data management may be
      inappropriate once extensive use is made of object-based mechanisms.
      Both of these assertions are true to a degree, but need qualification.
      This Data encapsulation does not remove the need to standardise the data
      that is exchanged between systems. Moreover, encapsulation only limits
      the degree of inter-system data agreement needed if the specific
      requests for information exchange (the 'methods' in object terminology)
      can be determined in advance. Therefore, even if object mechanisms are
      widely employed it will still be necessary to standardise core data
      elements relevant to inter-domain interoperability within the NISP, and
      to pre-determine the nature of requests for information exchange.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-3-data">
      <title>Database to database replication</title>

      <para>Database to database replication excludes simplistic transfer
      mechanisms using business-transaction-oriented data interchange formats,
      e.g. ADatP3; such interoperability mechanisms are considered under
      another heading. The mechanisms considered under this area are the more
      sophisticated protocols employed within commercial products capable of
      transaction management, selective attribute-based replication,
      etc.</para>

      <para>At present, each commercial database product provides its own
      proprietary replication mechanisms. Effective standards do not exist for
      protocols, nor for the data formats employed, or the integrity services
      provided. Replication between dissimilar products is only possible to a
      limited degree. It would be possible to adopt a proprietary product as
      an NCOE standard but no product currently has sufficient market
      dominance to justify this.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-4-oa">
      <title>OA interchange formats</title>

      <para><emphasis>De jure</emphasis>document interchange standards have
      neither the richness nor the product support to be credible interchange
      standards. (An exception to this is XML, a specific application of SGML,
      which is considered under a separate class.) Interchange between
      different OA applications (e.g. between Microsoft Word and Applixware)
      is generally much more effective where one of the proprietary formats is
      used rather than where vendor-neutral formats (e.g. RTF) are
      used.</para>

      <para>More recently products (such as VMWare) have emerged that allow
      the Windows operating system to be run in a UNIX environment thus
      permitting native Windows applications to be hosted. Although this is
      not a new idea, it is only recently that the products have become
      sufficiently mature and an acceptable performance achieved. It is,
      therefore, a practical option for high levels of cross-platform
      interoperability to be achieved by using the same applications on both
      Windows and UNIX platforms.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-5-hyp">
      <title>Hypertext interchange formats</title>

      <para>The requirement for document interchange can be satisfied to a
      degree by the adoption of hypertext formats (and other mark-up formats
      such as XML) as interchange formats. This offers more limited
      functionality than the OA formats themselves but can be useful in those
      circumstances where native support for the OA formats is not available.
      With the widespread adoption of XML (and XSL) the functionality gaps are
      narrowing.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-6-msg">
      <title>Messaging</title>

      <para>The X.400 functional model and a typical client/server messaging
      configuration are shown in <xref linkend="rdsi-f-03" />.</para>

      <para>Whilst many mail server products support X.400, this is generally
      only for server-to-server connections (i.e. the products support the
      X.400 P1 protocol but not the P3 or P7 protocols). Moreover, whilst
      X.400-compliant UA and MS components are commercially available, they
      offer very limited functionality compared with mainstream COTS messaging
      products. These often include Groupware functionality as well as
      messaging functionality that would force many systems adopting
      X.400-compliant MS and UA products to provide more mainstream
      products.</para>

      <para>For interoperability between domains, conformance with the P1
      protocol standard (plus body part formats) is necessary but conformance
      with other protocol standards (i.e. P3, P7) is not.<footnote>
          <para>It is assumed that domain boundaries are organised such that
          direct access by a mail client in one domain to a server in another
          domain is not required; this will usually be precluded on security
          grounds in any event.</para>
        </footnote></para>

      <figure id="rdsi-f-03">
        <title>X.400 Functional Model</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/rd-funcmod.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-7-dir">
      <title>Directory</title>

      <para>Projects' selection of a directory product is usually dictated by
      their choice of messaging product (e.g. Microsoft Exchange requires the
      use of Active Directory in order to provide a messaging service).
      However, X.500-compliant products (as required by NATO) are commercially
      available, and are becoming more de-coupled from the messaging service.
      Meta-directories now offer a viable solution to the integration of
      different directory products. LDAP v3 is the internationally accepted
      access protocol supported by all vendors.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-8-key">
      <title>Key management and distribution</title>

      <para>Few Defence IT systems presently employ asymmetric cryptographic
      algorithms and their future use is dependent upon the approval of
      algorithms for Defence use and the existence of suitable
      implementations. Therefore there is little possibility of standardising
      an asymmetric key distribution service within the NISP (although open
      standards for such services, and widely used implementations of
      commercial algorithms, do exist). There are no acceptably open standards
      for the distribution of symmetric encryption keys (other than in
      conjunction with a wider asymmetric distribution service).</para>

      <para>Clearly, however, if widespread use is to be made of
      cryptographically-delivered security services within other NISP services
      (notably messaging), there will ultimately be a requirement to
      standardise key distribution services. Progress on this front within the
      NISP is contingent upon current NATO security architecture work.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-9-sys">
      <title>System management</title>

      <para>This area is taken to mean the exchange of management information
      and services between systems in order to permit remote management or the
      management of several systems as a single whole.<footnote>
          <para>The management of interconnected systems in a coordinated
          manner to maintain interoperability (e.g. by carrying out software
          upgrades simultaneously to minize backwards compatibility problems)
          will be necessary but is expected to be achieved by procedural
          means.</para>
        </footnote></para>

      <para>With an ever-increasing level of integration between NATO and
      national CIS, system management responsibility is one of the few
      remaining criteria by which system boundaries are drawn. Strong control
      and management of a system is a prerequisite to the implementation of an
      effective security policy, which will also limit the degree to which
      management control can be federated amongst allies and coalition
      partners.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-10-net">
      <title>Network management</title>

      <para>This area is taken to mean the exchange of management information
      and services among end-systems and between end-systems and the wide-area
      communications infrastructure in order to permit remote network
      management or the simultaneous management of several systems' local
      network components. Strong local network management control is therefore
      usually required to enforce local system security policies.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-11-name">
      <title>Name services</title>

      <para>Irrespective of whether X.500 services are provided directly, an
      X.500 naming policy will be required because X.500 names are used in
      X.509 certificates; these in turn are used to support secure
      messaging.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-12-obj">
      <title>Object Interchange</title>

      <para>There are a number of competing standards for the interchange of
      objects between applications. All are emerging and there is no clear
      leader at present. There are no opestandards. Most use remote procedure
      call (RPC) mechanisms to effect distribution of computational effort,
      the exception being Java The main contendees are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Active X: this is Microsoft s standard based on its
          Distributed Component Object Model (DCOM) technology. It is being
          ported to most UNIX platforms.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>CORBA: Common Object Request Broker Architecture is the Object
          Management Groups (OMG) attempt to introduce open standards into
          distributed computing. The OMG is a consortium of companies
          developing these standards but relying on individual companies to
          provide products.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>DCE: Distributed Computing Environment is the Open Group's
          standard for distributed computing.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>JAVA: Sun's attempt to produce truly portable programs has
          been taken up by a number of vendors. It uses a Java Virtual Machine
          (JVM) to execute Java code. Any platform that support a JVM should
          (in theory) be able to execute any Java program. Java programs can
          be distributed (and executed) across a federation of computing
          platforms. It should be noted that practice and theory have not yet
          fully converged.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SOAP: is a W3C, XML-based, commercially supported protocol
          that is widely adopted. Unlike the currently mandated standards
          (CORBA &amp; COM) it uses an open transport mechanisms (e.g. HTTP)
          which is mandated in the NISP.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-13-alert">
      <title>Alert services</title>

      <para>An alert is a message which can contain multiple information
      types, as with other messages. Alerts services are normally
      distinguished from messaging services on the basis that they:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>are commonly sent on all-informed or multicast basis and, on
          efficieny grounds, use different distribution mechanisms;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>need to be brought directly to the attention of the user, and
          usually require positive acknowledgment before other tasks can be
          continued.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Requirements for alerts arise in two ways in NATO CIS:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>for distribution of urgent system management messages or
          instructions;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>for rapid dissemination of operationally significant
          information such as warnings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-14-arch">
      <title>Architectural concepts</title>

      <para>The NISP is predominately based upon the concept of a federation
      of fixed and mobile systems that together form a NATO Intranet. Embodied
      within the NISP, therefore, is the concept of a technical architecture
      that has the Internet standards and protocols at its heart. Central to
      these is the four-layer TCP/IP protocol stack which many applications
      (e.g. SMTP email) are designed to use. The layers are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>communications network layer;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Internet Protocol (IP) layer;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>TCP and UDP layer;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>applications layer;</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Other mandated applications, however, (e.g. X.400 messaging) have
      been designed to use the seven-layer OSI protocol stack (see <xref
      linkend="rd-f-tcp-stack" />) which has the following seven layers:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>physical layer;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>data link layer;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>network layer;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>transport layer;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>session layer;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>presentation layer;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>application layer;</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>These two protocol stacks align as shown in <xref
      linkend="rd-f-tcp-stack" />. Their use creates a dichotomy in the NISP
      that requires ISO transport services to be layered on top of TCP/IP (as
      defined in RFC 1006).</para>

      <figure id="rd-f-tcp-stack">
        <title>OSI and TCP/IP Protocol Stacks</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/rd-p-stack.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Both of these stacks are embodied in the NISP, although their
      purpose may not be immediately obvious, so that ISO-based applications
      such as X.400 and X.500 can be supported as illustrated in <xref
      linkend="rd-f-tcp-app" />.</para>

      <figure id="rd-f-tcp-app">
        <title>OSI and TCP/IP Applications</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/rd-applic.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-15-cwan">
      <title>Coalition Wide Area Network (CWAN) Management</title>

      <para>The CWAN, along with associated systems, applications, and
      services; is managed with remote monitoring and control capabilities via
      the Coalition Communications Control Center (CCCC or QuadC) and the Alt
      CCCC. It has links that electronically exchange information between
      management systems at all levels.</para>

      <sect2 id="rd-A-16-cccc">
        <title>CCCC Management Overview</title>

        <para>The purpose of the CCCC is to provide seamless, secure
        information products and services to JWID participants, especially
        warfighters, in support of decision-making and mission
        accomplishment.</para>

        <para>Within the Commander-in-Chief(CINC), Service and Agency (C/S/A)
        organisations today, network, system, application, and service
        management functions are performed by a wide range of individuals,
        activities, and organisations. These management and/or controlling
        functions are performed at all levels. However, in the JWID
        environment, these functions must be performed at the CCCC and
        Alternative CCCC (ACCCC). These control centers can be located within
        any domains. While it can provide virtual presence at any location on
        the network, each control center can perform independent and
        integrated management functions supporting communications and
        information systems. These systems include local area network (LAN)
        management and the CWAN. Each provides operational support essential
        to sustaining the CWAN. The CCCC CONOPS is aimed at realigning,
        consolidating, and integrating these functions to fulfill the
        following goals:</para>

        <para>The CCCC structure enables the capability to:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>reloutionize information exchange accross the CWAN;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>strengthen the ability to apply computing, communications
            and information management capabilities effectively to accomplish
            the JWID mission;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>significantly reduce information technology burdens on
            operational and functional staffs; and</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>facilitate the capability for the operational and functional
            staffs to access, share and exchange information worldwide, with
            minimal knowledge of communication and computing
            technologies.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>A wide range of individuals, activities and organizations
        perform network, system, application and service management functions
        within C/S/As, at all levels. However, in the JWID environment, these
        functions must be performed at the CCCC and Alternative CCCC (ACCCC).
        These control centers can be located within any domain. While it can
        provide virtual presence at any network location, each control center
        can perform independent and integrated management functions supporting
        communications and information systems. These systems, including local
        area network (LAN) management and the CWAN, provide operational
        support essential to sustaining the CWAN. The CCCC CONOPS realigns,
        consolidates and integrates these functions to fulfill the following
        goals:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enhanced C4IFTW support;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Secure operations;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Shared management information (status, availability);</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Global visibility;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Interoperable resources;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="rd-A-17-cccc">
        <title>CCCC Management Functions</title>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Fault Management</emphasis> is the
        detection, isolation, and correction of problems in, or abnormal
        operation of, disabled network or information processing system
        components. Appendix A of the CCCC CONOPS explains the functions
        associated with fault management.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Configuration Management</emphasis>
        identifies, exercises control over, collects data from, and provides
        data to networks for the purpose of preparing for, initialising,
        starting, providing for the continuous operation of, and terminating
        interconnection of processing services. Configuration management
        functions and tasks may overlap with both fault management and
        performance management, along with long-term planning of the network's
        topology, the information processing system's configuration, and
        inventory. Appendix A of the CCCC CONOPS summarises the functions
        associated with configuration management.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Performance Management</emphasis> monitors
        and controls the quality of network communications or information
        processing. It involves the processes of monitoring and analysing;
        tuning and controlling; and reporting on network or information
        processing system components and on the network or information
        processing system as a whole. Appendix A of the CCCC CONOPS summarises
        the functions associated with performance management.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Security Management</emphasis> includes
        the confidentiality, authenticity, and integrity of network management
        data such as routing tables, access lists, audit data protection, and
        accounting and billing information. Security management is the
        management of the following network or information processing system
        security services: authentication, access control, encryption, and
        audit trail. Security management controls and monitors the mechanisms
        that protect selected network or information processing system
        resources and user information, or security objects. Security
        management includes controlling access to resources, archiving and
        retrieving security information, and managing the encryption process.
        The management functions associated with security management are found
        in Appendix A of the CCCC CONOPS.</para>

        <para>The CCCC has oversight responsibility for the entire CWAN and
        interfaces directly with the network participants. The CCCC will
        provide the overall management control and technical direction of the
        CWAN. As the direct interface for the customers, the CCCC performs
        demonstration participant assistance and provides contemporary
        operational network services. It serves as a central point of contact
        in operational and emergency provisioning aspects of customer service
        when the needs are beyond the capability of the site engineers.
        Operational policies and procedures for the CCCC are under
        development. Additional C/S/A policies will also apply based on the
        mission being supported by the CCCC. The CCCC is responsible for the
        following functional responsibilities and requirements:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Providing CWAN policy, standards, and guidance for systems
            and network management</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Monitoring status, in real-time or near-real-time, of CWAN
            applications, networks systems, and JJPO concerns</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Providing access to Global CWAN status for authorized users
            as required</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Implementing tool suites, processes, and databases that
            provide the “global” view for applications, systems, and network
            assets</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The vulnerabilities of networks to information security attacks
        dictate that network management and information security management
        information be shared across multiple communities of interest. The
        end-user/JWID customer, upon discovering an information security
        anomaly, would report it to the CCCC, which would report
        enterprise-level anomalies to the CTFC. Anomalies to circuits or
        systems that are not of CTFC interest would be processed and resolved
        at the CCCC. The CCCC and/or ACCCC would be responsible for
        aggregating information reported to them and passing it to the CTFC
        and JJPO for fusion. Doctrine associated with such actions are under
        way to address, refine, and integrate the reporting structures.</para>

        <para>Successful CCCC operations rely on compatibility,
        interoperability and integration of policies, procedures, standards
        and tools.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-18-cis">
      <title>Deployed CIS</title>

      <para>The NISP has focused on CIS that are principally static in nature
      and has given limited consideration to the operation of deployed CIS.
      The constraints that exist in theatre typically relate to the
      communications systems (i.e. bandwidth, availability, quality of
      service) and must be resolved appropriately. The NISP has a part to play
      in resolving these issues.</para>

      <para>It is now considered possible that coalition forces may federate
      their CIS in a deployment so that local autonomous services are provided
      within the constrained environment. In other words, the coalition forces
      may interconnect systems or LANs locally “on the ground” forming one or
      more sub-networks. This would also mean that one nation could be
      responsible for providing services such as Naming, Addressing and
      Directory to other nation's systems. In this case each nation's systems
      would have to conform to additional standards such as CIDR VLSM for
      sub-netting, DHCP for IP address allocation and LDAP for directory
      access. This means that local services could be used thus reducing any
      dependency on premium resources such as long haul communications.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="rd-A-19-dcis">
      <title>Deployed CIS</title>

      <para>Linux (R) is the fastest growing operating system in the world. It
      already holds 34% of the Web market share. More and more developers,
      especially software companies, are focusing their efforts on creating
      Linux products. Even major corporations are currently responding. For
      instance, IBM, HP, Dell, Sun, and Oracle have all launched major
      initiatives, spending billions of dollars on Linux and Open Source
      software. It is anticipated that Linux and Linux based products, will
      provide a secure environment for defense oriented Web applications. Many
      defense organizations (e.g., the U.S. DoD) are moving toward Web-based
      architectures, even for combat operations. It is anticipated that the
      business decision to use freeware in conjunction with a simplified Web
      interface will save NATO, as well as NATO nations, billions of dollars.
      For military applications, the traffic needs to be encrypted and in
      dedicated networks using firewalls. However, such an environment will
      allow us to use this less expensive, dependable, and essentially common
      operating system. Linux DNS server, running BIND, can be configured to
      service Win95/98/2000/NT/XB clients. Linux also allows for the
      protection of data by using OpenSSH.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Linux is Interoperable: Linux is compatible with the World
          Wide Web and can be configured to work with non-Linux clients and to
          network with non-Linux servers. Using this capability, NATO could
          set up multiple intranets which are Web-based to capitalize on
          potential interoperability concerns.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Linux is Mature: Over one-third of the Web servers used today
          run Linux OS. Major vendors (see above) are investing billions of
          dollars in open source, Linux based, application solutions. LSB is
          based on POSIX (IEEE 1003.1-1990). Since the Open Group is currently
          developing test suites for LSB 1.1 and 1.2, it is anticipated that
          future versions of the LSB will fully conform to
          POSIX.1-2001.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Linux is Implementable now: The fact that Linux is in used in
          over a third of the Web servers and used to develop real-time and
          embedded commercial products attests to the implementability of
          Linux.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Linux is readily available: The LSB specifications are fee and
          publicly available at www.linuxbase.org.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>

</appendix>