<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<book lang="en">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles</title>

    <subtitle>Rationale for the Selection of NISP Services, Standards, and
    Technology</subtitle>

    <corpauthor>C3 CCSC NATO Open Systems Working Group</corpauthor>

    <productname>Allied Data Publication 34</productname>

    <biblioid class="pubnumber">ADatP-34 Edition (D)</biblioid>

    <volumenum>5</volumenum>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>4.0 DRAFT</revnumber>

        <date>7 December2009</date>

        <revremark>20091108 - Added Interoperability Profile Guidance</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </bookinfo>

  <!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 1
 ***************************************************************** 
-->

  <chapter id="v5c1-scoping">
    <title>NISP Scoping Principles</title>

    <sect1 id="v5c1s1-introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>This document "Rationale for the Selection of NISP Services and
      Standards" is hereafter known as the Rationale Document (RD).</para>

      <para>The RD states the process and a set of principles that has been
      used to govern the scope of technical standardization attempted under
      the NISP. NATO Common Funded (NCF) Systems will require the
      standardization of various aspects of Computer Information Systems (CIS)
      and their supporting Networking and Information Infrastructure (NII).
      These principles form the first stage of the standards selection
      rationale process. It is evolving to support the NNEC SOA.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v5c1s2-scoping">
      <title>NISP Scoping Principles</title>

      <para>The services within the scope of the NISP are derived from the
      Compendium of NNEC Related Architectures to support the NNEC Networking
      and Information Infrastructure and the NNEC Capability areas. These
      services must be scoped for the inclusion in the NISP according to a
      defined process and set of scoping principles. The NISP has three
      primary aims: <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>To support interoperability between NCF systems, NII and the
            national CIS and NII belonging to coalition partners;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>To deliver benefits to NCF systems by pursuing goals such as
            application accessibility, people portability and reduced training
            and through-life cost;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>To support nation to nation interoperability. This can be
            achieved using the same boundary services and standards supported
            at the nation to NCF system and NII boundaries.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>

      <para>To support interoperability the NISP must define within its scope
      a set of services that can reasonably be mandated and supported (within
      the constraints of security) at the boundary between the systems or
      infrastructures. For example it is reasonable to mandate that web
      services should be exchanged using HTTP, but it is unreasonable (and
      untenable) to mandate that all nations should adopt Windows XP as their
      operating system or use a common programming language.</para>

      <para>Consequently the standards specified for each service must be
      supported at the boundaries. These boundaries are referred to as a
      Interoperability Point (IOP). National systems may choose to use other
      standards internally and translate between the internal and boundary
      standards. For example, a nation may choose to use bitmap graphics
      internally but would be mandated to exchange JPEGs at the boundary. The
      interoperability model is shown diagrammatically below in <xref
      linkend="v5f1-IOmodel" />.</para>

      <para>A benefit of this model is that by supporting the boundary
      services between national and NCF systems, services, and
      infrastructures, nation-to-nation interoperability will also be
      supported. Interface Point concepts are described further in NISP volume
      1.</para>

      <figure id="v5f1-IOmodel">
        <title>Interoperability Model</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/v5f1-iomodel.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>In order to achieve the primary aims of the NISP, the services
      derived from the NII must be categorized into those that are essential
      to support: <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Interoperability at the boundary between systems or NII and
            must, therefore, be implemented by both coalition nation systems
            or NII and NCF systems or NII;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The wider goals of application accessibility, people
            flexibility, and reduced training; and</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Through-life cost for NCF systems.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>

      <para>In simple terms, the interoperability services relate mainly to
      server-server interactions across the boundary between NCF systems or
      NII and national systems or NII. The NCF system or NII services,
      however, additionally include both server-server and client-server
      interactions within NCF systems.</para>

      <para>Once the services have been categorized, it is then necessary to
      apply a set of scoping principles that will determine whether a service
      is within the scope of the NISP. The scoping principles can be
      subdivided into three groups: <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A general set of scoping principles that are applied to all
            services;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>An interoperability set of scoping principles that are
            applied to services that are shared between coalition nations, and
            between coalition nations and NCF Systems;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A set of scoping principles that only applies to NCF Systems
            or NII.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist></para>

      <para>A simple flowchart of the process for scoping the services is
      shown in <xref linkend="v5f2-flowchart" />. Once the services have been
      properly scoped into the NISP, the next step is to identify the
      standards that should be used to implement those services. Suitable
      justification should be provided as to the reason for each choice of
      standard.</para>

      <figure id="v5f2-flowchart">
        <title>Scoping Services</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/v5f2-scopingflow.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The ten key scoping principles are divided into three
      groups:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>General scoping principles that are applicable to
          all candidate services</emphasis> <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
              <listitem>
                <para>Standardization Requirement</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Openness</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Legacy Issues</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Procurement Issues</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Scoping principles applicable to System to System
          interoperability candidate services</emphasis> <orderedlist
              continuation="continues" numeration="arabic">
              <listitem>
                <para>System boundary issues</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Interconnection security issues</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>System evolution</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Scoping principles applicable to NATO Common Funded
          Systems (NCF) System candidate services (and which are not covered
          under interoperability)</emphasis> <orderedlist
              continuation="continues" numeration="arabic">
              <listitem>
                <para>Application Accessibility/Sharing (guaranteed
                interoperability by use of the same applications)</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Reducing life-cycle costs</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>People flexibility and reduced training costs</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Each of the ten scoping principles are elaborated and explained in
      the following sections.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v5c1s3-general">
      <title>General Scoping Principles</title>

      <para>This section defines the general scoping principles that should be
      applied to all services that are candidates for inclusion in the
      NISP.</para>

      <sect2 id="v5c1s4-stdreq">
        <title>Standardization Requirement</title>

        <para>For system to system interoperability the NISP should
        standardize only those services that are relevant to an achievable
        level of interoperability between NCF systems and between NCF systems
        and the systems or NII of Coalition partners.</para>

        <para>There are many NNEC services that are or could be routinely
        provided within a national NII or an individual system, but which are
        not relevant to NATO or to a nation's interoperability. An example of
        the latter might be a distributed print service (i.e. the ability of
        one computer to issue a print job to a networked printer or to another
        computer for spooling). This principle states that services not
        relevant to NCF interoperability or System to system's
        interoperability should be excluded from the scope of the NISP.</para>

        <para>For NCF systems or NII the NISP should only standardize those
        services for which there is clear requirement and that would deliver
        significant benefit when balanced against the reduction in diversity
        that such standardization would promote.</para>

        <para>The standardization of services within NCF systems or NII should
        only be applied when there is a clear need for a particular service.
        For a service to be standardized, the potential benefits of
        standardization such as avoidance of vendor lock-in must outweigh the
        risks of a possible limited market support.</para>

        <para>The NISP should only standardize services when there is evidence
        of a present or near term requirement for such standardization.</para>

        <para>The scope of the NISP, in terms of the services it specifies,
        will inevitably change over time. There is a temptation to standardize
        services just in case a future requirement for their use should arise.
        Although there may be instances where such pre-emptive action is
        beneficial, the main effect of such a policy is to foster unnecessary
        standardization.</para>

        <para>The NISP should standardize services only where there is
        sufficient scale of benefit to be gained.</para>

        <para>There are many standard services that could be potentially
        beneficial to NCF systems, NII, or in achieving system to system
        interoperability but their applicability is limited to particular
        functional niches or the services are needed only by small groups of
        systems. Unless there is clear benefit from widespread standardization
        across the NII (with the potential cost and risk penalties of
        enforcement), the NISP should be silent and the specification of
        standard services left to a more local level.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v5c1s5-openess">
        <title>Openness</title>

        <para>The NISP should use only open<footnote>
            <para>Formally, to be classified as 'open', a standard must exist
            in the form of a specification that is controlled and maintained
            by a public body. In some cases an acceptably open standard may
            include MIL-STDs, STANAGs and other non-commercial
            standards.</para>
          </footnote> standards wherever possible when attempting to
        standardize a service.</para>

        <para>Products exist that allow IT systems to exchange a wide range of
        services to achieve a high degree of interoperability; however, some
        open standards include vendor specific extensions. Therefore it is
        essential that products be validated against the open
        standards.</para>

        <para>Ideally, standardization of a service should only be undertaken
        where there is an effective open solution. However, there will remain
        circumstances where effective open solutions do not exist, yet the
        business benefits of standardization would be significant<footnote>
            <para>One possible example could be office automation; the
            commercial market has no widely accepted open standards but the
            business benefits of achieving interoperability in this area are
            great. In this case the NISP has selected the Microsoft Office
            formats for interoperability.</para>
          </footnote>.</para>

        <para>The following criteria are suggested to determine whether or not
        a solution qualifies as being acceptably open from a NISP
        perspective:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>There is an effective <emphasis>de jure</emphasis> or
            <emphasis>de facto</emphasis> standard. To be effective, there
            must be wide spread market support for the standard. Among
            competing standards it should be the dominant standard and it
            should have a substantial share of the market;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>There is a mainstream product achieving substantial market
            dominance. Examples of this could be the Microsoft Windows API or
            the file formats used by the Microsoft Office suite. Although
            these embody proprietary standards their overwhelming market
            dominance would force any serious competitor to provide a route to
            ready upgrade, mitigating the risks of lock-in;</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>There are several interchangeable, competing products
            providing the same service. This ensures that lock-in can be
            avoided and has the subsidiary benefit of maintaining a
            competitive environment.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v5c1s6-legacy">
        <title>Legacy Issues</title>

        <para>Existing standards and profiles implemented in legacy systems should be
        preferred if they are equal to other candidate standards.</para>

        <para>There are two reasons why standards already implemented in
        legacy systems might be preferred: first, they are demonstrated to
        work and have an experience base; second, and more importantly,
        migration of legacy systems to a new standard could be infeasible or
        prohibitively expensive. Standards that are already implemented should
        form a starting point, unless these are judged no longer appropriate.
        Subject to their continuing validity, this will lead to a preference
        for standards implemented in legacy systems. This principle ensures
        that change is not made purely for the sake of change: however, the
        NISP is in essence a forward-looking document that should also
        indicate the (non-legacy) target standard for migration (embodied
        later in the system evolution principle) to a more current standard
        and level of capability.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v5c1s7-procurement">
        <title>Procurement Issues</title>

        <para>For interoperability services, national procurement agencies are
        encouraged to use the NISP standards, however this should not
        unacceptably interfere with legitimate national project management or
        procurement freedoms.</para>

        <para>The objectives of the NISP require that certain services be
        standardized across NCF systems and the NII and facilitate
        interoperability with national NII. However, national projects will
        need to be individually responsible for specifying national
        requirements and managing the risks associated with their
        implementation. NISP standardization aspirations for national systems
        must therefore be moderated by genuine needs for national project
        management and control.</para>

        <para>For NCF systems and the NII the NISP should not standardize
        services that would interfere with competitive open bidding.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v5c1s8-interoperability">
      <title>Interoperability Scoping Principles</title>

      <para>This section defines the scoping principles that should be applied
      to the services required to support interoperability between NCF
      systems, the NII and national NII. These principles must be applied in
      addition to the general principles defined in <xref
      linkend="v5c1s3-general" />.</para>

      <sect2 id="v5c1s9-boundaries">
        <title>System and Infrastructure Boundary Issues</title>

        <para>As far as possible, conformance with NISP standards should be
        confined to requirements to provide specified services at the
        interface between systems or network infrastructures.</para>

        <para>For interoperability purposes, the NISP should be confined to
        specifying those characteristics of systems that are necessary to
        achieve NCF system interoperability and NCF to coalition nation NII
        interoperability. It will often be sufficient that systems or
        networking infrastructures comply with a standard at their external
        boundaries; interoperability does not necessarily demand that services
        conforming to the same standards be used internally. Conformance to a
        standard at the boundary will, however, often mean that certain
        requirements do need to be satisfied internally. For example, the NISP
        might demand that a certain external schema is used when relational
        DBMS information is exchanged; the schema used internally need not be
        identical to this but it must clearly be rich enough that data can be
        accurately translated between internal and external formats.</para>

        <para>Systems should be capable of meeting NISP external interface
        standards, but this should not preclude the agreement of additional
        interfaces between two or more systems if these satisfy local<footnote>
            <para>In this context 'local' can mean between two CIS or NII from
            a single nation, internal to NATO or between CIS or NII of
            different nations.</para>
          </footnote> requirements more effectively.</para>

        <para>Any system offering a service within the scope of the NISP is
        obliged to offer external interfaces conformant with the NISP
        standard. This allows any other system to interoperate readily if it
        also offers a compliant interface. However, there will remain
        circumstances where additional, agreed interfaces may be more
        effective in meeting specific local interoperability requirements,
        either in terms of performance or cost-effectiveness. In these cases,
        the NISP should not force projects to adopt a sub-optimal solution
        where it can be shown that alternative arrangements are more
        effective. (It is reiterated, however, that every system within the
        scope of the NISP must always offer NISP conformant interfaces, in
        addition to any other interfaces.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v5c1s10-security">
        <title>Interconnection Security Policy</title>

        <para>The NISP must embody a practical security policy compatible with
        the goals of widespread interconnection between systems and
        NII.</para>

        <para>Current NATO and Coalition partner security policy guidance
        regarding the interconnection of secure systems or NII is still being
        formulated by the NATO Security Committee (NSC). Until an agreed
        policy emerges it will be impossible to decide the level of security
        functionality and assurance that will be necessary to support the
        envisaged level of internetworking between NATO and Coalition partner
        systems or NII.</para>

        <para>A more fundamental difficulty exists, namely that
        interconnections between systems inevitably weaken security.
        Irrespective of security technology developments, a widely
        interconnected system will always provide opportunities for attack
        that are absent in a standalone system. Also, greater potential damage
        can be caused in an interconnected system by a security breach
        regardless of whether it was an unintentional mistake or the result of
        deliberate attack. A viable security policy within the NISP will be
        unachievable unless the NATO and Coalition partners can strike a
        realistic balance between the level of security provided (and thus
        risk accepted) and the extent of interconnection sought.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v5c1s11-evolution">
        <title>System Evolution</title>

        <para>The NISP must accept and provide for a range of standards and
        technologies to permit interoperability between systems or NII of
        different technological vintages.</para>

        <para>Although the NISP will need to evolve in response to
        technological developments, the pace of evolution of systems or NII
        will to a large degree depend upon factors outside NISP control (e.g.
        funding and operational constraints). This means that the NISP must
        support a range of compatible technologies to support continued
        interoperability between systems or NII of different NISP vintages:
        older technologies or standards versions will need to be supported to
        allow a realistic period for migration. Conversely, the introduction
        of new technologies or standards within the NISP must not be delayed
        too long since this could inhibit end-systems' or NII uptake of those
        technologies. A balance must therefore be struck between the desire to
        embrace new technological developments within the NISP and the
        practical ability of existing systems or NII to evolve to maintain
        conformance with it.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v5c1s12-ncf">
      <title>NATO Common Funded System Scoping Principles</title>

      <para>This section defines the scoping principles that should be applied
      to the services required by NCF systems and NII (other than to support
      interoperability between NCF systems and NII and national systems and
      NII). These principles must be applied in addition to the general
      principles defined in <xref linkend="v5c1s3-general" />. If any one of
      these principles provides sufficient benefit the corresponding standards
      should be adopted.</para>

      <sect2 id="v5c1s13-accessibility">
        <title>Application and Service Accessibility</title>

        <para>For NCF systems and NII it is desirable that the NISP should
        provide an ability to share common applications and services.</para>

        <para>Achieving the highest level of interoperability (i.e.
        guaranteeing that the interpretation and rendering of information is
        identical within a Community of Interest) frequently depends upon the
        use of common applications or services (for the same CIS security
        classification level). Even the best import/export filters can lose or
        corrupt important elements of information in the process of mapping
        between formats and encoding standards. In the past application
        portability was cited as a way of achieving this and deriving benefits
        from software re-use, but application portability has never been truly
        realized. However, the ability to have cross-platform availability of
        applications is achievable by executing applications on a remote
        server and rendering the display remotely on a user terminal. Hence,
        in a heterogeneous server environment, users with dissimilar desktops
        (such as Windows and UNIX) can still access essential applications.
        The widespread adoption of a Service Oriented Architecture which
        focuses on the interface, independent of the service implementation,
        further supports interoperability.</para>

        <para>Application and service availability also delivers further
        benefits in the form of reduced training costs (see <xref
        linkend="v5c1s15-flexibility" />). It also allows the range of
        different applications and services to be limited, thus limiting
        diversity and delivering benefits through the reduction of
        through-life costs (see <xref linkend="v5c1s14-costs" />).</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v5c1s14-costs">
        <title>Reducing Life Cycle Costs</title>

        <para>For NCF systems and the NII it is desirable that the NISP should
        support an architecture which can embrace technological change and
        manage obsolescence without the need for radical redesign.</para>

        <para>The ever-increasing pace of technological development has meant
        that obsolescence becomes an issue even as systems or services are
        delivered for the first time. Reducing life cycle costs requires the
        management of technology obsolescence, which effectively requires key
        decisions to be made that avoid lock-in or a high dependency on
        specific products. Systems must be able to evolve in such a way that
        technology can be refreshed without the need for fundamental
        redesign.</para>

        <para>Technology refresh will inevitably increase diversity. An
        architecture that permits, but manages, diversity will provide a much
        better environment for the management of obsolescence.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v5c1s15-flexibility">
        <title>People Flexibility and Training</title>

        <para>For NCF systems and the NII it is desirable that the NISP should
        reduce the need for training (and retraining) of personnel in the
        operation of workstations and applications.</para>

        <para>Personnel within NATO are required to move within the
        organisation to execute their role or when changing roles. To make
        such movements and transfers as efficient and easy as possible it is
        essential that users are presented with an interface to the services
        they need that operates and perform in a way that is common across NCF
        systems and the NII. Adopting a common look and feel through the use
        of common Human-Computer Interaction (HCI) and style guides will
        facilitate people portability.</para>

        <para>Closely linked with people flexibility, there is a need to
        minimize the amount of training required when personnel transfer
        between systems. This can best be achieved by adopting a common look
        and feel to the user interface and adopting a common style guide for
        application providers.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v5c1s16-natsup">
      <title>Australian and New Zealand National Supplements to NISP</title>

      <para>To further allied interoperability, NATO has also invited the CCEB
      nations to participate in the NOSWG with the intention that the NISP
      will be adopted by both NATO and CCEB as the Technical
      Architecture.</para>

      <para>If necessary, AS and NZ will develop and publish national
      supplements to document national variances or exceptions to NISP
      standards. These instances are expected to be rare.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 2
 ***************************************************************** 
-->

  <chapter id="v5c2-scope">
    <title>Assessment of Scope of NISP</title>

    <sect1 id="v5c2s1-introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>The application of the principles outlined in Chapter 1 has
      resulted in the assessments captured in the next tables (<xref
      linkend="rd-table-1" /> to <xref linkend="rd-table-4" />).</para>

      <!--                  T A B L E   1                            -->

      <table frame="all" id="rd-table-1" orient="land">
        <title>Application of General Scoping Principles</title>

        <tgroup align="left" cols="5">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Area/ class</entry>

              <entry>Standardization Requirement</entry>

              <entry>Openness</entry>

              <entry>Legacy</entry>

              <entry>Procurement Cost/ risk</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody valign="top">
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">1: User Interface
              Services</emphasis></entry>

              <entry></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Graphical User Interafce</entry>

              <entry>These services are not necessary for system to system
              interoperability but do provide benefits to NCF Systems e.g.
              people portability.training</entry>

              <entry>Standards exist to proliferate User Interface services
              (e.g. Character-Orientated, Graphical User Interafaces, as well
              as dedicated) within multiple functional domain areas.</entry>

              <entry>Support is required based on the version of Windows/X
              Windows utilized.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Look &amp; Feel</entry>

              <entry>As above</entry>

              <entry>As above</entry>

              <entry>As above</entry>

              <entry>The type of COTS available may be limited in scope or not
              all-inclusive (e.g. style guides). As a result Military should
              refer and conform to their respective Defence documents
              accordingly. Associated costs will differ based on resource
              applicability.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Toolkit</entry>

              <entry>As above</entry>

              <entry>Toolkits exist to support standards</entry>

              <entry>As above</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">2: Data
              Management</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Dictionary/ Directory</para><para>(Data
              Dictionary)</para></entry>

              <entry>Specific to individual nations, i.e. no Coaltion
              Interoperability requirement. However, NATO needs to identify,
              develop definitions, and store common data elements for NCF
              systems, in the NC3 IRDS.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Database management systems (Relational and
              Object-Orientated)</entry>

              <entry>Specific to individual nations i.e. no Coalition
              Interoperability requirement. Required for NCF systems.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Distributed Data</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Remote Data Access</entry>

              <entry>There is a Coalition Interoperability requirement for
              remote data access (e.g. between server/server
              environments).</entry>

              <entry><para>SQL CLI only open standard. ODBC is the Microsoft
              variant. SQL*NET (ORACLE) regarded as dominant product.</para>
              <para>Web-based access protocols are widely used across the
              Internet; these offer limited database functionality.</para>
              <para>SOAP and XML related protocols could serve this
              purpose.</para></entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Database Replication</entry>

              <entry><para>There is a requirement to support database
              replication by "push" only. There are some aspirations to use
              database replication as a mechanism to satisfy Coalition
              interoperability requirements although the extent of the
              requirement is not finalised.</para> <para>Replication may be
              employed within individual systems to meet survivability and
              performance requirements - this does not justify inclusion of
              this service within the NCSP at this time, but will need to be
              effectively addressed in the near future (e.g. ATCCIS, CCEB
              CWAN.)</para></entry>

              <entry><para>There are only a few acceptably open standards for
              replication protocols: this is the prime hindrance to
              standardization.</para> <para>See note A.3</para></entry>

              <entry>Many legacy systems employ flat-file databases which do
              not support efficient replication protocols.</entry>

              <entry>Adoption of a single database product NATO-wide will not
              be acceptable on procurement grounds.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">NATO Common Schema<para>See Note
              A.2</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Interoperability requires common syntactic and
              semantic understanding of data. This necessitates
              standardization of data definitions and schema. However, from a
              NCSP perspective:</para> <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>only data exchanged between systems needs to be
                    standardized;</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>only data common to all or most nations needs to be
                    standardized in the NCSP.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist> <para>Both categories are under development by
              the NATO Data Administration Group (NDAG).</para></entry>

              <entry>Metadata standards are open but there are no open
              standards for military data (except geospatial and Hydrographic;
              see standard data products below). It is important to note that
              the CALS standard [MIL-STD-28003B] for metadata
              references/profiles ISO 8632 CGM. The title is 'Digital
              Representation for Communication of Illustrative Data.'; There
              is also an ISO 8632 profile that has been developed in the US by
              NIMA.</entry>

              <entry>Much existing software uses well-established military
              data models such as ACP133.</entry>

              <entry>Widespread data standardization requires huge investment.
              Bilateral arrangements are likely to be cheaper for the
              bilateral arrangements, but much more expensive in multilateral
              arrangement situations.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">3: Data
              Interchange</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Graphics</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Images (Vector and Raster)</entry>

              <entry>There is a Coalition Interoperability requirement for
              standardization for formatting digital imagery files and imagery
              related products.</entry>

              <entry>Many open standards exist. Some standards are
              military-specific, but are open in the sense that they are
              widely supported. (E.g., CALS has developed a metadata standard
              MIL-PRF-28003A which profiles the ISO computer Graphics Metafile
              (CGM) standard ISO 8632. Also, a CALS Raster Standard
              MIL-PRF-28002C puts raster graphics into a binary
              format.</entry>

              <entry>The continuing support for the majority of these formats
              is required for legacy systems.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Fax</entry>

              <entry>There is a Coalition Interoperability requirement to
              exchange fax data.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Video/ Audio</para> <para>(Moving Images and Audio/
              Video)</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Packet Switched (Voice-over-IP)</entry>

              <entry>There is a Coalition Interoperability
              requirement.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist in most areas.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Circuit Switched</entry>

              <entry>There is a Coalition Interoperability
              requirement.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist in most areas.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Tactical Digital Information Links</para>
              <para>(Communication Standards for TADILs are dealt with under
              the Communication Service Area)</para></entry>

              <entry>There is a Coalition Interoperability requirement for
              real-time data interchange. Primarily a C2I requirement</entry>

              <entry>No open standards exist, so TADILs are military
              specific</entry>

              <entry>Different Data Link is in use. Guidance is provided in
              "Data Link Migration Strategy" SACLANT 3000 C/03/Ser: NU0606,
              Sept 1998</entry>

              <entry>COTs providers are limited</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Military Message Text Formats</entry>

              <entry><para>All formats identified thus far are specific to C2I
              systems.</para> <para>(This category does not cover formats
              related to message handling policy (e.g. P772) which is covered
              separately below.) C2I-specific messages can be included as the
              "body part" of STANAG 4406 messages.</para></entry>

              <entry>These formats are military-specific but most are
              effective in the sense that they are widely supported.</entry>

              <entry>The continuing support for the majority of these formats
              is required for legacy systems.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Civil Message Text</entry>

              <entry>There is a Coalition Interoperability requirement for
              these interchange formats. Certain message formats (e.g. CALS)
              are specific to a particular business function so the strength
              of the NATO-wide requirement for these is questionable.</entry>

              <entry>Effective standards (either military-specific de jure
              standards or open commercial specifications) exist in most
              areas.</entry>

              <entry>Some widely used message formats vital for continued
              interoperability with legacy systems.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Geographical </para> <para>(GIS)</para></entry>

              <entry><para>There is a Coalition Interoperability requirement
              for interchange of geospatially-referenced data (e.g. overlays).
              Primarily a C2I requirement.</para> <para>Formats for standard
              geospatial and Hydrographic data products need to be
              standardized across all recipient nations. </para> <para>There
              is a requirement to share geospatial data, but no requirement to
              standardize on an application.</para></entry>

              <entry><para>De jure format standards exist for distribution
              purposes.</para> <para>Attempts are being made by GIS vendors to
              develop some standards for APIs and data interchange.</para>
              <para>Agreement by the Open GIS Consortium (OGIS) on an API
              standard has now been achieved.</para></entry>

              <entry><para>There are many GIS in use in existing systems and
              significant quantities of GIS data in proprietary formats.
              Legacy applications software assumes proprietary formats which
              will require conversion either to other proprietary formats or
              to less common de jure format standards. Some NCSP-conformant
              systems will need to support additional (proprietary) formats to
              provide interoperability with specific legacy systems; the
              legacy systems themselves will dictate where and what additional
              formats will be needed.</para> <para>There are lots of legacy
              applications and geospatial databases around.</para></entry>

              <entry>Adoption of a de jure interchange format for
              geographically indexed data could preclude use of many COTS GIS
              products, unless partnership with GIS vendors helps to ensure
              development and maintenance of data interchange
              converters.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Document</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Mark-up Languages</entry>

              <entry>Coalition Interoperability requirements exist for
              transfer of information in device-specific formats (e.g.
              camera-ready documents and artwork or where an application
              unique to one NATO nation needs to pass a printable output to
              another NATO nation's system).</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist.</entry>

              <entry>Many systems will be unable to interpret the mark-up tags
              .</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Page description or display languages</entry>

              <entry>Coalition Interoperability requirements exist for
              transfer of information in device-specific formats (e.g.
              camera-ready documents and artwork or where an application
              unique to one NATO nation needs to pass a printable output to
              another NATO nation's system).</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist.</entry>

              <entry>Many systems will be unable to read, display or print
              current page description formats.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Office Automation interchange formats</para>
              <para>(Cover under remarks column in NCSP)</para></entry>

              <entry>There is a NATO-wide requirement to exchange OA
              documents.</entry>

              <entry><para>MS Office formats open by virtue of market
              dominance.</para> <para>Within NATO pdf is the exchange format
              for invariable documents.</para> <para>De jure document formats
              (e.g. ODA) are not sufficiently well supported to qualify as
              acceptably open.</para> <para>See note A.4</para></entry>

              <entry>Many legacy OA packages in use but functionally limited
              converters available for many formats.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Hypertext interchange formats</entry>

              <entry><para>There is a NATO-wide requirement to exchange
              hypertext documents (for Intranet purposes or as an alternative
              interchange format for OA).</para> <para>See note
              A.5</para></entry>

              <entry>Open formats exist (HTML plus widely supported
              proprietary extensions).</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Depends on organizational requirements. For instance, a
              single data stream can be used by a variety of applications to
              support multiple devices that include: cellular telephones,
              computers, web television, etc. This can be accomplished by
              processing XHTML tags within the XML data stream. As a result,
              this could reduce existing costs significantly</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>File compression and archiving</entry>

              <entry>There is a Coalition Interoperability requirement to
              exchange compressed data.</entry>

              <entry>Many open compression standards exist.</entry>

              <entry>Support may not be available on certain legacy systems
              for compression formats.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Military Symbology</entry>

              <entry>Coalition Interoperability requirements exist to pass
              symbolic information. This relates to the symbol types (e.g.
              heavy battle tank, frigate) and the actual graphical symbols
              used to represent them.</entry>

              <entry>No open standards exist, though there are military
              standards which are widely supported by NATO nations (e.g.,
              MIL-STD-1477B for engagement operations symbology). For force
              operations, MIL-STD-2525B is also referenced.</entry>

              <entry>Many systems will not support adopted standards.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Encoding</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Character sets and alphabets</entry>

              <entry>There is a NATO-wide requirement to support a common
              character set.</entry>

              <entry>International alphabet #5 (with National variants) is the
              only genuinely open standard at present. Future product support
              for internationalized character sets (e.g. UNICODE) will become
              more widespread. IA#5 assumed by other formats (e.g. for
              OA).</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Data Encoding</entry>

              <entry>There is a Coalition Interoperability requirement to
              exchange encoded data.</entry>

              <entry>Many open encoding standards exist.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Optical Encoding</entry>

              <entry>There is a Coalition Interoperability requirement
              particularly within the logistics community to read barcode data
              in support of TAV (Total Asset Visibility).</entry>

              <entry>Many open encoding standards exist.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Voice Encoding</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Multimedia and distributed real time service data
              interchange</entry>

              <entry>There is evidence that requirements exist for distributed
              real-time services and data interchange standards.</entry>

              <entry>Numerous national multimedia standards are accessible in
              version 4 through the [US] Federal Telecommunications
              Recommendation (FTR)-1080A-1998, Appendix A.:</entry>

              <entry>Support may or may not be available to various legacy
              systems.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">4: Graphics</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Graphics Development</entry>

              <entry>There is ar equirement for NCF systems</entry>

              <entry>National (US NIMA and CALS) standards are available as a
              reference point.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Graphics Programming/ Modelling</entry>

              <entry>There may be a requirement for NCF systems in the near
              future</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">5:
              Communications</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Application Layer</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Messaging</entry>

              <entry>These services are necessary for Coalition
              Interoperability</entry>

              <entry><para>Open solutions exist for server to server message
              transfer protocols (i.e. X.400 P1 protocol and equivalent). The
              openness of mail client to server protocols (i.e. X.400 P7,
              POP3, proprietary mail protocols) is not clear.</para> <para>See
              note A.6</para></entry>

              <entry>Support is required within the messaging infrastructure
              for ACP127 (Radio and Teletype RATT Broadcasts) and other legacy
              messaging protocols.</entry>

              <entry>Most COTS solutions do not satisfy all military
              requirements. However, systems which are designed specifically
              for military applications can result in higher developmental and
              life cycle costs due to the need to obtain additional
              maintenance support.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Directory Services</para>
              <para>(Schema, Access, Chaining, Replication, Operational
              Management)</para></entry>

              <entry><para>These services are necessary for Coalition
              Interoperability As a result, requirements exist for an allied
              directory system that can support the transfer of directory
              information. This requires that the following are standardized
              (as per ACP 133):</para> <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>access and interchange protocols;</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>common schema;</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>common security, authorization and certificate
                    policy;</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist> <para>The directory will also be responsible
              for provision of security certificates which are demanded by the
              NATO messaging profile.</para> <para>See
              conclusion</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Standards for directory systems exist (e.g. X.500,)
              and have growing product support.</para> <para>See note
              A.7</para></entry>

              <entry>Generally directory systems have been applied to network
              level services or in a localised context for local messaging
              systems. Support is required between an ACP 133/X.500 and either
              an ACP 100/ACP 117 environment or a proprietary/Internet
              environment. These will require integration and consolidation
              with ACP 133/X.500 based systems in order to scale and provide
              the allied service levels demanded with the full range of
              security requirements.</entry>

              <entry>The risk to allied capability is that the directory
              support services are not provided in a secure and scaleable way.
              Since ACP 133 defines a target, nations may in the interim
              implement similar, yet non-interoperable subsets of the
              specification.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Domain Name Service</entry>

              <entry>There is a Coalition Interoperability requirement for the
              exchange of naming and addressing data</entry>

              <entry><para>Open specifications exist: DNS and X.500</para>
              <para>Both will be required: see note A.11</para></entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Naming and Addressing</entry>

              <entry>There is a NATO Interoperability requirement for the
              standardization of names and addresses as documented in NACOSA
              Operating Instructions. This will have an impact on Coalition
              Interoperability having to use similar naming and addressing
              rules</entry>

              <entry>Names and addresses should follow DNS and X.500 rules. In
              addition procedural rules are required.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">File transfer</entry>

              <entry>There is an evident Coalition Interoperability
              requirement for file transfer.</entry>

              <entry>IPS applications are open.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Remote terminal</entry>

              <entry>There is a Coalition Interoperability requirement for
              remote terminal access between nations; it is limited to legacy
              systems.</entry>

              <entry>IPS applications are open.</entry>

              <entry>Remote terminal possibly the only means of
              interoperability with certain legacy systems.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Hypertext transfer</entry>

              <entry>There is a NATO-wide requirement to transfer hypertext
              documents (for Intranet purposes).</entry>

              <entry>Open protocols exist (HTTP).</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Bulletin Board</entry>

              <entry>There is a possible future Coalition Interoperability
              requirement for News group and bulletin services.</entry>

              <entry>Open protocols exist (e.g. NNTP)</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Time services</entry>

              <entry>No evidence of a Coalition Interoperability
              requirement.</entry>

              <entry>Open protocols exist (e.g. NTP)</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Audio/Video Teleconferencing</entry>

              <entry>There is evidence of a Coalition Interoperability
              requirement for transfer of sound between CIS</entry>

              <entry>Open protocols exist in most areas.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry>There is a Coalition Interoperability requirement to
              perform video conferencing.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Whiteboarding</entry>

              <entry>There is a possible future requirement for Whiteboarding
              services.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist.</entry>

              <entry>Most legacy systems will not support
              Whiteboarding.</entry>

              <entry>Adopting a product that subsequently fails to win market
              share could incur significant cost penalties.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Application Sharing</entry>

              <entry>There is a NCF requirement for application
              sharing.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist (Data protocols for multi-media
              conferencing (ITU T.120))</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Miscellaneous</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>

              <entry><para>Interoperability requirements arise from:</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>those communications applications (e.g. OSI X.400
                    applications) that make use of specific upper layer
                    profiles;</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>those distributed computing services that make use
                    of, or independently provide, upper layer
                    functionality.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></entry>

              <entry>Standards and profiles are readily available (e.g. ACP
              133 and DHCP)</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Presentation Layer</entry>

              <entry>OSI Presentation layer services are included within
              specific applications</entry>

              <entry>Profiles exist in the upper layer (e.g. ACP 133)</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Session Layer</entry>

              <entry>OSI Session layer services are included within specific
              applications</entry>

              <entry>Profiles exist in the upper layer (e.g. ACP 133)</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Transport Layer</entry>

              <entry>There is a requirement to standardize transport protocols
              between nations CIS</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Network Layer</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Internetworking</entry>

              <entry>There is a requirement to standardize methods for LAN/WAN
              &amp; LAN/LAN interworking for the purposes of inter-system
              interconnection.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Router Services</para> <para>(Covered
              in NCSP remarks column for Internetworking)</para></entry>

              <entry>Coalition Interoperability requirements exist.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Circuit Switched Wide Area
              Networking</entry>

              <entry>There is a requirement to link into national telephone
              networks of NATO nations during joint operations. There is also
              a requirement for NATO nations to communicate over secure
              telephone circuits.</entry>

              <entry>Standards are available</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Point-to-point services</para>
              <para>(Covered in NCSP remarks column for circuit
              switched)</para></entry>

              <entry>These services are necessary for Coalition
              Interoperability</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist. Point to Point standards such as
              IETF RFC, PPP Multilink Protocol allows for aggregation of
              bandwidth via multiple simultaneous dial-up connections.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact anticipated.</entry>

              <entry>Based on distributed system configuration
              restraints.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Packet Switched Wide Area
              Networking</entry>

              <entry>There is a requirement for standardization of the
              services provided by the wide-area communications
              infrastructure.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist</entry>

              <entry>See system evolution.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Tactical data link Services</entry>

              <entry>Tactical data links are widely used by the NATO nations.
              There is a requirement for these to be integrated into future
              CIS.</entry>

              <entry>De facto military standards exist.</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Disparate data link message formats and related
              communications often cause a delay in critical battlefield
              information. Associated cost and risk factors need to be taken
              into account as a result.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Data Link/ Physical Layer</entry>

              <entry></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">SATCOM</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>De facto military standards exist.</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Radio</entry>

              <entry>No Coalition Interoperability requirement (other than at
              point of attachment to wide-area communications infrastructure -
              see above).</entry>

              <entry>De facto military standards exist.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Cable</entry>

              <entry>No Coalition Interoperability requirement (other than at
              point of attachment to wide-area communications infrastructure -
              see above).</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">6: Operating
              Systems</emphasis></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Based upon specific OS releases and versions (e.g., NT
              vs. W2K or UNIX 95 vs. UNIX 98) most costs and associated risks
              may prove exponential to the project goals and objectives
              undertaken.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Kernel Operations</entry>

              <entry>There services are necessary for Coalition
              Interoperability</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Non Real Time</entry>

              <entry>There is a NATO requirement to standardize on platforms
              as much as possible for reasons for costs and training</entry>

              <entry>Two operating systems support application software (i.e.,
              POSIX &amp; Windows) for C2 systems in version 4 throughout most
              coalition environments. Within NATO Windows is the predominant
              platform .</entry>

              <entry>System administrative support is required for management
              purposes based on the operating platform, its resources and
              users based community.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Real Time</entry>

              <entry>There is a requirement to have real time platforms
              interoperate with non-real time platforms.</entry>

              <entry>When requiring real or near-real-time capabilities, open
              standards must be considered for this purpose (i.e., IEEE
              1003.13:1998).</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">7:
              Internationalisation</emphasis></entry>

              <entry>See Data Interchange Class Encoding</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">8: System and Network
              Management</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Enterprise Management</entry>

              <entry><para>No evidence of a Coalition Interoperability
              requirement</para> <para>See note A.9</para> <para>See
              Conclusion</para></entry>

              <entry>Sufficiently open standards exist (e.g. SNMP) for cross
              system management.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>System and Network Management</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">LAN Management</entry>

              <entry><para>No evidence of a Coalition Interoperability
              requirement for management of local area networks.</para>
              <para>Network management standardization will be required within
              the wide-area communications infrastructure. But this is not
              relevant to the management of networks under the control of
              end-systems.</para> <para>See note A.10.</para> <para>See
              Conclusion</para> <para>See systems management conclusion
              above.</para></entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist for LAN management only. However,
              these often do not meet security requirements associated with
              the management of Defence systems.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">WAN Management</entry>

              <entry><para>A Coalition Interoperability requirement exists for
              CWAN.</para> <para>For the immediate future, special procedures
              will be required to manage the CWAN.</para> <para>See note
              A.15</para> <para>See Conclusion</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">9a: General
              Security</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Authentication</entry>

              <entry><para>There is an aspiration in future to be able to
              provide a NATO-wide logon to national systems and the CWAN with
              automatic propagation of identity and access rights</para>
              <para>Less ambitious Inter-Nation requirements include</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>the ability to coordinate the management of user
                    identities, access rights, passwords etc. across
                    systems;</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>the ability to pass clearances or other privilege
                    attributes (e.g. group memberships) between systems when
                    making access requests.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist></entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist in this area (e.g. X.509), but
              agreement on the syntax and the semantics of clearance
              attributes is required.</entry>

              <entry>Few legacy systems offer any sophisticated security
              functionality which would make them amenable to interconnection
              in this way.</entry>

              <entry>Single log-on across heterogeneous systems is an immature
              area which would represent a risky standardization undertaking.
              A lack of commonality in approaches will be an increasingly
              significant impediment to interoperability. National constraints
              over system security policies will represent a cost and risk to
              many projects.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Access Control</entry>

              <entry>See authentication above</entry>

              <entry><para>As with authentication, the overwhelming
              requirement to standardize for interoperability can be argued to
              outweigh the openness disadvantages.</para> <para>NATO-specific
              standards will be required in areas such as security class
              labeling.</para></entry>

              <entry>Few legacy systems offer security functionality amenable
              to interconnection in this way.</entry>

              <entry>Inter-Nation access control mechanisms and policies need
              to be established that do not force all end-systems to adopt a
              uniform security policy or achieve the same assurance
              targets.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Key Management and Distribution</entry>

              <entry><para>Coalition Interoperability requirements arise
              from:</para> <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>the need to distribute keys from a central issuing
                    authority to individual end-systems. This; will be
                    determined by wider Government policy.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>the need for separate end-systems to exchange keys
                    (e.g. for digital signature purposes). This is a potential
                    NCSP requirement.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist></entry>

              <entry><para>There are open standards in this area. Assymetric
              keys can be distributed via PKI and Symmetric keys can be
              distributed via EKMS. Nation-specific variants of open standards
              are under development.</para> <para>See note A.8</para></entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Automated transfer of keys and other security attributes
              between systems is an immature technology and represents a
              significant risk.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Confidentiality</entry>

              <entry>Coalition Interoperability requirements exist for
              confidentiality and integrity options within more direct
              communications mechanisms, such as RPCs and transport layer
              protocols.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards do exist for options in transport
              protocols via Internet technologies (e.g. SSL, TLSP) may soon
              provide a solution. Operation of RPC mechanisms in version 4
              through firewalls is still immature.</entry>

              <entry>Link layer encryption has been the traditional means of
              providing confidentiality services, and few legacy systems offer
              this service at other layers. However, even if a common IP high
              grade crypto is achieved, it will not meet all the requirements
              for the foreseeable future in respect of availability, transec
              and traffic flow security, hence there will continue to be a
              need for high grade link cryptos to meet these
              requirements.</entry>

              <entry>Inter-nation data confidentiality mechanisms and policies
              need to be established that do not force all end systems to
              adopt a uniform security policy or achieve the same assurance
              levels. This will of course have an impact on the degree of
              interoperability</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Integrity</entry>

              <entry>See data confidentiality above.</entry>

              <entry>See above.</entry>

              <entry>See above.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Accounting and Audit</entry>

              <entry>These services are necessary for Coalition
              Interoperability</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist. Procedure-based mechanisms may need
              to be adopted.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Non-repudiation</entry>

              <entry>Coalition Interoperability requirements exist for
              non-repudiation of information exchange other than
              messaging.</entry>

              <entry>No specific open standard exists, but may be achieved by
              combing open standards, such as hashing and digital
              signature.</entry>

              <entry>Few legacy systems offer this service other than by
              procedural controls.</entry>

              <entry>Adoption of a non-COTS solution will increase cost and
              risk.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Security Domain Mediation</entry>

              <entry>Security domain mediation mechanisms are needed for
              interoperability but the requirement for them generally arises
              on a bilateral basis. A future NATO security policy may give
              rise to a need to standardize mediation services.</entry>

              <entry>No open standards for such services presently exist.
              Firewall products have a general utility in securing
              interconnections between end-systems. However, these are not
              sufficiently well standardized to qualify as being open.</entry>

              <entry>Special enabling mechanisms will continue to be needed to
              mediate between the security policies of legacy systems.</entry>

              <entry>Building high-assurance guard devices add to cost and
              risks of interconnection.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">9b: Message
              Security</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Message origin authentication</entry>

              <entry>There is a clear Coalition Interoperability requirement
              that the origin of all formal messages can be
              authenticated.</entry>

              <entry>Standards exist in this area (X.509) and five nations
              within the NATO have agreed common algorithms for digital
              signatures (e.g. DSS).</entry>

              <entry>Users on legacy systems that do not support the use of
              certificates and digital signatures will be unable to
              authenticate message origin unless a boundary device is utilized
              to verify the digital signature of the originator, and
              mechanisms are employed within the legacy system to guarantee
              integrity of the message between the boundary device and the
              recipient. Similarly outgoing messages can have the digital
              signature of the boundary device appended to provide a level of
              authentication in the other direction.</entry>

              <entry>Sufficiently strong algorithms are in the public domain,
              and commercial products are available to implement them. Five
              nations within the NATO have agreed on common algorithms for
              digital signatures. The main cost/risk issue is in the
              supporting infrastructure for the generation and distribution of
              certificates and tokens and the cost/risk impact of this aspect
              may be significant.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Message Access Control</entry>

              <entry>There is a clear Coalition Interoperability requirement
              for exchange of clearance information and security labels in
              support of formal messaging.</entry>

              <entry>Standards exist in this area (e.g. X.411).</entry>

              <entry>Other than communications and intelligence systems, few
              legacy systems support the use of security labels or the
              processing of clearance information.</entry>

              <entry>Commercial products today do not implement X.411 with the
              clearance extensions hence are not regarded as providing
              sufficiently strong security to meet the military requirement;
              but they appear to be moving in this direction so the cost/risk
              impact may be acceptable.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Message content privacy/ confidentiality</entry>

              <entry>Three of the five NATO/CCEB nations have stated a
              requirement for per-message confidentiality within message
              transfers.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist for options within messaging
              protocols; SMIME, PCT and ACP 120 support the military
              requirement.</entry>

              <entry>Few legacy systems offer security functionality within
              messaging protocols.</entry>

              <entry>All nations are implementing some type of security (ACP
              120, PCT or SMIME) and the cost to implement the necessary
              mechanisms and management infrastructure for interoperability is
              likely to be acceptable. Different national policies on
              encryption may hinder adoption of a common policy.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Message content integrity</entry>

              <entry>Coalition Interoperability requirements exist for
              integrity options within message transfers.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist (e.g. SHA-1, MD5) for options within
              messaging protocols.</entry>

              <entry>Few legacy systems offer security functionality within
              messaging protocols.</entry>

              <entry>Sufficiently strong algorithms for integrity are in the
              public domain, and commercial products are available to
              implement them. However, when these are combined with encryption
              to form a digital signature, the main cost/risk issue is in the
              supporting infrastructure for the generation and distribution of
              certificates and tokens and the cost/risk impact of this aspect
              may be significant.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Certificate managent and distribution</entry>

              <entry>Coalition Interoperability requirements arise from the
              need to distribute signed certificates from a central issuing
              authority to a directory which is accessible to individual
              end-systems, and for individual end systems to be able to verify
              the authenticity of those certificates.</entry>

              <entry>There are open standards for directories (e.g. X.500) and
              emerging standards for Public Key Authentication Frameworks and
              Certificate Management Infrastructures.</entry>

              <entry>Few legacy systems provide the necessary
              mechanisms.</entry>

              <entry>Automated transfer of signed certificates between systems
              is an immature technology and represents a significant risk.
              Current commercial products are not deemed sufficiently secure.
              Alternative mechanisms such as cross-certificates are currently
              being examined.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Message non-repudiation with proof of origin</entry>

              <entry>Coalition Interoperability requirements exist for
              non-repudiation of message transfers. No other instances of
              inter-nation non-repudiation requirements have been
              identified.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist (e.g. digital signatures) for
              options within messaging protocols.</entry>

              <entry>Few legacy systems offer security functionality within
              messaging or other protocols, however most legacy messaging
              systems offer this service in version 4 through procedural
              controls.</entry>

              <entry>Commercial products implementing ACP 120 are available,
              and products supporting SMIME are emerging. Cost/risk issues are
              not expected to be significant.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Message non-repudiation with proof of delivery</entry>

              <entry>Coalition Interoperability requirements exist for
              non-repudiation of message transfers. No other instances of
              inter-nation non-repudiation requirements have been
              identified.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist (e.g. signed receipts with trusted
              time stamps) for options within messaging protocols.</entry>

              <entry>Few legacy systems offer security functionality within
              messaging or other protocols, however most legacy messaging
              systems offer this service in version 4 through procedural
              controls.</entry>

              <entry>Commercial products are available so cost/risk issues are
              not expected to be significant.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Message security labelling</entry>

              <entry>This is a subset of Message Access Control.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Message accountability</entry>

              <entry>Coalition Interoperability requirements exist.</entry>

              <entry>Some standards do exist.</entry>

              <entry>Few legacy systems offer security functionality within
              messaging or other protocols, however most legacy messaging
              systems offer this service in version 4 through procedural
              controls.</entry>

              <entry>Implementation cost and risk will be high if commercial
              products cannot provide the required functionality and
              assurance.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">10: Distributed
              Computing</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Environment/ Remote Process</entry>

              <entry>No evidence of a present Coalition Interoperability
              requirement but future requirements may arise.</entry>

              <entry>No open standards. ONC+ RPC, DCE RPC and Windows RPC are
              all interoperable to an extent but not in a secure
              manner.</entry>

              <entry>Upgrades should be evaluated to eliminate security
              issues.</entry>

              <entry>Based on user/organizational requirements.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Distributed Database Management System</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Remote presentation services</entry>

              <entry>No evidence of a Coalition Interoperability
              requirement.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist for UNIX environment (X11). Widely
              licensed proprietary standards exist for the Windows
              environment.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>File Services</entry>

              <entry>No evidence of a Coalition Interoperability
              requirement.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist (SMB, NFS).</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Print Services</entry>

              <entry>No evidence of a Coalition Interoperability
              requirement.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist (SMB, LPD).</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Distributed transaction processing services</entry>

              <entry>No evidence of a present Coalition Interoperability
              requirement but future requirements may arise.</entry>

              <entry>No Open Standards.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Object Services</entry>

              <entry><para>Coalition Interoperability requirements in this
              area are presently confined to the representation of objects
              embedded within OA documents</para> <para>Wider use of
              distributed computing mechanisms for Inter-Nation
              interoperability is considered under the distributed computing
              category below.</para> <para>There may be a NATO Common Funded
              Systems (NCF) need for such services.</para> <para>See note
              A.12.</para></entry>

              <entry><para>DCOM is to be controlled in the future by an open
              standards body and will therefore qualify as an open
              standard.</para> <para>Sufficiently open standards (e.g., DCE
              and CORBA)</para></entry>

              <entry><para>No significant impact.</para> <para>No significant
              impact.</para></entry>

              <entry><para>No significant impact.</para> <para>No significant
              impact.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Time Services</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Simulation Services</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">11: Software
              Engineering</emphasis></entry>

              <entry>Services in this area are relevant only to NCF
              services</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Languages</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Case</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Software Development</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">12: Common C2
              Applications</emphasis></entry>

              <entry>No evidence of a Coalition Interoperability requirement.
              Porting of applications may be used as a route to
              interoperability where no open standards exist.</entry>

              <entry>No genuinely open products.</entry>

              <entry>Potentially relevant, e.g. Nauticus.</entry>

              <entry>Application standardization may lead to undesirable
              procurement constraints.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Correlation Services</entry>

              <entry>There is a requirement to share track data (and hence a
              common picture), but no requirement to standardize on an
              application.</entry>

              <entry>There are no open standards for track management
              services. Military standards for passing track data exist (e.g.
              OTH-Gold).</entry>

              <entry>Potentially relevant. The wide use of Nauticus as the
              main track management application could lead to problems if
              support for the product changes.</entry>

              <entry>Application standardization may lead to undesirable
              procurement constraints.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Alert Services</entry>

              <entry><para>There is evidence of a Coalition Interoperability
              requirement to pass alerts such as flash messages.</para>
              <para>See note A.13.</para></entry>

              <entry>No open standards</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Data Fusion</entry>

              <entry>There is no requirement at present, however as coalition
              forces become more integrated there may arise a need to fuse
              data from disparate sources.</entry>

              <entry>No open standards</entry>

              <entry>Not applicable at present.</entry>

              <entry>Not applicable at present.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">13: Collaborative Computing (This
              will not be added as a new area but all these services will be
              covered under other areas).</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Workflow Services</entry>

              <entry>There is a possible future Inter-Nation requirement for
              workflow services.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards are emerging.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Information Dissemination Management (IDM)</entry>

              <entry>There is a requirement for the support of group access
              but in read-only mode.</entry>

              <entry>Open standards exist.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <!--                  T A B L E   2                            -->

      <table frame="all" id="rd-table-2" orient="land">
        <title>Application of Interoperability Scoping Principles</title>

        <tgroup align="left" cols="5">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Area/ Class</entry>

              <entry>Boundary Issues</entry>

              <entry>Interconnection Security Policy</entry>

              <entry>System Evolution</entry>

              <entry>Conclusion</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody valign="top">
            <row>
              <entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">1: User Interface
              Services</emphasis></entry>

              <entry></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Graphical User Interafce</entry>

              <entry>N/A</entry>

              <entry>N/A</entry>

              <entry>N/A</entry>

              <entry>Not relevant for system to system
              interoperability.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Look &amp; Feel</entry>

              <entry>N/A</entry>

              <entry>N/A</entry>

              <entry>N/A</entry>

              <entry>Not relevant for system to system
              interoperability.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Toolkit</entry>

              <entry>N/A</entry>

              <entry>N/A</entry>

              <entry>N/A</entry>

              <entry>Not relevant for system to system
              interoperability.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">2: Data Management
              Services</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Dictionary/ Directory</para></entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Database Management System</para>
              <para>(Relational, Object Oriented)</para></entry>

              <entry>No significant impact</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Distributed Data</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Remote Data Access</entry>

              <entry>Interworking/middleware products exist which could offer
              a defined interface at system boundary.</entry>

              <entry>Interconnection security policy will often prohibit
              direct client/server access between systems.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>In scope of NCSP, however security issues may make
              system-to-system implementation difficult.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Database Replication</entry>

              <entry>It is generally not feasible to convert between
              replication protocols at system boundaries, so a common protocol
              needs to be supported by interoperating database products. A
              number of interoperable database products now exist which
              support a common protocol.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>NATO Common Schema</para> <para>(NATO
              level data management)</para></entry>

              <entry><para>For interoperability purposes standardization can
              be limited to external schema.</para> <para>Current work mainly
              presupposes a relational database-to-database method of
              interoperability. Object approaches providing encapsulation may
              permit standardization to be limited to methods provided at
              system boundaries.</para></entry>

              <entry>No significant impact</entry>

              <entry>Common data definitions obviate the need to update many
              local data definitions as individual systems evolve or are
              adapted to meet new requirements.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">3: Data
              Interchange</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Graphics</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Images (Vector and Raster)</para>
              <para>(Graphical/still image data interchange)</para></entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only; in all cases, different formats may be
              used internally.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Fax</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Special circuits or user equipment are required for
              secure fax transmission.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Video/ Audio</para> <para>(Moving Image and Audio/
              Video data interchange standards)</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Packet Switched (Voice-over-IP)</entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only; in all cases, different formats may be
              used internally.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Circuit Switched</entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only; in all cases, different formats may be
              used internally.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Tactical Digital Information Links</para>
              <para>(Communication Standards for TADILs are dealt with under
              the Communication Service Area)</para></entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Military Message Text Formats</para>
              <para>(Military data interchange formats)</para></entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only; in all cases, different formats may be
              used internally.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Civil Message Text</para>
              <para>(Business-transaction-orientated data interchange
              standards)</para></entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only; in all cases, different formats may be
              used internally.</entry>

              <entry>Meeting the security issues could incur significant cost
              and risk.</entry>

              <entry>There could be significant security issues regarding the
              use of digital signatures with EDI.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope (limited to those areas where NATO-wide
              requirements exist. It is important that National systems and
              NATO systems eventually utilize the same transaction sets. In
              addition, there is a need for a common bar code so that
              international shipments can be tracked effectively.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Geographical </para> <para>(GIS)</para>
              <para>(Geospatially referenced data interchange
              standards)</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Support for designated interchange formats is
              required at system boundaries only; in all cases, different
              formats may be used internally.</para> <para>Can avoid
              standardizing on products by adopting interchange formats (if
              they become sufficiently).</para></entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry><para>No significant impacts assuming that data
              interchange standards are sufficiently well supported.</para>
              <para>Application-specific GIS data bases can be difficult to
              evolve or port to newer systems</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Formats of geospatial and Hydrographic data within
              NCSP scope for distribution purposes. </para> <para>Emergence of
              future standards will need to be monitored and NCSP extended to
              include overlay interchange formats.</para> <para>If a suitable,
              widely adopted data interchange format emerges then there would
              be no requirement to standardize on a GIS application (except of
              application or people portability).</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Document</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Mark-up Languages</entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only; in all cases, different formats may be
              used internally.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Page description or display languages</entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only; in all cases, different formats may be
              used internally.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Office Automation interchange formats.</entry>

              <entry>Support required for designated interchange formats is
              required at system boundaries only; in all cases, different
              formats may be used internally.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Concurrent support for different generations of
              interchange format required.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Hypertext interchange formats</entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only; in all cases, different formats may be
              used internally.</entry>

              <entry>Based on evolving requirements, HTML may need to be
              reevaluated periodically in order to meet ongoing organizational
              web development specifications.</entry>

              <entry>Hypertext document standards are evolving rapidly but new
              versions are generally backward compatible. However, the next
              generation follow-on to HTML is XHTML (eXtensible HyperText
              Markup Language) which formulates HTML as an XML.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>File compression and archiving</entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only; in all cases, different formats may be
              used internally</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope. The NCSP should consider all open
              compression formats (.gz, .zip, .tar, etc.) and specify these
              instead of the compression utilities themselves.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Military Symbology</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>The standardization of graphical military symbols may be
              a desirable goal but at present it is only relevant to people or
              application portability. It is relevant for systems to be able
              to inform each other of the presence and location of other
              units. How those units are represented is a matter for
              individual nations. All nations want to be able to know if their
              airspace is being compromised. MIL-STD-2525B provides numerous
              military symbol information that can be passed digitally.
              MIL-STD-2525B provides each national system with the ability to
              interpret the digital signature and depict it in their own
              way.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Encoding</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Character sets and alphabets</entry>

              <entry>Support required for designated interchange formats is
              required at system boundaries only; in all cases, different
              formats may be used internally.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Data Encoding</entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only; in all cases, different formats may be
              used internally.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Optical Encoding</entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only (in this case the reader device); in all
              cases, different formats may be used internally.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Voice Encoding</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Multimedia and distributed real time service data
              interchange standards</entry>

              <entry>Support for designated video teleconferencing standards
              are based on specific system requirements (e.g., Real-time
              control protocol for simplex applications [H.224]).</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>All standards under this category are already covered in
              one of the other data interchange categories. For video, see
              sections on Graphical/Still Image, Moving Image and Audio/Visual
              data interchange standards. For audio, see section on Audio Data
              Interchange Standards.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">4: Graphics</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Graphics Development</para> <para>(Graphics
              programming languages and APIs)</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Graphics Programming/ Modelling</para>
              <para>(Product data and General Purpose)</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">5:
              Communications</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Application Layer</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Messaging</entry>

              <entry>Support is only required for message transfer protocols
              and message content formats. The NCSP does not specify messaging
              protocols or formats used nationally. Agreement is also required
              on security profiles used at boundaries, including
              message-labeling formats.</entry>

              <entry>Secure message gateways may be necessary to mediate
              security services between domains.</entry>

              <entry>COTS functionality is converging with military
              requirements.</entry>

              <entry><para>Only message transfer protocols and message content
              formats are within NCSP scope.</para> <para>Where attachments
              are to be exchanged, relevant data interchange standards also
              apply (see 7).</para> <para>Security services for messaging are
              considered separately below (12)</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Directory Services</para>
              <para>(Schema, Access, Chaining, Replication, Operational
              Management)</para></entry>

              <entry>Border directory systems will be used according to
              national policy to ensure that sensitive national directory
              information is protected from the shared environment. Strong
              Authentication will be used for client and server connections to
              provide the correct levels of trust in the access and transfer
              of directory information.</entry>

              <entry>As defined in ACP 133 and other ACPs that apply directory
              for security services.</entry>

              <entry>There is a need to rationalise and manage directory
              information within nations to ensure consistent information is
              input into any allied system.</entry>

              <entry>ACP 133 must be applied to provide the most effective and
              secure way of providing all forms of information and voice
              exchange between the allied nations. N ATO will need to
              identify, develop definitions, and store common data elements or
              there will be ongoing problems in the exchange of
              information.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Domain Name Service</entry>

              <entry>Different name services may be used internally (e.g.
              WINS).</entry>

              <entry>Automated exchange of naming information may be
              prohibited for some interconnections.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Naming and Addressing Services</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">File transfer</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Direct forms of interconnection will often be precluded
              by security policy.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Remote terminal</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Direct forms of interconnection, especially remote
              terminal, will often be precluded by security policy.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Hypertext transfer</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>HTTP only includes basic authentication. It therefore
              cannot be used where in situations where access controls need to
              be applied on the basis of subscriber identity.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Bulletin Board</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Time services</entry>

              <entry>Different time protocols may be used internally (e.g.
              Microsoft proprietary).</entry>

              <entry>System time is relevant to several system security
              functions (e.g. auditing) so many system security policies will
              preclude remote synchronisation.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Note: As bit rates increase, Universal time becomes more
              important.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Audio/Video Teleconferencing</para>
              <para>(Analogue)</para></entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only; in all cases, different formats may be
              used internally.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope. Video conferencing standards are
              relevant to the communications systems only.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Audio/Video Teleconferencing</para>
              <para>(Digital)</para></entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Supporting packet switched VTC across security boundaries
              is likely to require a dedicated VPN because of the close
              coupling of user terminals and the lack of security
              mechanisms.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Whiteboarding</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Supporting Whiteboarding across security boundaries is
              likely to require a dedicated VPN because of the close coupling
              of user terminals and the lack of security mechanisms.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Application Sharing</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Miscellaneous</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry valign="bottom"><para>(ISO services on top of the
              transport layer)</para></entry>

              <entry>Affiliated services should provide the capability to
              exchange information according to standardized reference models
              as deemed appropriate (see Openness).</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope. However, conformance to upper layer
              protocol standards is solely determined by NCSP requirements in
              other areas (e.g. messaging, RPC). See note A.14.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Presentation Layer</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Session Layer</para> <para>(Socket
              Services)</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Transport Layer</para> <para>(Transport
              Services)</para></entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Network Layer</para>
              <para>(Networking)</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Internetworking</entry>

              <entry>Internetworking regimes used internally within a system
              are outside NCSP scope.</entry>

              <entry>Internetworking methods may be complicated by the need
              for guard or firewall mediation in interconnections.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>NCSP scope limited to specification of the permissible
              modes of LAN/WAN &amp; LAN/LAN interworking for the purposes of
              interconnection.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Router services</entry>

              <entry>Routing regimes used internally within a system are
              outside NCSP scope.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Circuit Switched Wide Area
              Networking</para> <para>(Telephony)</para></entry>

              <entry>Secure telephony requires user equipment to conform to
              agreed standards, hence it is not purely a system boundary
              issue.</entry>

              <entry>Secure telephony requires the use of accredited user
              equipment.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Telephony standards are within NCSP scope. Specific
              communications compression standards (e.g. V.42) may need to be
              standardized within specific nations, or for use within the NATO
              communications infrastructure.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Point-to-point
              services</para></entry>

              <entry>Support is necessary for purpose of splitting,
              recombining, and sequencing datagrams across multiple PPP links
              connecting two systems.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact anticipated.</entry>

              <entry>It is expected that other multilink protocol standards
              will continue to emerge.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Packet Switched Wide Area
              Networking</entry>

              <entry>Unless interconnections are mediated by a communications
              application (e.g. messaging, firewall), interoperating
              end-systems must employ the same internetwork and transport
              protocol.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Wide-area communications infrastructure evolves slowly
              because of the investment required for change. Wide-area
              networks will continue to offer services long after the
              corresponding standards have been superseded.</entry>

              <entry><para>NCSP scope limited to specification of the services
              provided by the wide-area communications infrastructure (i.e.
              internetworking protocols, data link and physical layer
              specifications at point of attachment).</para> <para>The
              technologies used to implement the service are within NCSP
              scope, but see conclusion under Physical and non-physical bearer
              systems.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Tactical data link Services</entry>

              <entry>Due to the diversity of warfighter requirements, no
              single data link is applicable to every platform and weapon
              system.</entry>

              <entry>TDLs are structured on bit-oriented message standards
              that evolve to meet critical real-time and near-real-time
              message requirements. Security issues need to be addressed on a
              case by case basis.</entry>

              <entry>Greater emphasis must be placed on automated
              functionality.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Data Link/ Physical Layer</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Bearers</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">SATCOM</entry>

              <entry>Standardization is only required at the boundary.</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>National standards exist (see MIL-STD-188-180 series).For
              example, the US has standardized the terminals for UHFSATCOM
              DAMA</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Radio</entry>

              <entry>Standardization is only required at the boundary.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope in as far as it is necessary to capture
              the standards that could exist for non-physical bearer systems
              across the interconnection infrastructure. It is important to
              note that national standardization efforts have been put in
              place (e.g., for Joint Task Force LANS on behalf of the
              US).</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Cable</entry>

              <entry>Standardization is only required at the boundary.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope in as far as it is necessary to capture
              the standards for physical bearer systems that could exist
              across the interconnection infrastructure.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">6: Operating
              Systems</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Kernel Operations</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Non Real Time</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Real Time</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">7:
              Internationalisation</emphasis></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Not relevant except for character sets which are covered
              under data interchange.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">8: System and Network
              Management</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Enterprise Management</para> <para>(System
              Management)</para></entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry><para>Security policy will usually preclude system
              management interactions between systems.</para> <para>Special
              considerations required for transfer of access control and
              authentication data between systems (see below). SNMPv3 builds
              on SNMPV1 and addresses the deficiencies in SNMPv2 relating to
              security (e.g., authentication and privacy) and administration
              (e.g., naming of entities and key management, and proxy
              relationships). </para></entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Falls within the scope of NCSP (Systems management) for
              NATO common funded systems (NCF).</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>System and Network Management</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>LAN Management</para> <para>See note
              A.16</para></entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Security policy will usually preclude network management
              interactions between systems.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>LAN management is Outside NCSP scope (no requirement). It
              is important to note that a LAN standard for deployment is
              required (especially between NATO and National systems). LAN
              management should be integrated into the overall Network
              Management System. In addition, the system has to be protected
              by encryption.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>WAN Management</para> <para>(CWAN
              Management)</para></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope. A Coalition Wide Area Network
              management approach is required before deployment. LAN
              management has to be integrated into the overall Network
              Management System. Furthermore, the overall CWAN would have to
              be protected by encryption.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">9: Security</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>9a. General Security</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Authentication</entry>

              <entry>Security properties at the boundary between systems are
              strongly dependent upon the mechanisms used internally so any
              standardization is likely to have an extensive 'systemic'
              effect.</entry>

              <entry>Policy may preclude access or the transmission of
              security attributes between systems in many cases (e.g. where
              the systems have different security assurance levels). Proxy
              servers or boundary/border devices may be the only mechanisms
              allowed under national security policies.</entry>

              <entry>Any adopted policy that cannot be supported by commercial
              products will adversely affect the ability of systems to
              evolve.</entry>

              <entry>The current NCSP should standardize authentication
              mechanisms in support of secure inter-networking
              protocols.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Access Control</entry>

              <entry><para>As with authentication, security properties at the
              boundary between systems are strongly dependent upon the
              mechanisms used internally.</para> <para>Translation of certain
              aspects can take place at boundaries (e.g. security
              classification labels).</para></entry>

              <entry>See authentication above.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>The current NCSP should standardize security
              classification labels (i.e. permissible labels and their
              representation). Standardization in other areas will be
              conditional upon a significant shift in the market position of
              relevant technologies.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Key Management and Distribution</entry>

              <entry>There are several issues in both PKI (e.g. path
              processing across boundaries) and EKMS (e.g. common Transfer Key
              Encryption Keys) that need to be resolved before keys can be
              exchanged across national boundaries.</entry>

              <entry>Policy may preclude the transmission of security
              attributes between systems in many cases (e.g. where the systems
              have different security assurance levels or processing
              mechanisms).</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Outside NCSP scope at present but may be included in
              medium term. National policies need to be monitored to determine
              applicability of commercial standards and national
              variants.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Confidentiality</entry>

              <entry>Security policy needs to be defined to determine where
              the confidentiality security services terminate.</entry>

              <entry>At present, high grade security for connectivity can only
              be achieved in version 4 through link layer encryption. IP based
              encryption is not yet sufficiently mature.</entry>

              <entry>S/MIME is expected to evolve to include many of the
              features specified in ACP 120 and could become a suitable
              mechanism for application layer confidentiality services for
              some systems.</entry>

              <entry>Scope dependent on availability of standards.
              Confidentiality options within direct interworking mechanisms
              (e.g. HTTP, RPCs) may be relevant to the medium-term.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Integrity</entry>

              <entry>See above.</entry>

              <entry>No further issues.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Scope dependent on the extent to which direct
              interworking services are adopted in the NCSP in the medium
              term. As for confidentiality above.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Accounting and Audit</entry>

              <entry>Audit trails are usually maintained within a system
              boundary and require applications to produce the necessary logs.
              Audit logs can be passed across system boundaries (e.g. using
              SNMP), but national security policies may preclude this.</entry>

              <entry>Security Operating Procedures for Accounting and Audit
              within nations apply. Audit logs could be passed across system
              boundaries, however this can weaken security (see
              conclusion).</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry><para>Within NCSP scope. Accounting and audit mechanisms
              can be used locally to support non-repudiation</para>
              <para>Security is of concern when audit logs are passed in
              version 4 through firewalls which typically form the boundary of
              a system. Management protocols (e.g. SNMP) run over UDP;
              operating UDP in version 4 through a firewall will weaken the
              security it provides.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Non-repudiation</entry>

              <entry>Security policy needs to be defined to determine where
              the non-repudiation security service terminates.</entry>

              <entry>No further issues.</entry>

              <entry>Any adopted policy that cannot be supported by commercial
              products will adversely affect the ability of systems to
              evolve.</entry>

              <entry>Non-repudiation options within information exchange are
              within scope of the current NCSP. However there is currently a
              lack of standards.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Security Domain Mediation</entry>

              <entry>Firewalls typically form the boundaries of systems and
              are responsible for mediation between the internal system and
              external WAN environments.</entry>

              <entry>The effectiveness of a firewall is dependent upon the
              mediation principles that it enforces.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry><para>Outside NCSP scope.</para> <para>A future NATO-wide
              security policy may bring such services within NCSP
              scope.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>9b. Message Security</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Messge origin authentication</entry>

              <entry>Since a digital signature is formed by encrypting a
              message digest or hash with a private key, common algorithms and
              certificate profiles are required if this is to succeed across
              national boundaries. The binding of the corresponding public
              signature key to the originator is achieved by the signing of
              the certificate by the Certification Authority. For certificate
              path processing to be successful across boundaries, the
              Certificate Management Infrastructure Authentication Framework
              also needs to extend across these boundaries.</entry>

              <entry>No further issues.</entry>

              <entry>Lack of an acceptable certificate management
              infrastructure will slow system evolution.</entry>

              <entry>The NCSP should standardize authentication mechanisms in
              support of message transfer.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message Access Control</entry>

              <entry>Common security policies or policy equivalence mappings
              are required to support this service across boundaries.</entry>

              <entry>No further issues.</entry>

              <entry>Lack of acceptable commercial products will slow system
              evolution.</entry>

              <entry><para>Within NCSP scope.</para> <para>The current should
              adopt:</para> <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>X.411 security label syntax (i.e. the way the labels
                    are represented when they are exchanged);</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>security label semantics (i.e. standardize the
                    meaning of security labels) are currently being specified
                    by the INFOSEC ISME For signatures, see Message Origin
                    Authentication. However, given that, unlike NATO, the NATO
                    is not a treaty organisation, in the past it has been
                    deemed impossible to take this logical step
                    forward.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>clearance semantics (i.e. standardize the meaning of
                    clearance attributes) are a subset of the security label
                    and are currently being specified by the INFOSEC
                    ISME.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message content privacy/
              confidentiality</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Significant issues exist including key management and the
              use of common encryption algorithms.</entry>

              <entry>Lack of acceptable products will slow system
              evolution.</entry>

              <entry><para>Within NCSP scope</para> <para>The security policy
              should specify confidentiality options within messaging
              protocols.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message content integrity</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact, unless the message digest or hash
              is also encrypted to form a digital signature.</entry>

              <entry>There are significant issues relating to the issuing and
              management of digital signatures and certificates as well as the
              adoption of common algorithms.</entry>

              <entry>The reluctance of nations to decide to implement a
              Certificate Management Infrastructure will affect system
              evolution.</entry>

              <entry><para>Within NCSP scope</para> <para>NCSP should
              standardize integrity options within messaging
              protocols.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Certificate managent and
              distribution</entry>

              <entry>There are significant boundary issues particularly in
              relation to directory shadowing, replication and certificate
              path processing.</entry>

              <entry>There are significant issues relating to the generation,
              distribution, management and user validation of signed
              certificates.</entry>

              <entry>The reluctance of nations to decide to implement a
              Certificate Management Infrastructure may slow system
              evolution.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope at present, but may be more realistic
              to be included in future NCSP specifications. National policies
              need to be monitored to determine applicability of commercial
              standards and Government variants.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message non-repudiation with proof of
              origin</entry>

              <entry>Security policy needs to be developed to determine where
              the non-repudiation security service terminates.</entry>

              <entry>Significant issues including management of digital
              signatures and the adoption of common algorithms.</entry>

              <entry>Commercial products implementing ACP 120 are available,
              and products supporting SMIME are emerging.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message non-repudiation with proof of
              delivery</entry>

              <entry>Security policy needs to be developed to determine where
              the non-repudiation security service terminates.</entry>

              <entry>Significant issues including management of digital
              signatures and the adoption of common algorithms.</entry>

              <entry>Commercial products are available</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message security labelling</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message accountability</entry>

              <entry>Security policy needs to be defined to determine where
              the accountability security service terminates.</entry>

              <entry>Significant issues including management of digital
              signatures and the adoption of common algorithms.</entry>

              <entry>Lack of products will affect system evolution.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">10: Distributed
              Computing</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Environment/Remote Process</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>System security policy may preclude the direct
              interconnection between systems demanded for RPC. Should
              consider IP encryption to reduce current problems. Ipv6 could
              prove to be a good start.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact known at this time.</entry>

              <entry>Outside NCSP scope as there is no requirement. Possible
              requirements and status of standards and products need to be
              continuously monitored.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Distributed database management system</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Covered under project level data management</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Remote presentation services</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Outside NCSP scope. (For other graphics services see Data
              Interchange above)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>File Services</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>File services are usually at the heart of a system
              security policy. File sharing between systems may therefore
              force systems to adopt uniform security policies.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Outside NCSP scope. If an inter-nation requirement
              emerges then this service would come into scope. Security
              constraints would still be an issue.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Print Services</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Procedural aspects of control over printed output may
              limit the distribution of print jobs between systems.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Outside NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Distributed transaction processing services</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Outside NCSP scope at present. Possible requirements and
              status of standards and products need to be monitored.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Object Services</entry>

              <entry>Competing standards are interoperable to a
              degree.</entry>

              <entry>Risks associated with import of logic bombs or viruses
              are greatly magnified with distributed object technologies
              making interconnection impractical for many systems at present.
              See DCE Authentication and Security Specification C311 (Open
              Group) and OMG document formal/98-12-10, CORBA Security
              Service.</entry>

              <entry>May impact distributing computing configuration based on
              authentication requirements.</entry>

              <entry>Possible requirements and status of standards and
              products need to be continuously monitored.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Object Services</entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange formats is required at
              system boundaries only; in all cases, different formats may be
              used internally.</entry>

              <entry>DCOM uses RPC, for which no acceptably open security
              standard exists. There it will not be possible to use such
              mechanisms in situations where access controls need to be
              applied.</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>NCSP scope presently limited to OA document formats; see
              Document Interchange formats above.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Time Services</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Simulation Services</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">11: Software Engineering
              services</emphasis></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Not relevant.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Languages</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Case</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Software Development</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">12: Common C2
              Applications</emphasis></entry>

              <entry>Can avoid standardizing on products by adopting
              interchange formats in some cases.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Outside NCSP scope.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Correlation Services</entry>

              <entry>Can avoid standardizing on products by adopting
              interchange formats.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Outside NCSP scope. At present interoperability can only
              be achieved by specification of a single product. If a suitable
              data interchange format emerges then there would be no
              requirement to standardize on a product. Variable Message Format
              should be considered [Ref: MIL-STD-2045-47001B] as a viable
              alternative.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Alert Services</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Outside scope of current NCSP because there are no open
              standards. It is deemed desirable for certain alerts to be sent
              between NATO nations, particularly in relation to threat
              warnings. At present, however, there are no open standards and
              no suitable products.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Data Fusion</entry>

              <entry>Not applicable at present.</entry>

              <entry>Not applicable at present.</entry>

              <entry>Not applicable at present.</entry>

              <entry>Outside NCSP scope at present. However, national
              capabilities do exist. If permissible, source and method
              indicators can be removed from the information. This would allow
              information to be sent effectively to various units in the
              field.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">13: Collaborative Computing (This
              will not be added as a new area but all these services will be
              covered under other areas).</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Workflow Services</entry>

              <entry>The immature status of emerging standards make
              interoperability at system boundaries difficult to
              achieve.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>Outside NCSP scope at present because there are no
              sufficiently open standards. Future requirements, the status of
              standards from the Workflow Management Coalition<footnote>
                  <para>The Workflow Management Coalition, founded in August
                  1993, is an international organisation of workflow vendors,
                  users, analysts and university/research groups. The
                  Coalition's mission is to promote and develop the use of
                  workflow in version 4 through the establishment of standards
                  for software terminology, interoperability and connectivity
                  between workflow products. Consisting of over 130 members,
                  spread in version 4 throughout the world, the Coalition has
                  quickly become established as the primary standards body for
                  this rapidly expanding software market.</para>
                </footnote>and the status of products (e.g. Lotus Notes, SAP
              &amp; PeopleSoft) need to be monitored.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Information Dissemination Management (IDM)</entry>

              <entry>Support for designated interchange format is required at
              system boundaries only. Different formats may be used
              internally.</entry>

              <entry>Write access to on-line published information would need
              suitable security measures in place.</entry>

              <entry>Standards are evolving rapidly but new versions are
              generally backwards compatible.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope for read access only. Write access will
              come within the NCSP scope if security issues can be
              resolved.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <!--                  T A B L E   3                            -->

      <table frame="all" id="rd-table-3" orient="land">
        <title>Application of NCF System Scoping Principles</title>

        <tgroup align="left" cols="5">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Area/ Class</entry>

              <entry>Application Accessibility</entry>

              <entry>Reduce In version 4 through-life costs</entry>

              <entry>People Portability and Training</entry>

              <entry>Conclusion</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody valign="top">
            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">1: User Interface
              Services</emphasis></entry>

              <entry></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Graphical User Interafce</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Relevant to NCF Systems; remote presentation and IPC are
              addressed under distributed computing.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Look &amp; Feel</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Toolkit</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">2: Data Management
              Services</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">3: Data
              Interchange</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">4: Graphics</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Graphics Programming Languages and APIs</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Relevant to NCF Systems for application and people
              portability</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Graphics capability within applications</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Relevant to NCF Systems for application and people
              portability</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">5:
              Communications</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">6: Operating System
              Services</emphasis></entry>

              <entry><para>Most heterogeneous systems utilize either POSIX or
              Win 32 Application Program Interfaces (APIs). Defining which OS
              is used often depends on each Application Platform size and/or
              function. </para> <para>OS security services should be
              investigated in accordance with the OS being utilized
              (regardless if used in a standalone or distributed
              manner).</para></entry>

              <entry>Linux has emerged as a viable alternative to Unix within
              specific functional domain areas. However, it is not yet mature
              enough for implementation purposes within an NCF
              environment.</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Operating System services are necessary in order to
              perform and provide the functionality in which application
              software can access a particular platform.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">7:
              Internationalisation</emphasis></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Not relevant except for character sets which are covered
              under data interchange.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">8: System and Network
              Management</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>System Management</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Falls within the scope of NCSP (Systems management) for
              NATO Common Funded Systems (NCF).</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>LAN Management</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>LAN management is Outside NCSP scope (no requirement). It
              is important to note that a LAN standard for deployment is
              required (especially between NATO and National systems). LAN
              management should be integrated into the overall Network
              Management System. In addition, the system has to be protected
              by encryption.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>WAN Management</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>National WAN management will be managed by national staff
              hence there will be no Coalition Interoperability requirement.
              It is however important to take national interconnectivity into
              consideration (if deemed appropriate).</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Communications Bearer system management</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry><para>Outside of NCSP scope presently.</para>
              <para>Communications systems will be managed by national staff
              hence there is no inter-nation requirement.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">9: Security</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>9a. General Security</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>9b. Message Security</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">10: Distributed
              Computing</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">11: Software Engineering
              services</emphasis></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Not relevant.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">12: Common C2
              Applications</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">13: Collaborative
              Computing</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Workflow Services</entry>

              <entry>No significant impact.</entry>

              <entry>The current lack/immaturity of standards means that NCF
              systems would need to adopt a common application. This would
              effectively lock-in NCF systems to a single vendor and reduces
              NATO's ability to effectively manage technology
              obsolescence.</entry>

              <entry>Adopting a common workflow package would be a
              benefit.</entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope for NCF systems only.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Information Dissemination Management (IDM)</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Within NCSP scope for read access only. Write access will
              come within the NCSP scope if security issues can be
              resolved.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <!--                  T A B L E   4                            -->

      <table frame="all" id="rd-table-4" orient="land">
        <title>Justification for NCSP Standard Selection</title>

        <tgroup align="left" cols="3">
          <thead>
            <colspec colwidth="33*" />

            <colspec colwidth="33*" />

            <colspec colwidth="34*" />

            <row>
              <entry>Area/ Class</entry>

              <entry>Definition of class/sub class name</entry>

              <entry>Justification for NCSP Standard Selection</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody valign="top">
            <row>
              <entry align="left"><emphasis role="bold">1: User Interface
              Services</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Graphical User Interafce</entry>

              <entry>This category covers a miscellany of standards relevant
              to the Human-Computer Interface, including look and feel
              standards/conventions, APIs for windowing systems, desktop
              managers plus desktop hardware and operating system
              environments. It includes remote presentation protocols (e.g.
              X11) and inter-process communication protocols (e.g. DDE) which
              are also listed under Distributed Computing below.</entry>

              <entry>Standards are based on the 2 main platforms selected for
              NATO use: Windows 2000 and Unix. Standards carried forward from
              NCSP v 2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Look &amp; Feel</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Standards are based on the 2 main platforms selected for
              NATO use: Windows 2000 and Unix. Standards carried forward from
              NCSP v 2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Toolkit</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Standards are based on the 2 main platforms selected for
              NATO use: Windows 2000 and Unix. Standards carried forward from
              NCSP v 2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">2: Data
              Management</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Dictionary/ Directory</para> <para>(Data
              Dictionary)</para></entry>

              <entry>These are software development support tools that
              facilitate the management and use of project data
              dictionaries.</entry>

              <entry>The NC3 Repository is the common repository for standard
              data elements for the NATO CorpDM. This standard has been
              selected by the NDAG/NDAO</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Database Management System</para> <para>(Relational
              and Object Orientated)</para></entry>

              <entry>These are the facilities provided by a conventional RDBMS
              and OODBMS.</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v 2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Distributed Data</entry>

              <entry>See sub-classes below</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Remote Data Access</entry>

              <entry>These are mechanisms that allow clients to access data on
              remote database servers in a client/server environment.</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v 2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Database Replication</entry>

              <entry>These are mechanisms for replication of data between
              DBMSs, such as provided by modern commercial DBMS
              products.</entry>

              <entry>The ATCCIS Replication Mechanism (ARM) supports the land
              component as a View Model of the NATO CorpDM</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>NATO Common Schema</para> <para>See
              note A.2</para></entry>

              <entry>This category covers what would normally be described as
              data management. It includes data models plus associated
              metadata standards and data management procedures.</entry>

              <entry>The NATO CorpDM v1 has been selected by the
              NDAG/NDAO.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">3: Data
              Interchange</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Graphics</entry>

              <entry>See sub-classes below</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Images (Vector and Raster)</para>
              <para>(Graphical/still image data interchange)</para></entry>

              <entry>A wide range of standards used for representation of
              still image and graphic data,</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v 2. Some new
              standards have been added for interchange and compressed storage
              of raster images that will eventually replace GIF and
              NITFS</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Fax</entry>

              <entry>Fax standards for representation and transfer of page
              images.</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v 2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Video/ Audio</para> <para>(Moving Image and Audio/
              Video data interchange standards)</para></entry>

              <entry>As above but for moving images. It also includes
              standards for video conferencing and video telephony.</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v 2 and ACP
              140A</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Packet Switched (Voice-over-IP)</entry>

              <entry>A range of standards used for telephony over IP-based
              networks.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Circuit Switched</entry>

              <entry>Services for voice encoding across both analogue and
              digital dial-up connections. Includes modem services.</entry>

              <entry>New Sub-class and standards have been added to be used
              for Tactical Communications. Standards. These standards are
              currently in use in NATO and have been agreed by SC/6</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Tactical Digital Information Links</para>
              <para>(Communication Standards for TADILs are dealt with under
              the Communication Service Area)</para></entry>

              <entry>Links supporting the transfer of tactical information
              between coalition forces.</entry>

              <entry>Standards have been approved by the Data Link Working
              Group of the SC/5</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Military Message Text Formats</para></entry>

              <entry>Encodings of military-specific information in structured
              or unstructured form. Structured formats include both binary
              (bit-level) encodings and text-based (machine and
              human-readable) messages.</entry>

              <entry>Standards have been approved by the Message Text
              Formatting Working Group of the SC/5</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Civil Message Text</para></entry>

              <entry>Specific text- or bit-oriented formats for representation
              of business-related data.</entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v 2. EbXML is expected
              to replace EDIFACT</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Geographical</para> <para>(GIS)</para></entry>

              <entry>This category covers a wide range of standards used for
              representation of still image and graphic data, including
              geospatially referenced data formats. It also includes the fax
              standards (group 3 and group 4) for representation and transfer
              of page images.</entry>

              <entry>Digest and related exchange formats have been agreed by
              the Nations as the mandatory Geo Data exchange formats and are
              carried forward from NCSP v2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Document</entry>

              <entry>See sub-classes below</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Mark-up Languages</entry>

              <entry>Standards for marking-up (tagging) text, both structure
              and content.</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v 2 and ACP 140A.
              Other XML-related suite of standards also added for
              completeness.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Page description or display languages</entry>

              <entry>Standards for describing page layouts for submission to
              print or display devices (e.g. postscript).</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v 2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Office Automation interchange formats.</entry>

              <entry>Formats used for interchange of documents between OA
              tools (word processor, spreadsheet, etc.).</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v 2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Hypertext interchange formats</para>
              <para>Hypertext transfer protocols in Comms Service
              Area</para></entry>

              <entry>Formats for representation and transfer of hypertext
              documents.</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v 2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>File compression and archiving</entry>

              <entry>Standards for the extraction and encoding of compact file
              representations.</entry>

              <entry>Zip has been added as it is the de-facto market
              standard</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Military Symbology</entry>

              <entry>Standards for representation of military symbols (usually
              on map overlays).</entry>

              <entry>For CCEB the standard is Mil-Std 2525B. For NATO APP-6/
              STANAG 2019 and STANAG 3675 are the agreed standards</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Encoding</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Character sets and alphabets</entry>

              <entry>Binary encodings used to represent alphanumeric
              characters and special characters used in foreign languages or
              technical literature.</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v 2 Service Area
              Internationalisation</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Data Encoding</entry>

              <entry>Standards for encoding of binary or structured data,
              usually for transfer via a communications medium. This category
              covers ASN.1 and its encoding rules and UUENCODE.</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v 2 Service Area
              Internationalisation</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Optical Encoding</entry>

              <entry>Special characters that are transposed to represent
              binary encodings of scanned data via optical devices (e.g.
              barcodes).</entry>

              <entry>ISO standard xxxx (code 39) is widely used by the
              military and commercial logistics communities around the world.
              ISO standard xxxx (code 128) is rapidly emerging.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Voice Encoding</entry>

              <entry>Standards for encoding of voice, usually for transfer via
              a communications medium. This category covers ASN.1 and itsxs
              encoding rules and UUENCODE.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Multimedia and distributed real time service data
              interchange standards</entry>

              <entry>A range of standards used for reprasentation of moving
              images, including standards for video-coferencing and video
              telephony.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">4: Graphics</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Graphics Development</para></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Graphics Programming/ Modelling</para>
              <para>(Product data and General Purpose)</para></entry>

              <entry>Languages or language bindings to facilitate the
              production of graphics-based applications software.</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">5:
              Communications</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Application Layer</entry>

              <entry>OSI applications over TCP/IP lower layers are
              included</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Messaging</entry>

              <entry>Store-and-forward transfer of messages</entry>

              <entry>Standards agreed by the Message Handling Woking Group of
              the SC/5 and carried forward from NCSP v 2. X.400 has been
              deleted as it is part of STANAG 4406, and X.400 only systems are
              not foreseen.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Directory Services</para>
              <para>(Schema, Access, Chaining, Replication, Operational
              Management)</para></entry>

              <entry>Services for the provision of information relating to all
              forms of communications and information services including the
              support of messaging and security services.</entry>

              <entry>Standards agreed by the Directory Services Working Group
              of the SC/5 and carried forward from the NCSP v2. X.500 has been
              deleted as it is part of the ACP 133B Profile.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Domain Name Service</entry>

              <entry>Services for resolution of computer or server names into
              specific addresses.</entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v 2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Naming and Addressing Services</entry>

              <entry>The specification of rules and formats for Domain names
              and IP addresses.</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v2, but needs to be
              replaced by NACOSA Operating Instructions when
              available.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">File transfer</entry>

              <entry>Protocols and applications to provide a file transfer
              facility. They include both OSI application-layer standards and
              their IPS equivalents.</entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v 2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Remote terminal</entry>

              <entry>Protocols and applications that enable remote terminals
              to connect into a system. They include both OSI
              application-layer standards and their Internet Protocol Suite
              (IPS) equivalents. Such connections typically emulate
              character-based terminals and are used to provide access to
              legacy systems.</entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v 2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Hypertext transfer</entry>

              <entry>Protocols used for the transfer of hypertext documents
              between systems, including selective transfer for
              'browsing'.</entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v 2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Bulletin Board</entry>

              <entry>Information transfer services designed to notify
              registered subscribers of updates occurring in news groups and
              transfer relevant information</entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v 2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Time services</entry>

              <entry>Protocols for synchronisation of system clocks.</entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v 2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Audio/Video
              Teleconferencing</para></entry>

              <entry>Standards for transmitting audio and video between
              CIS</entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v 2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Whiteboarding</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the sharing of displays across a
              network allowing multiple users to collaborate simultaneously in
              the creation, review and updating of graphical or textual
              information.</entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v 2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Application Sharing</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the sharing of applications across a
              network.</entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v 2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Miscellaneous</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v 2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Presentation Layer</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>OSI Presentaion Layer standards have been deleted as
              their services are included within the applications that provide
              the higher layer services</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Session Layer</para></entry>

              <entry>This category includes APIs providing access to Internet
              protocols (e.g. WinSock) and associated applications.</entry>

              <entry>OSI Session Layer standards have been deleted as their
              services are included within the applications that provide the
              higher layer services</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Transport Layer</para></entry>

              <entry>Services providing user access to internetworking
              services and end-to-end quality enhancement</entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Network Layer</para></entry>

              <entry>See sub-classes below.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Internetworking</entry>

              <entry>Standards for the transfer of data across LAN/WAN and
              LAN/LAN boundaries.</entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Router services</para> <para>(Covered
              in NCSP remarks column for internetworking)</para></entry>

              <entry>Routers are used to interconnect networks of differing
              types, including sub-networks and end systems.</entry>

              <entry>OSPF carried forward from NCSP v2 and covered under
              Internetworking</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Circuit Switched Wide Area
              Networking</para></entry>

              <entry>Services for voice encoding across both analogue and
              digital dial-up connections. Includes modem services.</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>Point-to-point services</para>
              <para>(Covered in NCSP remarks column for circuit
              switched)</para></entry>

              <entry>Services providing full duplex, synchronous or
              asynchronous network connections over a serial line.</entry>

              <entry>Standard carried forward from NCSP v2 covered under
              Circuit Switched WAN</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Packet Switched Wide Area
              Networking</entry>

              <entry>Standards for the transfer of data across wide area
              networks including X.25, Frame Relay, ISDN, B-ISDN (ATM) and
              SONET</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v2.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Tactical data link Services</entry>

              <entry>Tactical data links provide the means for exchanging
              tactical information used for battle management</entry>

              <entry>Communication standards in use for Link 11, 16 and
              22.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Data Link/ Physical Layer</entry>

              <entry>See sub-classes below.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">SATCOM</entry>

              <entry>Standards for the transfer of data across SATCOM links
              including UHF, SHF and EHF.</entry>

              <entry>CCEB uses range of Mil-Stds carried forward from ACP140A.
              NATO uses STANAG4231, 4233 and 4522</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Radio</entry>

              <entry>Standards for the transfer of data across Radio links
              including VLF, LF, HF, VHF, UHF and SHF.</entry>

              <entry>CCEB uses range of Mil-Stds carried forward from ACP140A.
              NATO uses STANAG 4203, 4204, 4205, 4197A, 4285, 4444, 4246 and
              4175.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Cable</entry>

              <entry>Standards for the transfer of data across copper and
              fibre links including Optical, Shielded Twisted Pair and
              UTP</entry>

              <entry>Standards currently in use within NATO. (to be verified
              by SC/6)</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">6: Operating
              Systems</emphasis></entry>

              <entry>Standards for the services provided by computer operating
              systems and the means of accessing them by user
              applications.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Kernel Operations</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Non Real Time</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry><para>UNIX98 standard carried forward from NCSP v2</para>
              <para>MS Windows 2000 carried forward from NCSP v2</para>
              <para>LINUX LSB 1.1: Emerging std - second largest and fastest
              growing userbase in server market; open source provides
              advantages for implementation of security features. See Note
              A.17 </para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Real Time</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>UNIX98 standard: standard carried forward from NCSP
              v2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">7:
              Internationalisation</emphasis></entry>

              <entry>Internationalisation services are those standards and
              conventions that facilitate the use or re-use of systems or
              software within different National or cultural contexts. They
              cover a broad range of Internationalisation standards which can
              be loosely categorised as character sets, specific data
              representations and Internationalisation aspects of system
              interfaces (mainly HCI).</entry>

              <entry>Standards have been moved to Data Interchange: Encoding,
              Character Sets and Alphabets</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">8: System and Network
              Management</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Enterprise Management</para></entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the management of end-systems,
              including user administration, configuration management, fault
              management, security management, etc.</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>System and Network Management</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the management of networks under the
              control of end-systems or within the wide-area communications
              infrastructure.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>LAN Management</para></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right"><para>WAN Management</para></entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">9a: General Security</emphasis>
              <emphasis role="bold">(General security and message security
              will be comnbined into a service area called security with the
              classes General and Messages)</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Authentication</entry>

              <entry>Authentication services are those services supporting the
              reliable identification of individual users or groups of users
              of one system attempting to access services or information
              provided by another system.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Access Control</entry>

              <entry><para>Access control services are those services
              supporting the exercise and promulgation of access rights for
              service/information exchange between systems based on user
              identity, role, group, clearance or other privilege
              attributes.</para> <para>This includes standards for security
              labels where these are used (e.g. message
              exchange).</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Key Management and Distribution</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the management and distribution of
              cryptographic keys.</entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v2</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Confidentiality</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the confidentiality of
              information/services exchanged between systems.</entry>

              <entry>For CCEB standards carried forward from ACP120</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Integrity</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the integrity of information/services
              exchanged between systems.</entry>

              <entry><para>For CCEB standards carried forward from
              ACP120</para> <para>For NATO standards carried forward from NCSP
              v2</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Accounting and Audit</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the recording and analysis of
              security-relevant events involved in the exchange of
              services/information between systems.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Non-repudiation</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the verification of
              provision/acceptance of services or information between
              systems.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Security Domain Mediation</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the secure exchange of services
              between systems operating under differing security policies or
              within separate security domains.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">9b. Message
              Security</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Messge origin authentication</entry>

              <entry>Service providing assurance that a message was originated
              by the user indicated as the sender. It is the veritable
              identification of the user or organisation which originated the
              message.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message Access Control</entry>

              <entry><para>Services for validating authorisation of the user
              to originate messages is a national prerogative. The originator
              should ensure that the lowest common clearance of the
              communications system, end system and recipient dominate the
              classification of the message. This is to ensure that messages
              sent do not violate the security policies of the originating
              domains. Similarly, the receiving domain must compare the
              classification of the message with the clearance of the
              receiving domain. </para> <para>For the purposes of
              interoperability, this only includes standards for exchange of
              clearance information and security labels.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message content privacy/
              confidentiality</entry>

              <entry>Service providing assurance that a message was originated
              by the user indicated as the sender. It is the veritable
              identification of the user or organisation which originated the
              message.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message content integrity</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the integrity of messages
              exchanged.</entry>

              <entry>For NATO STANAG 4406 is carried forward from NCSP v2. For
              CCEB interoperability the standards ACP120 has been carried
              forward from ACP140A</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Certificate managent and
              distribution</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the management and distribution of
              certificates required to implement the message integrity and
              authentication security services.</entry>

              <entry>For CCEB interoperability the standards ACP120 has been
              carried forward from ACP140A</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message non-repudiation with proof of
              origin</entry>

              <entry>Services providing the recipient of a message with proof
              of its origin. This provides the ability to prove to a third
              party that a message was released by the originator and will
              protect against any attempt by the message originator to falsely
              deny having sent the message.</entry>

              <entry>For CCEB interoperability the standards ACP120 has been
              carried forward from ACP140A</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message non-repudiation with proof of
              delivery</entry>

              <entry>Services providing the originator of a message with proof
              of its delivery. This provides the ability to prove to a third
              party that a message was received by a particular recipient and
              will protect against any attempt by the message recipient
              falsely to deny having received the message.</entry>

              <entry>For CCEB interoperability the standards ACP120 has been
              carried forward from ACP140A</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message security labelling</entry>

              <entry>Services providing a method for associating security
              labels with objects in a MHS.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry align="right">Message accountability</entry>

              <entry><para>This service provides assurance that messages sent
              are received by the intended recipient, or permitted alternate
              recipient. The message originator is notified of any problems
              with message delivery. </para> <para>This can form a part of
              overall non-repudiation.</para></entry>

              <entry>For CCEB interoperability the standards ACP120 has been
              carried forward from ACP140A</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">10: Distributed
              Computing</emphasis></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Environment/ Remote Process</entry>

              <entry>Remote procedure call (included in this category are the
              other forms of inter-process communication).</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Distributed database management system</entry>

              <entry>Services for maintenance or querying of databases
              distributed over multiple physical locations.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Remote presentation services</entry>

              <entry>Protocols permitting graphical user interfaces to execute
              remotely from the client application (e.g. X11).</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>File Services</entry>

              <entry>File sharing protocols.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Print Services</entry>

              <entry>Protocols for transfer of print jobs from client to
              spooler/printer.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Distributed transaction processing services</entry>

              <entry>Services for the management of transactions involving
              participants on different end-systems.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Object Services</para></entry>

              <entry>Services for location of, or access to, objects when
              distributed over a network.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Time Services</entry>

              <entry>Protocols for synchronisation of system clocks.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Simulation Services</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><emphasis role="bold">11: Software Engineering
              services</emphasis></entry>

              <entry>This category mainly covers standards for the
              system/software lifecycle processes and associated tools but
              also includes standards for programming languages and their
              bindings</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Languages</entry>

              <entry></entry>

              <entry>Standards carried forward from NCSP v2. C# has been added
              as the Microsoft equivalent for Java.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Case</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Software Development</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para> <emphasis role="bold">12: Collaborative
              Computing</emphasis> </para> <para> <emphasis role="bold">(This
              will not be added as a new area but all these services will be
              covered under another area)</emphasis> </para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Workflow services</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the automated transfer of documents
              or other information between users or organisations on the basis
              of a predefined business process.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Information Dissemination Management (IDM)</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting group access (read/write) to
              structured or unstructured information on the basis of subject
              area or other categorisation.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Collaborative Computing</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the sharing of displays across a
              network.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para> <emphasis role="bold">13: Common C2
              Applications</emphasis> </para> <para> <emphasis
              role="bold">(Maps to NCOE component model)</emphasis>
              </para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Correlation Services</entry>

              <entry>Applications providing services relating to the
              acquisition, correlation, update and query of tracks.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Alert Services</entry>

              <entry>Information transfer services designed to support the
              rapid or widespread distribution of information, usually having
              great operational significance.</entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>Data Fusion</entry>

              <entry>Services supporting the fusion of data from a variety of
              possible sources in support of a common opertional
              picture.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 3
 ***************************************************************** 
-->

  <chapter id="v5c3-standards">
    <title>NISP Standards Definition</title>

    <sect1 id="v5c3s1-introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>This section explains the final stage of the NISP definition
      process, namely the selection and allocation of standards to the
      services within the scope of the NISP.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v5c3s2-overview">
      <title>Overview</title>

      <para>The process so far has been concerned with the scoping of services
      from the NII. It has identified those services which are required to
      support interoperability between NCF systems, the NII, and national
      systems and NII, and those services that support wider benefits but
      which can only be mandated for use within NCF systems or the NII. The
      resultant profile of services (built into a class / sub-class taxonomy)
      must be implemented using a range of de jure and de facto
      standards.</para>

      <para>Among the NII services that are within the scope of the current
      NISP, there are comparatively few technical choices available for
      standards that will stand serious scrutiny. This is because the current
      NISP is limited, for the most part, to those areas where technology is
      well defined and standards are reasonably stable and well supported.
      However, it is important that the choice of standards should be
      justified and to aid this justification a number of key drivers have
      been used.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v5c3s3-drivers">
      <title>Key Drivers</title>

      <para>A key driver in the process of selecting the NISP services has
      been the existence (or likely existence) of user requirements and
      whether or not the technology exists to provide those services. The
      selection of standards for the NISP specification has been driven by the
      following:</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Adoption of Internet and web technologies. The NISP cites the
          popular internetworking standards TCP, IP and UDP; the data exchange
          protocols in widespread use on the Internet and in commercial
          networks (HTTP, NNTP, FTP etc.); and common data interchange formats
          (HTML, JPEG, zip, etc.);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Need for security. The most significant departure from
          commercial standards is in the adoption of a common security
          protocol particularly in support of messaging. A common approach to
          secure messaging is fundamental to the existence of an effective
          NISP;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Adoption of essential requirements to meet military needs.
          Common elements of NATO standards for organizational messaging
          (STANAG 4406/ACP123) and directory (ACP133) are adopted.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>The NISP makes no statements about the security architecture or
      policy to be adopted for end-systems. However, the widespread
      interconnection of systems envisaged means that Secure Messaging alone
      cannot provide adequate protection. Depending upon the protective
      marking of the data and/or system and the geographical location and
      nature of the communications bearers, messaging interconnections between
      systems will continue to require COMSEC protection through the use of
      (an appropriate grade of) encryption at the net-work/link level. Even
      where the data exchanged has a low or even no security classification,
      COMPUSEC concerns, possibly derived from distant systems in the
      federation, will often lead to a supplementary requirement for
      network-level encryption.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v5c3s4-stds">
      <title>Multiple Standards</title>

      <para>The NISP specification generally identifies a single standard or
      group of interdependent standards for each service. In some cases,
      however, the Working Group agreed that it would be appropriate to
      specify multiple standards that progressively add functionality (e.g.
      HTML, XML and SGML). In such cases a primary standard is identified
      (HTML in this example) and must be supported regardless of whether any
      other standards are implemented.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 4
 ***************************************************************** 
-->

  <chapter id="v5c4-evolution">
    <title>NISP Evolution</title>

    <sect1 id="v5c4s1-introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>This section describes the way the NISP will evolve in future
      issues. It identifies the key change drivers that affect the
      functionality of systems, the NII and the technology supporting
      them.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v5c4s2-drivers">
      <title>Change Drivers</title>

      <para>The evolution for the NISP will be driven by the following key
      factors:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>New technology and its product support in the market
          place;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>New requirements resulting from the need to interoperate with
          NATO;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Resolution of shortfalls in long-term technical issues;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Feedback from projects and nations implementing the NISP,
          external stakeholders (e.g. CCEB) and relevant bodies.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v5c4s3-developments">
      <title>New Technology Developments</title>

      <para>Close monitoring is required of new technology areas to identify
      if and when acceptably open, capable standards suitable for NATO and
      national use become available. These will be addressed in NISP Volume 3,
      Mid-term Guidance.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v5c4s4-reqs">
      <title>New NATO Requirements</title>

      <para>As technological developments impact upon the way NATO nations
      perform combined operations, there is an increasing need to monitor new
      and changing requirements relevant to the NATO coalition. The assessment
      indicates that the NISP should monitor a number of service areas for
      possible inclusion in future NISP specifications. These additional
      services would enhance the capabilities of the existing NISP by:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Overcoming some significant information exchange limitations
          arising from a lack of acceptably open standards (e.g. Collaborative
          Computing services);</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Providing NATO-wide coherence of security and interconnection
          policies and the associated security services needed to allow the
          widest possible use to be made of existing interoperability services
          (e.g. http). This would allow over-restrictive security constraints
          limiting information access to be relaxed;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Standardizing more advanced interoperability mechanisms such
          as RPCs, other distributed computing mechanisms and database
          replication services (see <xref linkend="rd-A-3-data" />); these are
          also contingent on the security developments above;</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Accommodating emerging requirements for the exchange of
          multimedia-based services between nations.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v5c4s5-feedback">
      <title>Feedback from NCF Projects, NATO Nations and Other Nations and
      Organizations</title>

      <para>As NISP starts to become widely published and used, there will
      inevitably be feedback from NCF projects, NATO nations and other
      stakeholders. System designers and integrators will be able to
      contribute positively to the knowledge embodied within the NISP, thus
      increasing its usefulness and relevance. They will also be able to test
      the dependencies between the technical architecture, embodied in the
      NISP, and the systems and information architectures as they are
      instantiated in delivered systems.</para>

      <para>Work carried out under the auspices of the NATO and UN coalitions
      is frequently used by and influences other nations and coalitions. It is
      anticipated, therefore, that as other groups formulate technical
      strategies for achieving system interoperability, there will be
      additional feedback into the NATO Open Systems Working Group.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 5
 ***************************************************************** 
-->

  <chapter id="v5c5-tam">
    <title>Technology Assessment Methodology</title>

    <sect1 id="v5c5s1-intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>To ensure that NATO and its member nations maintain the best use
      of technology it is important to distinguish between retiring, mandated
      and emerging technologies/standards. Once they are identified and their
      applicability analyzed, then informed decisions can be made on what role
      each technology or standard will play in the current technical
      architecture.</para>

      <para>The rapid pace of technological change carries with it the
      potential benefits of faster and more cost-effective improvements in
      operational capability; however, the rapidity of change upon a broad
      technology front also makes the task of identifying emerging
      technologies particularly difficult.</para>

      <para>The process of analyzing these emerging technologies will follow 3
      steps. The first step is to filter the technologies down to those that
      are appropriate and applicable to NATO operations. The second step is
      identifying were in the technology's life cycle are we at the present
      time. The final step is to describe and forecast the emerging
      technology's impact on NATO operations.</para>

      <sect2 id="v5c5s2-fc">
        <title>Filter Criteria</title>

        <para>The first step in the process of analyzing emerging technologies
        for NATO is to determine which technologies are relevant to NATO. In
        other words, we need way to sort through vastly different technologies
        and focus on only those that influences the answers to the following
        questions:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Does it relate to interoperability within NATO
            Systems?</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Can it effect implementation of NATO CIS?</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Can it effect implementation of NATO Net-Enabled
            Capability?</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Does it relate to Nation-to-Nation Systems
            interoperability?</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>So for any given potential technology if we apply any of the
        above questions and the answer is yes, then that technology has passed
        the minimum threshold to be a candidate for consideration.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v5c5s3-gs">
        <title>Grading Scale</title>

        <para>By following 'The Rate of Adoption Theory'<footnote>
            <para>Rogers, E.M. (1995). Diffusion of innovations (4th ed.). New
            York: The Free Press</para>
          </footnote>, we can track the dissemination of a technology over
        time with innovations going through a slow, gradual growth period,
        followed by dramatic and rapid growth, and then a gradual
        stabilization and finally a decline. This model can best track the
        state of technologies in the IT area of interest.</para>

        <table>
          <title><emphasis>Key Attributes</emphasis></title>

          <tgroup cols="5">
            <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="27*" />

            <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="20*" />

            <colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="14*" />

            <colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="11*" />

            <colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="28*" />

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Phase</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Level</emphasis></entry>

                <entry nameend="col5" namest="col3"><emphasis role="bold">Key
                Attributes</emphasis></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Maturity</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Adoption</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Support</emphasis></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Emerging</emphasis></entry>

                <entry>1</entry>

                <entry>Basic principles observed and reported; Concept and/or
                applications formulated.</entry>

                <entry>Embraced by early adopters willing to absorb high costs
                to take advantage of technology</entry>

                <entry>One organization or company controls technology
                development.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>2</entry>

                <entry>Analytical and experimental critical function and/or
                characteristic proof of concept.</entry>

                <entry>Embraced by early majority; Common in few NATO
                nations</entry>

                <entry>Multiple organizations control the technology's
                development. .</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Mandated</emphasis></entry>

                <entry>3</entry>

                <entry>Component and/or breadboard validation in laboratory
                and relevant environment.</entry>

                <entry>Internationally widespread and mass market appeal;
                Common in most NATO nations</entry>

                <entry>Large community involved in the development and
                improvement of the technology.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Retiring</emphasis></entry>

                <entry>4</entry>

                <entry>System/subsystem model or prototype demonstration in
                relevant &amp; operational environments.</entry>

                <entry>Embraced by the conservative late adopters; Still
                common, but other alternatives on the horizon.</entry>

                <entry>Many advocates, one rival</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>5</entry>

                <entry>Actual system completed and qualified through test and
                demonstration. Actual system proven through successful mission
                operations</entry>

                <entry>Better alternatives available.</entry>

                <entry>No advocates, many better alternatives</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <sect3 id="v5c5s4-ma">
          <title>Maturity Attribute</title>

          <para>Technology maturity is a measure of the degree of readiness to
          which proposed critical technologies meets NATO's objectives. This
          assessment examines concepts, technology requirements, and
          demonstrated technology capabilities in order to determine
          technological maturity. In general,</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Emerging technologies are at a low level of
              readiness.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Mandated and retiring technologies have a high level of
              readiness.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v5c5s5-aa">
          <title>Adoption Attribute</title>

          <para>The adaptation attribute deal with the question of how
          widespread is the use of a technology. The more ubiquitous a
          technology becomes, then the lower the costs are for that
          technology. High rates of adoption also reduce the likelihood of
          encountering interoperability problems.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v5c5s6-sa">
          <title>Supportability Attribute</title>

          <para>The supportability attribute is a measure of the number of
          organizations that endorse or supports a technology. More entities
          involved in developing and sustaining a technology translate into
          stability.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 6
 ***************************************************************** 
-->

  <chapter id="v5c6-iop">
    <title>Interoperability Profile Guidance</title>
	<sect1 id="v5c6-iopref">
		<title>References</title>
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>NATO Interoperability Standards Profile (NISP) AdatP-34(B)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>NATO Architecure Framework Version 3</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>ISO/IEC TR 10000-3:1998(E) Information technology - Framework and taxonomy of International Standardized Profiles - Part 3: Principals and Taxonomy for Open System Environment Profiles</para>
          </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="v5c6-iopcb">
		<title>Conceptual Background</title>
		<para>ISO/IEC TR 10000 (Ref. C) defines the concept of profiles as a set of one or more base standards and/or International Standardized Profiles, and, where applicable, the identification of chosen classes, conforming subsets, options and parameters of those base standards, or International Standardized Profiles necessary to accomplish a particular function.</para>
		<para>The NATO Open Systems Working Group (NOSWG) has extended the profile concept to encompass references to NAF architectural views (Ref. B), characteristic protocols, implementation options, technical standards, Service Interoperability Points (SIOP), and related profiles.</para>
		<para>Nothing in this guidance precludes the referencing of National profiles or profiles developed by non-NATO organizations in the NISP.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="v5c6-ioppurpose">
		<title>Purpose of Interoperability Profiles</title>
		<para>Interoperability Profiles aggregate references to the characteristics of other profiles types to provide a consolidated perspective.</para>
		<para>Interoperability Profiles identify essential profile elements including Capability Requirements and other NAF architectural views (Ref. B), characteristic protocols, implementation options, technical standards, Service Interoperability Points, and the relationship with other profiles such as the system profile to which an application belongs. Interoperability profiles will be incorporated in the NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles (NISP) (Ref. A) for a specified NATO Common Funded System or Capability Package to include descriptions of interfaces to National Systems where appropriate.</para>
		<para>NATO and Nations use profiles to ensure that all organizations will architect, invest, and implement capabilities in a coordinated way that ensure interoperability for NATO and the Nations. Interoperability Profiles will provide context and assist or guide information technologists with an approach for building interoperable systems and services to meet required capabilities.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="v5c6-iopappl">
		<title>Applicability</title>
		<para>Since the NISP impacts on the full NATO project life cycle, NISP stakeholders may include engineers, designers, technical project managers, procurement staff, architects and other planners. Architectures, which identify the components of systems operation, are most applicable during the development phase of a project, when applied to the dynamic NNEC environment, where interoperability of mature National systems requires an agile approach to architectures.</para>
		<para>The NOSWG has undertaken the development of interoperability profiles in order to meet the need for specific guidance at interoperability points between NATO and Nations systems and services required for specific capabilities. As a component of the NISP, profiles have great utility in providing context and interoperability specifications for using mature and evolving systems during exercises, pre-deployment or operations. Application of these profiles also provides benefit to Nations and promotes maximum opportunities for interoperability with NATO common funded systems as well as national to national systems. Profiles for system or service development and operational use within a mission area enable Nations enhanced readiness and availability in support of NATO operations.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="v5c6-iopgfd">
		<title>Guidelines for Interoperability Profile Development</title>
		<para>Due to the dynamic nature of NATO operations, the complex Command and Control structure, and the diversity of Nations and Communities of Interest (COI), interoperability must be anchored at critical points where information and data exchange between entities exists. The key drivers for defining a baseline set of interoperability profiles include:
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Identify the Service Interoperability Points and define the Service Interface Profiles</para></listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use standards based consistent with the common overarching and reference architectures</para></listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Develop specifications that are service oriented and independent of the technology implemented in National systems where practical</para></listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use mature technologies available within the NATO Information Enterprise</para></listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Develop modular profiles that are reusable in future missions or capability areas</para></listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Use an open system approach to embrace emerging technologies</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</para>
		<para>The starting point for development of a profile is to clearly define the Service Interoperability Point where two entities will interface and the standards in use by the relevant systems.</para>
		<para>The use of "shall" in this guidance document is intended to establish a minimum level of content for NATO and NATO candidate profiles, but is suggested-but-not-binding on non-NATO profiles (national, NGO, commercial and other entities).</para>
		<para>The NISP is the governing authoritative reference for NATO interoperability profiles. DOTMLPFI capability analysis may result in a profile developer determining that some of the capability elements may not be relevant for a particular profile. In such cases, the 'not applicable' sections may either be marked 'not applicable' or omitted at the author's discretion.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="v5c6-ioptaxonmy">
		<title>Profile Taxonomy</title>
		<para>The objective of the interoperability profile taxonomy is to provide a classification scheme that can categorize any profile. In order to achieve this objective, the classification scheme is based on NATO Architecture Framework views and DOTMLPFI characteristics.</para>
		<para>The taxonomy illustrated in the figure below will also provide a mechanism to create short character strings, used as a root mnemonic to uniquely identify profiles.
</para>

      <figure id="v5c6f1-ioptaxy">
        <title>Interoperability Profile Taxonomy</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/v5c6f1-ioptaxy.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="v5c6-iopstructure">
		<title>Structure of Interoperability Profile Documentation</title>
		<para>This section identifies typical elements of Interoperability Profile Documentation.</para>
		<sect2 id="v5c6-iopid">
			<title>Identification</title>
				<para>Each NATO or candidate NATO Interoperability Profile <emphasis role="bold">shall</emphasis> have a unique identifier assigned to it when accepted for inclusion in the NISP. This <emphasis role="bold">shall</emphasis> be an alpha-numeric string appended to the root mnemonic from the NISP profile taxonomy.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="v5c6-iopelements">
			<title>Profile Elements</title>
				<para>Profile elements provide a coherent set of descriptive inter-related information to NATO, national, NGO, commercial and other entities ('actors') desiring to establish interoperability.</para>
				<para>Profiles are not concepts, policies, requirements, architectures, patterns, design rules, or standards. Profiles provide context for a specific set of conditions related to the aforementioned documents in order to provide guidance on development of systems, services, or even applications that must consider all of these capability related products. Interoperability Profiles provide the contextual relationship for the correlation of these products in order to ensure interoperability is 'built-in' rather than considered as an 'after-thought'.</para>
			<sect3 id="v5c6-iopcs">
				<title>Capabilities Set</title>
<para>Each profile <emphasis role="bold">shall</emphasis> list the Capabilities supported by the profile. The intention of this section is to trace NATO capabilities to the applicable element(s) in the NATO capability taxonomy/database and NNEC Maturity Level (NML), as well as any relevant authoritative capabilities operational reference documents (e.g., Overarching Architecture, EXTAC reference, etc.). Identification of applicable functional attributes is desired to link capability requirements to objective or subjective interoperability performance objectives.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopcs-1" orient="land">
<title>Capability Set Taxonomy, Reference and Applicable Functional Attributes</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="6">
 	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Related Capability Title</entry>
              <entry>High-level Capability Description (extract from NATO Capabilities Database)</entry>
              <entry>NML Ref #</entry>
              <entry>NATO Capability Taxonomy Ref. #</entry>
              <entry>Reference (Overarching Architecture, EXTAC, etc.)</entry>
              <entry>Applicable Functional Attribute(s)</entry>
        </row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	</tbody>
 </tgroup>
</table>
<para>Each profile should list the Functional Attributes supported by the profile. The intention of this section is to identify what functional attributes are desired and thus link capability requirements to interoperability performance thresholds and objectives. For example, a typical threshold for satisfactory equipment performance may be achieving 95% reliability calculated in accordance with a specified military standard such as MIL-HDBK-217F(2) 'RELIABILITY PREDICTION OF ELECTRONIC EQUIPMENT'. 
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopcs-2" orient="land">
<title>Functional Attributes**</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="3">
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Functional Attribute</entry>
              <entry>Threshold/ (for minimum satisfactory performance)</entry>
              <entry>Objective</entry>
	</row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
		<row>
		<entry>Superior Decision Making</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry>Flexible Synchronization</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry>Shared Understanding</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry>Responsible and Adaptable Organization</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry>Dispersed C2</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry>Simultaneous C2 Processes</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry>Full Spectrum Integration</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry>Shared Quality Information</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry>Robust Networking</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		<entry>TBD</entry>
		<entry></entry>
		<entry></entry>
		</row>
		</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>** 'notional' Attributes shown in the table above are for illustrative purposes only.
</para>
<para>Each profile should document the relationship between Capabilities and Operational Activities supported by the specific interoperability profile. The intention of this section is to map capabilities to operational activities thereby providing implementation authorities with vital understanding as to what actors will be establishing what NML is being sought at specific Service Interoperability Points (SIOPS). Identification of entities may be generic, specific, or a combination of generic and specific entities. For example, it may be unrealistic and inappropriate to identify specific operational units, deployable headquarters, and/or non-NATO actors for a reference-architecture (high-level) profile. However, specific identification of operational activities may be totally appropriate for developing a target-level profile associated with promoting interoperability for a specific discrete event or set of events in theatre.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopcs-3" orient="land">
<title>Capability to Operational Activities Mapping</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="4">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Related Capability/ Title</entry>
              <entry>Operational Activity</entry>
              <entry>Requirement Reference</entry>
              <entry>Cross Reference</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="v5c6-iopas">
				<title>Applicable Standards</title>
<para>Each profile <emphasis role="bold">shall</emphasis> document the standards required to support this or other associated profiles and any implementation specific options. The intention of this section is to provide an archive that shows the linkage between evolving sets of standards and specific profile revisions.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopas-1" orient="land">
<title>Applicable Standards</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="4">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Profile ID</entry>
              <entry>Mandatory Standards</entry>
              <entry>Emerging Standards</entry>
              <entry>Implementation Options</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
	<row>
              <entry>A unique profile identifier</entry>
              <entry>A unique Standard Identifier from the NISP</entry>
              <entry>A unique Standard Identifier from the NISP</entry>
              <entry>Implementation specific options associated with this profile (may be a reference to a separate annex or document)</entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
	
			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="v5c6-ioprp">
				<title>Related Profiles</title>
<para>Each profile should document other key related system or service profiles in a cross reference table. The intention of this section is to promote smart configuration management by including elements from other profiles rather than duplicating them in part or in whole within this profile. Related profiles would likely be referenced in another section of the profile.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-ioprp-1" orient="land">
<title>Related Profiles</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="4">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Profile ID</entry>
              <entry>Profile Description</entry>
              <entry>Community of Interest</entry>
              <entry>Associated SIOPs</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
	<row>
              <entry>A unique profile identifier</entry>
              <entry>A short description of the profile</entry>
              <entry>Air, Land, Maritime, Special Ops, etc.</entry>
              <entry>Unique SIOP identifiers</entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="v5c6-iopsm">
				<title>Services Mapping</title>
				<sect4 id="v5c6-iopcfsm">
					<title>Capability / Function / Service Mapping</title>
<para>Each profile should provide a cross reference between Capabilities, System Functions and Services. The intention of this section is to specify 'services mapping' both for stakeholders with relevant service-oriented architectures (SOAs), and for interoperability within multi-entity federated environments where functional information may be relied upon as a key information source or 'service'. The services mapping is vital to illustrating the sometimes complex interoperability interrelationships among services, system functions and operational capabilities.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopcfsm-1" orient="land">
<title>Capability-to-Function-to-Service Mapping</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="4">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Service ID #</entry>
              <entry>Supported Capability Title (from table 1)</entry>
              <entry>System Function (from table 17)</entry>
              <entry>Service/(from tables 7 and 8)</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

				</sect4>
				<sect4 id="v5c6-iopcscs">
					<title>Capability Specific COI Services</title>
<para>Each profile <emphasis role="bold">shall</emphasis> describe any known COI services required to support the profile. The intention of this section is to specify those services for which reuse in other capability areas would be the exception rather than the rule. For example, if one developed a service for developing Air Tasking Orders (ATOs) in support of Air Command and Control, this would be a COI-specific service.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopcscs-1" orient="land">
<title>COI Services Description (capability-specific)</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>ID #</entry>
              <entry>COI Service (capability-specific)</entry>
              <entry>Service Definition  Description</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

				</sect4>
				<sect4 id="v5c6-iopccsr">
					<title>Cross COI Service Re-use</title>
<para>Each profile should describe any other COI services being reused to support this profile. The intention of this section is to specify those services for which reuse in other capability areas is expected or likely. For example, geospatial display capabilities would be useful in support of a variety of capabilities, and thus should be listed in this Cross COI / Service Re-use section of the profile.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopccsr-1" orient="land">
<title>COI Services (cross-COI / re-use)</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>ID #</entry>
              <entry>COI Service (cross-COI / re-use)</entry>
              <entry>Service Definition / Description</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

				</sect4>
				<sect4 id="v5c6-iopsrcsc">
					<title>Service Related Capability Specific Constraints</title>
<para>Each profile should describe any service related capability constraints, such as Quality of Service (QoS). The intention of this section is to identify Quality of Service (QoS) requirements and related constraints. QoS is often vital to establishing viable interoperability. Interoperability is of limited or questionable value if the information does not meet the expectations of the actors/entities on the other side of the Service Interoperability Point (SIOP). Identification of constraints is intended to supplement the Quality of Service definitions by adding to the understanding of factors that may limit interoperability QoS on either or both sides of the SIOP (e.g., available bandwidth, format restrictions, circuit limitations, etc.).
</para>
<para>NOTE: Information Assurance (IA) constraints have been intentionally omitted from this revision of profile guidance with the view that IA features will be embedded in the architectures and tend not to be a capability-specific concern. However, if capability-specific IA functionality is required, it may be appropriate to include IA-specific constraints in this section, or to insert a separate IA section.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopsrcsc-1" orient="land">
<title>Service-related capability-specific constraints</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="4">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>ID #</entry>
              <entry>Constraint</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
              <entry>Reference</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

				</sect4>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="v5c6-iopkod">
				<title>Key Operational Definitions</title>
<para>Each profile should list relevant agreed operational definitions within the scope of the profile. The intention of this section is to promote a common understanding of the operational terms used across interfaces among different entities (i.e., semantic interoperability). For example, for an MSA profile, one may provide a specific definition for the term 'vessel of interest' in order that the term may be properly understood and/or translated across the interface.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopkod-1" orient="land">
<title>Key Operational Definitions (semantic vocabulary)</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="4">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Abbreviation (if any)</entry>
              <entry>Term</entry>
              <entry>Definition</entry>
              <entry>Reference</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="v5c6-iopocd">
				<title>Operational Concepts Descriptions</title>
<para>Each profile should list the operational concepts within the scope of the profile. The intention of this section is to identify operational concepts that provide relevant context for implementation authorities to understand how interoperability will enable and support achieving mission success. 'DOTMLPFI' categories refer to considering interoperability within the context of delivering comprehensive capabilities to operational users. 'DOTMLPFI' is an acronym that means 'Doctrine, Organization, Training, Materiel, Leadership and education, Personnel, Facilities and Interoperability'. Some of these elements may not be applicable. The use of the term DOTMLPFI is not intended to be exhaustive or exclusive. Thus, other capability elements such as policy and legal may be added as deemed appropriate.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopocd-1" orient="land">
<title>Key Operational Definitions (semantic vocabulary)</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="5">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Operational Concept</entry>
              <entry>Categories (DOTMLPFI, policy, legal, etc.)</entry>
              <entry>Classification</entry>
              <entry>Reference</entry>
              <entry>Originating Organization</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="v5c6-ioponcd">
				<title>Operational Node Connectivity Description</title>
<para>Each profile should provide a diagram of the operational nodes connectivity supported by this profile. The intention of this section is to identify operational nodes to provide implementation authorities with a more detailed description of the required/desired interoperability end state (i.e., goal baseline) connectivity. Identification of operational nodes may be generic, specific, or a combination of generic and specific elements.
</para>

      <figure id="v5c6f2-ioponcd">
        <title>Notional Node Connectivity Diagram</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/v5c6f2-ioponcd.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>



<para>Each profile should describe the contribution and connectivity of each operational node supported by the profile. The intention of this section is to support the development or use of NOV-2 or NOV-2-like architecture view(s).
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-ioponcd-1" orient="land">
<title>Operational Node Connectivity Description (NOV-2 precursor)</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Operational Node</entry>
              <entry>Contribution(s)</entry>
              <entry>Connectivity Description</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="v5c6-iopoir">
				<title>Operational Information Requirements</title>
<para>Each profile should list the relevant operational information requirements (preferably described using APP-15) within the scope of the profile. This section is intended to promote the NNEC need to share information in a Service Oriented Architecture by documenting Information Requirements associated with this profile to support the NATO Data Strategy making data visible, accessible and understandable. If such information is maintained in an external document, reference to such documentation is preferred - including the most recent revision associated with this particular profile baseline.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopoir-1" orient="land">
<title>Operational Information Sharing Matrix (NOV-3 precursor)</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="10">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>IER/#</entry>
              <entry>X x #</entry>
              <entry>Event Action</entry>
              <entry>Information Characterisation</entry>
              <entry>Receving Node</entry>
              <entry>Critical</entry>
              <entry>Format</entry>
              <entry>Timeliness</entry>
              <entry>Classification</entry>
              <entry>Cross Reference</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry> </entry>
              <entry> </entry>
              <entry> </entry>
              <entry> </entry>
              <entry>(Command, Etc.)</entry>
              <entry>Yes No</entry>
              <entry>Text Data Audio Video Voice</entry>
              <entry>(eg. less than 15 Sec.)</entry>
              <entry>NU NR NS</entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="v5c6-iopcoi">
				<title>Criteria of Operational Interest</title>
<para>Each profile should list relevant key conformance criteria of operational interest. The intention of this section is to document criteria such as alerts, thresholds or other parameters that may be important to understanding and employing information shared across an interface. This list of key criteria is not intended to be exhaustive. Additionally, if such criteria are described in a separate document referencing the document is appropriate. For the sake of brevity, it is highly encouraged to reference (not duplicate) other documents when completing this section.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopcoi-1" orient="land">
<title>Criteria of Operational Interest</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>ID #</entry>
              <entry>Key Criteria of Operational Interest</entry>
              <entry>Definition / Description</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="v5c6-iopcc">
				<title>Capability Configuration</title>
<para>Each profile should describe the capability baseline that the profile supports. The intention of this section is to identify "as is" capability baselines that have used this profile. Since profiles tend to evolve, the specific profile revision used to achieve interoperability is also noted.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopcc-1" orient="land">
<title>Capability Configuration</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="4">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Capability Baseline #</entry>
              <entry>Date (YYYYMMDD)</entry>
              <entry>Name of Capability Baseline and Originator</entry>
              <entry>Profile(s) / Revision Used/(High Level Overview / Synopsis)</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="v5c6-iopoi">
				<title>Organizational Interfaces</title>
<para>Each profile <emphasis role="bold">shall</emphasis> include a description of the organizational interfaces supported by the profile. The intention of this section is to promote visibility and interactions among stakeholders. Note that the intention of this section is very different than the aim of the Operational Node Connectivity Description. This section is intended to be more administrative in nature and identify stakeholders and contributors to the profile. Generic organizational billets and/or specific points of contact may be identified in this section as desired.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopoi-1" orient="land">
<title>Organizational Interfaces</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Organization (Short Title)</entry>
              <entry>List of Required Organizational Interfaces</entry>
              <entry>Detailed Notes regarding Organizational Interfaces</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="v5c6-iopsf">
				<title>System Functions</title>
<para>Each profile should list the system functions that the profile supports. The intention of this section is to provide a basic understanding of the system functional decomposition on the profile implementation authority's side of the SIOP. The intent of this section is to make the profile less abstract and more concrete for the implementation authorities on both sides of the SIOP as they work to achieve interoperability. There is no intention of renaming functions on the other side of the SIOP, but rather to provide insight regarding what functions will be supported by information crossing the SIOP interface(s). Detailed system functional descriptions should be cited as references, not duplicated.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopsf-1" orient="land">
<title>System Functions and Descriptions</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="3">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>ID #</entry>
              <entry>System Function</entry>
              <entry>Function Definition/Description</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="v5c6-iopct">
				<title>Candidate Technologies</title>
<para>Each profile should document the current and emerging technologies required to support this profile and any implementation specific options. The intention of this section to identify current and emerging technologies associated with promoting interoperability as an aid to stakeholder organization program managers as they consider (with interoperability in mind) their own mid-term (2-6 years) and long term (>6 years) investment plans in relevant technologies.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopct-1" orient="land">
<title>Candidate Technologies</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="4">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Technology ID</entry>
              <entry>Current Technologies</entry>
              <entry>Current Technologies</entry>
              <entry>Implementation Options</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry>A unique technology identifier</entry>
              <entry>Technology name(s)</entry>
              <entry>Technology name(s)</entry>
              <entry>Implementation specific options associated with this profile (may be a reference to a separate annex or document)</entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

			</sect3>

		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="v5c6-iopvc">
		<title>Verification and Conformance</title>
<para>Each profile <emphasis role="bold">shall</emphasis> identify authoritative measures to determine verification and conformance with agreed quality assurance, Key Performance Indicators (KPIs), and Quality of Service standards such that actors are satisfied they achieve adequate performance.</para> 

<para>Stakeholders are invited to provide feedback to improve a profile's verification and conformance criteria.</para> 

<para>Verification and Conformance is considered in terms of the following five aspects: <orderedlist>
          <listitem><para>Approach to Validating Service Interoperability Points 
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Relevant NNEC Maturity Level (NML) Criteria 
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) 
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Experimentation 
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Demonstration</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>
		<sect2 id="v5c6-iopavsip">
			<title>Approach to Validating Service Interoperability Points</title>
<para>Each profile should describe the validation approach used to demonstrate the supporting service interoperability points. The intention of this section is to describe a high-level approach or methodology by which stakeholders may validate interoperability across the SIOP(s).
</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="v5c6-ioprnmlc">
			<title>Relevant NNEC Maturity Level (NML) Criteria</title>
<para>Each profile should describe the NML criteria applicable to the profile. The intention of this section is to describe how this profile supports the achievement of improved interoperability within the NML framework.
</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="v5c6-iopkpi">
			<title>Key Performance Indicators {KPIs)</title>
<para>Each profile should describe the associated Key Performance Indicators (KPIs) to establish a baseline set of critical core capability components required to achieve the enhanced interoperability supported by this profile. The intention of this section is to assist all stakeholders and authorities to focus on the most critical performance-related items throughout the capability development process.
</para>
<table frame="all" id="rd-iopkpi-1" orient="land">
<title>Key Performance Indicators {KPIs)*</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Key Performance Indicators (KPI)</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry>KPI#1: Single (named) Architecture</entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry>KPI#2: Shared Situational Awareness</entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry>KPI #3: Enhanced C2</entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
   	<row>
              <entry>KPI #4: Information Assurance</entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
   	<row>
              <entry>KPI #5: Interoperability</entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
   	<row>
              <entry>KPI #6: Quality of Service</entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry>KPI #7: TBD</entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>*'notional' KPIs shown in the table are for illustrative purposes only
</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="v5c6-iope">
			<title>Experimentation</title>
<para>Each profile should document experimentation venues and schedules that will be used to determine conformance. The intention of this section is to describe how experimentation will be used to validate conformance.
</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="v5c6-iopd">
			<title>Demonstration</title>
<para>Each profile should document demonstration venues and schedules that demonstrate conformance. The intention of this section is to describe how demonstration will be used to validate conformance.
</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="v5c6-iopcmg">
		<title>Configuration Management and Governance</title>
		<sect2 id="v5c6-iopcm">
			<title>Configuration Management</title>
<para>Each profile <emphasis role="bold">shall</emphasis> identify the current approach or approaches toward configuration management (CM) of core documentation used to specify interoperability at the Service Interoperability Point. The intention of this section is to provide a short description of  how often documents associated with this profile may be expected to change, and related governance measures that are in place to monitor such changes [e.g., the NOSWG].
</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="v5c6-iopg">
			<title>Governance</title>
<para>Each profile <emphasis role="bold">shall</emphasis> identify <emphasis role="bold">one or more authorities</emphasis> to provide feedback and when necessary, Request for Change Proposals (RFCP) for the Profile in order to ensure inclusion of the most up-to-date details in the NISP. The intention of this section is to provide a clear standardized methodology by which stakeholders may submit recommended changes to this profile. 
</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="v5c6-iopdefn">
		<title>Definitions</title>

<table frame="all" id="rd-iopdefn-1" orient="land">
<title>Defintions</title>
        <tgroup align="left" cols="4">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />
	<thead>
	<row>
              <entry>Term</entry>
              <entry>Acronym</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
              <entry>Reference</entry>
      </row>
      </thead>
	<tbody>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
 	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	<row>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
              <entry></entry>
      </row>
  	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>


	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="v5c6-iopad">
		<title>Annex Descriptions</title>
<para>The following describes a list of potential 
<emphasis role="bold">optional</emphasis> annexes to be used as needed. The intention of this section is to place all classified and most lengthy information in Annexes so that the main document stays as short as possible. In cases where tables in the main document become quite lengthy, authors may opt to place these tables in Annex D.
</para>
<para>Annex A - Classified Annex (use only if necessary)</para>
<para>Annex A-1 - Profile elements (classified subset)</para>
<para>Annex A-2 - (Related) Capability Shortfalls</para>
<para>Annex A-3 - (Related) Requirements (classified subset)</para>
<para>Annex A-4 - (Related) Force Goals</para>
<para>Annex A-5 - other relevant classified content</para>
<para>Annex B - Related Architecture Views (most recent)</para>
<para>Annex B-1 - Capability Views (NCV)</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>NCV-1, Capability Vision</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NCV-2, Capability Taxonomy</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NCV-4, Capability Dependencies</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NCV-5, Capability to Organisational Deployment Mapping</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NCV-6, Capability to Operational Activities Mapping</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NCV-7, Capability to Services Mapping</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Annex B-2 - Operational Views (NOV)</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>NOV-1, High-Level Operational Concept Description</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NOV-2, Operational Node Connectivity Description</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NOV-3, Operational Information Requirements</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Annex B-3 - Service Views (NSOV)</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>NSOV-1, Service Taxonomy</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NSOV-2, Service Definitions (Reference from NAR)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NSOV-3, Services to Operational Activities Mapping (in conjunction with NCV-5, NCV-6, NCV-7, NSV-5 and NSV-12)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Quality of Services metrics for the profiled services</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Annex B-4 - System Views (NSV)</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>NSV-1, System Interface Description (used to identify Service Interoperability Point (SIOP))</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NSV-2, Systems Communication DescriptionNSV-2d, Systems Communication Quality Requirements</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NSV-3, Systems to Systems Matrix</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NSV-5, Systems Function to Operational Activity Traceability Matrix</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NSV-7, System Quality Requirements Description</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NSV-12, Service Provision</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Annex B-5 - Technical Views (NTV)</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>NTV-1, Technical Standards Profile. Chapter 4 of the NAF Ref (B) provides more specific guidance.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NTV-3, Standard Configurations</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Annex C - Program / Inter-Programme Plans</para>
<para>Annex C-1 - (Related) Mid-Term Plan excerpt(s)</para>
<para>Annex C-2 - (Related) Programme Plan excerpt(s)</para>
<para>Annex D - Other Relevant Supporting Information</para>
	</sect1>			  
     </chapter>

  <xi:include href="vol5-annexA.xml"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xpointer="v5a-rdsi-A" />

  <xi:include href="vol5-annexB.xml"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xpointer="v5b-rdtm-B" />

  <index></index>
</book>