<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
	<serviceprofile id="fmn4-proposed-geospatial-data-exchange-profile" title="Proposed FMN Spiral 4 Geospatial Data Exchange Serviceprofile">
		<refprofilespec refid="profspec-fmn4-proposed"/>
		<description>
			<para>Maps, geographical overviews and digital images provide valuable knowledge of a mission area and are intensively
used for planning and mission execution purposes at every level of command. Geospatial information (GI) requirements
are typically defined by product type (what is required – the level of detail at a specific scale) and coverage (where it is
required). Geospatial support covers land, sea and air-space (battle space) segments and consists of four main product
types: topographical, hydrographical, aeronautical information and suitable geospatially referenced imagery.</para>
			<para>Typically, maps and geospatial datasets are being produced by different organisations and need to be exchanged (e.g.
via automated or manual file transfer) between different participants using standardised exchange formats. These
datasets would then be loaded into specialised geospatial information systems (GIS) and published via standardized
Web Services.</para>
		</description>
		<!-- Geospatial Services -->
		<reftaxonomy refid="T-54a19444-8cd5-4766-9140-6cdc53aafb79-X"/>
		<refgroup obligation="recommended" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>File geodatabases store geospatial datasets and can hold any number of these large, individual
datasets. File geodatabases can be used across multiple platforms. Users are rapidly adopting file
geodatabases in place of using legacy shapefiles.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- OGC 12-128r12 - "GeoPackage Encoding Standard" -->
			<refstandard refid="ogc-12-128r12"/>
		</refgroup>
		<refgroup obligation="mandatory" lifecycle="candidate">
			<!-- OGC 07-147r2 - "Keyhole Markup Language" -->
			<refstandard refid="ogc-07-147r2"/>
		</refgroup>
		<refgroup obligation="recommended" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>File based storage and exchange of digital geospatial mapping (raster) data.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- MIL-PRF-89038 - "Performance Specification: Compressed Arc Digitized Raster Graphics (CADRG)" -->
			<refstandard refid="nga-mil-prf-89038"/>
			<!-- MIL-STD-2411 - "Department of Defense Interface Standard: Raster Product Format" -->
			<refstandard refid="nga-rpf"/>
		</refgroup>
		<refgroup obligation="mandatory" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>File based storage and exchange of digital geospatial mapping (raster) data.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- GeoTIFF Revision 1.0 - "GeoTIFF Format Specification, GeoTIFF Revision 1.0, Specification Version 1.8.2, 28 December 2000" -->
			<refstandard refid="osgeo-geotiff"/>
			<!-- OGC 05-047r3 - "OpenGIS GML in JPEG 2000 for Geographic Imagery Encoding Specification" -->
			<refstandard refid="ogc-05-047r3"/>
		</refgroup>
		<guide>
			<para>Often the exchange of large geospatial(raster) data sets between Geo organizations of different
Mission Participants is conducted in the proprietary Multi-resolution seamless image database format
(MrSID Generation 3). Data in MrSID format could be transformed to GeoTIFF. The JPEG 2000
image compression standard offers many of the same advantages as MrSID, plus the added benefits
of being an international standard (ISO/IEC 15444).</para>
		</guide>
		<status mode="accepted">
			<history>
				<event date="2019-12-12" flag="added" rfcp="12-025" version="13.0"/>
			</history>
		</status>
		<uuid>68f0f495-e985-4e9d-b444-e2eae967041a</uuid>
	</serviceprofile>
