<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
	<serviceprofile id="fmn4-proposed-cyber-information-exchange-profile" title="Proposed FMN Spiral 4 Cyber Information Exchange Serviceprofile">
		<refprofilespec refid="profspec-fmn4-proposed"/>
		<description>
			<para>The Cyber Information Exchange Profile provides standards are used to exchange information about cyber threats.</para>
			<para>Structured Threat Information Expression (STIX) is an information model and serialization for cyber threat intelligence
(CTI). By allowing the consistent expression of CTI in a machine­readable specification, STIX supports shared threat
analysis, machine automation, and information sharing. It enables use cases such as indicator exchange, management
of response activities, shared malware analysis, and higher ­level threat intelligence sharing.</para>
			<para>Trusted Automated eXchange of Intelligence Information (TAXII) is an application layer protocol for the communication
of cyber threat information in a simple and scalable manner. It defines services and message exchanges that enable
organizations to share the information they choose with the partners they choose. TAXII is designed to transport STIX
Objects.</para>
			<para>Some of the important use cases are data feed providers such as an intel provider trying to share what indicators they
see for threats, and sharing that with either Threat Intelligence Platforms (TIPS), sharing it with threat mitigation systems
for example, like a firewall.</para>
		</description>
		<!-- Undefined Taxonomy Node -->
		<reftaxonomy refid="user.undefined.taxonomynode"/>
		<refgroup obligation="recommended" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>STIX provides a bundle as a container for STIX objects to allow for transportation of bulk STIX data.
TAXII is specifically designed to support the exchange of CTI represented in STIX. This does not
mean TAXII cannot be used to share data in other formats; it is designed for STIX, but is not limited
to STIX. Nonetheless, TAXII is not mandatory for this exchange and C_SOC are suggested to
distribute STIX Bundles via mailing lists or web-publication.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- TAXII Version 2 - "Trusted Automated eXchange of Intelligence Information" -->
			<refstandard refid="oasis-taxii-2.0"/>
		</refgroup>
		<refgroup obligation="mandatory" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>STIX 2.0 is transport-agnostic, i.e., the structures and serializations do not rely on any specific
transport mechanism.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- STIX V2.0 Part 1 - "STIX™ Version 2.0. Part 1: STIX Core Concepts" -->
			<refstandard refid="oasis-stix-2.0-p1"/>
			<!-- STIX V2.0 Part 2 - "STIX™ Version 2.0. Part 2: STIX Core Concepts" -->
			<refstandard refid="oasis-stix-2.0-p2"/>
			<!-- STIX V2.0 Part 3 - "STIX™ Version 2.0. Part 3: Cyber Observable Core Concepts" -->
			<refstandard refid="oasis-stix-2.0-p3"/>
			<!-- STIX V2.0 Part 4 - "STIX™ Version 2.0. Part 4: Cyber Observable Objects" -->
			<refstandard refid="oasis-stix-2.0-p4"/>
			<!-- STIX V2.0 Part 5 - "STIX™ Version 2.0. Part 5: STIX Patterning" -->
			<refstandard refid="oasis-stix-2.0-p5"/>
		</refgroup>
		<status mode="accepted">
			<history>
				<event date="2019-12-12" flag="added" rfcp="12-025" version="13.0"/>
			</history>
		</status>
		<uuid>1fba1458-03c7-4bc1-b3ac-13f18378bc17</uuid>
	</serviceprofile>
