<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
	<serviceprofile id="fmn4-proposed-scip-x509-profile" title="Proposed FMN Spiral 4 SCIP X.509 Serviceprofile">
		<refprofilespec refid="profspec-fmn4-proposed"/>
		<description>
			<para>The X.509 standard is used in cryptography to define the format of public key certificates, which are used in many
Internet protocols. One example is the use in Transport Layer Security (TLS) / Secure Sockets Layer (SSL), which is the
basis for HTTPS, the secure protocol for browsing the web. Public key certificates are also used in offline applications,
like electronic signatures.</para>
			<para>An X.509 certificate contains a public key and an identity (a hostname, or an organization, or an individual), and is either
signed by a certificate authority or self-signed. When a certificate is signed by a trusted certificate authority, or validated
by other means, someone holding that certificate can rely on the public key it contains to establish secure
communications with another party, or validate documents digitally signed by the corresponding private key.</para>
			<para>Besides the format for certificates themselves, X.509 specifies certificate revocation lists as a means to distribute
information about certificates that are no longer valid, and a certification path validation algorithm, which allows for
certificates to be signed by intermediate Certificate Authority (CA) certificates, which are in turn signed by other
certificates, eventually reaching a trust anchor.</para>
		</description>
		<!-- Undefined Taxonomy Node -->
		<reftaxonomy refid="user.undefined.taxonomynode"/>
		<refgroup obligation="conditional" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>When X.509 is applied for the Secure Communications Interoperability Protocol (SCIP), the following
standards need to be followed.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- SCIP-233.109 - "X.509 Elliptic Curve (EC) Key Material Format Specification" -->
			<refstandard refid="iicwg-scip-233.109"/>
			<!-- SCIP-233.307 - "ECDH Key Agreement and TEK Derivation Specification" -->
			<refstandard refid="iicwg-scip-233.307"/>
			<!-- SCIP-233.401 - "Application State Vector Processing" -->
			<refstandard refid="iicwg-scip-233.401"/>
			<!-- SCIP-233.423 - "Universal Fixed Filler Generation Specification" -->
			<refstandard refid="iicwg-scip-233.423"/>
			<!-- SCIP-233.444 - "Point-to-Point Cryptographic Verification w/Signature" -->
			<refstandard refid="iicwg-scip-233.444"/>
			<!-- SCIP-233.601 - "AES-256 Encryption Algorithm Specification" -->
			<refstandard refid="iicwg-scip-233.601"/>
		</refgroup>
		<status mode="accepted">
			<history>
				<event date="2019-12-12" flag="added" rfcp="12-025" version="13.0"/>
			</history>
		</status>
		<uuid>2091780d-faec-418b-a947-482d6bb90445</uuid>
	</serviceprofile>
