<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
	<serviceprofile id="fmn4-proposed-service-implementation-request-managing-profile" title="Proposed FMN Spiral 4 Service Implementation Request Managing Serviceprofile">
		<refprofilespec refid="profspec-fmn4-proposed"/>
		<description>
			<para>The Service Implementation Profile for Request Managing enables the handover of service requests between a sending
Service Provider and a receiving Service Provider. The handover point is set after the request data validation and
request prioritization and before the approval steps.</para>
			<para>The Service Implementation Profile for Request Managing provides implementation guidance for the TMForum Product
Ordering API REST Specification. The IER for an incident record handover is represented in this API as follows:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>id: ID created on the receiving side request management system (initially empty)</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>externalId: ID of the request on the requestor's system (to facilitate searches afterwards)</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>description: Description of the request</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>priority: The consumers indication based on per agreed priority levels (0 = highest priority, 4 = lowest priority)</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>orderDate: Date when the request was created</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>requestedCompletionDate: Requested delivery date from the requestor perspective</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>expactedCompletionDate: Expected delivery date amended by the provider</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>requestedStartDate: Order start date wished by the requestor</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>completionDate: Date when the order was actually completed</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>notificationContact: Customer contact to be notified on request completion</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>href: hyperlink to access the order direct access to REST resource</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>id: ID created on the receiving side request management system (this MUST be initially empty)</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>externalId: ID of the request on the requestor's system (used to facilitate searches afterwards)</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>description: Description of the request</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>priority: The consumers indication based on preagreed priorities ranging from levels 0 = highest priority to 4 = lowest
priority</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>orderDate: Date when the request was created</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</description>
		<!-- Web Hosting Services -->
		<reftaxonomy refid="T-06d559b4-1bdf-40cc-904f-4e745a170f24-X"/>
		<refgroup obligation="mandatory" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>Service Providers using the TMForum Product Ordering API to federate their ITSM systems are
responsible for implementing internally the business logic to utilize the additional related attributes.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- TMForum TMF622 - "TMForum Product Ordering API REST Specification R14.5.1" -->
			<refstandard refid="tm-forum-tmf622"/>
			<!-- TMForum TR250 - "TMForum API REST Conformance Guidelines R15.5.1" -->
			<refstandard refid="tm-forum-tr250"/>
		</refgroup>
		<refgroup obligation="recommended" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>The following extended attribute should be included in the message as nested sub-entities mapped
as follows: confidentialityInformation as "related object" with involvement "confidentialityInformation"
data-origID="input_13" class="createboxInput autoGrow" rows="2" cols="90" style="width: auto">The
following extended attribute should be included in the message as nested sub-entities mapped as
follows: confidentialityInformation as "related object" with involvement "confidentialityInformation" and
with PolicyIdentifier, Classification, Privacy Mark and Category.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- STANAG 4774 Edition 1 - "Confidentiality Metadata Label Syntax" -->
			<refstandard refid="nato-stanag4774"/>
		</refgroup>
		<guide>
			<para>The following additional attributes shall be included in the message as nested sub-entities as
specified in:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>securityMarking</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>orderItem</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>product</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>relatedParty</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>note</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>location</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>securityDomain</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>releasabilityCommunity</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>orderItem</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>product</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</guide>
		<status mode="accepted">
			<history>
				<event date="2019-12-12" flag="added" rfcp="12-025" version="13.0"/>
			</history>
		</status>
		<uuid>96145863-af83-415f-889e-51eae0b786d9</uuid>
	</serviceprofile>
