<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
	<serviceprofile id="fmn4-proposed-battlespace-event-federation-profile" title="Proposed FMN Spiral 4 Battlespace Event Federation Serviceprofile">
		<refprofilespec refid="profspec-fmn4-proposed"/>
		<description>
			<para>The Battlespace Event Federation Profile provides standards and guidance to support the exchange of information on
significant incidents, important events, trends and activities within a coalition network or a federation of networks.</para>
		</description>
		<!-- Battlespace Event Services -->
		<reftaxonomy refid="T-54f06201-f6f4-4939-a537-75a0c1ff70bc-X"/>
		<refgroup obligation="mandatory" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>To support exploitation the following APP-11 message formats MUST be supported (MTF Identifier,
MTF Index Ref Number):
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>Incident Report (INCREP, A078)</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>Incident Spot Report (INCSPOTREP, J006)</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>Troops in Contact SALTA format (SALTATIC, A073)</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>Events Report (EVENTREP, J092)</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>Improvised Explosive Device Report (IEDREP, A075)</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>The INCREP is used to report any significant incident caused by terrorism, civil unrest, natural
disaster, or media activity.</para>
				<para>The INCSPOTREP is used to provide time critical information on important events that have an
immediate impact on operations.</para>
				<para>The SALTATIC is used to report troops in contact, the report should be made as soon as possible by
the unit that has come under some form of attack. It uses the following basic format: Size of enemy,
Action of enemy, Location, Time and Action taken.</para>
				<para>The EVENTREP is used to provide the chain of command information about important Events, trends
and activities that do not have an element of extreme urgency, but do influence on-going operations.</para>
				<para>The IEDREP is sent when an IED has been encountered. It identifies the hazard area, tactical
situation, operational priorities and the unit affected. This initial report should be followed by normal
EOD/Engineer reporting requirements.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- APP-11(E) - "NATO Message Catalogue" -->
			<refstandard refid="nato-app-11-ed.e-v1"/>
		</refgroup>
		<status mode="accepted">
			<history>
				<event date="2019-12-12" flag="added" rfcp="12-025" version="13.0"/>
			</history>
		</status>
		<uuid>f116271a-8f85-487a-b30e-eb482ebad283</uuid>
	</serviceprofile>
