<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
	<serviceprofile id="fmn4-proposed-jreap-profile" title="Proposed FMN Spiral 4 JREAP Serviceprofile">
		<refprofilespec refid="profspec-fmn4-proposed"/>
		<description>
			<para>The Joint Range Extension Application Protocol (JREAP) enables Link 16 tactical data to be transmitted over digital
media and networks not originally designed for tactical data exchange. Full detail of JREAP instructions and procedures
can be found in STANAG 5518 Ed1 - Interoperability Standard for Joint Range Extension Application Protocol (JREAP).</para>
			<para>Link 16 messages (i.e. J-series) are embedded inside of the JREAP. JREAP management messages (i.e. X-series) are
used, in order to ensure proper dissemination of the Link 16 messages.</para>
			<para>Capabilities are provided that include:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Extending the range-limited tactical networks to beyond LOS while reducing their dependence upon relay platforms</para>
						<para>Reducing the loading on stressed networks</para>
						<para>Providing backup communications in the event of the loss of the normal link</para>
						<para>Providing a connection to a platform that may not be equipped with the specialized communications equipment for
that TDL.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<para>For media that do not support OSI network and transport layers, the JREAP provides network and transport layer
functionality. For media supporting OSI network and transport layers, the JREAP is encapsulated within those layers.
JREAP software can be integrated into a host system or into a stand-alone processor. The appropriate interface
terminals are required at each end of any JREAP alternate media link.</para>
		</description>
		<!-- Track Distribution Services -->
		<reftaxonomy refid="T-7de33633-668c-4d32-ba13-944acbc798fe-X"/>
		<refgroup obligation="mandatory" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>JREAP offers the transmission mechanism. Track Service is performed by Link 16</para>
			</description>
			<!-- STANAG 5516 Edition 8 - "Tactical Data Exchange - Link 16" -->
			<refstandard refid="nato-stanag5516ed8"/>
			<!-- STANAG 5518 Edition 1 - "Interoperability Standard for Joint Range Extension Application Protocol (JREAP)" -->
			<refstandard refid="nato-stanag5518ed1"/>
		</refgroup>
		<refgroup obligation="conditional" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>STANAG 5602 covers ATDLP-6.02 (SIMPLE), which specifies the requirements for the transfer of
data between remote sites to support the interoperability testing of tactical data link implementations
in different platforms.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- STANAG 5602 Edition 4 - "Standard Interface for Multiple Platform Link Evaluation (SIMPLE)" -->
			<refstandard refid="nato-stanag5602ed4"/>
		</refgroup>
		<guide>
			<para>===JREAP=== JREAP is designed to support operations using Link 16 over most communication
media (JRE media) including forwarding TDL data over SATCOM links (JREAP-A), Serial links
(JREAP-B), and over IP networks (JREAP-C).</para>
			<para>Each JRE medium has unique characteristics. It supports UDP Unicast, UDP multicast, and TCP.</para>
			<para>For implementation in FMN only JREAP, Appendix C - ENCAPSULATION OVER INTERNET
PROTOCOL (IP) - is to be used.</para>
			<para>===SIMPLE=== The SIMPLE protocol is going to be used only for Verification and Validation
purpose of all systems employing or interfacing with tactical data links and only when the systems do
not support JREAP. It is not going to be used within the operational network for operational purpose.</para>
		</guide>
		<status mode="accepted">
			<history>
				<event date="2019-12-12" flag="added" rfcp="12-025" version="13.0"/>
			</history>
		</status>
		<uuid>5bc97ea3-92b0-4f4f-8971-68df0fa1aa3f</uuid>
	</serviceprofile>
