<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
	<serviceprofile id="fmn4-proposed-web-content-profile" title="Proposed FMN Spiral 4 Web Content Serviceprofile">
		<refprofilespec refid="profspec-fmn4-proposed"/>
		<description>
			<para>The Web Content Profile provides standards and guidance for the processing, sharing and presentation of web content
on federated mission networks. Web presentation services must be based on a fundamental set of basic and widely
understood protocols, such as those listed below.</para>
			<para>Recommendations in the FMN Spiral 2 Service Interface Profile for Web Applications are intended to improve the
experience of Web applications and to make information and services available to users irrespective of their device and
Web browser. However, it does not mean that exactly the same information is available in an identical representation
across all devices: the context of mobile use, device capability variations, bandwidth issues and mobile network
capabilities all affect the representation. Some services and information are more suitable for and targeted at particular
user contexts. While services may be most appropriately experienced in one context or another, it is considered best
practice to provide as reasonable experience as is possible given device limitations and not to exclude access from any
particular class of device, except where this is necessary because of device limitations.</para>
		</description>
		<!-- Web Hosting Services -->
		<reftaxonomy refid="T-06d559b4-1bdf-40cc-904f-4e745a170f24-X"/>
		<refgroup obligation="mandatory" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>Providing a common style sheet language for describing presentation semantics (that is, the look and
formatting) of documents written in markup languages like HTML.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- W3C - Cascading Style Sheets Level 2 Revision 1 (CSS 2.1) Specification - "Cascading Style Sheets Level 2 Revision 1 (CSS 2.1) Specification" -->
			<refstandard refid="w3c-rec-css2-2011067"/>
			<!-- W3C - CSS Style Attributes - "CSS Style Attributes" -->
			<refstandard refid="w3c-rec-css-style-attr-20131107"/>
			<!-- W3C - CSS Namespaces Module Level 3 - "CSS Namespaces Module Level 3" -->
			<refstandard refid="w3c-rec-css-namespaces-3-20140320"/>
			<!-- W3C - CSS Color Module Level 3 - "CSS Color Module Level 3" -->
			<refstandard refid="w3c-rec-css3-color-20110607"/>
		</refgroup>
		<refgroup obligation="mandatory" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>Publishing information including text, multi-media, hyperlink features, scripting languages and style
sheets on the network.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- RFC 2854 - "The 'text/html' Media Type" -->
			<refstandard refid="ietf-rfc2854"/>
			<!-- W3C - HTML5 - "HTML5" -->
			<refstandard refid="w3c-rec-html5-20141028"/>
			<!-- RFC 4329 - "Scripting Media Types" -->
			<refstandard refid="ietf-rfc4329"/>
			<!-- W3C - Media Queries - "Media Queries" -->
			<refstandard refid="w3c-rec-css3-mediaqueries-20120619"/>
			<!-- W3C - Selectors Level 3 - "Selectors Level 3" -->
			<refstandard refid="w3c-rec-css3-selectors-20110929"/>
		</refgroup>
		<guide>
			<para>To enable the use of web applications by the widest possible audience, web applications shall be
device independent and shall be based on HTML5 standards and criteria for the development,
delivery and consumption of Web applications and dynamic Web sites. HTML5 is a new version of
the mark-up language HTML, with new elements, attributes, and behaviours (data format) and it
contains a larger set of associated technologies such as CSS 3 and JavaScript that allows more
diverse and powerful Web sites and applications.</para>
			<para>Web applications will not require any browser plug-ins on the client side as some organizations or
end user devices do not allow the use of Java Applets or proprietary extensions such as Silverlight
(Microsoft), Flash (Adobe) or Quick Time (Apple). Implementers shall use open standard based
solutions (HTML5 / CSS3) instead.</para>
			<para>The requirements defined in the FMN Spiral 2 Service Interface Profile for Web Applications are
mandatory for all web content consumers (browsers) and are optional for web content providers. It is
expected that in the future FMN Spiral Specifications they will become mandatory also for the web
content providers.</para>
		</guide>
		<status mode="accepted">
			<history>
				<event date="2019-12-12" flag="added" rfcp="12-025" version="13.0"/>
			</history>
		</status>
		<uuid>e3112e96-3cc8-472a-abb7-55716277b35c</uuid>
	</serviceprofile>
