<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
	<serviceprofile id="fmn4-proposed-overlay-distribution-profile" title="Proposed FMN Spiral 4 Overlay Distribution Serviceprofile">
		<refprofilespec refid="profspec-fmn4-proposed"/>
		<description>
			<para>This profile covers the standards for (military) symbology and overlays that identify locations on the surface of the
planet. These overlays are employed when disseminating recognized domain or functional pictures and related picture
elements as overlays between different communities of interest in a federated mission network environment.</para>
		</description>
		<!-- Symbology Services -->
		<reftaxonomy refid="T-3edec962-1d0e-4dc0-ab28-b01e0efc1064-X"/>
			<refgroup obligation="conditional" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>Conditional for two use cases that typically involve cross-domain information exchange:
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>sharing overlays with non-military partners who are not on the mission network and who do not
	use military symbology, and</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>exchanging of targeting and intelligence products that are prepared on national networks.</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>When exporting KML files that reference external resources, KMZ as defined in "Annex C: KMZ Files"
	must be used and all relevant referenced external resources must be included in the KMZ structure
	as relative references. The references to these files can be found in the href attribute (or sometimes,
	the element) of several KML elements. To enable cross domain exchange and long-term preservation
	relative references must be used for those resources that are included in the KMZ structure. As many
	Earth Viewers only work with legacy PKZIP 2.x format for KMZ, .zip folders shall be created in
	accordance with https://www.pkware.com/documents/APPNOTE/APPNOTE-2.0.txt.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- GEOINT - OGC KML 2.3 - "OGC KML, Version 2.3, 4 Aug 2015" -->
			<refstandard refid="ogc-07-147r2"/>
		</refgroup>
		<refgroup obligation="mandatory" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>If NVG 2.0.2 becomes available in the NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles (ADatP-36)
	before approval of the FMN Spiral 4 Specification, the newer version shall be used.</para>
			</description>
			<!-- NISP Standard - NVG 1.5 -->
			<refstandard refid="nato-tide-nvg"/>
		</refgroup>
		<refgroup obligation="mandatory" lifecycle="candidate">
			<description>
				<para>Applies to NVG only</para>
			</description>
			<!-- APP-6(D) - "NATO JOINT MILITARY SYMBOLOGY" -->
			<refstandard refid="nato-app-06-ed.d-v1"/>
		</refgroup>
		<guide>
			<para>All presentation services shall render tracks, tactical graphics, and Battlespace objects using these
symbology standards except in the case where the object being rendered is not covered in the
standard. In these exceptional cases, additional symbols shall be defined as extensions of existing
symbol standards and must be backwards compatible. These extensions shall be submitted as a
request for change within the configuration management process to be considered for inclusion in the
next version of the specification.</para>
		</guide>
		<status mode="accepted">
			<history>
				<event date="2019-12-12" flag="added" rfcp="12-025" version="13.0"/>
			</history>
		</status>
		<uuid>e04ec905-ac73-4c46-a841-8336e6b79b48</uuid>
	</serviceprofile>
