<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<book lang="en">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles</title>
	<titleabbrev>NISP</titleabbrev>
    <subtitle>Agreed Interoperability Standards and Profiles (Version 10)</subtitle>
    <corpauthor>C3B Interoperability Profiles Capability Team</corpauthor>
    <productname class="trade">Allied Data Publication 34</productname>
    <biblioid class="pubnumber">ADatP-34</biblioid>
    <volumenum>2</volumenum>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>9.15</revnumber>
        <date>26 January 2017</date>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <subjectset><subject><subjectterm>DO NOT REMOVE</subjectterm></subject></subjectset>
  </bookinfo>
  <!--
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 1
 *****************************************************************
-->
  <chapter id="v2c-int">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Volume 2 of the NISP focuses on agreed interoperability standards and profiles.</para>
<para>The NISP references Standards from different standardization bodies<footnote><para>In case of conflict between any recommended non-NATO standard and relevant NATO standard, the definition of the latter prevails.</para></footnote>. In the case of a ratified STANAG, NATO Standardization procedures apply. The NISP only references these STANAG’s without displaying the country-specific reservations. The country-specific reservations can be found in the NATO Standardization Agency Standards database.</para>
    <para>The Combined Communications Electronics Board (CCEB) nations
    will use NISP Volume 2 <xref linkend="v2c-std" /> and <xref linkend="v2s1-ts" />
    tables to publish the interoperability standards
    for the CCEB under the provisions of the NATO-CCEB List of Understandings
    (LoU)<footnote><para>References:NATO Letter AC/322(SC/5)L/144 of 18 October 2000,
    CCEB Letter D/CCEB/WS/1/16 of 9 November 2000, NATO Letter AC/322(SC/5)L/157 of 13
    February 2001</para></footnote>.</para>
    <sect1>
      <title>Scope</title>
      <para>The scope of this volume includes:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Identifying the standards and
          technologies that are relevant to a service oriented environment,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Describing the standards and technologies
          to support federation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <!--
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 2
 *****************************************************************
-->
  <chapter id="v2c-refmod">
    <title>Reference Models: Transition from Platform Centric to Service
    Oriented Models</title>
    <para>Information technology has undergone a fundamental shift from
    platform-oriented computing to network-oriented computing. Platform-oriented
    computing emerged with the widespread proliferation of personal computers
    and the global business environment. These factors and related
    technologies have created the conditions for the emergence of
    network-oriented computing. This shift from platform to network is what
    enables the more flexible and more dynamic network-oriented operation. The
    shift from viewing NATO and partner Nations as independent to viewing them as part of
    a continuously adapting network ecosystem fosters a rich information sharing
    environment.</para>
    <para>This shift is most obvious in the explosive growth of the Internet,
    intranets, and extranets. Internet users no doubt will recognize
    transmission control protocol/internet protocol (TCP/IP), hypertext
    transfer protocol (HTTP), hypertext markup language (HTML), Web browsers,
    search engines, and Java<footnote><para>Registered Trademark of ORACLE and/or its affiliates. Other names
    may be the trademarks of their respective owners.</para></footnote> Computing. These technologies, combined with
    high-volume, high-speed data access (enabled by the low-cost laser) and
    technologies for high-speed data networking (hubs and routers) have led to
    the emergence of network-oriented computing. Information &#x201C;content&#x201D; now can
    be created, distributed, and easily exploited across the extremely
    heterogeneous global computing environment. The &#x201C;power&#x201D; or &#x201C;payoff&#x201D; of
    network-enabled computing comes from information-intensive interactions
    between very large numbers of heterogeneous computational nodes in the
    network, where the network becomes the dynamic information grid
    established by interconnecting participants in a collaborative,
    coalition environment. At the structural level, network-enabled warfare
    requires an operational architecture to enable common processes to be
    shared.</para>
    <para>One of the major drivers for supporting net-enabled operations is
    Service-Oriented Architectures (SOA). SOA is an architectural style that
    leverages heterogeneity, focuses on interfaces between services and as such this approach is inherently platform-neutral. It is
    focused on the composition of Services into flexible processes and is more
    concerned with the Service interface and above (including composition
    metadata, security policy, and dynamic binding information), more so than
    what sits beneath the abstraction of the Service interface. SOA requires a
    different kind of platform, because runtime execution has different
    meanings within SOA. SOA enables users and process
    architects to compose Services into processes, and then manage and evolve
    those processes, in a declarative fashion. Runtime execution of such
    processes is therefore a metadata-centric operation of a different kind of
    platform -- a Service-oriented composite application platform.</para>
    <para>Network-enabled operations are characterized by new concepts of
    speed of command and self-synchronization.</para>
    <para>The most important SOA within an enterprise is the one that links
    all its systems. Existing platforms can be wrapped or extended in order to
    participate in a wider SOA environment. NATO use of the NISP will provide
    a template for new systems development, as well as assist in defining the
    path for existing systems to migrate towards net-enabled
    operations.</para>
  </chapter>
  <!--
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 3
 *****************************************************************
-->
  <chapter id="v2c-std">
    <title>Standards</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <para>This purpose of this chapter is to specify the agreed NISP standards. The document organizes these standards, following  baseline 2.0 NATO's C3 Taxonomy, as endorsed by the NATO C3 Board per AC/322-N(2016)0021-AS1 on 11 February 2016. A graphical representation of this taxonomy is included in volume 1.</para>
      <para>For some standards it was not clear yet which service identified in the C3 Taxonomy should be used. Therefore, as an interim solution, the taxonomy was extended with user-defined "Cloud Services". In a separate section, all standards are listed for which could not yet be defined how they should be linked to the C3 Taxonomy.</para>
<para>The standards are presented in tabular form. The left column of the table corresponds to a service in the C3 Taxonomy. The section headers correspond to a service at a higher (or the same) level. In general, a service is only listed if at least one standard is assigned to this service.</para>
      <sect2 id="v2s2-rel">
        <title>Releasability Statement</title>
        <para>In principle, NISP only contains or references standards or related documents, which are
          generally available for NATO/NATO member nations/CCEB.</para>
       </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Operational Capabilities</title>
      <para condition="ignore" />
      <?dbmerge node="T-7f14b843-3b55-44cd-81ef-f614a8e73d2d-X" obligation="mandatory"?>
    </sect1>


    <sect1>
      <title>User Applications</title>
      <para condition="ignore" />
      <?dbmerge node="T-cdd0fd6c-5d52-4d46-8d36-6f9c67475fcb-X" obligation="mandatory"?>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v2s1-ts">
      <title>Technical Services</title>
      <para>Technical services provide fundamental support to service based
        frameworks both in the form of information integration and communication
        services, and in the form of COI independent general service building
        blocks.</para>
      <para>COI services provide more specialized services in order to give
        the business more specific business benefits within a &#x201C;domain&#x201D; or &#x201C;area
        of interest&#x201D;.</para>
      <para>A COI is a collaborative group of users who have shared goals,
        interests, missions or business processes that result in information
        exchange and shared vocabulary.</para>
      <para>Information services include services that are either made
        available to all users by the infrastructure, or are mandatory to be
        provided by all users, by all providers or by all consumers. Information
        services also include specification of services of general interest that
        may be voluntarily exchanged by any parties on the network. Currently, information services are based only on Core Enterprise
        Services (CES), but may be extended in the future.</para>
      <para>Any service based framework, such as the Business Process
        Infrastructure Framework (BPIF), needs to provide a basic set of
        services that support and facilitate implementation and deployment of
        actual business services and processes. Such basic services are
        usually referred to as Core Enterprise Services.</para>
      <para>Here we will provide an overview of such CESs in a BPIF
        context in terms of the way such services are categorized. A few
        examples of CESs in each category is also provided, but a
        complete set of well defined core services cannot be provided as it to
        a large extent will depend on the actual implementation of the
        BPIF.</para>
      <para>Core services in a BPIF context are divided into two main
        categories according to their primary role in the implementation of
        business services and processes.</para>
       <!-- Service Area Table: Technical Services -->

      <sect2>
        <title>Community Of Interest (COI) Services</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge node="T-c4eea9ff-c404-4ae6-9f02-a12826657675-X" obligation="mandatory"?>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Core Services</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge node="T-3567de6b-7a0a-47c9-bc7f-18d7904c5df6-X" obligation="mandatory"?>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Communications Services</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge node="T-2c978bbc-f422-42e8-83e6-105a6bdb1e54-X" obligation="mandatory"?>
      </sect2>
       <sect2>
        <title>Cloud Services</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge node="user.cloud" obligation="mandatory"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Un-assigned standards</title>
      <para>The following standards have been declared mandatory standards for NATO common funded system. However, no information of how to map the standard to the C3 Taxonomy have been provided.</para>
      <?dbmerge node="user.undefined.taxonomynode" obligation="mandatory"?>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <index></index>

<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    Mandatory PROFILES
 *****************************************************************
-->


  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol2-annex-profiles.xml"
    xpointer="v2-baseline-profiles" />

</book>
