<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 2 -   A N N E X - A
*****************************************************************  
-->
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v2a-a">
  <title>Technologies</title>
  <para>This annex describes the technologies that are projected to be available today or in the
        near term period which will enable the transformation towards the NII.</para>
  <sect1>
    <title>Data Strategy</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Data Management Strategy</title>
      <para>Reference: TBD</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>JC3IEDM</title>
      <para>The JC3IEDM is a merger of both the C2IEDM (C2 IEDM, developed by the 
        Multitlateral Interoperability Programme (MIP)) and the Reference Data Model 
        of the NATO Corporate Data Model, which was developed by a predecessor of the
        DMSWG. The JC3IEDM is published under cover of STANAG 5525.</para>
      <para>The Data Management Authority  in NATO publishes the JC3IEDM and Directive
        and Guidance documents for Data Management in NATO. It will also register and 
        manage both the Standard Data Elements and the Information Exchange Requirements
        (IER) used in the development process of data assets.</para>
      <para>The main tool for Data Management in an NCW-environment is the NATO Metadata
        Registry and Repository. A version of the NMRR is currently posted under the
        DoD XML Registry.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>NATO Discovery Metadata Specification (NDMS)</title>
      <para>The NATO Discovery Metadata Specification defines discovery metadata elements 
        for resources posted to NATO shared spaces. „Discovery” is the ability to locate
        data assets through a consistent and flexible search method. The NDMS specifies
        a set of information fields that are to be used to describe any data or service 
        asset that is made known to NATO. It serves as a reference for developers,
        system architects, and engineers by identifying a minimum set of metadata
        elements in support of Discovery Services. Whilst discovery of data assets
        is the primary use of the NDMS it is also important to note that widespread
        use of the metadata elements will also improve documents record management in
        general. The NDMS will be employed consistently throughout the organization but
        it is not intended or necessary for it to displace other specifications that
        offer different semantics.</para>
      <para>To support data asset discovery, NATO has developed the NDMS as
        the common set of descriptive metadata elements that are to be
        associated with each data asset that is made visible to the enterprise
        discovery capability. Metadata is often defined as being "data that
        describes and defines other data". Data assets available in the
        enterprise must be described with metadata, using the elements defined
        in this document to permit discovery through the enterprise discovery
        capability. The NDMS defines a minimum set of elements that must be
        used to describe data assets made visible to the enterprise. Users and
        system agents acting on their behalf that search the enterprise will
        discover data assets that have been tagged and entered into catalogues
        or repositories that respond to search queries specified in terms of
        NDMS entries as depicted in the NDMS Usage Conceptual Diagram in
        <xref linkend="v2-ndms" />.</para>
      <figure id="v2-ndms" float="0">
        <title>NDMS Usage Conceptual Diagram</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/ndms.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The elements specified in the NDMS are designed to be platform,
        language, and implementation independent. This allows system
        developers to generate and retain discovery metadata using any
        implementation approaches, including using COTS products. As future
        enterprise discovery interface specifications are defined, programs
        should have the appropriate discovery metadata available for their
        data assets and will only be required to format this metadata in
        accordance with the interface specifications.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Extensible Markup Language (XML)</title>
      <para>The Extensible Markup Language (XML) is a simple, very flexible 
	    text format, much like HTML, used to structure, store and to send information.
	    XML was designed to describe data and to focus on what data is. XML is 
	    also playing an increasingly important role in the exchange of a wide 
	    variety of data on the Web and elsewhere.</para>
      <para>Role of XML in the Web Services model is lies within communication.
	    When one application talks to another to perform a web service, the application 
	    doing the talking must package the message it is sending in a format that 
	    is understandable by the listening application.  XML is the format of 
	    the message content in this communication process.</para>
      <para>The Extensible Markup Language tags provide information about a 
	    document's components.  The Uniform Resource Identifiers contained in 
	    the XML tags expand the concept of Uniform Resource Locators (URLs) 
	    by adding IDs for objects, concepts and values that are not dependent on location.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Information Modelling</title>
    <para>The ability to share information is a key factor for military
      success. As such, NATO and National Information Systems have to provide
      the means for information exchange in all mission types. The basic
      resource for all information systems is data, which, through the right
      interpretation, becomes information, and knowledge in turn. As NNEC is
      considered the core theme for C3 systems within NATO transformation, a
      fundamental requirement is to work in the most effective manner through
      semantic interoperability at the data level for NATO/national C3
      systems. The expanding missions of NATO involve consultation based on
      the sharing of information. Alliance members and partners are engaged in
      collective decision-making, with each nation retaining sovereignty and
      responsibility for its own decisions and taking action only on the basis
      of unanimity. In this environment, it is critically important that the
      Alliance members and partners have access to all shared information at
      the same time and that both the consultation process and the decisions
      taken are adequately documented. Information modelling and information
      management initiatives must be formalized throughout the NATO Enterprise
      to leverage the collective assets of NATO and national systems in
      support of information operations.</para>
    <para>Information management is the handling of information acquired by
      one or many disparate sources in a way that optimizes access by all who
      have a share in that information or a right to that information.
      Information modelling establishes a conceptual schema that defines how
      the managed elements in an information environment are represented as a
      common set of objects and relationships between them. This allows
      multiple parties to exchange management information about these managed
      elements. Additionally, it provides means to actively control and manage
      these elements. By using a common model of information, management
      software can be written once and work with many implementations of the
      common model without complex and costly conversion operations or loss of
      information.</para>
    <para>Appropriate Information management will enable:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Awareness -- Products identified by metadata (keywords) and
          cataloged with a common schema providing a simple yet integrated
          query search for the right information (product);</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Access -- with information tags to define privileges;
          and,</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Delivery -- Assured delivery of the information product over
          the right network and to the right location.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>This integrated approach to information modelling leverages the
      concepts of Net Centricity throughout all information resource providers
      and consumers in a coalition operation. Key components of this strategy
      include a dissemination capability, with associated management services,
      that directs end-to-end information flows throughout the NII in
      accordance with command policy. The NISP will contibute to the core technical
      model for systems designers to develop new platforms capable of the
      intensive compilation, cataloguing, caching, distribution, and retrieval
      of data necessary to provide the life cycle information management and
      necessary information sharing across NATO members.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Network Infrastructure</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Background</title>
      <para>With the NATO Network Enabled Capability Feasibility Study (NNEC
        FS) a new concept of ensuring service interoperability was introduced
        that complements and reuses the architectural views. This concept
        dubbed the Interoperability Performance Parameters (IPP), inspired by
        the US developed concept of Key Performance Parameters (KPP), forces
        the system architects and designers to specify a wider context of
        their capabilities sufficient to allow secure service interoperability
        in a Federation of Systems (FOS). The interfaces at which
        interoperability between separate infrastructure capabilities is to be
        managed are called the Service Inter Operability Points (SIOP).</para>
      <para>The principle is that an individual capability needs to work
        seamlessly with and within a FOS. The infrastructure services in a FOS
        and the international interoperability interfaces are described in the
        context of the total C4ISR systems architecture, often referred to as
        the Overarching Architecture (OAA).</para>
      <para>This section describes the NATO General-Purpose Segment
        Communication System (NGCS) Reference Architecture (RA). NGCS is part of the
        NII, representing the NATO owned capability. It provides the
        communication services and associated management and security
        services. Also it describes the timeframe for NGCS up to 2014, first
        implementations are in progress.</para>
      <para>The major change to classical network infrastructures is the
        coherence and interoperability of infrastructure capabilities brought
        by different coalition partners that needs to be achieved. In the NNEC
        FS the concept of a Maturity Model was introduced to describe,
        qualify and quantify the different levels of infrastructure
       capability. Increasing levels of maturity are characterised by
        enhanced sets of services, performances, and support, including
        advances in the associated Doctrine, Organisation, Training,
        Materials, Personnel, Leadership, Facilities (DOTMLPF)
        spectrum.</para>
      <para>Interoperability of separate infrastructure capabilities is
        managed by the earlier mentioned concept of IPP. The IPP allows a more
        comprehensive description and specification of those parameters that
        are essential for providing scalable end-to-end services over combined
        infrastructure capabilities.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>NGCS 2007 Target Architecture</title>
      <para>A reference model of the baseline network infrastructure for
        NGCS RA is depicted in <xref linkend="v2-ngcs-2007" />. This architecture
        is described in the NGCS RA ed1. At the time of writing the NSIE and
        the NATO IP Cryptographic Equipment / Secure Access Router(NICE/SAR) had
	not been fielded, but the implementation projects were in progress. The
	Bandwidth Manager Function (BMF) had been fielded.</para>
      <figure id="v2-ngcs-2007" float="0">
        <title>NGCS Digital User-Network Access Reference
          Configuration</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/ngcs-2007.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Communications &amp; Networking</title>
      <sect3>
        <title>Internet Protocol Version 4 (IPv4)</title>
        <para>Internet Protocol Version 4 (IPv4) is currently the dominant network
	    layer protocol used in the communication between networked devices.
	    IPv4 is a data-oriented protocol to be used on a packet switched inter-network 
	    (e.g., Ethernet). It is a best effort protocol in that it doesn't guarantee delivery.
	    It doesn't make any guarantees on the correctness of the data; it may 
	    result in duplicated packets and/or packets out-of-order. All of these 
	    things are addressed by an upper layer protocol (e.g. UDP).</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Construction of a robust IP-network infrastructure</title>
      <para>Operational relevant service availability should be one of the
        main design criteria and operational evaluation criteria for the NGCS.
        Despite the migration of users onto a single network and the
        introduction of significant additional complexity, e.g. QoS, the
        service availability has to be improved. Service availability and
        performance are exponents of infrastructure, organization, human
        aspects and others. The assessment of operational service readiness
        and performance is a structural activity required in the NGCS product
        life-cycle management. It should give input to transformational
        processes and for the development of Target Architectures (TA) that
        underpin infrastructure investment projects.</para>
      <sect3>
        <title>NGCS Overview</title>
        <para>The NATO General Purpose Communications System (NGCS) has a
          Circuit Switched Component (CSC) and a Packet Transport Component
          (PTC). The services offered are presented at the NGCS User Network
          Interface (NUNI). The NGCS user-network access domain incorporates
          functions for user access of circuit switched functions and packet
          transport functions. The circuit switched component provides
          on-demand switched access and also access to semi-permanent
          circuits. Both can be provided either in secure or non-secure modes.
          The packet transport component provides for both secure and
          non-secure IP access services.</para>
        <para>A secure service offered by the network at the NUNI provides
          for interconnection within a single security domain. If
          telecommunication services are required for a second security
          domain, this is implemented by installation of another cryptographic
          device - e.g. NATO Secure ISDN Equipment (NSIE) offering bulk
          encryption or NATO IP Cryptographic Equipment (NICE) (with the
          associated RED networking functions). In order to provide greater
          throughput, more than one instance of this might exist for a single
          security domain.</para>
        <para>In mid-term, a complete migration to a fully IP based network
          is planned for the NGCS.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Definition and implementation of a QoS architecture</title>
        <para>In the public standardization bodies, e.g. IETF, ITU, ETSI,
          ANSI, many initiatives are ongoing regarding the specification of a
          global QoS architecture in support of network convergence. Likewise
          many government organizations are doing the same.</para>
        <para>The operation and control of QoS enabled IP-services requires
          many new Operation and Support Systems as well as a thorough
          reassessment of the management organization.</para>
        <para>The complexity and the novelty of IP QoS warrant a
          step-by-step introduction. The entities affected by the introduction
          are:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The end-user;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The applications;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The infrastructure;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The OSS/BSS;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The policies;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The third party providers, e.g. SP, NDN;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The introduction should follow the developments in the
          commercial sector, and each successive introduction step in NATO
          should be done when the technology is stable and mature.
          Nevertheless NATO may want to implement additional functionality
          like additional CoS to implement MLPP, but this always be based on
          an underlying commercial standard based QoS architecture. Eventually
          the QoS architecture must take account of the requirements in
          military tactical radio networks and future QoS enabled MANETs. It
          is envisaged however that commercial standards for wireless MANETs
          will be developed among others by the ZigBee Alliance</para>
        <para>The model of spiral development should be applied. Each step
          is first tested in the laboratory (applications, infrastructure and
          OSS/BSS), evaluated against user requirements, operational issues,
          architectural principles, before it is gradually rolled out in the
          operational network.</para>
        <para>Business cases for network convergence are becoming
          increasingly viable. As more and more services are uniquely
          available on IP and standardization for IP based service support is
          becoming mature, it becomes more cost effective to migrate an
          existing infrastructure based on TDM and IP bearers to a single
          IP-bearer service system. However, network convergence does not come
          for free. Following items and activities are required:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specification of a comprehensive set of Classes of Service
              (CoS) for the ultimate network, which can be initially collapsed
              to a basic set and further expanded with each implementation
              step.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Definition of application mapping to telecommunications
              services (the CoS).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Specification of CoS handling in the network</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>NATO policy with the objective to have uniform QoS
              handling in the multinational network.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Supporting management and control systems (NGOSS
              compliant) that need to be integrated in the total SLM
              complex.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Proof of concept testing.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>The migration of applications onto an IP-bearer</title>
        <para>All the applications that are often traditionally carried on
          the CSC, i.e. telephony, switched VTC, leased line (for real-time
          data, for bandwidth pipe) need to be adapted so that they can also
          perform on an IP-bearer. Most of the applications require an QoS
          enabled IP infrastructure. In addition the connection oriented
          application services require call signalling, DNS, directory (for
          the gatekeeper) and resource reservation functionality. This
          infrastructure should be provided as a common core functionality for
          all application services requiring it. Target architectures for VoIP
          (SVoIP and VoSIP) and VTCoIP therefore need to be coordinated. For
          interoperability purposes NATO needs to standardize the signalling
          at the respective Service Interoperability Points.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Transition to IPv6</title>
        <para>IPv6 is an enabler for establishing coalition wide
          connectivity in a network enabled NII. The transition strategy of
          the NATO CIS to IPv6 is described in [TN1088] <footnote><para>Derived from Technical Note 1088: NATO IPv6 Transition
              Plan, Preliminary Version, NC3A, June 2006</para></footnote>from which the top-level roadmap is repeated here in
          <xref linkend="v2-roadmaptoIPv6" />.</para>
        <figure id="v2-roadmaptoIPv6" float="0">
          <title>Roadmap to IPv6</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../figures/roadmaptoIPv6.svg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</appendix>
