<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<book lang="en">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles</title>
    <subtitle>Near Term</subtitle>
    <corpauthor>C3 CCSC NATO Open Systems Working Group</corpauthor>
    <productname class="trade">Allied Data Publication 34</productname>
    <biblioid class="pubnumber">ADatP-34</biblioid>
    <volumenum>2</volumenum>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>4.16</revnumber>
        <date>22 December 2010</date>
        <revremark></revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <productnumber>$Id$</productnumber>
  </bookinfo>
  <!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 1
 ***************************************************************** 
-->
  <chapter id="v2c-int">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>This document is a draft under development by the NATO Open Systems
    Working Group (NOSWG) under the authority the NATO Consultation, Command and
    Control Board (NC3B). In due course it is expected to be noted by the NATO C3
    Board making the Volume 2 standards and profiles mandatory for use in NATO
    common funded systems, and to be made available to the general public as a
    replacement for ADatP-34(D).</para>
    <para>Volume 2 of the NISP focuses on interoperability standards and prfoiles
    in the near-term or a timeframe of 0 to 2 years into the future.
    This is the short-term step describing the state-of-the-art of NATO
    systems today and the framework for new systems actually under procurement
    or specification. For new systems, it describes the initial step towards
    the NII.</para>
    <para>The Combined Communications Electronics Board (CCEB) nations
    will use NISP Volume 2 <xref linkend="v2c-std" />,
    <xref linkend="v2s1-omat" />, <xref linkend="v2s1-uis" />,
    <xref linkend="v2s1-ts" />, <xref linkend="v2s1-ias" /> and
    <xref linkend="v2s1-esm" /> tables to publish the interoperability standards
    for the CCEB under the provisions of the NATO-CCEB List of Understandings
    (LoU) detailed in Volume 1 Annex A. For the CCEB Chapter 4 is only applicable
    to the CCEB Nations when taking part in NATO lead operations.</para>
    <sect1>
      <title>Scope</title>
      <para>The scope of this volume will include:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Identifying the standards, profiles and
          technologies that are relevant to a service oriented environment,
	  as described in the NATO NNEC Technical Services Strategy,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Describing the near term standards, profiles, and technologies
          to support the initial step towards NNEC Technical Services,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Planning the transition of legacy systems.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 2
 ***************************************************************** 
-->
  <chapter id="v2c-refmod">
    <title>Reference Models: Transition from Platform Centric to Service
    Oriented Models</title>
    <para>Information technology is undergoing a fundamental shift from
    platform-oriented computing to network-oriented computing. Platform-oriented
    computing emerged with the widespread proliferation of personal computers
    and the global business environment. These factors and related
    technologies have created the conditions for the emergence of
    network-oriented computing. This shift from platform to network is what
    enables the more flexible and more dynamic network-oriented operation. The
    shift from viewing partners as independent to viewing partners as part of
    a continuously adapting ecosystem fosters a rich information sharing
    environment.</para>
    <para>This shift is most obvious in the explosive growth of the Internet,
    intranets, and extranets. Internet users no doubt will recognize
    transmission control protocol/internet protocol (TCP/IP), hypertext
    transfer protocol (HTTP), hypertext markup language (HTML), Web browsers,
    search engines, and Java<footnote><para>Registered Trademark of SUN Microsystems,
    INC.</para></footnote> Computing. These technologies, combined with
    high-volume, high-speed data access (enabled by the low-cost laser) and
    technologies for high-speed data networking (hubs and routers) have led to
    the emergence of network-oriented computing. Information &#x201C;content&#x201D; now can
    be created, distributed, and easily exploited across the extremely
    heterogeneous global computing environment. The &#x201C;power&#x201D; or &#x201C;payoff&#x201D; of
    network-enabled computing comes from information-intensive interactions
    between very large numbers of heterogeneous computational nodes in the
    network, where the network becomes the dynamic information grid
    established by interconnecting partners participating in a collaborative,
    coalition environment. At the structural level, network-enabled warfare
    requires an operational architecture to enable the common processes to be
    shared by all parties.</para>
    <para>One of the major drivers for supporting net-enabled operations is
    Service-Oriented Architectures (SOA). SOA is enterprise architecture that
    leverages heterogeneity, and thus inherently platform-neutral. It is
    focused on the composition of Services into flexible processes and is more
    concerned with the Service interface and above (including composition
    metadata, security policy, and dynamic binding information), more so than
    what sits beneath the abstraction of the Service interface. SOA requires a
    different kind of platform, because runtime execution has different
    meanings within SOA. SOA enables business users and business process
    architects to compose Services into processes, and then manage and evolve
    those processes, in a declarative fashion. Runtime execution of such
    processes is therefore a metadata-centric operation of a different kind of
    platform -- a Service-oriented composite application platform.</para>
    <para>Network-enabled operations are characterized by new concepts of
    speed of command and self-synchronization.</para>
    <para>The most important SOA within an enterprise is the one that links
    all its systems. Existing platforms can be wrapped or extended in order to
    participate in a wider SOA environment. NATO use of the NISP will provide
    a template for new systems development, as well as assist in defining the
    path for existing systems to migrate towards net-enabled
    operations.</para>
  </chapter>
  <!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 3
 ***************************************************************** 
-->
  <chapter id="v2c-std">
    <title>Standards</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <para>This purpose of this chapter is to specify the NISP near term standards.
        The document organises these standards into five service areas and included
	service categories:</para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Operational Mission/Activities/Tasks</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>User Information Services</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Technical Services</para>
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>COI Services</para>
              <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                  <para>Generic COI Services</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Specific COI Services</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Information Integration</para>
              <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                  <para>Core Enterprise Services</para>
                  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Discovery</para>
                      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Service Discovery Services</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Information Discovery Services</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Repository</para>
                      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Metadata Registry Services</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Enterprise Directory Services</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Mediation</para>
                      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Composition Services</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Translation Services</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Interaction</para>
                      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Messaging Services</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Publish/Subscribe Services</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Transaction Services</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Collaboration Services</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Infrastructure</para>
                      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Application Services</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                          <para>Storage Services</para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Communication Services</para>
              <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                <listitem>
                  <para>Network and Transport Services</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Data Link and Connection Services</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Information Assurance</para>
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>SMI Services</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Confidentiality</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Encryption</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Integrity</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Authentication</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Detection</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Transsec</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Service Management and Control</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>This section describes the role and requirements of each service
      area, and presents all associated standards in tabular form. The tables
      refine each service area into one or more service categories, with
      service components mapping to one or more mandatory, emerging near term
      or fading categories (see NISP vol. 1). A remarks column provides optional
      supplementary information on each standard plus CCEB-specific information.
      The NISP Rationale Document (RD) provides further explanation on why service
      and standards categories have been selected.</para>
      <sect2 id="v2s2-rel">
        <title>Releasability Statement</title>
        <para>In principle, NISP includes only standards/STANAGs/documents, which are
          generally available for NATO/Nato member nations/CCEB.</para>
        <para>However, a subset of documents are only available for those nations/
          organisations, who are joining a specific mission (e.g. ISAF) or are member
          of a special working group (I-ICWG). The mebership in these activities is
          outside the scope of NISP.</para>
       </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v2s1-omat">
      <title>Operational Mission/Activities/Tasks</title>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Operational Mission/Activities/Tasks -->
      <para>In the military organisations operational missions are generally planned
          activities that can be viewed in terms of distinct chronological stages of
          completion which in turn consist of shorter tasks. Operational missions do
	  not involve combat (see combat mission, and can vary in duration from a few 
	  hours to several weeks, though usually in peacetime are limited to the working 
	  week.</para>
      <para>This set of services is described in mission related terms to provide
	  consistency with the set of possible NATO missions identified through the
	  NATO Defense Planning process.  Each Operational Service is dependent on
	  one or more Information Services.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge area="omat"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v2s1-uis">
      <title>User Information Services</title>
      <!-- Service Area Table: User Information Services -->
      <para>These services are hierarchically organised and focused on information:
	  content, management, processes, and standards.  Each Information Service
	  is enabled by one or more NNEC Services.</para>
      <para>These NNEC services represent the technology required to enable the
	  Information Services to make information available to user communities of
	  interest.  At the lowest level, NNEC Services are composed of components,
	  processes, management.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge area="uis"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v2s1-ts">
      <title>Technical Services</title>
      <para>Technical services provide fundamental support to service based
        frameworks both in the form of information integration and communication
        services, and in the form of COI independent general service building
        blocks.</para>
      <para>COI services provide more specialized services in order to give
        the business more specific business benefits within a &#x201C;domain&#x201D; or &#x201C;area
        of interest&#x201D;.</para>
      <para>A COI is a collaborative group of users who have shared goals,
        interests, missions or business processes that result in information
        exchange and shared vocabulary.</para>
      <para>Information services include services that are either made
        available to all users by the infrastructure, or are mandatory to be
        provided by all users, by all providers or by all consumers. Information
        services also include specification of services of general interest that
        may be voluntarily exchanged by any parties on the network.</para>
      <para>Actually information services are based only on core enterprise
        services (CES), but may be extended in the future.</para>
      <para>Any service based framework, such as the Business Process
        Infrastructure Framework (BPIF), needs to provide a basic set of
        services that support and facilitate implementation and deployment of
        actual business services and processes. Such basic services are
        usually referred to as Core Enterpise Services.</para>
      <para>Here we will provide an overview of such CESs in a BPIF
        context in terms of the way such services are categorized. A few
        examples of CESs in each category is also provided, but a
        complete set of well defined core services cannot be provided as it to
        a large extent will depend on the actual implementation of the
        BPIF.</para>
      <para>Core services in a BPIF context are divided into two main
        categories according to their primary role in the implementation of
        business services and processes.</para>
      <sect2>
        <title>Basic Infrastructure Services</title>
        <para>The first main category of core services, here referred to as
            Basic Infrastructure Services (BIS), are used to support the
            infrastructure (BPIF) that support deployment, operation and
            management of business processes. BIS is further divided into three
            subcategories according to three of the main aspects of a
            BPIF.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Service Selection BIS are concerned with the basic
                mechanisms for discovery and visibility of services. Typically
                this encompasses basic service directories with support for
                syntactic description and lookup of services.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Management and operation BIS are concerned with various
                types of management and operation of services and
                infrastructure. There are at least four subcategories.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>BIS handling policies, including required security
                    level, conditions for service delivery, availability,
                    quality of service undertakings etc.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Security BIS include basic functions for managing
                    information security, and a typical example is a service
                    that keeps track of role and person oriented authorization,
                    distribution of keys, handling of certificates etc.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Service Management BIS handle life cycle management of
                    other services, including for example monitoring and
                    configuration.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Resource Management BIS are used to manage
                    infrastructure resources and will be highly dependent on
                    infrastructure implementation. A typical example is resource
                    management in a Grid.</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Network Management BIS are concerned with networking
                    and communication aspects of the infrastructure, and involve
                    for example router configuration.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Process Composition BIS are concerned with support for
                business processes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Business Service Enablers</title>
        <para>The second of the main core service categories is Business
          Service Enablers (BSE). While BIS services are concerned with the
          BPIF infrastructure per se, they are not used a foundation for
          implementation of business services. This is instead the role of
          BSE, which provide basic functionality that is shared by many
          business services independently of Community of Interest
          (COI).</para>
        <para>BSE are divided into three main subcategories based on the
          types of functionality they offer.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Collaboration BSE support basic exchange of data between
              services. Examples include message passing (uni- and multicast,
              email, etc.), distributed file sharing, publication (web pages
              etc.), and data format conversion.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Synchronization BSE support synchronization of service and
              process interaction, and includes for example time services, and
              event notification.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Common Information Services (CIS) is the third and last
              subcategory of BSE. CIS provide COI-independent support for
              access to general information like maps, glossaries, standards,
              and document registries.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Note: Not all functions in this category are necessarily
          service oriented in a SOA sense. They are nevertheless important for
          a network-oriented capability.</para>
        <para>The third area of the technical services is the communication
          services. These services provide a transparent, seamless information
          exchange capability to allow a communication between the various
          information entities above.</para>
      </sect2>
      <!-- Service Area Table: COI Services -->
      <sect2>
        <title>List of COI Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge subarea="ts-coi"?>
      </sect2>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Information Integration Services -->
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Information Integration Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge subarea="ts-integ"?>
      </sect2>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Communications Services -->
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Communications Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge subarea="ts-com"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v2s1-ias">
      <title>Information Assurance</title>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Information Assurance -->
      <sect2>
        <title>List of Standards</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge area="ias"?>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v2s1-esm">
      <title>Service Management and Control</title>
      <!-- Service Area Table: Service Management and Control -->
      <para condition="ignore" />
      <?dbmerge area="esm"?>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
<!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 4
 ***************************************************************** 
-->
  <chapter id="v2c-prf">
    <title>Profiles</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>Introduction</title>
	<para>The purpose of this chapter is to specify the NISP near term profiles.
          The document organises these profiles under the following considerations:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
	    <para>Profiles derived from NATO Reference Architectures</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Profiles derived from NATO Operations</para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>Profiles derived from NATO member nations</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>The above list will be enhanced dynamically, based on updated profile
	  defintions being developed in relevant NATO bodies.</para>
	<para>The standards being used in these profiles may differ in version from
	  those being liested in chapter 3. This is based on the time for the development
	  of these standards and may be modified in newer versions of these profiles.
	</para>
	<para>Standards, which are listed in NISP Vol. 2 and are beloging to one or
	  more profiles, as listed in chap. 4 of this document or in NISP Vol. 4,
	  are marked in the Remarks column as follows:</para>
	<para>Used in Profile(s): standard1 (, standard2, ...)</para>
	<para>Standards, which are not included by a valid RFCP in NISP,  Vol.2, but
	  are only included in a profile, are marked in the Remarks column in
	  <emphasis>italics</emphasis> as follows:</para>
	<para>Used in Profile(s):<emphasis>standard1 (, standard2, ...)</emphasis></para>
	<sect2>
	  <title>Profiles derived from NATO Reference Architectures</title>
	  <para>This chapter contains profiles from various NATO Reference Architectures
	    or equivalent documents. Currently, the following documents are recognised:
	  </para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>NATO NII Communications Reference Architecture, consisting of:</para>
	      <itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>
		  <para>SIOP1</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>SIOP2</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>SIOP5</para>
		</listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Core Enterprise Services Implementation Specifications - Spiral 1</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	  <title>Profiles derived from NATO Operations</title>
	  <para>This chapter contains profiles from current or future planned NATO
	    operations. Currently, the following operations are recognised:
	  </para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Afghan Mission Network (AMN)</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
	  <title>Profiles derived from NATO member nations</title>
	  <para>This chapter contains profiles from member nations being proposed
	    for interoperability purposes in NATO and between NATO nations:
	  </para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>Tactical Enterprise Service Bus (tactESB)</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</sect2>
      </sect1>
      <sect1>
        <title>Profile Specifications</title>
	  <para>This section contains the details of all profiles, being listed in
	    section 4.1:</para>
	  <sect2>
	    <title>SIOP1</title>
	    <!-- SIOP1: Interface between Protected Core Segments -->
            <para condition="ignore" />
            <para>Text TBD</para>
            <?dbmerge area="siop1"?>
	  </sect2>
	  <sect2>
	    <title>SIOP2</title>
	    <!-- SIOP2: Interface between a Protected Core Segment and a CC -->
            <para condition="ignore" />
            <para>Text TBD</para>
            <?dbmerge area="siop2"?>
	  </sect2>
	  <sect2>
	    <title>SIOP5</title>
	    <!-- SIOP5: Interface between  -->
            <para condition="ignore" />
            <para>Text TBD</para>
            <?dbmerge area="siop5"?>
	  </sect2>
	  <sect2>
	    <title>NCES - Spiral 1</title>
	    <!-- NCES: Core Services within NATO -->
            <para condition="ignore" />
            <para>This document seeks to outline the profiles and standards that projects
              in NATO and in the nations should aim to use, with the aim of ensuring
              future compatibility and longevity. In this specification we focus on
              the use of stable versions of the standards and specifications, which
              are supported by industrial and open source implementations. This will
              give the widest range of interoperability scenarios in the near to medium
              term, as well as the greatest level of functionality.</para>
            <para>This specification is based on the NC3A recommendation [NC3A RD-2814].
              Much of the text from that document has been re-used in this specification
              with permission from the authors.</para>
            <para>Details of this profile are contained in: NATO CES Implementation Specification Spiral 1 v1.0.doc</para>
            <?dbmerge area="nces"?>
	  </sect2>
	  <sect2>
	    <title>AMN - Profile</title>
	    <!-- Service Profile for the Afghan Mission Network -->
            <para condition="ignore" />
            <para>The purpose of this specification is to define an Interoperability
              Standars Profile to support the Afghanistan Mission Network (AMN) and
              transition from today's legacy systems to NNEC be defining a basic 
              level of system interoperability in order to enhance the exchange of
              information within and across the AMN. To support the goal of widespread
              interoperability the AMN Interoperability Profile defines a minimum profile
              of services and standards for Technical Interfaces , Data Interchange 
              Standards  and Application Profile Standards that are sufficient to provide
              a useful level of interoperability.</para>
            <para>Details of this profile are contained in: 2010-11-17_NUI_NISP_AMN_Profile.docx</para>
            <?dbmerge area="amn"?>
	  </sect2>
	  <sect2>
	    <title>tactESB - Profile</title>
	    <!-- Service Profile for a tactical Eterprise Service Bus -->
            <para condition="ignore" />
            <para>The aim of this specification is to describe a profile for a tactical
              Enterprise Service Bus (tact ESB) to be used in a coalition, highly mobile
              and disturbed environment. The profile focuses specifically on requirements
              from military usage and goes beyond the ESB specification, available in 
              civil implementations/products.</para>
            <para>The profile is a generic specification; following the principle 
              construction elements, it allows for na-tional implementations a derivation
              from the proposed one, not losing the interoperability aspects.</para>
            <para>Details of this profile are contained in: IT-AmtBw_A5_RuDi-High_Level_Concept_400.pdf (DEU)</para> 
            <?dbmerge area="amn"?>
	  </sect2>
      </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="vol2-annexA.xml" />
  <index></index>
</book>
