<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<book lang="en">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles</title>
	<titleabbrev>NISP</titleabbrev>
    <subtitle>Agreed Interoperability Standards and Profiles</subtitle>
    <corpauthor>C3B Interoperability Profiles Capability Team</corpauthor>
    <productname class="trade">Allied Data Publication</productname>
    <biblioid class="pubnumber">ADatP-34</biblioid>
    <volumenum>2</volumenum>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>14.2</revnumber>
        <date>6 May 2022</date>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <subjectset><subject><subjectterm>DO NOT REMOVE</subjectterm></subject></subjectset>
  </bookinfo>
  <!--
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 1
 *****************************************************************
-->
  <chapter id="v2c-int">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Volume 2 of the NISP focuses on agreed interoperability standards and profiles.</para>
<para>The NISP references Standards from different standardization bodies<footnote><para>In case of conflict between any recommended non-NATO standard and relevant NATO standard, the definition of the latter prevails.</para></footnote>. In the case of a ratified STANAG, NATO Standardization procedures apply. The NISP only references these STANAG’s without displaying the country-specific reservations.
  The country-specific reservations can be found in the NATO Standardization Office&apos;s NATO Standardization Document Database (NSDD).</para>
    <para>The Combined Communications Electronics Board (CCEB) nations will use NISP Volume 2 <xref linkend="v2c-std" /> and <xref linkend="v2s1-ts" />
    tables to publish the interoperability standards for the CCEB under the provisions of the NATO-CCEB List of Understandings
    (LoU)<footnote><para>References:NATO Letter AC/322(SC/5)L/144 of 18 October 2000, CCEB Letter D/CCEB/WS/1/16 of 9 November 2000, NATO Letter AC/322(SC/5)L/157 of 13 February 2001</para></footnote>.</para>
    <sect1>
      <title>Scope</title>
      <para>The scope of this volume includes:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Identifying the standards and
          technologies that are relevant to a service oriented environment,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Describing the standards and technologies
          to support federation.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <!--
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 2
 ****************************************************************
-->
  <chapter id="v2c-refmod">
    <title>Reference Models: Transition from Platform Centric to Service
    Oriented Models</title>
    <para>Information technology has undergone a fundamental shift from
    platform-oriented computing to service-oriented computing. Platform-oriented
    computing emerged with the widespread proliferation of personal computers
    and the global business environment. These factors and related
    technologies have created the conditions for the emergence of
    network-oriented computing. This shift from platform to network is what
    enables the more flexible and more dynamic network-oriented operation. The
    shift from viewing NATO and partner Nations as independent to viewing them as part of
    a continuously adapting network ecosystem fosters a rich information sharing
    environment.</para>
    <para>This shift is most obvious in the explosive growth of the Internet,
    intranets, and extranets. Internet users no doubt will recognize
    transmission control protocol/internet protocol (TCP/IP), hypertext
    transfer protocol (HTTP), hypertext markup language (HTML), Web browsers,
    search engines, and Java<footnote><para>Registered Trademark of ORACLE and/or its affiliates. Other names
    may be the trademarks of their respective owners.</para></footnote> Computing. These technologies, combined with
    high-volume, high-speed data access (enabled by the low-cost laser) and
    technologies for high-speed data networking (switches and routers) have led to
    the emergence of network-oriented computing. Information &#x201C;content&#x201D; now can
    be created, distributed, and easily exploited across the extremely
    heterogeneous global computing environment. The &#x201C;power&#x201D; or &#x201C;payoff&#x201D; of
    network-oriented computing comes from information-intensive interactions
    between very large numbers of heterogeneous computational nodes in the
    network, where the network becomes the dynamic information grid
    established by interconnecting participants in a collaborative,
    coalition environment. At the structural level, network-enabled warfare
    requires an operational architecture to enable common processes to be
    shared.</para>
    <para>One of the major drivers for supporting net-enabled operations is
    Service-Oriented Architectures (SOA). SOA is an architectural style that
    leverages heterogeneity, focuses on interfaces between services and as such this approach is inherently platform-neutral. It is
    focused on the composition of Services into flexible processes and is more
    concerned with the Service interface and above (including composition
    metadata, security policy, and dynamic binding information), more so than
    what sits beneath the abstraction of the Service interface. SOA requires a
    different kind of platform, because runtime execution has different
    meanings within SOA. SOA enables users and process
    architects to compose Services into processes, and then manage and evolve
    those processes, in a declarative fashion. Runtime execution of such
    processes is therefore a metadata-centric operation of a different kind of
    platform -- a Service-oriented composite application platform.</para>
    <para>Service-enabled operations are characterized by new concepts of
    speed of command and self-synchronization.</para>
    <para>The most important SOA within an enterprise is the one that links
    all its systems. Existing platforms can be wrapped or extended in order to
    participate in a wider SOA environment. NATO use of the NISP will provide
    a template for new systems development, as well as assist in defining the
    path for existing systems to migrate towards net-enabled
    operations.</para>
  </chapter>
  <!--
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 3
 *****************************************************************
-->
  <chapter id="v2c-std">
    <title>Standards</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <para>The purpose of this chapter is to specify the agreed NISP standards. The document organizes these standards, following  baseline 3.1 of NATO's C3 Taxonomy, as endorsed by the NATO C3 Board per AC/322-D(2019)0034-AS1(INV) on “C3 Taxonomy Baseline 3.1” dated 26 August 2019. A graphical representation of this taxonomy is included in volume 1.</para>
      <para>For some standards it was not clear yet which service identified in the C3 Taxonomy should be used. Therefore, as an interim solution, the taxonomy was extended with e.g. user-defined &#x201C;Cloud Services&#x201D;. In a separate section, all standards are listed for which could not yet be defined how they should be linked to the C3 Taxonomy.</para>
      <para>The standards are presented in tabular form. Each table represent a subtree from the C3 taxonomy and each table line (marked in bold and spanning all columns in the table) represents a taxonomy node from the subtree.  Under each taxonomy node title, all standards which are mapped to the node are listed with the following attributes: title of the standard; where possible, a link to the standard; publication number of the standard<footnote><para>If the standard is a NATO standard and has a cover document, the publication number is followed by a slash and the publication number of the cover document.</para></footnote>; a list of all the capability profiles where the standard is used; and finally the "responsible party" which is the domain expert that advises NATO about the standard. In general, a taxonomy node is only listed if at least one standard is assigned to this taxonomy node.</para>
      <para>When STANAG X Ed Y is in ratification process, this is indicated by STANAG (RD) X Ed Y, and when it is a study draft, this is indicated by STANAG (Study) X Ed Y.</para>
      <sect2 id="v2s2-rel">
        <title>Releasability Statement</title>
        <para>In principle, NISP only contains or references standards or related documents, which are
          generally available for NATO/NATO member nations/CCEB.</para>
       </sect2>
    </sect1>

<!-- Ignore this section, since no standards are selected for this subtree
    <sect1>
      <title>Operational Capabilities</title>
      <para condition="ignore" />
      <?dbmerge node="T-7f14b843-3b55-44cd-81ef-f614a8e73d2d-X" lifecycle="current"?>
    </sect1>
-->

    <sect1>
      <title>User Applications</title>
      <para condition="ignore" />
      <?dbmerge node="T-cdd0fd6c-5d52-4d46-8d36-6f9c67475fcb-X" lifecycle="current"?>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v2s1-ts">
      <title>Technical Services</title>
      <para>The &#x201C;Technical Services&#x201D; include those services required to enable &#x201C;User Applications&#x201D;.
        They are part of the &#x201C;Back-End Capabilities&#x201D; while &#x201C;User Applications&#x201D; are part of &#x201C;User-Facing Capabilities&#x201D;.</para>
      <para>According to the C3 Taxonomy, they consist of &#x201C;Community Of Interest (COI) Services&#x201D;, &#x201C;Core Services&#x201D; and &#x201C;Communications Services&#x201D;.
        The complete collection of Technical Services is sometimes referred to as the &#x201C;Technical Services Framework" (TSF) or &#x201C;NNEC Services Framework" (NSF).</para>
      <para>In addition to the &#x201C;Technical Services&#x201D; identified in the C3 Taxonomy, a taxonomy layer &#x201C;Cloud Computing&#x201D; has been added.
        This enables a more useful categorization of cloud-based standards (currently only included as candidate standards).</para>
      <!-- Service Table: Technical Services -->
      <sect2>
        <title>Community Of Interest (COI) Services</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge node="T-c4eea9ff-c404-4ae6-9f02-a12826657675-X" lifecycle="current"?>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Core Services</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge node="T-3567de6b-7a0a-47c9-bc7f-18d7904c5df6-X" lifecycle="current"?>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Communications Services</title>
        <para condition="ignore" />
        <?dbmerge node="T-2c978bbc-f422-42e8-83e6-105a6bdb1e54-X" lifecycle="current"?>
      </sect2>

    </sect1>

  </chapter>
  <chapter id="v2-baseline-profiles">
<title>Agreed Profiles</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles include the set of Agreed Profiles listed below.
	<table>
        <title>Agreed Profiles</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" />
          <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Service Area</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">Title</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry namest="col1" nameend="col2">
                <emphasis role="bold">Abstract</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">URI</emphasis>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <emphasis role="bold">ID</emphasis>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Federated Mission Networking</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">FMN Spiral 3 Profile</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
<para>This document defines the Standards Profile for Federated Mission Networking (FMN) Spiral 3. The FMN Standards Profiles provides a suite of interoperability standards and other standardized profiles for interoperability of selected community of interest services, core services and communications services in a federation of mission networks. It places the required interoperability requirements, standards and specifications in context for FMN Affiliates.</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/20181118_Final_FMN_Spiral_3_Standards_Profile_Bundle.pdf">FMN Spiral 3 Profile</ulink></entry>
              <entry>FMN3</entry>
            </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Federated Mission Networking</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">FMN Spiral 4 Profile</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
<para>Federated Mission Networking is founded on a service-oriented approach. The interoperability standards applicable to these services are identified and specified in line with the C3 Taxonomy. Similarly, the breakdown of the standards profiles more or less follows the taxonomy.</para></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/20210208_FMN_Spiral_4_Standards_Profile.pdf">FMN Spiral 4 Overview of Standards and Profiles</ulink></entry>
              <entry>FMN4</entry>
            </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Architecture</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Profile for the Architecture development</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This profile lists recommended standards for miscellaneous architecture releated subjects.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/architecture-profile.pdf">architecture-profile.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>ARCHITECTURE</entry>
            </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Archive</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Profile for the Long Term Preservation of NATO Digital Information of Permanent value</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>Outlines the file formats and package structures approved by the Archives Committee for the long-term preservation of NATO digital information of permanent value.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/NISP-V2-archive-profile.pdf">NISP-V2-archive-profile.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>ARCHIVE-ARCHIVE</entry>
            </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Security Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile Security Services</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This Service Interface Profile (SIP) describes the key elements that make up the NNEC Core Enterprise Services (CES) Security Services.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.01_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.01_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
             <entry>SIP-SEC</entry>
           </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">REST Security Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile For REST Security Services</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This specification provides the profile for securing representational state transfer (REST) web services (known as RESTful web services) that are deployed within the NNEC web service infrastructure. It specifies security requirements that need to be accounted for depending on the environment in which the services are being deployed, and the level of assurance required for protecting those services. This profile covers the required security protection profile for a Client to access protected resources on a Resource Server using REST.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.02_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.02_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-REST</entry>
            </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Security Token Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile For Security Token Services</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>The purpose of this Service Interface Profile (SIP) is to specify how the security token service component of the Core Enterprise Services (CES) Security Services may be called.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.03_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.03_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-TOKEN</entry>
            </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Policy Enforcement Points</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile For Policy Enforcement Points</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>The purpose of this Service Interface Profile (SIP), which should be read along with the Agency Directive 06.05.04.02.H 2, "Service Interface Profile for Security Services" [NCIA AD 06.05.04.02.H], is to specify how services may be called that are protected by the Core Enterprise Services (CES) Security Services.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.04_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.04_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-POLICY-ENFORCE</entry>
      	    </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Enterprise Directory Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile For Enterprise Directory Services</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>The purpose of this Service Interface Profile (SIP) is to specify the interface of the directory service itself.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.05_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.05_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-ENTR-DIR</entry>
	    </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Messaging</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile For Messaging</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This specification provides the interface control for simple object access protocol (SOAP) web services that are deployed within the NNEC web service infrastructure.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.06_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.06_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-MESG</entry>
	    </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">REST Messaging</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile For REST Messaging</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This specification provides the profile for securing representational state transfer (REST) web services (known as RESTful web services) that are deployed within the NNEC web service infrastructure. This covers only the call from a Web Service Consumer to a Web Service Provider using REST, and the response from the service provider. It includes how the message must be structured and the elements that must be contained within the call.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.07_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.07_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-REST-MSG</entry>
	          </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Publish-Subscribe Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile For Publish-Subscribe Services</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This document gives directives along with clarifications and amendments to the [OASIS WS-BaseNotification, 2006] and [OASIS WS-BrokeredNotification, 2006] specification on how to implement a notification broker/subscription manager to promote interoperability between the publish/subscribe engines and generic message subscribers. Some extensions to the protocol have
been introduced in order to meet NATO requirements.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.08_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.08_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-PUBSUB</entry>
	          </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Publish-Subscribe Notification Broker With Subscription Manager</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile For Publish-Subscribe Notification Broker With Subscription Manager</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This document is part of a Service Interface Profile (SIP) for Publish/Subscribe Core Enterprise Services (CES) and should be read together with the main document [NCIA AD 06.05.04.02.E]. It gives guidance on implementation of a WS-Notification compliant notification broker. It is REQUIRED that each notification broker implementation also includes the subscription manager functionality.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.09_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.09_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-PUBSUB-NOTIF-BROOKER</entry>
	          </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Publish-Subscribe Notification Consumer</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile For Publish-Subscribe Notification Consumer</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This document is part of a Service Interface Profile (SIP) for publish/subscribe Core Enterprise Services (CES) and should be read together with the main document "Service Interface Profile for Publish/Subscribe Services" [NCIA AD 06.05.04.02.E]. It gives guidance on implementation of a WS-Notification-compliant notification consumer.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.10_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.10_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-PUBSUB-NOTIF-CONSUMER</entry>
	          </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">A Notification Cache Service</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile For A Notification Cache Service</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This Service Interface Profile (SIP) describes the key eleme nts that make up the NNEC Core Enterprise Services (CES) Notification Cache service. It describes and profiles the operations which a Notification Cache service offers together with the associated message formats, and serves as a template and guideline for implementations.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.11_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.11_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-NOTIF-CACHE</entry>
      	    </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Basic Collaboration Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile For Basic Collaboration Services</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This Collaboration Service Interface Profile (SIP) is focused on instant messaging and is based on the extensible messaging and presence protocol (XMPP).</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.12_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.12_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-BCS</entry>
	          </row>
            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Core And Advanced Instant Messaging Collaboration Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile For Core And Advanced Instant Messaging Collaboration Services</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This document specifies the Service Interface Profile (SIP) for a number of instant messaging services that can be implemented and used by any XMPP entity (XMPP Client or XMPP Server) on the XMPP network.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.13_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.13_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-MESG-COL-SERV</entry>
            </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Geospatial Services – Map Rendering Service</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile For Geospatial Services – Map Rendering Service</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This document gives guidance on the implementation of a Map Rendering Service, being a special kind of a Geospatial Service.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/AI_TECH_2016.06.02.14_SIP.pdf">AI_TECH_2016.06.02.14_SIP.pdf</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-GEO-MRS</entry>
	          </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Recognized Air Picture Data Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile for Recognized Air Picture Data</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This Service Interface Profile provides detailed information, guidance, instructions, standards and criteria
              to define the minimum set of data elements that are required to be available for operational or technical
              reasons so that correctly formatted technical message can be generated to establish a Recognized Air Picture
              in a federated environment.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/20181118_Final_FMN_Spiral_3_Standards_Profile_Bundle.pdf">FMN Spiral 3 Profile including SIP for RAPD</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-RECOGNIZED-AIR-PICTURE-DATA</entry>
	          </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Service Management Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile for Service Management and Control</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This Service Interface Profile provides guidance and technical details to the procedures,
          supporting services, infrastructure and data attributes required to implement Service Management and Control
          (SMC) services in Mission Networks. As such, this document contributes to the establishment of
          capabilities in support of Federated Mission Networking (FMN) as an affordable, effective and efficient
          means to enable sharing of information in a coalition environment.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/20181118_Final_FMN_Spiral_3_Standards_Profile_Bundle.pdf">FMN Spiral 3 Profile including SIP for SMC</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-FOR-SMC</entry>
	          </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Transport Layer Security</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile for Transport Layer Security</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This Service Interface Profile (SIP) provides detailed information, guidance, instructions, standards and
          criteria to be used as a  for the usage of Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol to provide authentication,
          confidentiality and integrity services for protecting the communication between a consumer and a provider.
          This publication is a living document and will be periodically reviewed and updated to reflect technology developments,
          emerging best practices, evolving standards and new or deprecated cryptographic schemes
          and algorithms.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/20181118_Final_FMN_Spiral_3_Standards_Profile_Bundle.pdf">FMN Spiral 3 Profile including SIP for TLS</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-FOR-TLS</entry>
	          </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Web Applications</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Service Interface Profile for Web Applications</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This Service Interface Profile (SIP) provides detailed information, guidance, instructions, standards and
         criteria to be used for development, delivery and consumption of Web applications and dynamic Web sites.
         This publication is a living document and will be periodically reviewed and updated to reflect technology
         developments and emerging best practices.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/20181118_Final_FMN_Spiral_3_Standards_Profile_Bundle.pdf">FMN Spiral 3 Profile including SIP for Web Apps</ulink></entry>
              <entry>SIP-FOR-WEB-APPS</entry>
	          </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Cryptographic Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Cryptographic Artefact Binding Profiles</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>Profile the use of cryptographic protocols, which can be used to implement support for different cryptographic techniques and mechanisms, for generating cryptographic artefacts to be stored in a cryptographic binding.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
         <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/ADatP-4778.2_EDA_V1_E.pdf">ADat-P 4778.2 Ed A Ver 1:2020 - Profiles for Binding Metadata to a Data Object</ulink> - Chapter 2</entry>
              <entry>BINDING-CRYPTO-V2</entry>
	          </row>

      <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
      <row>
        <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Informal Messaging Services</emphasis></entry>
        <entry align="left" colname="col2">Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP) Binding Profile</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
      <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
      <para>This profile specifies the mechanism for binding metadata to Internet Email (both formal and informal) including MIME entities.</para>
      </entry>
      </row>
      <row>
        <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/ADatP-4778.2_EDA_V1_E.pdf">ADat-P 4778.2 Ed A Ver 1:2020 - Profiles for Binding Metadata to a Data Object</ulink> - Chapter 2</entry>
        <entry>BINDING-SMTP-V2</entry>
      </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">XMPP Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Extensible Message and Presence Protocol (XMPP) Binding Profile</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>Confidentiality metadata labels can be supported in XMPP stanzas as indicated by XEP-0258 whereby a mechanism for carrying Enhanced Security Services (ESS) Security labels is standardized. This profile extends the XEP-0258 specification to support carrying an Embedded or Detached BDO for Message stanzas. This profile supports the XMPP use cases for one-to-one instant messaging and multi-user chat.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf">TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf</ulink> - Annex C</entry>
              <entry>BINDING-XMPP-V2</entry>
	          </row>


                  <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
                  <row>
                    <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Metadata Services</emphasis></entry>
                    <entry align="left" colname="col2">Office Open XML (OOXML) Formats Binding Profile</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                  <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
                  <para>This profile for the OOXML describes how metadata can be maintained.</para>
                  </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry align="left">
      <ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf">TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf</ulink> - Annex D</entry>
                    <entry>BINDING-OOXML-V2</entry>
            	    </row>

                              <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
                              <row>
                                <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">SOAP Services</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry align="left" colname="col2">Simple Object Access Protocol (SOAP) Profile</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                              <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
                              <para>This profilesupports for both SOAP 1.1 and SOAP 1.2. To support information sharing between partners it may be necessary to
                              locate a Binding Data Object (BDO) in the SOAP protocol layer. Metadata may be bound to the whole data object (SOAP message) or may be
                              bound to subsets of the SOAP message (data object(s) in the SOAP body). In an environment where data objects must have bound metadata,
                              the resource identified in the URI will already contain a BDO (detached, encapsulating or embedded).</para>
                              </entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                <entry align="left">
                  <ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf">TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf</ulink> - Annex E</entry>
                                <entry>BINDING-SOAP</entry>
                              </row>



                              <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
                              <row>
                                <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">REST Services</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry align="left" colname="col2">Representational State Transfer (REST) Profile</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                              <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
                              <para>In an environment where data objects must have bound metadata, the resource identified in the URI will already contain a BDO (detached, encapsulating or embedded). As such, there is no requirement for metadata binding that is specific for REST. However, to support information sharing between partners it may be necessary to locate a Binding Data Object (BDO) in the HTTP protocol layer.</para>
                              </entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                <entry align="left">
                  <ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf">TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf</ulink> - Annex F</entry>
                                <entry>BINDING-REST-V2</entry>
                              </row>



                        <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
                        <row>
                          <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Generic Packaging Services</emphasis></entry>
                          <entry align="left" colname="col2">Generic Open Packaging Convention (OPC) Binding Profile</entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                        <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
                        <para>This profile defines a generic packaging mechanism, based upon the Open Packaging Container (OPC) defined in ISO/IEC 29500-2:2008, to associate any arbitrary file that do not use the Office Open XML (OOXML) format or have no specific profile for supporting the Binding Information with their own file format.</para>
                        </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                          <entry align="left">
            <ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf">TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf</ulink>  - Annex G</entry>
                          <entry>BINDING-GENERIC-V2</entry>
                  	    </row>



                              <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
                              <row>
                                <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">Sidecar Services</emphasis></entry>
                                <entry align="left" colname="col2">Sidecar Files Binding Profile</entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                              <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
                              <para>Sidecar files allow the association of metadata with a data object for which there is no profile.</para>
                              </entry>
                              </row>
                              <row>
                                <entry align="left">
                  <ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf">Sidecar_Files_Binding_Profilev1.0.pdf</ulink> - Annex H</entry>
                                <entry>BINDING-SIDECAR-V2</entry>
                        	    </row>




            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">XMP Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Extensible Metadata Platform (XMP) Binding Profile</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This Binding Profile for XMP describes how metadata should be incorporated within an XMP packet as a structured value.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf">TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf</ulink>  - Annex I</entry>
              <entry>BINDING-EXTENSIBLE-V2</entry>
	          </row>


            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">WSMP Services</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Web Service Messaging Profile (WSMP) Profile</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>The Web Service Messaging Profile (WSMP) defines a set of service profiles to exchange
arbitrary XML-based messages. WSMP is extensible and may be used by any Community of Interest
(COI). This profile supports the requirement to explicitly bind metadata to data (or subsets thereof)
whereby the data is XML-based and exchanged between service consumers and service providers using
the WSMP message wrapper mechanism.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf">TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf</ulink>  - Annex J</entry>
              <entry>BINDING-WSMP</entry>
	          </row>

            <row><!-- Intentional Blank Line --><entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2"> </entry></row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left" colname="col1"><emphasis role="bold">XML Artifacts Profile</emphasis></entry>
              <entry align="left" colname="col2">Common XML artefacts 2.0</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
            <entry align="left" namest="col1" nameend="col2">
            <para>This profile supports the requirement to bind metadata to data (or subsets thereof) whereby
            the data is XML-encoded in one of the following schemas: XML Schema, ISO Schematron, XML Stylesheet, Generic Codelist,
            Context/Value Assosiation or Security Policy Information File.</para>
            </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry align="left">
<ulink url="https://storage.nisp.nw3.dk/TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf">TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf</ulink>  - Annex K</entry>
              <entry>BINDING-COMMON-XML</entry>
	          </row>


          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>

  <index></index>



</book>
