<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<book lang="en">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles</title>
    <subtitle>Design Rules</subtitle>
    <corpauthor>C3 CCSC NATO Open Systems Working Group</corpauthor>
    <productname class="trade">Allied Data Publication 34</productname>
    <biblioid class="pubnumber">ADatP-34</biblioid>
    <volumenum>5</volumenum>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>4.1</revnumber>
        <date>30 April 2010</date>
        <revremark>DRAFT</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <productnumber>$Id$</productnumber>
  </bookinfo>
<!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 1
 ***************************************************************** 
-->
  <chapter id="v5c1-designrules">
    <title>NISP Design Rules</title>
    <sect1 id="v5c1s1-intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
	<para>This document is a draft under development by the NATO Open Systems Working Group (NOSWG)
 under the authority the NATO Consultation, Command and Control Board (NC3B).
  In due course it is expected to be noted by the NATO C3 Board making the Volume 2 standards 
and profiles mandatory for use in NATO common funded systems, and to be made available to
the general public as a replacement for ADatP-34(D).</para>
</sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Summary</title>
  <para>This guideline document describes a concept and model for how
  knowledge of proven solutions can be documented and packaged in order to
  form a shared basis for supporting the development and the implementation of
  NNEC based systems for NATO.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This document introduces the concept of design rules by describing
    what design rules are and how they shall be applied in a NATO Network
    Enabled Capabilities context.</para>

    <para>Design rules are about reusing knowledge of proven solutions for
    reoccurring problems. Reuse of solutions that give NNEC-specific
    characteristics is particularly important. These solutions should solve
    frequent and/or difficult problems, promote important system
    characteristics and/or improve the quality of the resulting product in a
    cost effective way.</para>

    <para>A design rule consists mainly of the following three parts:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Context; describes under what circumstances the design rule is
        valid</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Problem/Opportunity; is a description of the problem it solves
        or the opportunity it exploits.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Solution; is a description how the problem/opportunity
        shall/should be resolved in the given context</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Design rules can give solutions on all levels, but it is anticipated
    that the produced design rules mainly takes care of the higher system
    levels (relating to the breakdown patterns in a system design) in order to
    avoid a cumbersome number of rules. If possible design rules shall be
    based on standards and/or NISP/NAF and will preferably be associated with
    as concept (generic concept of design).</para>

    <para>The introduction of design rules in the NISP will also need to be
    integrated with other design related artefacts and frameworks within NATO
    such as the NATO Architectural Framework (NAF).</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>General</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Target Group</title>

      <para condition="ignore"></para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Definitions, Abbreviations and Acronyms</title>

      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="4">
          <colspec colwidth="16*" />

          <colspec colwidth="22*" />

          <colspec colwidth="22*" />

          <colspec colwidth="50*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry><para>Acronym</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Explanation</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Reference</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Definition</para></entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><para>DR</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Design Rule</para></entry>

              <entry><para>NOSWG</para></entry>

              <entry><para>A standardized, reusable solution to a design
              problem in a specific context within a problem space that
              provides value to the user.</para> <para>Note: There are four
              (4) types of design rules:</para> <para>a. A development method
              that supports the life cycle perspective;</para> <para>b. A
              defined structure that supports descriptions of complex
              relations;</para> <para>c. A detailed description of suggested
              technical solutions;</para> <para>d. A proven and reusable
              solution for a generic problem.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>DRP</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Design Rule Package</para></entry>

              <entry><para>NOSWG</para></entry>

              <entry><para>A specific set of design rules that make up a
              solution package within a defined problem area.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>SIOP</para></entry>

              <entry><para>service interoperability point</para>
              <para></para></entry>

              <entry><para>EAPC(AC/322)D(2006)0002-REV1</para>
              <para></para></entry>

              <entry><para>A reference point within an architecture where one
              or more service interfaces are physically or logically
              instantiated to allow systems delivering the same service using
              different protocols to interoperate.</para> <para>Note: A
              service interoperability point serves as the focal point for
              service interoperability between interconnected systems, and may
              be logically located at any level within the components, and its
              detailed technical specification is contained within a service
              interface profile.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>SIP</para></entry>

              <entry><para>service interface profile</para>
              <para></para></entry>

              <entry><para>EAPC(AC/322)D(2006)0002-REV1</para>
              <para></para></entry>

              <entry><para>A set of attributes that specifies the
              characteristics of a service interface between interoperable
              systems in the Networking and Information Infrastructure.</para>
              <para>Note: A service interface profile is identified at a
              service interoperability point in an architecture system
              view.</para> <para></para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>References</title>

      <para condition="ignore"></para>

      <bibliography>
        <title>Referenced documents</title>

        <bibliomixed><author>
            <surname>Alexander</surname>

            <firstname>C.</firstname>
          </author> et al. <pubdate>1997</pubdate> <title>A Pattern
        Language</title>, <publishername>Oxford University
        Press</publishername>, <address>New York</address>,</bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed><author>
            <firstname>E.</firstname>

            <surname>Gamma</surname>
          </author>, <author>
            <firstname>R.</firstname>

            <surname>Helm</surname>
          </author>, <author>
            <firstname>J.</firstname>

            <surname>Vlissides</surname>
          </author> <pubdate>1995</pubdate>. <title>Design Patterns: Elements
        of Reusable Object-Oriented Software</title>. <address>Reading, MA</address>:
        <publishername>Addison-Wesley</publishername></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed><author>
            <surname>Buschmann</surname>

            <firstname>F.</firstname>
          </author>, <author>
            <surname>Meunier</surname>

            <firstname>R.</firstname>
          </author>, <author>
            <surname>Rohnert</surname>

            <firstname>H.</firstname>
          </author>, <author>
            <surname>Sommerlad</surname>

            <firstname>P.</firstname>
          </author> and <author>
            <firstname>M.</firstname>

            <surname>Stal</surname>
          </author>. <pubdate>1996</pubdate>. <title>Pattern-Oriented Software
        Architecture, A System of Patterns</title>. <address>New York</address>:
        <publishername>John Wiley and Sons</publishername></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed><title>Designrules, in the commercial world</title>.
        <author>
            <firstname>David B. Kim</firstname>

            <surname>Clark</surname>
          </author></bibliomixed>
      </bibliography>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Background</title>

    <para>Packaging knowledge into something reusable is nothing new in the
    software engineering field of science. Almost ten years ago a book was
    published that made a huge impact on how software engineers look upon
    packaging and sharing knowledge of proven solutions. The Design
    Pattern-book gave the engineers a tool not only on how to describe,
    formalize, package and distribute their knowledge and experience but also
    a tool on how to discuss different possible solution alternatives to a
    specific problem. It enables efficiency in both the communication and the
    implementation of software design, based upon a common vocabulary and
    reference.</para>

    <para>The design pattern concept described in this book was not an
    original idea but the adaptation of the ideas from a building architect,
    Dr Christopher Alexander, who wrote a book on patterns found when
    categorizing floor plans, buildings, neighbourhoods, town, cities, etc. In
    that book Alexander writes:</para>

    <para>&ldquo;Each pattern is a three-part rule, which expresses a relation
    between a certain context, a problem, and a solution.&rdquor;</para>

    <para>This is the central thing about being able to package our knowledge
    and experience. It is not enough to describe a solution. To make a
    solution useful you also have to state what problem the solution solves or
    what opportunity that the solution makes possible as well as the context
    in which the problem/opportunity &ndash; solution pair is valid. For
    instance, the optimal solution to the problem on how to enter and exit a
    building will be very different in the context of a building situated in
    Stockholm or somewhere in the arctic.</para>

    <para>The design patterns from the Design Pattern-book are the type of
    patterns that have become most widely known. These patterns solve problems
    or makes opportunities possible at a analysis or design level of
    abstraction. However, this is not the only level of abstraction covered by
    patterns. 1996 an important piece of work regarding patterns was published
    dealing with patterns on an architectural level of abstraction. This book
    identified patterns for system architecture at a higher level than the
    original design patterns. The patterns relate to the macro-design of
    system components such as operating systems or network stacks.</para>

    <para>After this, patterns of higher and higher level of abstraction have
    been published, sometimes, but not very often, also on lower levels. A
    specific level of interest to us is the system level-of abstraction.
    System-level patterns identify and describe the overall structure and
    interactions that can occur between components of a system. Furthermore,
    Enterprise-level patterns are possible, showing how to efficiently
    organise ones enterprise and what type of services to offer to its
    clients.</para>

    <para>Consequently, mechanisms similar to the design rules described in
    this guideline have been used in different contexts and at different
    levels of abstraction. In many cases they have been quite popular and
    proven practical. Thus, it can be assumed that the design rule concept can
    be an efficient means to provide reuse of knowledge within the future
    development of the NNEC.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Design rules summary</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Introduction to design rules</title>

      <para>Design rules are about reusing knowledge of proven solutions for
      reoccurring problems. Reuse of solutions that give NNEC-specific
      characteristics is particularly important. These solutions should solve
      frequent and/or difficult problems, promote important system
      characteristics and/or improve the quality of the resulting product in a
      cost effective way.</para>

      <para>Design rules consist mainly of the following three parts:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Context; describes under what circumstances the design rule is
          valid</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Problem/Opportunity; is a description of the problem it solves
          or the opportunity it exploits.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Solution; is a description how the problem/opportunity
          shall/should be resolved in the given context</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Design rules can give solutions on all levels, but it is
      anticipated that the produced design rules mainly takes care of the
      higher system levels (relating to the breakdown patterns in a system
      design) in order to avoid a cumbersome number of rules. If possible
      design rules shall be based on standards and/or NISP/NAF and will
      preferably be associated with as concept (generic concept of
      design).</para>

      <para>A design rule package is a mechanism for packaging of design rules
      (by reference) within a certain domain or for a specific kind of system.
      The dependencies between design rules that are part of a design rule
      package shall be defined and minimized.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Benefits from using design rules</title>

      <para>In today&rsquor;s knowledge oriented organizations it is very
      important to make sure that the knowledge of people is preserved in the
      organization even if the people change positions or leave the company.
      Design rules are important tools to be able to aid the process of
      managing this knowledge since they force documentation of knowledge in a
      structured way.</para>

      <para>The use of design rules to document and package proven solutions
      is expected to speed up development, and reduce cost and risk, by
      reusing knowledge on how to solve recurring problems and by providing
      verified solutions to those problems.</para>

      <para>Moreover, the use of design rules provide the means to coordinate
      development of different federated systems in order to make them network
      enabled and facilitate the evolvement of combined capabilities. Another
      important aspect is also that design rules aid organisations in creating
      a common understanding of the problems and challenges they are
      facing.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Consequences of using design rules</title>

      <para>In order for design rules to have effect in an organization there
      must be a framework which describes what design rules are and how they
      shall be used, i.e. this document. Design rules will also affect the way
      solutions are described and must be an integral part of the architecture
      description framework.</para>

      <para>Another important thing to remember is that design rules will
      affect the way we work, thus putting new requirements on the processes
      and people within our organization.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Design rules in a NATO NEC federated environment</title>

    <para>This guideline document describes a concept and model for how
    knowledge of proven solutions in the form of design rules can be
    documented and packaged in order to form a shared basis for the future
    development of NNEC based systems for NATO.</para>

    <para>The processes in which design rules are identified, produced and
    used are not described within this guideline.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Problems or opportunity description</title>

      <para>In the development of large systems of systems or federated
      systems for the future needs of the NATO there are several problems to
      be solved as well as opportunities to exploit. The problems range from
      what methods to use for requirements capture and design to how to solve
      detailed technical matters.</para>

      <para>In order to be able to establish a set of building blocks that can
      be used to meet the needs of the future NNEC, design regulations are
      absolutely essential if the building blocks shall be possible to be used
      together and combined in different ways, from a technical as well as
      from a business point of view.</para>

      <para>Design regulations in this context are the descriptive or
      normative regulation work necessary for NATO nations to be able to
      implement, configure and use systems in a federated environment. This
      includes not only technical and business design, but also the ability to
      manage and maintain these regulations to be able to provide the NATO
      nations with flexible component based systems.</para>

      <para>Moreover, there is a strong incentive to endorse reuse of proven
      solutions or implementations and thus get a more cost-effective
      solution. The overall quality is also expected to benefit from this kind
      of reuse.</para>

      <para>In this document we will focus on the model for design rules, and
      the patterns for setting up the SIOP and SIP:s between federations, this
      in order to be able to exchange information services between
      parties.</para>

      <para>Design rules patterns and knowledge for supporting NATO Nations in
      designing NNEC compliant components and services can also be retrieved
      from different Nations repositories as reference architectures, Sweden
      Design rules (releasable to NATO) will be included as one of the Partner
      nations reference architecture as recommended and proven patterns in
      order to achieve NNEC interoperability.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Solution</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Design rules in the NNEC context</title>

        <para>Design rules are about reusing knowledge of proven solutions. In
        the context of NNEC we are especially interested in reuse of solutions
        that provide typical NNEC characteristics. In addition to this, the
        use of design rules aim at making the development of NNEC more
        cost-effective and improve the quality in the resulting
        products.</para>

        <para>As mentioned before, a design rule is in the most general
        description a three-part rule, which expresses a relation between a
        certain context, a problem or an opportunity and a solution.</para>

        <para>Different design rules may be in conflict with each other, e.g.
        in that the solution of one design rule can be incompatible with the
        solution of the other.</para>

        <para>Moreover, design rules can be singular or aggregates meaning
        that it either is an atomic rule or an aggregate of rules that
        together constitute the rule. The aggregate may include rules on how
        to combine the possibly conflicting aggregated rules in order to
        generate a rule according to the current priorities.</para>

        <para>Design rules may be implemented for solutions on different
        levels. There may be design rules for specific technical design
        problems or rules, how to handle a major business opportunities. It is
        however anticipated that the majority of design rules valid for an
        NNEC-system will be focused on the higher levels.</para>

        <para>Design rules can be used in order to meet functional as well as
        non-functional needs of the system of interest. It should be clear
        from all design rules which problem or opportunity it is supposed to
        solve.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>General guidance for using design rules</title>

        <para>The prime prerequisites for implementing a design rule
        are:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The use of the design rule shall make the resulting design
            &ldquo;NNEC-compliant&rdquor;, i.e. the design rules shall provide
            essential NNEC-characteristics such as flexibility,
            interoperability, security and usability</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A design rule shall provide a solution to frequently shown
            problems, to enable reuse of solutions or implementations and thus
            get a more cost-effective solution.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A design rule shall provide a solution to difficult
            problems, or explore an opportunity, i.e. be a part of the
            corporate or federated memory</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A design rule shall improve the quality of the resulting
            product relative a product solution not using the design
            rule.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>At least one of the mentioned prerequisites should be fulfilled.
        There may of course be other valid prerequisites, which will be
        assessed and used to initiate the design of a design rule.</para>

        <para>Design rules shall consist of either atomic rules or aggregates
        of rules that together shall constitute the rule. The aggregate may
        include rules on how to combine the possibly conflicting rules in
        order to generate a rule according to the priorities.</para>

        <para>An atomic design rule must not contain solutions for more than
        one subject area, e.g. mixing of business and technical subjects shall
        be avoided. Detailed technical rules shall in the same way be
        separated from rules of information or logical nature.</para>

        <para>Design rules shall where applicable be based on concepts and
        rules in an extended NATO Architecture Framework.</para>

        <para>A design rule shall not be of too low granularity or too trivial
        in order to avoid an explosion in the number produced of design rules.
        To achieve the approved mandatory validity, a design rule shall
        specify the way to solve the problem it is intended for. Rules that
        can be expressed in single sentences are collected in general sections
        in the design rule solution part.</para>

        <para>Great efforts shall be made to ensure that the design rule is
        maintainable. This is primarily achieved by limiting the problem area
        that the design rule is intended for. More complex problems or
        opportunities shall be supported by aggregates of rules.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Design rule model</title>

        <figure>
          <title>Design rule model</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../figures/dr-guide-designrulemodel.svg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The design rule product consists of:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The basic design rule which, as already described, is a
            three part rule consisting of context, problem and solution. This
            shall also be complemented with one or more rejected solutions,
            i.e. solutions which shall not be used.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>An analysis and motivation why the solution fits the problem
            in the given context. This needs to be linked to direct business
            benefits such as cost savings or increased efficacy in
            operations.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>A description of the consequences from the proposed solution
            which is used to create an understanding at what cost the solution
            comes. This could include financial impacts, but also how people,
            processes or technology needs to be adjusted in order to achieve
            the solution. When describing the consequences from a design rule
            solution the impact on (at least) the following areas should
            always be considered:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Security</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Interoperability</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Cost</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Usability</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Flexibility and</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Procedures</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Verification information which explains how the application
            of the rule can be verified.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>A template for design rules, including guidelines, is defined in
        a separate document.</para>

        <para>A design rule product is like Standards in the NISP related to
        near, mid and far term. A design rule can also exist in different
        versions with different status. The status of the design rule
        indicates which state of development the design rule is in.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Candidates</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Approved</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Disposed</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The solution described in a design rule may refer to other
        design rules to form an aggregate design rule. This may be the case
        for instance in a design rule describing a configuration to use in a
        specific context or for a specific type of system. If so, the validity
        of the referenced design rule within the current context shall be
        stated.</para>

        <para>Each design rule is configured in one, and only one, Design Rule
        Package.</para>

        <para>The status of a design rule indicates in which state of
        development it is.</para>

        <para>Validity of a design rule is only used when referring as e.g. to
        form aggregates. The validity labels that can be used are defined in
        the table below.</para>

        <table frame="all">
          <title>Rule validities</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colwidth="20*" />

            <colspec colwidth="80*" />

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry><para>Validity</para></entry>

                <entry><para>Description</para></entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><para>Mandatory</para></entry>

                <entry><para>The rule shall be treated as a norm and is
                mandatory to use.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Optional</para></entry>

                <entry><para>The rule gives good design principles and is
                recommended for use.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Candidate</para></entry>

                <entry><para>The rule is planned for future use in this
                context. The design rule exist but is not appropriate to use
                due to reasons like cost, compatibility etc.</para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>The lifecycle for a design rule must be coordinated with
        profiles and standards in the manner, following the NOSWG NISP
        model</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Packaging of Rules (Rule Package)</title>

        <para>Design rules are configured in packages named DRP, Design Rule
        Package. A DRP may also configure other DRPs, thus creating a
        hierarchy of packages. A design rule or DRP belongs to one, and only
        one, DRP.</para>

        <para>DRPs are defined so that each DRP-structure covers rules that
        are specific to one particular domain defined for a specific subject
        area of norms.</para>

        <para>Dependencies between DRPs shall be defined, and the dependencies
        shall be minimized. Circular dependencies must not exist. The
        visibility of design rules configured by a DRP may in addition be
        limited to the DRP only; default is however that only the DRP exposes
        the external visibility for a design rule.</para>

        <para>No design rule shall be part of more than one DRP, if necessary
        cross-references between DRPs according to the rules for dependencies
        between DRPs shall be used. Common design rules must for this reason
        be allocated to higher levels in a DRP hierarchy.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Consequences</title>

      <para>If the design rule concept is going to be successfully
      implemented, it is important to understand how they impact the other
      frameworks and processes used in design. These frameworks and processes
      also have to be adjusted so it becomes clear as to what is documented
      where and when.</para>

      <sect3>
        <title>Standards with the use of design rules</title>

        <para>Standards is often about WHAT but not always about HOW. A vast
        number of standards are applicable for NNEC, what are applied where,
        how and together with what, does not always mean that complex system
        will work. In order to support profiling development when using NISP,
        Designrules is adopted by NATO as a complementary set of tools for
        :</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Helping to choose the right standard</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>How to apply the standard on a specific problem</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Understanding the relations between different
            standards</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Applicability in different domains</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Helping with best practice and good patters in order to
            speed up the development of a profile.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Profiling with the use of NAF and Standards and Designrules in
        the NISP</title>

        <para>The relations between the NISP and NAF objects in focus. The
        following picture shows the relations between the NISP objects
        Profile, Standards and Designrules. For more information about Profile
        guidance document.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Releationship between NISP objects Profiles, standards and
          Designrules</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../figures/dr-guide-profiling.svg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Reference architecture - National design rules</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>The Swedish Design rules contributions</title>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">FMLS Architecture Framework
      Designrules</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>LT9O P05-0486 Executive Summary 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>Leif Nyberg, JV Network Based Defence, Framework Service
      Description LT1K P04-0320 Version 7.0 December 2006.</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P05-0074 Overarching Architecture 4.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P05-0075 Systems Engineering Vision FMLS 2010
      5.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P05-0026 - SOA for NBD Principles 3.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P05-0507 Architecture Description Framework 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0025 Integrated Dictionary for FMLS 2010 Technical
      Systems rev 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">FMLS Generic
      Designrules</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P04-0438 Definition of service Service Registry
      3.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P05-0235 Definition of service User Registry 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P05-0446 NERE metadata specs for tech and softw syst
      2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0036 SD Provide Report 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0039 SD Access COP Information 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0061 Definition of Service SW and Data Distribution
      1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0064 Definition of Service Configuration 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0102 Definition of Service GetRevocation 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0269 Definition of Service TimeStamp 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0272 Definition of Service ComBroker 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0298 D3C 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P05-0034 Infrastructure Overview 3.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P05-0236 Definition of service Organization Registry
      2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P05-0557 Design Target Architecture NERE 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0037 SD Process intelligence 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0059 Definition of Service Policy 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0062 Definition of Service Action 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0091 COPS Information model 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0134 Definition of Service DNS 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0270 Definition of Service AccessControl 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0274 Definition of API data validation 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P05-0035 Communication Infrastructure Overview
      4.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P05-0443 NCES Reference Architecture 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0035 SD Provide Streaming Data 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0038 SD Support COPS 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0060 Definition of Service Log 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0063 Definition of Service Monitoring 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0095 NCES Management Information and Data models
      1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0145 Design Overview 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0271 Definition of Service NereRegistryAdmin
      1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0279 Definition of Service Network Time
      synchronization 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">FMLS Technical
      Designrules</emphasis></simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P05-0217 - DR Data Incest Prevention 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0049 DR Risk management 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0106 Design Rule Mobility 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0350 DRP Flexibility 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P05-0547 - DRP Common Operational Picture 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0050 DR Flexibility 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0108 DR security aspects of information 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0351 DRP Interoperability 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0008 Design Rule Legacy Integration 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0051 DR Interoperability 2.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0321 DR Scalability 1.0</simpara>

      <simpara>LT1K P06-0352 DRP Security 1.0</simpara>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Nation x &hellip;</title>

      <para condition="ignore"></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="v5c2-drmil">
  <title>International Military Interoperability for information exchange in
  the NNEC context</title>

  <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Summary</emphasis></simpara>

  <para>This design rule describes how military organisations can develop and
  implement the ability to exchange information and services with military
  organizations from other nations to become interoperable. It touches on, but
  does not fully address the problems related to organizational structures and
  behaviour when multiple organisations collaborate in a federative manor in a
  mission.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>General</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Unique Identity</title>

      <para>[An identifier that uniquely identifies the design rule. (Product
      ID)]</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Target Group</title>

      <para>This design rule targets any military organization that plan or
      foresee that it will participate in a mission where exchange of
      information and services with other military organizations is
      vital.</para>

      <para>Within these organizations, the intended users are requirement
      analysts, architects and high-level designers of NNEC compliant
      systems.</para>

      <para>This document defines patterns for enabling information exchange
      between parties in federations, and is to be used by architects
      designing SIOPs and SIPs according to NISP and the NATO C3 System
      Architecture Framework <xref linkend="dr-mil-ref-nc3saf" />.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Definitions and abbreviations</title>

      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="20*" />

          <colspec colwidth="80*" />

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><para>CIA</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Confidentiality, Integrity and Availability.
              Aspects which are to be considered when performing security
              analysis.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>COI</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Community Of Interest.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Design rule</para></entry>

              <entry><para>A standardized, reusable solution to a design
              problem in a specific context within a problem space that
              provides value to the user.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>ESB</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Enterprise Service Bus. An ESB refers to a software
              architecture construct, implemented by technologies found in a
              category of middleware infrastructure products usually based on
              Web services standards that provides foundational services for
              more complex service-oriented architectures.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>IEAT</para></entry>

              <entry><para>A concept for Information Exchange Architecture and
              Technology developed within the frame of Multinational
              Experiment 5 with Sweden as lead nation.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>IEG</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Information Exchange Gateway. A technical system
              which is used to protect information assets. IEG are described
              in the IEG concept <xref
              linkend="dr-mil-gwimpl" />.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>IEM</para></entry>

              <entry><para>An Information Exchange Model (IEM) is a
              specification of the information which is exchanged between
              operational nodes. IEMs are used when deciding which information
              objects are to be exchanged in service
              interactions.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>IER</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Information Exchange Requirement, a specification
              of the required information exchanged between operational nodes
              which are described in an architecture.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>IES</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Information Exchange Service, a part of an
              IEG.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Information Zone</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Information Zones is a concept identified and
              defined <xref linkend="_11-fmls-sa-overview" /> to achieve
              confidentiality with high assurance, for a gathering of
              information within a defined perimeter, and interactions to its
              surrounding with a number of services and nodes inside the
              zone.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>IPS</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Information Protection Service, a part of an
              IEG.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>NAF</para></entry>

              <entry><para>NATO Architectural Framework.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>NEC</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Network Enabled Capabilities.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>NNEC</para></entry>

              <entry><para>NATO Network Enabled Capabilities.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>NISP</para></entry>

              <entry><para>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles <xref
              linkend="dr-mil-ref-nisp-vol1v3" />.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>NPS</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Node Protection Service, a part of an
              IEG.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Operation</para> <para></para></entry>

              <entry><para>An operation where actors from multiple national
              system is tasked in a federation of system.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>Service</para></entry>

              <entry><para>In this context a technical mechanism which allows
              access to one or more capabilities in order to enable service
              interaction.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>SIOP</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Service Interoperability Point. A reference point
              within an architecture where one or more service interfaces are
              physically or logically instantiated to allow systems delivering
              the same service using different protocols to interoperate <xref
              linkend="dr-mil-ref-nc3saf" />.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>SIP</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Service Interoperability Profile. A set of
              attributes that specifies the characteristics of a service
              interface between interoperable systems in the Networking and
              Information Infrastructure. A SIP is identified at a SIOP in an
              architecture system view <xref
              linkend="dr-mil-ref-nc3saf" />.</para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>SOA</para> <para></para></entry>

              <entry><para>Service Oriented Architecture. An architectural
              style which aims at a loose coupling of services with operating
              systems, programming languages and other technologies which
              underlie applications.</para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </sect2>

    <bibliography>
      <bibliodiv>
        <title>Steering documents</title>

        <bibliomixed><title>Design Rule Framework,</title> <contrib>See NATO
        NISP DR guidance document</contrib></bibliomixed>
      </bibliodiv>

      <bibliodiv>
        <title>References</title>

        <bibliomixed id="dr-mil-ref-drinteroperability"><title>DR
        Interoperability</title> <pubsnumber>Sweden proposal, P06-0051 rev
        3.0</pubsnumber></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed id="dr-mil-ref-ieat"><title>IEAT Concept</title>,
        <bibliomisc>MNE-5 initiative</bibliomisc></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed id="dr-mil-ref-flex"><title>Design Rule
        Flexibility</title>, <pubsnumber>Sweden P06-0050 (NATO doc
        ?)</pubsnumber></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed><title>Design Rule Security aspects of
        information</title>, <pubsnumber>Sweden P06-0108 (NATO doc
        ?)</pubsnumber></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed id="dr-mil-ref-nc3saf"><title>NATO C3 System Architecture
        Framework</title>,
        <pubsnumber>EAPC(AC/322)D(2006)0002-REV1</pubsnumber></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed id="dr-mil-ref-gov-ee"><title>Federated Governance of
        Information Sharing Within the Extended Enterprise</title>,
        <orgname>AFEI Information Sharing Working Group</orgname>,
        <pubdate>Nov 17 2007</pubdate></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed id="dr-mil-ref-nisp-vol1v3"><title>NISP Volume 1</title>,
        <edition>Version 3</edition></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed id="dr-mil-ref-naf3"><title>NATO Architecture Framework
        (NAF)</title>, <edition>Version 3</edition>.
        <pubsnumber>AC/322-D(2007)0048</pubsnumber></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed id="dr-mil-gwimpl"><title>Guidance Document on the
        Implementation of Gateways for Information Exchange between NATO and
        External CIS Communities</title>,
        <pubsnumber>AC/322(SC/4)N(2007)0007</pubsnumber></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed id="_11-fmls-sa-overview"><title>Swedish FMLS Security
        Architecture Overview</title>,
        <bibliomisc>http://www.fmv.se/upload/Bilder%20och%20dokument/Vad%20gor%20FMV/Uppdrag/LedsystT/Overgripande%20FMLS-dokument/Generiska%20designdokument/LT1K%20P04-0385%20Security%20Architecture%20Overview%205.0.pdf
        </bibliomisc>, <pubsnumber>33442/2006</pubsnumber>
        <edition>Version 5.0</edition>, <pubdate>May 4 2007</pubdate></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed id="dr-mil-ref-nisp-vol3v3"><title>NISP Volume 3, Version
        3</title></bibliomixed>

        <bibliomixed id="dr-mil-ref-tacoms"><orgname>TACOMS</orgname>:
        <title>TACOMS Post 2000 Profile</title>, <pubsnumber>STANAG
        4637</pubsnumber></bibliomixed>
      </bibliodiv>
    </bibliography>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Design Rule</title>

    <para>This design rule is developed for use in NATO Interoperability
    Standards &amp; Profiles (NISP) version 4. It is based on experiences from
    the Swedish Network Based Defence initiative where it extends the design
    rule for Interoperability <xref linkend="dr-mil-ref-drinteroperability" />
    and the IEAT concept developed within the frame of Multinational
    Experiment 5<xref linkend="dr-mil-ref-ieat" />. The design rule also
    considers the NATO Information Exchange Gateway (IEG) concept<xref
    linkend="dr-mil-gwimpl" />.</para>

    <para>The design rule is applicable for collaborative federations in the
    coming 2-6 years which means that it covers both existing systems which
    won&rsquor;t be replaced as well as new systems which are developed and
    implemented during this time period.</para>

    <para>The technical scope for the design rule is the highlighted areas of
    <xref linkend="v6f-simpleNNECframework" />. The design rule does not
    describe how to achieve interoperability on the Transport/Network level.
    Furthermore, it does not cover interoperability on the Community of
    Interest level. However, when design rules for these levels are created,
    this design rule will be used as the basis for enabling information
    exchange via services.</para>

    <figure id="v6f-simpleNNECframework">
      <title>Simplified NNEC Technical Services framework with design rule
      scope</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../figures/dr-mil-simpleNNECtsf.svg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <sect2>
      <title>Context</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Introduction</title>

        <para>The design rule should be used when there is a need for several
        different military actors to cooperate in a federative manor in order
        to solve a common mission. The key capabilities that this design rule
        will help enable are:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Collaborative planning between multiple actors in a
            federation</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Collaborative synchronization of execution between multiple
            actors in a federation</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Collaborative assessment between multiple actors in a
            federation</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The design rule does not address the operational activities
        needed to achieve the above capabilities, nor does it address the
        Community Of Interest (COI) technical services which supports these
        activities. Instead the design rule describes a set of principles,
        technologies and activities needed to create a technical platform
        which enables information exchange between the actors and can act as a
        foundation for the COI specific technical services when these are to
        be developed and deployed.</para>

        <para>Since the design rule captures knowledge from previous
        experiences in this area it can save time and money for the involved
        actors. If the design rule is applied when defining the profile for
        such a mission, less time will be spent on getting to agreement on
        which services and underpinning technologies shall be used in the
        mission.</para>

        <para>Many of the activities and technologies described in this design
        rule can also be applied when exchanging information and services with
        other actors than military organizations. However, there are specific
        aspects of collaborating with this type of organizations which are not
        covered by this design rule.</para>

        <para>A suitable definition of interoperability in this design rule
        context (i.e. technical context) is: The ability of technical systems
        and/or organizations using technical systems to operate together by
        making (necessary) data &amp; information and/or services produced by
        one system or organization available to the others, in an agreed
        format.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="v6s-intmilfed">
        <title>The International Military Federation</title>

        <para>There are many challenges that have to be overcome in order to
        make collaborative work and knowledge sharing among the actors in an
        operation successful. In <xref linkend="v6s-solution" /> of this
        design rule mainly addresses the technical aspects of the
        establishment of federation in which collaborating actors can exchange
        information. However, organizational, process and legislation aspects
        must be covered to some extent since all of these needs to be
        harmonized in order to make the collaboration effective. Therefore, a
        number of non-technical issues are described in <xref
        linkend="v6s-problem" />.</para>

        <para>The federation, depicted in <xref linkend="v6f-fedoverview" />,
        is where the collaborating actors provide services which the other
        actors can consume. To create a federation, the actors need to create
        a federation agreement which defines the rules of the federation, such
        as which data formats, information classifications should be used.
        Rules regarding information ownership and service levels (including
        quality of service) are also included in the federation
        agreement.</para>

        <para>Collaboration in multilateral operations has previously been
        based on bi-lateral agreements between all participants, but in order
        to achieve the speed and flexibility needed today, there is a need to
        establish a baseline federation agreement which can be used as a
        starting point when creating new missions.</para>

        <para>Actors which participate in the federation connect networks and
        systems within their responsibility (i.e. domain) to other actors in
        order to be able to exchange information. To protect the internal
        information and control which information is being exchanged one or
        more Information Exchange Gateways (IEG) are stood up between the
        federation and the actors&rsquor; network. In the IEG, one or more
        service interfaces are physically instantiated. This is referred to as
        a Service Interoperability Point (SIOP) according to the NATO C3
        System Architecture Framework <xref
        linkend="dr-mil-ref-nc3saf" />.</para>

        <para>Within an actor&rsquor;s domain there can be one or more
        networks where information is stored. The decision which internal
        networks shall be connected is taken by each actor (Federation member)
        independently of the other actors. In <xref
        linkend="v6f-fedoverview" /> two example networks are depicted, one
        federation network which holds information only relevant to the
        federation and one which is the actors&rsquor; internal network. In
        this case, the IEG handles information exchange between these two
        networks as well as information exchange with other actors
        IEGs.</para>

        <figure id="v6f-fedoverview">
          <title>Federation Overview</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../figures/dr-mil-fed-overview.svg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The remainder of the design rule describes the challenges the
        actors face and how they can cooperate in order to create a federation
        to exchange information in a secure manor.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Related design rule areas</title>

        <para>Interoperability is closely linked to the following other design
        rule areas:</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Flexibility</emphasis>: The requirements
        on interoperability will change over time. Also, in some situations,
        very limited time will be available for making the necessary
        modifications of the system in order to fulfil the new requirements.
        This means that the organization, security and technical systems need
        to be very flexible with respect to configuration and modifiability in
        order to be able to adapt to changing and extended interoperability
        requirements. For more information, refer to <xref
        linkend="dr-mil-ref-flex" />.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Information security</emphasis>: With
        interoperability follows information security risks that must be
        handled. The connection of external systems must be done in such a way
        that the information security of each nation or organisation is not
        compromised. However information security mechanisms cannot be allowed
        to be static. In each specific case the need to protect information
        must be balanced against the possible consequences from not sharing
        the information. The three aspects of security; confidentiality
        integrity and availability, must all be considered.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="v6s-problem">
      <title>Problem</title>

      <para>There are several challenges to the effort of creating a
      federation for collaboration between military partners, both related to
      technology, but also related to how organizations, humans and
      legislation systems work.</para>

      <para>This chapter summarizes the basic requirements for the federation
      and identifies the challenges which must be overcome in order to
      establish the federation. The issues identified for these challenges are
      given an answer to in <xref linkend="v6s-solution" />.</para>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Basic requirements for information
      exchange</emphasis></simpara>

      <para>The intent of this section is to identify a few of the most
      elementary (information exchange) requirements which are set on all
      international military federations. This is not a complete list, but
      these requirements acts as a driver for identifying the basic set of
      technologies needed in a federation.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry id="ier1" xreflabel="[IER 1]">
          <term>[IER 1]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>People from the different organisational actors SHALL be
            able to communicate with each other using voice or text
            communication.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="ier2" xreflabel="[IER 2]">
          <term>[IER 2]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>It SHALL be possible to discover and retrieve information
            (i.e. search) provided to the federation by different
            actors.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Challenges based on international
      agreements and regulations</emphasis></simpara>

      <para>Information and services exchange between nations and
      organisations (e.g. unclassified, restricted, secret and top secret
      classification) is based on government agreement between nations and
      organisations. Qualified information and services exchange can only take
      place if such agreement exists. To achieve this agreement is a lengthy
      process that often takes many months to finalize. It has also been
      proven complicated to negotiate and sign such an agreement between more
      than two nations and organisations at a time (multilateral). Nations are
      willing to share more information and services with some parties and
      less with others. This creates complicated situations during
      multilateral operations.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry id="issue1" xreflabel="[Issue_1]">
          <term>[Issue_1]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>How can a common, agreed description for analyzing and
            describing international military interoperability be
            created?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Challenges based on national law,
      national integrity and regulations</emphasis></simpara>

      <para>Differing laws, rules and regulations together with different
      cultures regarding information sharing are likely to impact willingness
      to share information and slow down process of getting agreements on what
      to share.</para>

      <para>Parties participating in a multilateral operation are likely to
      have different requirements and priorities which will imply different
      scope and granularity of information exchange for each party. The
      parties will be required to protect their national integrity while
      sharing information with the other parties. By this, it is likely that
      the parties wish to get access to more information and services than
      they are willing to provide themselves. It is also so that the parties
      will need to limit the possibilities for others to control how and what
      information is provided.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry id="issue2" xreflabel="[Issue_2]">
          <term>[Issue_2]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>How can the impact of national laws and regulations in
            coming to agreement of what information to share be minimized in
            order to support the requirements of flexibility and ability to
            change?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="issue3" xreflabel="[Issue_3]">
          <term>[Issue_3]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>How can parties participating in a multilateral operation
            protect their national integrity by using mechanisms to protect
            internal information and be able to control what information is
            released to others?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="issue4" xreflabel="[Issue_4]">
          <term>[Issue_4]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>How can the parties in a multilateral operation jointly come
            to agreement of what information shall be exchanged, how it shall
            be exchanged and how it shall be handled by receiving
            parties?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Challenges based on interpretation of
      information content</emphasis></simpara>

      <para>Semantic differences, i.e. differences in languages and the
      meaning of words and expressions, are likely to be an issue when
      exchanging information. If the collaborating parties cannot understand
      the information being communicated, the information will not be of any
      use and the trust of accessible information will be challenged. There is
      a need for the parties to eventually meet in a combined opinion, a
      common and agreed set of descriptions in order to reach wanted
      effects.</para>

      <para>In order to solve the semantic challenge there is a need to
      understand the content of information and services exchanged between
      different systems/actors to be able to come to an agreement of the
      meaning of the information. However, the increasing requirements of the
      ability to rapidly change directions of the flow of information, as well
      as the actual content, means that the work with defining models and
      requirements for information exchange must be done continuously and
      during the whole lifecycle of an operation.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry id="issue5" xreflabel="[Issue_5]">
          <term>[Issue_5]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>How can the parties in a multilateral operation agree on
            what information shall be exchanged?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="issue6" xreflabel="[Issue_6]">
          <term>[Issue_6]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>How can differences in semantics and information models be
            handled in order to minimize the risk of the parties not
            understanding each other?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="issue7" xreflabel="[Issue_7]">
          <term>[Issue_7]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>How can it be ensured that the work with understanding
            others semantics and information models is done in all stages of
            the development lifecycle?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Challenges based on technical
      issues</emphasis></simpara>

      <para>Architecture and technical implementations of information systems
      will be different in most of the cases. The complete technical system
      will probably not be homogenous, rather a federation of heterogeneous
      systems and therefore hard to govern and manage.</para>

      <para>Agreeing on standards, formats and mechanisms for information
      exchange is a critical success factor, however the sovereignty of the
      parties will increase the complexity of this task since there is no
      governing organ that can make the decisions.</para>

      <para>A common understanding and agreement on the architecture and
      design for the federation is vital in order to succeed with agreeing on
      how information shall be exchanged. A major challenge in this
      perspective is that the maturity of using architecture and design as
      governing tools is likely to vary greatly among collaborating parties,
      thus slowing down the agreement process.</para>

      <para>Since each actor has huge amounts of data of various kinds within
      their internal networks there is a need to have the means to organize
      and prioritize what to share. Also, when information has been shared
      within the federation, there must be mechanisms to be able to verify the
      authenticity, track usage of and prevent that the information is used by
      actors which are not meant to use it.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry id="issue8" xreflabel="[Issue_8]">
          <term>[Issue_8]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Which architecture can enable governance and structure to
            mechanisms for information exchange between heterogeneous
            systems?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="issue9" xreflabel="[Issue_9]">
          <term>[Issue_9]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Which standards, formats and mechanisms for information
            exchange should be used?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="issue10" xreflabel="[Issue_10]">
          <term>[Issue_10]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>What does a common architecture description framework for
            multilateral operations contain?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="issue11" xreflabel="[Issue_11]">
          <term>[Issue_11]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>What mechanisms shall be used in order to control what
            information to make available to partners in an international
            military operation?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry id="issue12" xreflabel="[Issue_12]">
          <term>[Issue_12]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>What mechanisms can be used to maintain information security
            and system safety, e.g. weapon safety, when external systems are
            connected to a nation&rsquor;s internal network?</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Challenges based on culture, lack of
      trust and organizational issues</emphasis></simpara>

      <para>Even if we have solved &ldquo;challenges based on international
      agreements and regulations&rdquor; we will still most likely hesitate to
      share information since the organizational culture does not foster
      incentives to share information<xref linkend="dr-mil-ref-gov-ee" />.
      This is understandable, but not very efficient from an operational
      perspective. We have to overcome these limitations and see the goal of
      the operations as more important than the individual organizations
      ego.</para>

      <para>Today&rsquor;s military organizations are experienced and usually
      organized around various stovepipe principles. This is a convenient,
      straight forward way of defining requirements, responsibilities and
      timetables for implementing new and enhanced systems. Operations were
      information is expected to be exchanged between both organizations and
      technical systems will set new requirements on the procurement process,
      working methods and the organizations working those issues.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry id="issue13" xreflabel="[Issue_13]">
          <term>[Issue_13]</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Data are not generally created to support enterprise needs.
            There are typically technical and political boundaries that
            inhibit this. To "line" applications development organizations,
            enterprise-level requirements for data are typically viewed as
            "external", as their direct customers, and typically the sponsor
            of the application, is not rewarded for serving the greater good,
            but for locally optimizing the performance of their
            organization<xref linkend="dr-mil-ref-gov-ee" />.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="v6s-solution">
      <title>Solution</title>

      <sect3>
        <title>Architecture for interoperability</title>

        <para>The most important instrument in resolving the issue of creating
        a description for analyzing and describing international military
        interoperability as described in <xref linkend="issue1" /> is to
        create an architecture. This design rule outlines an architecture
        which provides the means to create a foundation for the federation in
        which information exchange among parties can take place.</para>

        <para>The architecture is described by:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Governing aspects (design principles and rules) used to
            explain and develop architectural principles and structures in
            important areas of the architecture.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Common terminology &amp; definitions.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Structure. How systems, aspects and terminology/definitions
            are organized and grouped.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Systems in terms of mission and/or technical systems.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Services which describe how systems interact.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>It is absolutely vital that the architecture addresses both
        operational and technical aspects so that there is a clear description
        of what purpose the technical implementation has <xref
        linkend="principle4" />.</para>

        <sect4>
          <title>Service Oriented Architecture</title>

          <para>The Architecture outlined in this Design rule is Service
          Oriented <xref linkend="principle5" />. The aim of this is to
          achieve a loose coupling of services with underlying systems,
          whether it is mission or technical systems. So, instead of
          describing interaction directly between systems, the systems use
          services to interact with each other. By specifying a contract for
          information exchange, a service definition <xref
          linkend="principle6" />, the inside of a system can be replaced or
          modified without having to change other systems which interacts with
          it. Thereby the issue of enabling information exchange between
          heterogeneous systems <xref linkend="issue8" /> is resolved.</para>

          <para>Services used or provided by technical systems should as far
          as possible be expressed in a common way and contain formal
          descriptions suitable for IT processing.</para>

          <para>The Service description shall contain:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The allowed service protocols (process) to be used for
              information exchange.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The interfaces (or message types) that are used to
              exchange information between a service consumer and a service
              producer.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The definition of the data types that are used in the
              interfaces (messages) and therefore are in the information
              exchange model.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The properties that consumers can use to distinguish
              between different implementations of a service.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>To enable systems to find and connect to each other,
          information about services shall be published and accessible for the
          collaborating parties&rsquor; IT systems.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title>Architecture description framework</title>

          <para>In order for all parties to obtain a common
          &ldquo;language&rdquor; on how to describe their systems and the
          services they bring to the federation this design rule also covers
          an architecture description framework. The architecture description
          framework does not describe the architecture itself, but rather
          guides how the architecture shall be structured and what it should
          describe.</para>

          <para>The current valid description framework within NATO is the
          NATO Architectural Framework (NAF) version 3<xref
          linkend="dr-mil-ref-naf3" /> which provide the rules, guidance, and
          product descriptions for developing, presenting and communicating
          architectures which includes both operational aspects as well as
          technical aspects <xref linkend="principle4" />.</para>

          <para>In the Framework, there are seven major perspectives (i.e.,
          views) that logically combine to describe the architecture of an
          enterprise. These are the NATO All View (NAV), NATO Capability View
          (NCV), NATO Programme View (NPV), NATO Operational View (NOV), NATO
          Systems View (NSV), NATO Service-Oriented View (NSOV) and NATO
          Technical View (NTV). Each of the seven views depicts certain
          architecture attributes. Some attributes bridge several views and
          provide integrity, coherence, and consistency to architecture
          descriptions.</para>

          <para>To support the creation of views and make sure they are
          consistent, NAF v3 defines a metamodel. The NATO Architecture
          Framework Metamodel (NMM) defines the relationships between the
          different components of the framework. It defines the architectural
          objects and components that are permitted in NAF v3 views and their
          relationships with each other.</para>

          <para>There are certain views which are more important when
          designing architectures for multinational operations where
          interoperability is in focus <xref linkend="issue10" />:</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">NATO All-Views (NAV)</emphasis> which
          capture aspects which overarch all other views. These views set the
          scope and context of the architecture, such as goals and vision,
          scenario and environmental conditions as well as time.</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">NATO Capability View (NCV)</emphasis>
          which explain what capabilities are needed in order to fulfil the
          strategic intent for the mission. Specifically, capabilities related
          to interaction between actors are important to identify in these
          views. If produced correctly, these views can already say a lot of
          which services are needed to fulfil the business needs. In
          particular, the NCV-2, Capability Taxonomy and NCV-7, Capability to
          Services Mapping views are important.</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">NATO Operational View (NOV)</emphasis>
          which is a description of the tasks and activities, operational
          elements, and information exchanges required to accomplish NATO
          missions. To design for interoperability all of these views do not
          have to be complete, but it is important to know which operational
          nodes exist and how they interact (NOV-2). Also, the information
          model defined in the NOV-7 view is important, especially for such
          information for which there are no or unclear standards to rely on.
          When going into more details of the architecture, the requirements
          on information exchange (NOV-3) are necessary to understand.</para>

          <para>Currently, the operational views in NAF does not fully support
          modelling of services. The authors of this design rule recommends
          that future versions of NAF are complemented with the capabilities
          of using services to describe interaction between operational nodes
          instead of needlines.</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">NATO Service-Oriented View
          (NSOV)</emphasis> focuses strictly on identifying and describing
          services. The view also supports the description of service
          taxonomies, service orchestrations and a mapping of services to
          operational activities. The service description (NSOV-2) is a key
          component of a Service Oriented Architecture <xref
          linkend="principle6" />. It is used to detach the functionality
          provided by a system (or services provided by an organizational
          unit) from the actual system. A service description includes
          information on how to interact with the service, what requirements a
          system must fulfil if it implements the service and what information
          model the services uses. Within NSOV-2 a SIOP can be depicted as a
          higher-level service interface. The detailed technical specification
          of a SIOP is contained within a Service Interoperability Profile
          (SIP). SIPs are addressed in NTV-1 Technical Standards
          Profile.</para>

          <para>In the <emphasis role="bold">NATO Systems View
          (NSV)</emphasis>, the NSV-1 view is the most important since it
          describes how the different systems interact to fulfil the
          operational needs. The system descriptions should be kept on a
          black-box level, i.e. it is not relevant to describe the internals
          of the systems.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Key Principles</title>

        <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Sovereignty of collaborating
        parties</emphasis></simpara>

        <para>The sovereignty of the collaborating parties is fundamental;
        organizational right to use organic information systems and working
        methodology with various support tools shall in all situations be
        respected. The decision to publish information to the federation is
        the responsibility, and right, of each actor. Information content and
        possible restrictions will always be any actor&rsquor;s sovereign
        decision.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry id="principle1" xreflabel="[Principle_1]">
            <term>[Principle_1]</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Each collaborating party decides which information to
              publish into the federation.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <simpara><emphasis role="bold">View on
        information</emphasis></simpara>

        <para>Information shall be regarded as an operations wide asset and
        not be exclusive to any single operational area or function, with
        exceptions for agreed confidentiality. Collaborating parties should
        avoid over-classification of information. Information should be
        provided as a published service.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry id="principle2" xreflabel="[Principle_2]">
            <term>[Principle_2]</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Information published into the arena is available to all
              parties, if no restrictions have been agreed.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Agreements for Information
        Exchange</emphasis></simpara>

        <para>Agreements to facilitate Information Exchange shall exist for
        the operation and between the collaborating parties. The agreements
        includes which information is required to be exchanged, models for how
        exchanged information shall be structured, how information can be
        translated between models and the format of the exchanged
        information.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry id="principle3" xreflabel="[Principle_3]">
            <term>[Principle_3]</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Requirements, models, translations and format for
              information exchange in the arena are regulated by
              agreements.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Architecture</emphasis></simpara>

        <para>Establishment of a consistent and understandable architecture
        should be supported by a common terminology and a common architecture
        description framework. In order to ensure that the technical
        architecture fully supports the operational needs, there is a need for
        a joint architecture.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry id="principle4" xreflabel="[Principle_4]">
            <term>[Principle_4]</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The operational and technical aspects of the architecture
              are described using a common description framework.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>The architecture of the federation must support exchange of
        information between many heterogeneous systems in order to fit all
        actors&rsquor; needs. A Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) achieves
        this by separating information exchange capabilities from business
        logic and system specific implementations.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry id="principle5" xreflabel="[Principle_5]">
            <term>[Principle_5]</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>The technical architecture for information exchange
              follows the tenets of the Service Oriented Architecture
              concept.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>OASIS (organization) defines Service as "a mechanism to enable
        access to one or more capabilities, where the access is provided using
        a prescribed interface and is exercised consistent with constraints
        and policies as specified by the service description."</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry id="principle6" xreflabel="[Principle_6]">
            <term>[Principle_6]</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Technical services for information exchange are specified
              in a service description.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Technology</emphasis></simpara>

        <para>Open and accepted international standards, both civilian and
        military should be used. Bespoke and proprietary standards shall only
        be considered when it delivers significant higher value.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry id="principle7" xreflabel="[Principle_7]">
            <term>[Principle_7]</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Technical services for information exchange uses open
              standards whenever possible.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Security</emphasis></simpara>

        <para>To achieve information exchange in a secure way using services,
        a set of principles which guides the use of security functions is
        needed:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry id="principle8" xreflabel="[Principle_8]">
            <term>[Principle_8]</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>Service consumers and service providers use a common
              methods for authentication and authorization of users and
              services.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry id="principle9" xreflabel="[Principle_9]">
            <term>[Principle_9]</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>There is a common method to obtain integrity by which a
              service consumer can check that the data sent from another part
              is not changed by a third part.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry id="principle10" xreflabel="[Principle_10]">
            <term>[Principle_10]</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>There is a common method to guarantee the confidentiality
              of the information exchanged. This means that it is possible to
              prevent outsiders from getting access to the information that is
              exchanged.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>It is important to remember that these principles only apply
        between the borders of the actors in the federation, not end-to-end
        between users. The reason for this is that it is very hard and cost
        driving to govern how security mechanisms shall be implemented within
        an actor.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="v6s-infoaspect">
        <title>The information aspect</title>

        <para>In order to meet operational needs for information exchange and
        to build a federation, supported by technical systems serving as
        operational nodes, a number of areas must be addressed:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Information Exchange Requirement specifications</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Information Exchange Models within collaboration areas and
            their relation to international standards, domain Community Of
            Interest (COI) models, semantic structures etc</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Translation specifications and translation mechanisms</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Specification of information exchange mechanisms in the
            federation e.g. common data management services, mediation
            services and bridges to external systems</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>Documenting the above according to <xref linkend="principle3" />
        address issues <xref linkend="issue1" />, <xref linkend="issue2" />,
        <xref linkend="issue4" />, <xref linkend="issue5" />, <xref
        linkend="issue6" /> and <xref linkend="issue9" /> by creating
        agreements of what information is to be exchanged, how to interpret
        the information and which mechanisms are utilised to enable the
        information exchange.</para>

        <para>This chapter covers the definition aspect of information,
        technologies which implement these definitions, like for example
        mediation, are covered in <xref linkend="v6s-solution" />.</para>

        <sect4>
          <title>Information Exchange Requirements</title>

          <para>An Information Exchange Requirement (IER) is a specification
          of the required information exchanged between operational nodes.
          IERs are identified in the business modelling process and specify
          the elements of the user information used in support of a particular
          activity. The specification is done according to the NOV-3 view of
          NAF<xref linkend="dr-mil-ref-naf3" />.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title>Information Exchange Models</title>

          <para>An Information Exchange Model (IEM) is a specification of the
          information which are exchanged between operational nodes. IEMs are
          used when deciding which information objects are to be exchanged in
          service interactions. The specification is done according to the
          NOV-7 view of NAF<xref linkend="dr-mil-ref-naf3" />.</para>

          <para>An IEM is constructed top-down based on model elements from
          other existing Information Models e.g. standards as well as
          bottom-up based on information requirements specifications from
          Operational Concepts and Requirements Implications (OCRI)<xref
          linkend="dr-mil-ref-nisp-vol1v3" />.</para>

          <para>When designing Information Exchange Models several different
          approaches exist:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Model based, e.g. JC3IEDM, ISO19100 series</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Ontology based e.g. Semantic web</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Message based e.g. ADatP-3</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Given the timeframe for this design rule, a model based
          approach is the best approach considering what the technology can
          handle and results from ongoing modelling work. The ontology based
          approach can be adopted at a later stage when the technology and
          methods are more mature while the message based approach is to be
          avoided if possible since it cannot handle the complexity of
          integrated models.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title>Translations</title>

          <para>There may be a large number of translations between two
          information models. Each translation is based on thorough analysis
          and is documented in a translation specification together with
          estimates of information loss.</para>

          <para>There are different approaches to making translations between
          the models:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Manual model mapping, that is when two models are compared
              and decision are made at element level on how to map and/or
              translate to the other models. This is often the case when the
              models to compare are documented according to different
              standards regarding ontological metadata notation, modelling
              style etc.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Rule based model mapping that is when two models are
              compared and mapped to each other based on formalized rules.
              Automated translation has the potential to be applied in
              runtime, thus increasing flexibility in information
              exchange.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Technologies which perform automated translation between
          information models is not yet available to any greater extent.
          Therefore, the translation technologies described in <xref
          linkend="v6s-medserv" /> focuses on supporting translation rules
          which are based on manual model mappings.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title>Information Exchange Objects</title>

          <para>An information object is a set of data elements that are
          contained and treated as one unit. The content structure may vary in
          complexity from the simplest form with a number of data elements and
          an identifier to complex data structures and large quantities of
          data elements. Examples of information objects are documents,
          messages and data sets such as geographical data sets.</para>

          <para>Information objects are created, processed, stored and
          moved/exchanged via services. An information exchange object is a
          standardised view, or an excerpt from, an information exchange model
          which from a technical point of view is suitable to exchange as a
          coherent set. Thus information exchange objects is a subset of all
          information objects which are meant to be exchanged via
          services.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title>Services and the information aspect</title>

          <para>In a Service Oriented Architecture <xref
          linkend="principle5" />, information objects are created, processed,
          stored and moved/exchanged via services. Therefore it is important
          to understand the architectural relationship between services and
          information. I.e. how are services and information specified in
          order to enable the implementation of a service oriented
          architecture.</para>

          <para>As depicted in <xref linkend="v6f-servinfasp" />, a service
          has operations. They are used for specification of how a consumer
          can interact with the service, for example create, read, update,
          delete. An operation requires one or more information objects to be
          exchanged between the consumer and provider, for example a message
          or a document. These exchange objects are excerpts from an
          information exchange model.</para>

          <figure id="v6f-servinfasp">
            <title>Services and the information aspect</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/dr-mil-servinfasp.svg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>Translations are use to describe how information exchange
          models relate to each other and can also be used by mechanisms to
          automatically translate exchange objects from different information
          models. Information exchange requirements are set on service
          operations and exchange objects, i.e. what functionality shall the
          service provide and what information shall it handle.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>The security aspect</title>

        <para>When determining appropriate security solutions for a federation
        it is of outmost importance to analyse the information which needs to
        be assured. This is important in order to avoid a &ldquo;too
        secure&rdquor; solution, thus introducing higher costs and more
        difficult procedures than needed. The flexibility which is introduced
        by the NNEC concept requires a constant analysis of the need for
        information confidentiality, integrity and availability (CIA). Also,
        time needs to be considered in these analyses, i.e. how long does the
        information need to be protected.</para>

        <para>This design rule does not cover how to perform CIA analyses, but
        it is certain that there is a need to be able to handle different
        levels of security in the federation. A set of scenarios has been
        defined in the IEG concept<xref linkend="dr-mil-gwimpl" /> which are
        used in this design rule to handle difference in security
        levels.</para>

        <simpara><emphasis role="bold">The Information Exchange Gateway
        Concept</emphasis></simpara>

        <para>Information Exchange Gateways (IEGs) are used to protect
        information assets of the participants in the federation. Since each
        participant provides an IEG to protect their assets there is a need to
        standardise the services and the architecture of IEGs in order to
        enable sharing of IEG components between the participants and use of
        commercially available technology. The NATO IEG concept<xref
        linkend="dr-mil-gwimpl" /> describes that each IEG has three major
        services:</para>

        <para>&ldquo;The first is the Node Protection Service (NPS). The NPS
        provides protection to the infrastructure; its purpose is to protect
        the physical assets of the &ldquo;node&rdquor; or nation being
        protected by the IEG.&rdquor;</para>

        <para>&ldquo;The second major component/service is the Information
        Protection Service (IPS). NATO and each nation are responsible for
        protecting the flow of information out of its area (node or network).
        The mechanisms used to protect the information flow must satisfy the
        organization (nation or NATO) that the IEG is
        protecting.&rdquor;</para>

        <para>&ldquo;The third major component/service is the Information
        Exchange Service (IES). The IEG must facilitate the flow of
        information between the protected node/network and the external
        organizations that are authorized (by the Information Protection
        Service).&rdquor;</para>

        <para>Together these services provide the solution to issues <xref
        linkend="issue3" />, <xref linkend="issue11" /> and <xref
        linkend="issue12" />. More details on the implementation of IEGs can
        be found in <xref linkend="v6s-infassserv" />.</para>

        <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Information zones</emphasis></simpara>

        <para>Information Zones is a concept identified and defined <!--
   REF 11 --> to achieve confidentiality with high assurance, for a gathering
        of information within a defined perimeter, and interactions to its
        surrounding with a number of services and nodes inside the zone. The
        concept gives the advantage to separate assurance on security
        mechanisms to meet external and internal threats.</para>

        <para>In a federative approach such as the one described in this
        design rule, each federation participant (actor) is to be considered
        as (at least) one information zone. The reason for this is that there
        is a clear responsibility for information and information management
        within each actor. At the border of the information zones there are
        Information Exchange Gateways (IEG) which protects the information
        within the zone and allows controlled sharing of information between
        information zones. See <xref linkend="v6f-fedinfozones" />.</para>

        <figure id="v6f-fedinfozones">
          <title>Informationzones in the federation</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../figures/dr-mil-fedinfozones.svg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The information classification level in each zone will differ
        and therefore the information assurance level needs to be adjusted
        accordingly. I.e. the more sensitive information within a zone, the
        more protection and dissemination control is needed.</para>

        <para>By basing the security on information zones with boundary
        protection and controlled information flow and access to the zone, it
        is made easier to achieve high assurance since only a few mechanisms,
        i.e. the IEG, needs to be inspected/evaluated to meet the security
        requirement.</para>

        <para>In the federation there may be several information zones
        depending on the classification of exchanged information. However, the
        number of information zones should be kept to a minimum in order to
        avoid unnecessary costs and complexity for implementation and
        maintenance of the federation.</para>
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="v6s-techprofiles">
        <title>Technology and profiles</title>

        <para>As mentioned in <xref linkend="v6s-intmilfed" />, there is
        &ldquo;a need to establish a baseline federation agreement which can
        be used as a starting point when creating new missions&rdquor;. The
        technology described in this chapter supports the creation of such an
        agreement by addressing <xref linkend="issue9" /> &gt; &ldquo;Which
        standards, formats and mechanisms for information exchange should be
        used?&rdquor;</para>

        <para>In other terms, the standards, formats and mechanisms defined in
        this chapter shall serve as the baseline for an international military
        federation.</para>

        <para>There are two basic user requirements defined in <xref
        linkend="v6s-problem" /> which acts as drivers for the technology
        defined in this chapter. These requirements are:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>[IER 1]</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>People from the different organisational actors SHALL be
              able to communicate with each other using voice or text
              communication.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>[IER 2]</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>It SHALL be possible to discover and retrieve information
              (i.e. search) provided to the federation by different
              actors.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>To be able to fulfil these requirements, a set of technical
        capabilities are needed. First of all, there must be network (IP)
        connectivity between the actors in the federation; however this is not
        covered by this design rule. Once network connectivity is established,
        the technical systems of the actors need to be able to publish and
        find the services which are to be used. Of course, all communication
        in the federation network must be secured by relevant security
        mechanisms.</para>

        <para>In order to fulfil <xref linkend="ier1" />, users first need to
        be able to find each other and once they have done that they can start
        collaborating.</para>

        <para>To fulfil <xref linkend="ier2" /> the Information Discovery
        Services are used to find relevant information. To retrieve the
        information, Messaging Services can be used. In some cases the
        information models used by the different actors does not match and
        then the Translation Services are used to translate the
        content.</para>

        <para>Lastly, it is important for the actors in the federation to know
        the status of the services in the federation, especially if there are
        mission critical services which are provided by other actors.</para>

        <para>The following chapters describe the above in more detail giving
        advice how to implement the technologies needed to provide these
        services.</para>

        <sect4>
          <title>Discovery services</title>

          <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Service Discovery
          Services</emphasis></simpara>

          <para>The Service registry enables the technical systems to discover
          each other. The service registry is a vital part needed for enabling
          the loose coupling between systems since it provides functionality
          for the systems to find each other , with such registry the
          relationships between the systems does not need to be hard coded
          into the systems. This means that it will be easy to add or remove
          participants and services from the federation.</para>

          <para>The Service registry SHALL be implemented using UDDI v3
          according to NISP<xref linkend="dr-mil-ref-nisp-vol3v3" />. In order
          to achieve high availability and allow each participant to be able
          to publish services, the Service registry shall be implemented using
          a replication pattern. I.e. the service registry is replicated
          between all participants in the federation.</para>

          <para>The Service registry SHALL include the following information
          (metadata):</para>

          <simpara>Service provider</simpara>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Unique id, Name, Description</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <simpara>Service type</simpara>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Unique id, Name, Description, Version</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <simpara>Service instance</simpara>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Unique id, Name, Description,Service interfaces (bindings
              e.g. WSDL) and applicable security mechanisms, Endpoint (e.g.
              URL), Owner - both service provider and human user owning the
              service, Security Classification - UNCLASS, RESTRICTED
              etc</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Information Discovery
          Services</emphasis></simpara>

          <para>Each actor in a federation holds information which might be
          relevant to other actors. Therefore it is of outmost importance that
          there are mechanisms to discover information across actors. These
          mechanisms have to include the capability for an actor to decide
          which information shall be available to others according to <xref
          linkend="principle1" /> and <xref linkend="principle2" />.</para>

          <para>There are mainly two ways of making the information discovery
          happen. One is to copy information between actors and let each actor
          make the information searchable, but this is not very efficient
          since it requires a lot of bandwidth and makes it hard to keep track
          of which information has been copied.</para>

          <para>The other way of enabling information discovery is to use a
          federated search pattern where each actor provides a search
          interface to its information. This is much more efficient from a
          data distribution point of view, but requires that all actors come
          to agreement on the search interface. There are initiatives ongoing
          to standardise the ability to perform federated search, the most
          prominent one is the OpenSearch initiative<footnote>
              <para>http://www.opensearch.org/</para>
            </footnote>. Even though OpenSearch is not a formal standard it is
          well on its way to be adopted by many of the major tool
          vendors.</para>

          <para>In either case, the actors in the federation must implement
          search engines which can index information (if the have any) and
          search clients which can access the search engines. A search client
          is in most cases an ordinary web browser, but can also be a more
          complex application if there are specific needs.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title>Repository Services</title>

          <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Metadata Registry
          Services</emphasis></simpara>

          <para>A metadata registry is a database which contains information
          about information which is useful for enabling information
          discovery. For example, search engines create metadata registries
          when they index content. But there are also other applications for
          metadata registries, like when an actor has sensitive information
          which needs to be able to be discovered. Say that there is a
          database which contains classified analyses of some sort. The
          analyses are of very good quality and can be of use to many, but it
          is impossible to publish them to everyone in the federation. So in
          order to make other actors aware that the analysis exists,
          unclassified analysis metadata, like what the analysis looks at and
          who has done it, can be published in a metadata repository. Now the
          other actors can discover that there is an analysis and contact the
          author to get approval for getting the contents.</para>

          <para>To be able to store the metadata, the NATO Discovery Metadata
          Specification (NDMS) SHALL be used. This specification is based on
          the international standard ISO 15836 the Dublin Core (DC) Metadata
          Element Set.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title>Directory Services</title>

          <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Enterprise Directory
          Services</emphasis></simpara>

          <para>Sharing information about users is key to a federation since
          it enables people to find each other. The user directory holds
          information which enables authentication of users by certificates
          and public keys, authorization of users by roles and discovery of
          users by contact information which enables collaboration.</para>

          <para>Each actor in the network shall provide information about the
          users that represents them. However, it is preferable if the
          federation has one point of access to all user directories.
          Therefore, the implementation of user directories in a federation
          shall follow the federated database pattern. This means that each
          actor provides their own database, but one actor provides a single
          entry point to all databases.</para>

          <para>For the user registry LDAP shall be used according to
          NISP<xref linkend="dr-mil-ref-nisp-vol3v3" />. Products which can
          provide the single entry point to multiple LDAP databases are often
          referred to as Virtual LDAPs.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title>Collaboration Services</title>

          <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Audio based conference
          service</emphasis></simpara>

          <para>For voice communications standards SHALL be applied as
          according to TACOMS<xref linkend="dr-mil-ref-tacoms" />. Streaming
          voice and video communication cannot be handled by the IEGs, TACOMS
          describes how to implement this functionality without the use of
          IEGs.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="v6s-messserv">
          <title>Messaging Services</title>

          <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Server-to-server e-mail messaging
          service</emphasis></simpara>

          <para>E-mail has become one of the most important applications for
          any business or organization of today. The main challenge for using
          e-mail in a federation is to be able to control that no classified
          information is embedded or attached to e-mails going out from an
          actor and protecting the actors from malicious software, such as
          viruses. This means that the IEG needs to be able to scan and filter
          incoming and outgoing messages.</para>

          <para>Extra care needs to be taken for outgoing information where
          confidential information can be hidden in document history and
          inside images. Therefore, only text-based attachments (like
          OpenDocument Format or Office Open XML, see NISP<xref
          linkend="dr-mil-ref-nisp-vol3v3" />) without inserted code or images
          shall be allowed through the IEG.</para>

          <para>It is also vital to have a manual inspection capability in the
          IEG to be able to assess the degree of confidentiality of the e-mail
          messages leaving an actor.</para>

          <para>As described by NISP<xref linkend="dr-mil-ref-nisp-vol3v3" />,
          SMTP according to RFC 2821 and others SHALL be used for e-mail. To
          secure communication between SMTP agents, TLS according to RFC 3207,
          SHOULD be used.</para>

          <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Instant messaging
          service</emphasis></simpara>

          <para>For instant messaging XMPP (IETF RFC3920:2004 -3923:2004)
          SHALL be used according to NISP<xref
          linkend="dr-mil-ref-nisp-vol3v3" />. XMPP is an XML based
          publish/subscribe protocol which is used by most of the dominant
          tool vendors. Using XML enables possibility for inspection and
          control of messages in IEGs which is very important in a
          federation.</para>

          <para>There is one important aspect of XMPP which is not covered by
          the current standard specification; there is no security tagging
          options available which is needed when messages shall be passed
          between information zones with different security classifications.
          So if this is required a custom extension to XMPP needs to be
          defined.</para>

          <para>Another thing which must be considered in a federation is
          routing of messages. Currently there are no XMPP servers which
          support routing of XMPP messages. This consequence of not being able
          to route messages is that the IEG has to be implemented as a
          transparent proxy, i.e. the systems on the outside of the IEG need
          to know about the systems on the inside. Even though the IEG can be
          used for inspection and filtering of messages in this case; it is
          not always a preferred solution from a security perspective. So, if
          the security requirements say that the IEG needs to act as a
          non-transparent proxy, the XMPP server needs to be modified to be
          able to act as an XMPP server and be able to route messages between
          XMPP domains.</para>

          <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Message passing
          service</emphasis></simpara>

          <para>In order to achieve an efficient exchange of information
          between the actors in a federation there is a need to be able to
          route and distribute messages. This type of capability is often
          included in the Enterprise Service Bus (ESB) concept.</para>

          <para>An ESB refers to a software architecture construct,
          implemented by technologies found in a category of middleware
          infrastructure products usually based on Web services standards that
          provides foundational services for more complex service-oriented
          architectures.</para>

          <para>An ESB generally provides an abstraction layer on top of an
          implementation of an Enterprise Messaging System which allows
          integration architects to exploit the value of messaging without
          writing code.</para>

          <para>The ESB shall enable endpoints to interact in their native
          interaction modes through the bus. It shall support a variety of
          endpoint protocols and interaction styles. These interaction
          patterns are the least which shall be supported:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Request/response: Handles request/response-style
              interactions between endpoints. The ESB is based on a messaging
              model, so a request/response interaction is handled by two
              related one-way message flows -- one for the request and one for
              the response.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Request/multi-response: A variant of the above, where more
              than one response can be sent. Is often referred to as a
              subscription pattern.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Event propagation: Events may be anonymously distributed
              to an ESB-managed list of interested parties. Services may be
              able to add themselves to the list.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>When passing messages in the above patterns, the ESB SHALL be
          able to perform the following:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Route: Changes the route of a message, selecting among
              service providers that support the requester's intent. Selection
              criteria can include message content and context, as well as the
              targets' capabilities.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Distribute: Distributes the message to a set of interested
              parties and is usually driven by the subscribers' interest
              profiles.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The ESB SHALL be able to handle the following formats and
          protocols:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>SOAP over HTTP for Web Services</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>JMS for Java messages</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>XMPP for Instant messaging and XML based Publish subscribe
              messaging</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>When implementing the ESB concept in federations there are
          some things which must be considered. First, the products which
          realize the messaging and mediation capabilities needs to be the
          same everywhere since there are very small chances of realizing
          integration between two different products due to a lack of
          standardization. This means that the federation agreement must
          include which product to use.</para>

          <para>Secondly, the management of rules for transformation of
          messages needs to be considered. ESB and messaging products are
          often built for central management of transformation rules, thus
          enabling a better control over the messaging capabilities in an
          enterprise. However, this can be problematic in a federative
          approach since all actors need to agree on the transformation rules
          or appoint one actor which has the authority to manage these.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="v6s-medserv">
          <title>Mediation Services</title>

          <simpara><emphasis role="bold">Translation
          Services</emphasis></simpara>

          <para>Translation is about manipulating messages in-flight between a
          service provider and a consumer (requests or events). This means
          that messages dispatched by a requester are transformed into
          messages understood by a slightly incompatible provider selected
          from a set of potential endpoints.</para>

          <para>Translation services are often considered being a part of the
          ESB concept.</para>

          <para>The patterns which translation products SHALL be able to
          handle are:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Protocol switch</emphasis>: Enables
              service requesters to dispatch their messages using a variety of
              interaction protocols or APIs, such as SOAP/HTTP and JMS.
              Transcodes requests into the targeted service provider's format.
              Can be applied at the requester or the provider end of an
              interaction, at both ends, or anywhere in between.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Transform</emphasis>: Translates the
              message payload (content) from the requester's schema to the
              provider's schema. This may include enveloping, de-enveloping,
              or encryption.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Enrich</emphasis>: Augments the
              message payload by adding information from external data
              sources, such as customization parameters defined by the
              mediation, or from database queries.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Correlate</emphasis>: Derives
              complex events from message or event streams. Includes rules for
              pattern identification and rules that react to pattern
              discovery, for example, by generating a complex event derived
              from content of the triggering event stream.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Also see <xref linkend="v6s-messserv" /> for details in ESB
          implementation.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4 id="v6s-infassserv">
          <title>Information Assurance Services</title>

          <para>As a minimum baseline for IEGs in a federation, the following
          shall be implemented in order to fulfil <xref
          linkend="principle8" />, <xref linkend="principle9" /> and <xref
          linkend="principle10" />:</para>

          <para>The IEGs shall include a Information Protection Service (IPS).
          This shall provide the following services:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Authentication to verify the identity of users and systems
              sending/receiving data</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Authorization to verify rights for users and systems to
              send/receive data</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Content encryption/decryption capabilities to assure
              confidentiality and integrity of the data</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Information dissemination control to be able to control
              which data is passed through the IEG.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>To be able to inspect the data flowing through the IEG, the
          data must be unencrypted. The IEG can send and receive encrypted
          data, but encrypted data must be decrypted by the IEG before it can
          be inspected and decrypted again for further transport.</para>

          <para>The Information Exchange Service (IES) which the IEG shall be
          able to handle is described in the other technology sections of
          <xref linkend="v6s-techprofiles" />.</para>

          <para>The requirements for Node Protection Service (NPS) is not
          determined by this design rule, however some type of node protection
          is always needed. Since this design rule does not cover the
          communication layer, there is a need to create a design rule which
          describes this.</para>
        </sect4>

        <sect4>
          <title>Service Management Services</title>

          <para>Service management can be divided into managing, where the
          technical systems and services are being controlled, and monitoring
          where information regarding the status of the technical systems and
          services are shared.</para>

          <para>In a federation, the participants may be able to managed
          systems and services provided by other participants, but this is
          unlikely due to information responsibility of organizations. I.e. a
          participant which is responsible for the information within its
          information zone will not let another actor have administrative
          privileges to the system where this information resides.</para>

          <para>However, sharing monitoring information between the
          participants is essential if the Service Level Agreements (SLAs)
          shall be fulfilled. These SLAs are included in the agreements for
          information exchange as specified by <xref
          linkend="principle3" />.</para>

          <para>Monitoring information is to be provided using the Simple
          Network Management Protocol version 3 (SNMP v3) standard according
          to NISP<xref linkend="dr-mil-ref-nisp-vol3v3" />. Using a non-XML
          based format for monitoring, like SNMP, will require a special
          filtering engine in the IEG IPS (see chapter <xref
          linkend="v6s-infassserv" />).</para>

          <para>It is important to set the monitoring scope properly when
          implementing the monitoring solution in order to avoid dissemination
          of to much information into the federation. Therefore, monitoring
          information SHALL only be provided regarding the services which are
          provided by an actor. Important metrics to provide monitoring
          information about are:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Availability of services, both past, current and future
              (planned outages)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Performance in the form of response times and
              throughput</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Capacity, like for example maximum number of users or used
              storage space</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>

      <sect3>
        <title>Summary</title>

        <para>To summarize, <xref linkend="v6f-techoverview" /> depicts all
        the technologies mentioned in the chapters above. Together these
        technologies provide the foundation for secure information exchange in
        a multilateral collaboration federation in the NNEC context.</para>

        <figure id="v6f-techoverview">
          <title>Technology Overview</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../figures/dr-mil-techoverview.svg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Rejected solutions</title>

      <para condition="ignore"></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Motivation</title>

    <para>The NATO Network Enabled Capability (NNEC) Feasibility
    Study<footnote>
        <para>EAPC(AC/322)N(2005)0007</para>
      </footnote> highlights that &ldquo;at their meeting in November 2002,
    the NATO C3 Board (NC3B) agreed that there was a need to develop a NATO
    concept to adapt national initiatives such as the U.S. Network Centric
    Warfare (NCW) and the U.K. Network Enabled Capability (NEC) to the NATO
    context. This NATO concept is referred to as (NNEC) &hellip;. The NNEC
    must provide for the timely exchange of secure information, utilising
    communication networks which are seamlessly interconnected, interoperable
    and robust, and which will support the timely collection, fusion, analysis
    and sharing of information&rdquor;.</para>

    <para>One of the key milestones along the route towards realising the NNEC
    strategy has been set out in the NATO Networked Consultation, Command and
    Control Interoperability Policy<footnote>
        <para>AC/322-D(2008)0041 (INV) dated 30 October 20008</para>
      </footnote> refers.</para>

    <para>In particular, the policy states that &ldquo;It is the intent of
    NATO that measures shall be put into effect by the Organisation and by
    individual nations to ensure that information sharing requirements are met
    securely and expeditiously. This intent requires that appropriate
    interoperability solutions and procedures to match IOR over time shall be
    identified/developed with the nations and documented by the
    NC3B.&rdquor;</para>

    <para>This design rule satisfies the above requirement of the NATO
    Networked C3 Interoperability Policy by identifying the high level design
    rules required for exchange of information services.</para>

    <para>Information services are the primary mechanism for information
    interchange in a NATO environment. This is highlighted in the NATO
    Networked C3 interoperability policy: &ldquo;This policy identifies
    NATO&rsquor;s intent for NNC3 interoperability, and identifies the
    principles and responsibilities for ensuring the development and effective
    use of systems to provide interoperable services supporting the sharing of
    information across the physical, information and human
    domains&rdquor;.</para>

    <figure id="v6f-nnec-techreq">
      <title>Evolving C3 Requirements and Technology Trends for NNEC</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../figures/dr-mil-nnec-techreq.svg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Consequences from the solutions</title>

    <para>SOA offers a mechanism for achieving the agility required for NNEC.
    Whereas the current stove-piped way of doing business is rigid and
    difficult to adapt because business functions and the supporting IT are so
    tightly coupled, an SOA exploits newly available software components and
    web standards that can be reconfigured easily and quickly. SOA translates
    capabilities, processes and functions into services which can be invoked
    by a user through an interface. This requires the services to be available
    and the user to know the &ldquo;what, how, how much and when&rdquor; of
    accessing them. How the services work is of no consequence to the user but
    is important to designers and architects. The underlying principles are
    not new, but the web services and related technology to bring it to life
    are; reinforced by their wide acceptance.</para>

    <para>The predominant precept is that SOA is business driven. This puts
    designated defence Process Owners in the driving seat because they place
    requirements for service provision. If SOA is to be successful it means
    that they must truly understand what drives the capability they are
    entrusted to deliver so that they are in a position to inform/drive how it
    can be delivered to users in the most effective and efficient manner
    possible. New technology enables much looser coupling between business
    processes and the IT systems which support them and so overcome one of the
    key drivers of cost in most IT deployments &ndash; tight coupling i.e.
    changes in one area requiring a cascade of other required changes in order
    to work; with familiar cost, time and performance penalties. To support
    this, a high level governance structure is essential to enforce data and
    quality of service standards which enable reuse of services.</para>

    <para>There are many benefits to SOA. They include access to previously
    unavailable information, the design of reusable services, the ability to
    make up new services from existing ones, the ability for businesses to
    make changes without costly IT expenditure, and so on. Moreover, the
    issues subtending from the use of legacy systems and the requirement to
    leverage as much value for money as possible from their continued use,
    becomes much less difficult by adopting a service perspective. For those
    who embrace SOA and see it through, the prospect of a working NNEC becomes
    realisable for the first time.</para>

    <para>SOA is already here and any new major system provided by any one of
    the leading industry vendors is likely to have an SOA capability embedded
    in it. However, it should be noted that the federated model of SOA
    described in this design rule is still an emerging concept which will take
    time to reach maturity.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Examples</title>

    <para>The diagram below shows the concept of federated SOA using a
    simplified model with participants of Organisation A and Organisation B.
    Organisations are required to build SOA enterprise scale systems that
    conform to the NATO Overarching Architecture. The organisations&rsquor;
    SOA are connected in a federated manner providing maximum scalability and
    interoperability.</para>

    <para>The actual physical connection between the SOAs is at the
    communications layer. The point of interconnection is called the Service
    interoperability point (SIOP). The standards used to connect at the SIOP
    are documented in a Service interoperability profile or SIP.</para>

    <para>There are also logical connections at the Core Services layer and
    COI Services layers. These connections also have associated SIPs.</para>

    <para>An example of the Core Services SIOP is currently being investigated
    and demonstrated by UK MOD.<footnote>
        <para>Federated ESB Interoperabilty Specification - version dated 1
        April 2008.</para>
      </footnote></para>

    <para>There is also a logical connection at the COI Services layer. The
    ability to share COI services is where the main benefit is realised as
    these are the business services used to undertake missions. Using the
    guidelines outlined in this design rule, organisations can interoperate by
    sharing COI services to perform business tasks. For example the UK MOD SOA
    pilot project has demonstrated a &ldquo;logistics demand service&rdquor;
    which follows a business process to fulfil a request for a store item or
    spare part.</para>

    <figure id="dr-mil-relSIPandOA">
      <title>Service Interoperability Points and their relationship to the
      Overarching Architecture</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../figures/dr-mil-relSIPandOA.svg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Meta data</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Keywords</title>

      <para>Interoperability, partner, national, international, external,
      interface,</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Associated design rules</title>

      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="5">
	  <colspec colwidth="13*"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="13*"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="48*"/>	  
	  <colspec colwidth="13*"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="13*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry><para>Assoc. #</para></entry>

              <entry><para>DR ID</para></entry>

              <entry><para>DR Product Name &amp; Solution
              Reference</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Release</para></entry>

              <entry><para>Validity</para></entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry><para>1.</para></entry>

              <entry><para></para></entry>

              <entry><para></para></entry>

              <entry><para></para></entry>

              <entry><para></para></entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry><para>2.</para></entry>

              <entry><para></para></entry>

              <entry><para></para></entry>

              <entry><para></para></entry>

              <entry><para></para></entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
</book>
