<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html
          PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
          "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>Introduction</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <h2 class="title">Introduction</h2>
		<p>The NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles (NISP) is
		developed by the NATO Consultation, Command and Control (C3)
		Board Interoperability Profiles Capability Team (IP CaT).</p>

		<p>The included interoperability standards and profiles (Volume 2)
		are <b>mandatory</b> for use in NATO common funded Communications
		and Information Systems (CIS). Volume 3 contains <b>candidate</b>
		standards and profiles.</p>

		<p>In case of conflict between any recommended non-NATO standard and
		relevant NATO standard, the definition of the latter prevails.</p>

    <h3 class="title">Purpose of the NISP</h3>

		<p>NISP gives guidelines to capability planners, programme
		managers and test managers for NATO common funded systems
		in the short or mid-term timeframes.</p>
		<p>The NISP prescribes the necessary technical standards and
		profiles to achieve interoperability of Communications and
		Information Systems in support of NATO's missions and
		operations. In accordance with the Alliance C3 Strategy
		(ref. C-M(2014)0016) all NATO Enterprise (ref. C-M(2014)0061)
		entities shall adhere to the NISP mandatory standards and
		profiles in volume 2.</p>
		<p>Other activities, that assure interoperability within the
		alliance should list their profiles in the NISP.</p>

    <h3 class="title">Intended Audience</h3>
		<p>The intended audience of the NISP are all stakeholders in
		the NATO Enterprise, and Allied and Partner nations involved
		in development, implementation, lifecycle management, and
		transformation to a federated environment.</p>
		<p>There are specific viewpoints that are mapped to the NISP
		structure. NISP gives guidelines to:
    <ul>
      <li><p>capability planners involved in NDPP and NATO led initiatives</p></li>
      <li><p>programme managers for building NATO common funded systems</p></li>
      <li><p>test managers for their respective test events (such as CWIX, CIAV, etc.)</p></li>
      <li><p>national planning and programme managers for their national initiatives</p></li>
    </ul>
		</p>
		<p>Specific NATO or national views to the NISP, based on data export to external
		planning and management systems will be possible upon delivery of the NISP
		Exchange Specification in 2017.</p>

    <h2 class="title">NISP Structure</h2>

    <p>The structure of the NISP is organized to list and categorize the standards
		and profiles according to their usage in NATO. It contains three volumes:</p>

    <ul>
	  	<li><p><a href="volume1/index.html" target="_top">Volume 1</a>: NATO
      Interoperability Standards and Profiles - Introduction: This
		  volume introduces basic concepts, provides the management
  		framework for the configuration control of the NISP and the
		  process for handling Request for Change (RFC). It includes
		  also guidance on development of interoperability profiles.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="volume2/index.html" target="_top">Volume 2: Agreed
		  Interoperability Standards and Profiles</a>: This volume lists
		  agreed interoperability standards and profiles, mandatory for
		  NATO common funded systems. These should support NATO and
		  National systems today and new systems actually under
		  procurement or specification.</p></li>

      <li><p><a href="volume3/index.html" target="_top">Volume 3: Candidate
		  Interoperability Standards and Profiles</a>: This Volume provides
		  Standards and Interoperability Profiles for programmes to start
		  in 1 to 2 years.</p></li>
		</ul>

		<p>Volume 2 is normative for NATO common funded systems and Volume 3 is informative.</p>

	</body>
</html>
