<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE html
          PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Strict//EN"
          "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">

<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <head>
    <title>Introduction</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <h2 class="title">Background</h2>

    <p>The NATO C3 Board Interoperability Profiles Capability Team (IP
    CaT) has developed the attached version of the NATO
    Interoperability Standards and Profiles (NISP) taking into
    account, wherever relevant, national Technical Architecture
    programmes.</p>

    <p>The work undertaken in this development takes into
    consideration the interoperability shortfalls experienced by both
    NATO and the nations. These shortfalls are notably assessed to
    result from an interoperability strategy limited to standards
    adherence only, whilst in large parts ignoring other design and
    implementation considerations. From this viewpoint, NISP aims to
    improve, complement and complete an Open Systems approach, by
    providing architectural building blocks, standards and profile
    recommendations.</p>

    <p>NISP development also tracked the evolution of the
    Communication and Information Technology market where commercial
    aspects have become predominant and Service Oriented Architecture
    approaches have risen to the forefront.</p>

    <p>Against this background, the challenge that the NISP has to
    face is to propose the best trade-off between the two
    complementary approaches in line with NATO requirements:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>COTS-based approach to optimise the cost-effectiveness of
      NATO C3S programmes development;</li>

      <li>Open Systems approach based on an appropriate selection of
      interface standards to adapt to technology advances while
      avoiding any product or vendor lock-in.</li>

      <li>Service Oriented Architecture approach to directly support
      Interoperability in NATO's Network Enabled Capability
      initiatives.</li>
    </ul>

    <h2>Context</h2>

    <p>NATO Policy for Interoperability of C3 systems addresses
    development, from the perspective of achieving specified
    interoperability requirements, on the basis of three architectural
    views: Operational, System and Technical.</p>

    <p>The NISP is intended to contain and describe the capabilities
    and attributes of all procedures, data (standards and products)
    and their relationships necessary to develop the Technical View
    and part of the System View.</p>

    <h2 class="title">NISP Broad Contents</h2>

    <p>In practical terms, the NISP consists of a set of 4
    documents.</p>
      
    <p><a href="volume1/index.html" target="_top">Volume 1: NATO
    Interoperability Standards and Profiles - Introduction and
    Management:</a> This volume deals with the NISP purpose, the
    structure and the process of collecting standards from
    stakeholders, including the configuration management and
    publication of the NISP.</p>
      
    <p><a href="volume2/index.html" target="_top">Volume 2: Agreed
    Standards:</a>This volume lists agreed interoperability
    standards. These shoul support state of-the-art of NATO and
    National systems today and new systems actually under procurement
    or specification. For new systems, it contains near-term standards
    and technologies to support the NNEC Networking and Information
    Infrastructure (NII).</p>

    <p><a href="volume3/index.html" target="_top">Volume 3: Agreed
    Profiles:</a>This Volume provides guidance on the development of
    Interoperability Profiles and references or includes published
    agreed profiles.</p>

    <p><a class="ulink" href="volume4/index.html" target="_top">Volume
    4: Design Rules:</a> This volume provides Design Rule Guidance and
    references.</p>
  </body>
</html>
