<?xml version="1.0"?>
<capabilityprofiles>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>NISP Basic Standards profile</title>
    <servicearea></servicearea>
    <description></description>
    <id>bsp</id>
    <pdf></pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations></locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>X-TMS-SMTP</title>
    <servicearea>Tactical Messaging</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>Defines military header fields to be used for SMTP messages that are gatewayed across military mail
        environment boundaries.</para>
    </description>
    <id>x-tms-smtp</id>
    <pdf>NISP-V2-X-TMS-SMTP</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_MnBRY0pBWDZlX1E</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>FMN Spiral 1.1 Profile</title>
    <servicearea>Federated Mission Networking</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>Defines the Standards Profile for Federated Mission Networking (FMN) Spiral 1. FMN Standards Profiles
        provide a suite of interoperability standards and other standardized profiles for interoperability of selected
        community of interest services, core services and communications services in a federation of mission networks.
        It places the required interoperability requirements, standards and specifications in context for
        FMN Affiliates.</para>
    </description>
    <id>fmn1</id>
    <pdf>NISP-V2-FMN-spiral-1</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_eDNrVy02Wi14V2M</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>FMN Spiral 2 Profile</title>
    <servicearea>Federated Mission Networking</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This document defines the Standards Profile for Federated Mission Networking (FMN) Spiral 2. The FMN
        Standards Profiles provides a suite of interoperability standards and other standardized profiles for
        interoperability of selected community of interest services, core services and communications services
        in a federation of mission networks. It places the required interoperability requirements, standards
        and specifications in context for FMN Affiliates.</para>
    </description>
    <id>fmn2</id>
    <pdf title="FMN Spiral 2 Profile">20170929_FMN_Spiral_2-Standards_Profile</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>FMN Spiral 3 Profile</title>
    <servicearea>Federated Mission Networking</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This document defines the Standards Profile for Federated Mission Networking (FMN) Spiral 3.
        The FMN Standards Profiles provides a suite of interoperability standards and other standardized
        profiles for interoperability of selected community of interest services, core services and
        communications services in a federation of mission networks. It places the required interoperability
        requirements, standards and specifications in context for FMN Affiliates.</para>
    </description>
    <id>fmn3</id>
    <pdf title="FMN Spiral 3 Profile">20181118_Final_FMN_Spiral_3_Standards_Profile_Bundle</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Profile for the Long Term Preservation of NATO Digital Information of Permanent value</title>
    <servicearea>Archive</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>Outlines the file formats and package structures approved by the Archives Committee for the long-term
        preservation of NATO digital information of permanent value.</para>
    </description>
    <id>archive-archive</id>
    <pdf>NISP-V2-archive-profile</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_dzhvZHRGYml2RGc</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE SECURITY SERVICES</title>
    <servicearea>SECURITY SERVICES</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This Service Interface Profile (SIP) describes the key elements that make up the NNEC Core Enterprise
        Services (CES) Security Services.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-sec</id>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.01_SIP</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_czZNSi1aODBxaXc</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE FOR REST SECURITY SERVICES</title>
    <servicearea>REST SECURITY SERVICES</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This specification provides the profile for securing representational state transfer (REST)
      web services (known as RESTful web services) that are deployed within the NNEC web service infrastructure.
      It specifies security requirements that need to be accounted for depending on the environment in which
      the services are being deployed, and the level of assurance required for protecting those services.
      This profile covers the required security protection profile for a Client to access protected resources
      on a Resource Server using REST.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-rest</id>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.02_SIP</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_bl93RTY2RU1waGM</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE FOR SECURITY TOKEN SERVICES</title>
    <servicearea>SECURITY TOKEN SERVICES</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>The purpose of this Service Interface Profile (SIP) is to specify how the security token service
      component of the Core Enterprise Services (CES) Security Services may be called.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-token</id>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.03_SIP</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_b1g1YWV2NmdXdG8</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE FOR POLICY ENFORCEMENT POINTS</title>
    <servicearea>POLICY ENFORCEMENT POINTS</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>The purpose of this Service Interface Profile (SIP), which should be read along with the
        Agency Directive 06.05.04.02.H 2, "Service Interface Profile for Security Services"
        [NCIA AD 06.05.04.02.H], is to specify how services may be called that are protected by
        the Core Enterprise Services (CES) Security Services.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-policy-enforce</id>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.04_SIP</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_b3hEeWNlWXZlVjA</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE FOR ENTERPRISE DIRECTORY SERVICES</title>
    <servicearea>ENTERPRISE DIRECTORY SERVICES</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>The purpose of this Service Interface Profile (SIP) is to specify the interface of the
        directory service itself.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-entr-dir</id>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.05_SIP</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_NmMxNy1YR09kUms</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE FOR MESSAGING</title>
    <servicearea>MESSAGING</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This specification provides the interface control for simple object access protocol (SOAP)
        web services that are deployed within the NNEC web service infrastructure.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-mesg</id>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.06_SIP</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_alE0NjdxUm9kUE0</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE FOR REST MESSAGING</title>
    <servicearea>REST MESSAGING</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This specification provides the profile for securing representational state transfer (REST)
        web services (known as RESTful web services) that are deployed within the NNEC web service infrastructure.
        This covers only the call from a Web Service Consumer to a Web Service Provider using REST, and the
        response from the service provider. It includes how the message must be structured and the elements
        that must be contained within the call.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-rest-msg</id>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.07_SIP</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_a0gxYTg2Wnp5ZzA</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE FOR PUBLISH-SUBSCRIBE SERVICES</title>
    <servicearea>PUBLISH-SUBSCRIBE SERVICES</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This document gives directives along with clarifications and amendments to the [OASIS
        WS-BaseNotification, 2006] and [OASIS WS-BrokeredNotification, 2006] specification on how to
        implement a notification broker/subscription manager to promote interoperability between
        the publish/subscribe engines and generic message subscribers. Some extensions to the protocol
        have been introduced in order to meet NATO requirements.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-pubsub</id>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.08_SIP</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_ek4xY0pwRFdTVWs</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE FOR PUBLISH-SUBSCRIBE NOTIFICATION BROKER WITH SUBSCRIPTION MANAGER</title>
    <servicearea>PUBLISH-SUBSCRIBE NOTIFICATION BROKER WITH SUBSCRIPTION MANAGER</servicearea>
    <description>
            <para>This document is part of a Service Interface Profile (SIP) for Publish/Subscribe Core Enterprise Services (CES) and should be read together with the main document [NCIA AD 06.05.04.02.E]. It gives guidance on implementation of a WS-Notification compliant notification broker. It is REQUIRED that each notification broker implementation also includes the subscription manager functionality.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-pubsub-notif-brooker</id>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.09_SIP</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_WlZja1FDQlRzMm8</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE FOR PUBLISH-SUBSCRIBE NOTIFICATION CONSUMER</title>
    <servicearea>PUBLISH-SUBSCRIBE NOTIFICATION CONSUMER</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This document is part of a Service Interface Profile (SIP) for publish/subscribe
        Core Enterprise Services (CES) and should be read together with the main document
        "Service Interface Profile for Publish/Subscribe Services" [NCIA AD 06.05.04.02.E].
        It gives guidance on implementation of a WS-Notification-compliant notification consumer.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-pubsub-notif-consumer</id>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.10_SIP</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_OVl0NWhWOXdtUmc</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE FOR A NOTIFICATION CACHE SERVICE</title>
    <servicearea>A NOTIFICATION CACHE SERVICE</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This Service Interface Profile (SIP) describes the key eleme nts that make up the NNEC Core
        Enterprise Services (CES) Notification Cache service. It describes and profiles the operations
        which a Notification Cache service offers together with the associated message formats, and serves
        as a template and guideline for implementations.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-notif-cache</id>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.11_SIP</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_a0IzanZCQ2FPOWc</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE FOR BASIC COLLABORATION SERVICES</title>
    <servicearea>BASIC COLLABORATION SERVICES</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This Collaboration Service Interface Profile (SIP) is focused on instant messaging and is based
        on the extensible messaging and presence protocol (XMPP).</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-bcs</id>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.12_SIP</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_LUdkbFNCdWR6eEE</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE FOR CORE AND ADVANCED INSTANT MESSAGING COLLABORATION SERVICES</title>
    <servicearea>CORE AND ADVANCED INSTANT MESSAGING COLLABORATION SERVICES</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This document specifies the Service Interface Profile (SIP) for a number of instant messaging
        services that can be implemented and used by any XMPP entity (XMPP Client or XMPP Server) on the XMPP network.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-mesg-col-serv</id>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.13_SIP</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_dmdUc05WRWxzNVk</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>SERVICE INTERFACE PROFILE FOR GEOSPATIAL SERVICES – MAP RENDERING SERVICE</title>
    <servicearea>GEOSPATIAL SERVICES – MAP RENDERING SERVICE</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This document gives guidance on the implementation of a Map Rendering Service, being a special
        kind of a Geospatial Service.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-geo-mrs</id>
    <pdf>AI_TECH_2016.06.02.14_SIP</pdf>
    <docinfo></docinfo>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_R1h5LURTcWJJS28</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Service Interface Profile for Recognized Air Picture Data</title>
    <servicearea>Recognized Air Picture Data Services</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This Service Interface Profile provides detailed information, guidance, instructions, standards and criteria
        to define the minimum set of data elements that are required to be available for operational or technical
        reasons so that correctly formatted technical message can be generated to establish a Recognized Air Picture
        in a federated environment.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-recognized-air-picture-data</id>
    <pdf title="FMN Spiral 3 Profile including SIP for RAPD">20181118_Final_FMN_Spiral_3_Standards_Profile_Bundle</pdf>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Service Interface Profile for Service Management and Control</title>
    <servicearea>Service Management Services</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This Service Interface Profile provides guidance and technical details to the procedures,
        supporting services, infrastructure and data attributes required to implement Service Management and Control
        (SMC) services in Mission Networks. As such, this document contributes to the establishment of
        capabilities in support of Federated Mission Networking (FMN) as an affordable, effective and efficient
        means to enable sharing of information in a coalition environment.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-for-smc</id>
    <pdf title="FMN Spiral 3 Profile including SIP for SMC">20181118_Final_FMN_Spiral_3_Standards_Profile_Bundle</pdf>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Service Interface Profile for Transport Layer Security</title>
    <servicearea>Transport Layer Security</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This Service Interface Profile (SIP) provides detailed information, guidance, instructions, standards and
        criteria to be used as a  for the usage of Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol to provide authentication,
        confidentiality and integrity services for protecting the communication between a consumer and a provider.
        This publication is a living document and will be periodically reviewed and updated to reflect technology developments,
        emerging best practices, evolving standards and new or deprecated cryptographic schemes
        and algorithms.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-for-tls</id>
    <pdf title="FMN Spiral 3 Profile including SIP for TLS">20181118_Final_FMN_Spiral_3_Standards_Profile_Bundle</pdf>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Service Interface Profile for Web Applications</title>
    <servicearea>Web Applications</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This Service Interface Profile (SIP) provides detailed information, guidance, instructions, standards and
        criteria to be used for development, delivery and consumption of Web applications and dynamic Web sites.
        This publication is a living document and will be periodically reviewed and updated to reflect technology
        developments and emerging best practices.</para>
    </description>
    <id>sip-for-web-apps</id>
    <pdf title="FMN Spiral 3 Profile including SIP for Web Apps">20181118_Final_FMN_Spiral_3_Standards_Profile_Bundle</pdf>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Cryptographic Artefact Binding Profiles</title>
    <servicearea>Cryptographic Services</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>Profile the use of cryptographic protocols, which can be used to implement support for different
        cryptographic techniques and mechanisms, for generating cryptographic artefacts to be stored in
        a cryptographic binding.</para>
    </description>
    <id>binding-crypto-v2</id>
    <pdf>TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed</pdf>
    <docinfo>Annex A</docinfo>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP) Binding Profile</title>
    <servicearea>Informal Messaging Services</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This profile specifies the mechanism for binding metadata to Internet Email (both formal and informal)
        including MIME entities.</para>
    </description>
    <id>binding-smtp-v2</id>
    <pdf>TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed.pdf</pdf>
    <docinfo>Annex B</docinfo>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Extensible Message and Presence Protocol (XMPP) Binding Profile</title>
    <servicearea>XMPP Services</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>Confidentiality metadata labels can be supported in XMPP stanzas as indicated by XEP-0258 whereby
        a mechanism for carrying Enhanced Security Services (ESS) Security labels is standardized.
        This profile extends the XEP-0258 specification to support carrying an Embedded or Detached BDO for
        Message stanzas. This profile supports the XMPP use cases for one-to-one instant messaging
        and multi-user chat.</para>
    </description>
    <id>binding-xmpp-v2</id>
    <pdf>TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed</pdf>
    <docinfo>Annex C</docinfo>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Office Open XML (OOXML) Formats Binding Profile</title>
    <servicearea>Metadata Services</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This profile for the OOXML describes how metadata can be maintained.</para>
    </description>
    <id>binding-ooxml-v2</id>
    <pdf>TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed</pdf>
    <docinfo>Annex D</docinfo>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Simple Object Access Protocol (SOAP) Binding Profile</title>
    <servicearea>SOAP Services</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This profilesupports for both SOAP 1.1 and SOAP 1.2. To support information sharing between partners
        it may be necessary to locate a Binding Data Object (BDO) in the SOAP protocol layer. Metadata may be
        bound to the whole data object (SOAP message) or may be bound to subsets of the SOAP message
        (data object(s) in the SOAP body). In an environment where data objects must have bound metadata,
        the resource identified in the URI will already contain a BDO (detached, encapsulating or embedded).</para>
    </description>
    <id>binding-soap</id>
    <pdf>TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed</pdf>
    <docinfo>Annex E</docinfo>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Representational State Transfer (REST) Profile</title>
    <servicearea>REST Services</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This profile defines a generic packaging mechanism, based upon the Open Packaging Container (OPC)
        defined in ISO/IEC 29500-2:2008, to associate any arbitrary file that do not use the Office Open XML
        (OOXML) format or have no specific profile for supporting the Binding Information with their own
        file format.</para>
    </description>
    <id>binding-rest-v2</id>
    <pdf>TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed</pdf>
    <docinfo>Annex F</docinfo>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Generic Open Packaging Convention (OPC) Binding Profile</title>
    <servicearea>Generic Packaging Services</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This profile defines a generic packaging mechanism, based upon the Open Packaging Container (OPC)
        defined in ISO/IEC 29500-2:2008, to associate any arbitrary file that do not use the Office Open XML
        (OOXML) format or have no specific profile for supporting the Binding Information with their own
        file format.</para>
    </description>
    <id>binding-generic-v2</id>
    <pdf>TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed</pdf>
    <docinfo>Annex G</docinfo>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Sidecar Files Binding Profile</title>
    <servicearea>Sidecar Services</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>Sidecar files allow the association of metadata with a data object for which there is no profile.</para>
    </description>
    <id>binding-sidecar-v2</id>
    <pdf>TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed</pdf>
    <docinfo>Annex H</docinfo>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Extensible Metadata Platform (XMP) Binding Profile</title>
    <servicearea>XMP Services</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This Binding Profile for XMP describes how metadata should be incorporated within an XMP packet
        as a structured value.</para>
    </description>
    <id>binding-extensible-v2</id>
    <pdf>TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed</pdf>
    <docinfo>Annex I</docinfo>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Web Service Messaging Profile Binding Profile</title>
    <servicearea>WSMP Services</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>The Web Service Messaging Profile (WSMP) defines a set of service profiles to exchange
        arbitrary XML-based messages. WSMP is extensible and may be used by any Community of Interest
        (COI). This profile supports the requirement to explicitly bind metadata to data (or subsets thereof)
        whereby the data is XML-based and exchanged between service consumers and service providers using
        the WSMP message wrapper mechanism.</para>
    </description>
    <id>binding-wsmp-v2</id>
    <pdf>TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed</pdf>
    <docinfo>Annex J</docinfo>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>XML Artifacts Profile</title>
    <servicearea>Common XML artefacts 2.0</servicearea>
    <description>
      <para>This profile supports the requirement to bind metadata to data (or subsets thereof) whereby
        the data is XML-encoded in one of the following schemas: XML Schema, ISO Schematron, XML Stylesheet,
        Generic Codelist, Context/Value Assosiation or Security Policy Information File.</para>
    </description>
    <id>binding-common-xml</id>
    <pdf>TN-1491_Edition2-Binding_Profiles_v1.0-Signed</pdf>
    <docinfo>Annex K</docinfo>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <!--
  <capabilityprofil e>
    <title>FMN Spiral 2 Profile (Candidate)</title>
    <id>fmn2-2017-03-21</id>
    <pdf>Proposed FMN Spiral 2 Standards Profile</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_RTBqQ25FZ1VjMkU</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Cryptographic Artefact Binding Profiles</title>
    <id>binding-crypto-v1</id>
    <pdf>Cryptographic_Artefacts_Binding_Profilesv1.0</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_NXdUT0NmZ2V5aWM</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Extensible Message and Presence Protocol (XMPP) Binding Profile</title>
    <id>binding-xmpp-v1</id>
    <pdf>Extensible_Message_and_Presence_Protocol_Binding_Profilev1.0</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_ZV9haWs2R0dLTE0</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Extensible Metadata Platform (XMP) Binding Profile</title>
    <id>binding-extensible-v1</id>
    <pdf>Extensible_Metadata_Platform_Binding_Profilev1.0</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_MXZuRnk0ekdqRFk</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Generic Open Packaging Convention (OPC) Binding Profile</title>
    <id>binding-generic-v1</id>
    <pdf>Generic_Open_Packaging_Convention_Binding_Profilev1.0</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_MktCb0ZSQjllZGc</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Profiles for Binding Metadata to a Data Object</title>
    <id>binding-metadata</id>
    <pdf>Introduction_to_Binding_Profile_Set</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_dHFYZUhzR1p4TzA</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Office Open XML (OOXML) Formats Binding Profile</title>
    <id>binding-ooxml-v1</id>
    <pdf>Office_Open_XML_Binding_Profilev1.0</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_c3N4LVNSSnpmTXM</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Representational State Transfer (REST) Profile</title>
    <id>binding-rest-v1</id>
    <pdf>Representational_State_Transfer_Protocol_Binding_Profilev1.0</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_ZU5TMFJkRmRXMEk</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Sidecar Files Binding Profile</title>
    <id>binding-sidecar-v1</id>
    <pdf>Sidecar_Files_Binding_Profilev1.0</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_eWhMTFlKUEpqY2M</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol (SMTP) Binding Profile</title>
    <id>binding-smtp-v1</id>
    <pdf>Simple_Mail_Transfer_Protocol_Binding_Profilev1.0</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_YUp1VU1qODJFeEk</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  <capabilityprofile>
    <title>Simple Object Access Protocol (SOAP) Binding Profile</title>
    <id>binding-soap-v1</id>
    <pdf>Simple_Object_Access_Protocol_ Binding_Profilev1.0</pdf>
    <locations>
      <location name="googledrive">https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B6B3JkLK_Va_a05mZ2NpTXVPTE0</location>
    </locations>
  </capabilityprofile>
  -->
</capabilityprofiles>
