<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 6 -   A N N E X - B
*****************************************************************  
-->
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v6b-NEC">
  <title>NATO, National and Industry NEC Implementation Approaches</title>
  <sect1 id="v1s1-int-nnee">
    <title>NATO Network Enabled Efforts</title>
    <sect2 id="v1s2-act">
      <title>Transformational Areas</title>
      <para>In August 2004 the NATO Strategic Commanders described the
      following framework for transformation shown in <xref linkend="v1f2-framework" /> which is structured around Transformation
      Goals and Objectives. A central tenet of this Bi-Strategic Command
      (Bi-SC) strategic vision is that future operations will be effects-based
      in that they will involve all instruments of Alliance power, political,
      diplomatic, economic and military, exercised in an integrated fashion to
      create a desired effect in order to achieve a strategic objective.
      Regarding the transformation goals, NATO must be able to achieve
      Coherent Effects, Decision Superiority and Joint Deployment and
      Sustainment. In order to achieve these goals, the NNEC Vision &amp;
      Concept identified specific areas where NATO needs to conduct research
      and develop concepts to improve capabilities. These are entitled
      Transformation Areas. NNEC is one of them and is seen as a key enabler
      to nearly all the others.</para>
      <figure id="v1f2-framework" float="0">
        <title>Framework for Transformation</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/v1-framework.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-NNEC">
        <title>NATO Network Enabled Capability (NNEC) Feasibility
        Study</title>
        <para>In November 2002 the NATO C3 Board (NC3B) agreed that there was
        a need to develop NATO NEC. NNEC is based on adapting national
        initiatives like the U.S. Network Centric Warfare (NCW) and the UK
        Network Enabled Capability (NEC).</para>
        <para>In January 2004, 12 Nations, through the NC3B, sponsored the
        NNEC Feasibility Study. Version 1.0 of the Feasibility Study was
        delivered to the sponsoring nations and version 2.0 was delivered to
        all NATO nations in October 2005. In December 2005 the NC3B endorsed
        the NNEC Feasibility Study recommendations and its release to Partners
        and industry.</para>
        <para>The aims of the Feasibility Study are listed below:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Support further development of the NNEC concept</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Identify types of C2ISR capabilities required to enable NATO
            Network Centric Operations</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Develop a strategy and roadmap for realization of a
            Networking and Information Infrastructure (NII)</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Key conclusions in the Feasibility Study included the need for a
        highly interconnected CIS to support future operational needs of the
        Alliance; and the need for a NII based on a federation of NATO and
        National systems. The NISP must be structured to support the
        development of the NII.</para>
        <para>Another major conclusion of the NNEC FS is that change is a
        constant. In order to make change manageable a model for NNEC Maturity
        Levels has been developed along the structure of four maturity stages.
        The NISP must be restructured to align with these stages. As a first
        step alignment with four stages was not yet feasible.</para>
        <para>The NNEC FS also concluded that the required flexibility for
        federating NATO and national systems into an NII can only be reached
        by adopting the service-oriented approach. In practice, this leads to
        a need for identification of a coherent and comprehensive services
        framework, including strict interface definitions. The framework
        should be provided as a result from architecture work (typically
        Overarching Architecture). The solution patterns for services and
        interface definitions need to be developed using time-phased standards
        and technology profiles. Again the NISP needs to be structured to
        provide the required inputs to this process.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-NII-FOS">
        <title>Networking and Information Infrastructure / Federation of
        Systems</title>
        <para>The Networking and Information Infrastructure (NII) strategy
        assumes that the NII will be implemented as a Federation of Systems
        (FoS), involving the use of Service Oriented Architectures
        (SOAs).</para>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-NII">
          <title>Networking and Information Infrastructure (NII)</title>
          <para>The NII can be viewed as an evolving, multi national military
          "Intranet" - a "Federation-of-Systems" (FoS) - interoperating
          seamlessly to provide information to anyone, anywhere, anytime; if
          appropriately authorised. Similar to the Internet-driven Information
          Age transformation that is occurring world-wide, so will the NII
          support the transformation of mission capabilities of NATO nations,
          NATO, and coalition partners. The NII can be defined as:
          "<emphasis>A federation of systems, formed by the synergistic
          amalgamation of a dynamic set of globally interconnected,
          multi-national, autonomous systems, each comprised of networking and
          information infrastructure components, providing information
          capabilities, associated processes, and personnel for collecting,
          processing, storing, disseminating and managing information to
          authorised users on demand, on an end-to-end
          basis.</emphasis>"</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-perspectives">
          <title>Perspectives</title>
          <para>The NII can be looked at from three points of view.</para>
          <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
            <listitem>
              <para>At a conceptual level the NII captures the vision of the
              future shared information environment for NATO nations, NATO,
              and coalition partners.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>At the planning level, the NII architecture defines the
              structure of NII systems and components, their relationships,
              and the principles and guidelines governing their design,
              operation and evolution over time. The NII Architecture is used
              to determine interoperability and capability requirements,
              advance the use of commercial standards, accommodate
              accessibility and usability requirements, and implement security
              requirements both within NATO and between federated
              systems.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>At the physical level and in the day-to-day environment,
              the NII will provide information and communication services
              vital to the effective conduct activities and is the foundation
              for allowing NATO nations and NATO to achieve their network
              enabled capabilities.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-C-and-O">
          <title>Composition and Ownership</title>
          <para>It is thought that the NII will be comprised of both owned and
          leased communication an computing systems, information services,
          software, data, security services, and other associated capabilities
          necessary to achieve Information Superiority for the Nations and
          organisations contributing to the NII. The NII includes service
          interfaces between participants including NATO nations, NATO
          agencies, coalition partners, and non-NATO users including potential
          participation from Non-Governmental Organisations (NGOs), civilian
          police, emergency services, and local governmental groups. The NII
          provides capabilities from all operating locations (e.g. government
          facilities, headquarters, posts, camps, stations, facilities, mobile
          platforms, deployed sites, and agencies).</para>
          <para>The NII will also be made of service-based systems provided by
          multiple sovereign nations as well as NATO itself and will operate
          on a co-operative basis. It encompasses not only the physical and
          personnel resources necessary to plan, implement, and operate the
          actual infrastructure, but also includes the necessary agreed
          processes to ensure continued coherent evolution and effectiveness
          of the NII. The infrastructure will be a dynamic heterogeneous
          entity with configuration changing with the environment and
          technological advances. This environment is considerably different
          from a national-only environment and will therefore require greater
          emphasis on standardisation and interoperability, not only for
          equipment but also in management methodologies including Service
          Level Agreement (SLA) management.</para>
          <para>Inclusion of a service-based system within the NII does not
          imply ownership or control by any entity other than the contributor.
          Contributed systems are independently managed and controlled by
          their owners within the framework of the Federation-of-Systems
          (FoS), which is a concept explained later in the Chapter. However
          inclusion of a system within the NII does imply that the
          contribution will comply with agreed NII community policies,
          security requirements, and procedures.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-Strategy-NII">
          <title>Strategy for the Networking and Information Infrastructure
          (NII)</title>
          <para>The strategy for developing the networking and information
          sharing aspects of NNEC focuses on the 'joining together' of
          networking systems and core information systems from NATO and NATO
          nations, to form a Federation-of-Systems (FoS) capability that
          implements the NII. The FoS concept is used here to refer to a set
          of different systems, which are not centrally managed, but are so
          connected or related so as to produce results beyond those
          achievable by the individual systems alone. In effect, the NII is to
          be made up of a combination of national Networking and Information
          Infrastructures segments and a NATO Networking and Information
          Infrastructure (NNII), which together will provide capabilities that
          no one system can provide by itself. The need for the NII is
          consistent with the tenets of NNEC, which have evolved from earlier
          concepts<footnote><para>Network Centric Warfare : developing and leveraging
              information superiority /David S. Alberts, John J. Garstka,
              Frederick P. Stein. p. cm. -- (CCRP publication series) Includes
              bibliographical references.ISBN 1-57906-019-6</para></footnote>, which are outlined below:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>A robustly networked force improves information
              sharing.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Information sharing enhances the quality of information
              and shared situational awareness.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Shared situational awareness enables collaboration and
              self-synchronisation, and enhances sustainability and speed of
              command.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>These, in turn, dramatically increase mission
              effectiveness.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-FoS">
          <title>Federation-of-Systems (FoS)</title>
          <para>Definition and term: <emphasis role="bold">Federation-of-Systems (FoS)</emphasis>: <emphasis>A
          Federation-of-Systems is a System-of-systems but one managed without
          central authority Constituent systems are independently managed and
          have a purpose of their own.</emphasis></para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-FoSApproach">
          <title>Federation-of-Systems Approach</title>
          <para>The strategy for developing the networking and information
          sharing aspects of NNEC focuses on the "joining together" of
          networking systems and core information systems from NATO and NATO
          nations, to form a Federation-of-Systems (FoS) capability that
          implements the NII. The FoS concept is used here to refer to a set
          of different systems, which are not centrally managed, but are so
          connected or related so as to produce results beyond those
          achievable by the individual systems alone. In effect, the NII is to
          be made up of a combination of national Networking and Information
          Infrastructures segments and a NATO Networking and Information
          Infrastructure (NNII), which together will provide capabilities that
          no one system can provide by itself.</para>
          <para>The Internet is the best known example today of a
          Federation-of-Systems. There is no central control, and
          participation is through collaboration and co-operation to meet the
          objectives of the federation. A FoS is characterised by a greater
          degree of autonomy, heterogeneity, and distribution than is found in
          a system-of-systems (SoS) approach, which also involves the "joining
          together" of systems, but allows for a degree of centralised
          control. Although it is thought that the NII will operate as a FoS,
          it is also possible that there may be times when nations may wish to
          allow for the centralised management of segments of their systems,
          in order to meet shared operational objectives. It is important that
          the implementation of the NII allow for this possibility.</para>
          <para>The need to support national autonomy in the implementation
          and operation of the NII forces the adoption of participation models
          capable of supporting a flexible, adaptable approach to
          participation in the NII. It is clear that the successful
          implementation of the NII will require architectures, technical
          solutions, and operational procedures beyond that which any single
          nation will require or can provide.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-SOA">
          <title>Service Oriented Architecture</title>
          <para>Definition and term: <emphasis role="bold">Service Oriented
          Architecture (SOA)</emphasis>: <emphasis>An architecture within
          which functions are defined as independent services with
          well-defined interfaces which can be called separately or in defined
          sequences to form business processes. The interface is the focus and
          is defined in terms of the required parameters and the nature of the
          result when the service is invoked. A SOA enables services to be
          published, discovered and utilized.</emphasis></para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-Strategy-FutureC3">
          <title>Strategy for Future C3 Capabilities</title>
          <para>The strategy for developing future C3 capabilities is based on
          the Capability-Based Planning (CBP) approach. A capabilities-based
          paradigm focuses more on how an adversary might fight than on who
          the adversary might be and where a war might occur. It requires us
          to identify capabilities that military forces will need to deter and
          defeat a particular type of adversary. This approach involves a
          functional analysis of operational requirements, leading to the
          identification of capabilities required to accomplish a mission.
          Once the required capability inventory is defined, the most cost
          effective and efficient options to satisfy these requirements are
          sought. This process involves the mapping of operational capability
          requirements to a supporting set of system functional requirements,
          which identifies the system capabilities required to support a
          mission.</para>
          <para>The CBP methodology builds on the CBP approach introduced as
          part of the 2003 NATO Defence Requirements Review processes and the
          CBP planning approach used within the NATO Overarching Architecture
          and provides a new approach to conducting NATO C3 planning.</para>
          <para>While the concept of CBP is key to the identification of
          required system functionality, the concept of Service Oriented
          Architectures (SOAs) is key to meeting those requirements and is an
          essential part of the overall strategy.</para>
          <para>SOAs provide a flexible modular approach for implementing
          system functional requirements in the form of services. This
          strategy for developing future C3 capabilities responds to the need
          to for a flexible, modular approach for meeting future Consultation
          and C2 requirements.</para>
          <para>The use of SOAs has emerged as a major trend within the
          commercial sector and among nations developing NNEC type
          capabilities, because of the flexibility they provide in sharing
          information and information processing capabilities. SOAs provide
          mechanisms for using existing information services as well as
          providing a basis for developing new more advanced information
          services, utilising existing services. Such mechanisms will allow
          many Consultation and C2 needs to be satisfied by linking together
          existing information services in a modular, flexible fashion that
          can be readily adapted to changing operational needs. The
          flexibility provided through the use of SOAs is particularly well
          suited to supporting the needs of coalition based Network-Centric
          Operations.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-Key-info">
          <title>Key Information and Integration Elements</title>
          <para>The Information and Integration component of the NII is
          characterised by the use of Service Oriented Architectures to expose
          software functions as consumable services that can be discovered and
          invoked across the network. The use of SOAs ease application and
          data sharing and provide a flexible mechanism for reusing existing
          services to enable the development of new, value-added information
          services.</para>
          <para>A primary goal of the SOA approach is to make information
          resources available to all consumers on the network and support the
          efficient discovery and delivery of that information to the
          consumer.</para>
          <para>The use of the SOA approach requires that we adopt a common
          Net-Centric Data strateg to ensure that we make information visible,
          accessible, understandable and interoperable with other sources of
          information. Trusting the information we get and trusting that the
          information we supply will be handled correctly will be a key
          success factor. The ability to provide flexible, secure, role-based,
          information access that can be quickly configured to support
          changing policy is foundational to the long-term success of the
          NII.</para>
          <para>Realising the benefits of the SOA approach will require that
          we agree on a standardised set of foundational services covering
          such areas as service discovery security, metadata management,
          identify management, service management and mediation.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-SOA-loose">
          <title>SOA, Loose Coupling and Federated Services</title>
          <para>The need for improved system interoperability is clearly
          spelled out in the latest versions of the NATO Interoperability
          Management Plan (NIMP) and NATO Architecture Framework (NAF).</para>
          <para>In order to achieve the principle of flexible
          interoperability, a change of focus is required: from the idea of
          standalone, stovepipe systems (i.e. platform-oriented) to the idea
          of shareable, universal information (i.e. service-oriented).</para>
          <para>This "service oriented" architectural view indicates that
          rather than information being inextricably tied to a particular
          system, it should be available to all who need it (and have rights
          to it). Information would still have "consumers" and "producers" but
          the assignment of these roles would be dynamic and would cross
          system boundaries.</para>
          <para>The guiding principle of information services is the adoption
          of service oriented architecture (SOA) and where appropriate, the
          implementation of web services.</para>
          <para>A simple definition of an SOA is "a broad set of concepts that
          enable units of functionality to be provided and consumed as
          'services'. This essentially simple concept can and should be used,
          not just for web services, but also at each tier of the
          architecture, in order to compartmentalise and provide flexibility".
          For example, an SOA allows the use of 'thin clients' by tailoring
          the provided services to the needs and capabilities of a consumer.
          This allows a more flexible use of hardware resources and is more
          cost-effective (i.e. a reduced number of software licenses).</para>
          <para>In an SOA, loosely coupled systems view one another as
          "services", accessible via a standard interface without knowledge of
          the underlying implementation of the service. A "registry" manages
          and directs the interactions between services. Data is exchanged in
          a common format using standard protocols, which helps to ensure
          compatibility. All this allows user-to-system or direct
          system-to-system interactions that have not previously been
          generally feasible.</para>
          <para>The concept of every system viewing others as "services" in a
          loosely coupled manner is coherent with the concept of NNEC being a
          FoS. From an SOA perspective, it means that IIS is to be thought of
          as a federation of services, where any NATO or national information
          system will be autonomous and provide specific services by means of
          implementing a standardised service interface.</para>
          <para>Thus, it will be necessary not only to define the standards to
          regulate the implementation of such interfaces but also a set of
          service interoperability points that will facilitate the
          interoperation of similar ser ices provided by different nations in
          a seamless manner.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-NNEC-SF">
        <title>NNEC Strategic Framework</title>
        <para>In June 2005 the Military Committee tasked Allied Command
        Transformation (ACT) to develop the NNEC Strategic Framework as a
        means of describing NNEC developmental activities. The Strategic
        Framework will consist of the following documents: NNEC Vision and
        Concept, NNEC Roadmap(s), NNEC Business Case(s), Compendium of NNEC
        related Architectures, and detailed Plan. Although the NNEC
        Feasibility Study was not identified as Strategic Framework document,
        it is recognized as providing the technical foundation for NNEC
        through the NII. The development of the Strategic Framework is
        depicted in <xref linkend="v1f3-nnec-sf" /> below.</para>
        <figure id="v1f3-nnec-sf" float="0">
          <title>NNEC Strategic Framework</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/v1-nnec-sf.svg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="v1s1-National-NEE">
    <title>National Network Enabled Efforts</title>
    <para>As stated previously NNEC is based on national initiatives. Many
    NATO and Partner Nations have initiated network enabled programs in their
    respective nations. NNEC will be a federation of NATO and National service
    based systems, with the Nations contributing around 90 percent of the
    capabilities, it is important that the standards and profiles described in
    the NISP take into account the ongoing developments in the nations.</para>
    <sect2 id="v1s2-finland">
      <title>Finland</title>
      <para>The C4 development started in Finland in the 1980's. At that time,
      all systems were developed separately for the Army, Navy, and the Air
      Force, thus resulting in a situation with a large number of distributed
      stove-piped systems. Although these systems have served us well in the
      past, their lifecycle is coming towards an end, and new systems need to
      be developed to serve our current and future needs. We face the same
      challenges as many other militaries as we realize that it is not
      affordable to develop new systems on top of the old ones by patching and
      bridging gaps. Furthermore, there is a limit to which technical, data,
      and application integration can take us. Therefore we have decided to
      give up most of our old systems by 2010. This decision became the
      starting point for the development of our IC4I and forms the basis for
      our Network Enabled Defence (NED), which comprises a domestic roadmap to
      which crisis management is aligned.</para>
      <para>The Finnish view on NED is that it is a working title for a
      concept that uses the principles of Network Enabled Capabilities for
      providing total defence (also called homeland security). Finland has a
      long tradition in total defence, where the armed forces cooperate with
      other governmental agencies and industry to secure the functions vital
      to the society. NED is defined to describe how future networks with
      improved and integrated information and weapon systems can enable
      command and control in joint and territorial operations with multiple
      partners. The basic requirement in our system development is
      interoperability with the international development. Thus, there is no
      significant difference whether the crisis is in Finland or somewhere
      else, nor is there a technical difference whether the coalition is lead
      by the UN, EU, NATO or a nation.</para>
      <para>The Finnish approach to NED is very pragmatic and based on
      incremental development. We place high emphasis on innovation
      opportunities that are technically feasible, cost-efficient, and
      organizationally achievable. NED is not seen as a goal, but as a journey
      in the right direction together with partners. Especially industry
      partnerships are considered valuable, as they have the research and
      production capabilities needed to turn innovations into solutions and
      applications - again, real implementations, not just visions and
      theories. One example of such partnership is the establishment of a
      Network Centric Operations Centre of Excellence (NCO CoE) together with
      IBM in Finland.</para>
      <para>The first task that we did was to rationalize system development
      in order to cut the number of overlapping systems. This lead to system
      centralization, and the idea of "the network as the computer" emerged,
      which in practise means that thin clients capable of doing local
      processing are used, but the applications and data storage are performed
      via the network. We also decided to take a leap into a SOA-based
      approach. The two main issues in this first phase are the reliance on
      COTS as well as our architecture development. In our architecture
      development, we have found the usage of overarching and reference
      architectures as drivers for change, and ended up with an overarching
      architecture and two reference architectures (C4I and administrative).
      In the near future, there will be two additional reference
      architectures, which are shared with other agencies for collaboration
      purposes. As for using COTS, we have taken a very pragmatic approach in
      building and deploying our systems. For example, for voice communication
      we have developed a TETRA based system, which was gradually deployed in
      Finland as well as in international exercises and operations, such as in
      the Finnish battalion in Kosovo (2002), the Nordic PfP Exercise (2003),
      MN Brigade (C) in Kosovo (2003), and MN TF Althea (2004). During the
      years 2001-2004 we developed civilian crisis management systems, which
      were based on the idea that whatever can be deployed in our national
      defence can be used in international operations as well. Another
      developed COTS product was the Deployed COTS Network (DCN), which
      connects virtually any digital and analogue network together. In less
      than four months we procured, tested trained, and deployed a brigade
      level DCN to KFOR.</para>
      <para>The second step involves a functional change and is concerned with
      information sharing. At this stage, SOA is used as the basis for the
      architecture. At the moment, we have three main experiences developed or
      in development for the second phase. One is the Network Enabled
      Operations Centre (NEOC), where we tested the centralization of
      information powerhouses into the core network. The concept of
      information powerhouses basically means that all information is
      centralized into a few server hotels, which are connected to the
      backbone and accessible through the access networks. The demonstrator
      proved increased survivability, better situational awareness, and
      brought new processes and a new C4 structure. The second issue is
      SECNET, the interagency networking concept. This is still under
      development, but we are getting there in a pragmatic way, developing
      services that can be shared between authorities. The third concept is
      METO, which is a Sea Surveillance Information System (SSIS) shared by
      the Navy, Border control, and Maritime traffic safety, and thus
      coordinated by the defence ministry, ministry of transportation, and the
      interior ministry.</para>
      <para>In the third phase, we are concerned with a cultural change that
      involves collaboration based on the SOA approach. To mention two
      examples, we have build proof-of-concepts for a joint Common Operational
      Picture (COP) service. In the first PoC, we tested the scalability of
      having a "mother database" with all information. This database was
      reachable from the Defence Staff through a common portal. Information
      was collected from various local environments, which all had a picture
      of their own environment. The PoC showed us that the technology worked.
      In the second PoC, we tested what we call the "child's architecture",
      where some of the local environments are detached from the "mother
      environment". The idea is that the detached unit is able to operate on
      its own even without a network connection, seeing only its own
      environment. However, as the network connection is resumed, it should be
      possible to rejoin to the common environment. The focus was on the
      scalability of SOA, information handling when coming back online, and
      integrity issues. In this PoC we scaled down to brigade and battalion
      level, but it is possible to scale it further down to team or even
      individual fighter level.</para>
      <para>We have learnt many lessons on our still ongoing journey towards
      NED. We believe that our pragmatic and incremental approach together
      with strong industrial partnership, where development and deployment
      lifecycles can be brought down to 18 months, is a good way to go ahead.
      Collaboration with NATO in architectural development, using the idea of
      overarching and reference architectures, and working together on open
      service interface descriptions has proven valuable. Also testing the
      systems in exercises and deploying them on the field in various
      operations have given us a lot of experience.</para>
      <para>Still, several challenges remain. The main challenge is IA, which
      often is a hot potato that nobody wants to address. This is the next
      challenge that we will really focus on solving. The IA challenge is
      especially difficult at the moment due to the cultural change related to
      the transition from "need to know" to "need to hide" and "duty to
      share". Whereas communication security has been addressed by various
      security protocols, network and content security are still open
      questions. For example, the concept of CBIS/MLIS has suffered from a
      standstill for several years.</para>
      <para>Another challenge is the difficulty in integrating differ nt
      approaches from NATO, EU, the government and industry. However, we are
      hoping that the industry will help us solve the problem, and hence we
      will continue with our strong partnership approach. Furthermore, future
      services are still unknown, thus leading to "ad hoc system design". The
      best we can do at the moment is to try to develop a common and generic
      environment, in which to fit future services in a standard way. Also
      decomposing current systems to services provided by applications using
      core and common services is a challenge.</para>
      <para>The biggest challenge, perhaps, is not technical, but cultural.
      The user needs to feel "a return of investment" for his efforts to learn
      new ways of doing business. Training and educating users is one thing,
      but the real challenge is to get people to truly adopt the concept of
      collaboration in a network-centric environment using unified process
      workflows.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="v1s2-france">
      <title>France</title>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-fr1">
        <title>Background</title>
        <para>The objective of the present document is to describe the French
        orientations to rationalize the interconnection between the French CIS
        and NATO CIS.</para>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-fr2">
          <title>France involvement in NATO force structures</title>
          <para>France is involved in many NRF rotations:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>2006 : NRF7 French participation in the Eurocorp at LCC
              level</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>2008 : NRF10 MCC</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>2008 : NRF11 LCC</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>2009 : NRF12 JFACC</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>2009 : NRF13 CJSOTF</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>2010 : NRF14 MCC and LCC (Eurocorp)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>Besides, France has already 2 HRF HQ located in France: a
          maritime HQ in Toulon (southern part of France) and a LCC HQ in
          Lille (northern part of France).</para>
          <para>Each time France is on alert for HRF or NRF purposes, it is
          mandated to setup a special interconnection between NATO HQ and
          these headquarters. In order to optimise those interconnections from
          a personnel perspectives and a cost point of view (equipments,
          leased lines..), the intention is to setup a permanent network.
          Furthermore, this permanent network will facilitate the exchange of
          information with NATO and will enable France to be in line with the
          NNEC perspectives to offer the available services to all the
          military users.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-fr3">
          <title>French participation in NRF5</title>
          <para>France has participated as the JFACC during the NRF5 rotation.
          That was the starting point of the rationalisation work which is
          made in the logical continuity from this participation. The <xref linkend="v1a3-frfig01" /> displays the roles played by the French
          units and the information systems involved during the certification
          exercise ALLIED ACTION 05.</para>
          <figure id="v1a3-frfig01" float="0">
            <title>French participation in Allied Action 05</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/v1a3-fr01.svg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>The French systems used during this exercise were the
          following:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>SCCOA (command and control system for air
              operation)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Document management system</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>STRADIVARIUS : French integrated air picture</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>IRIS : AdatP3 formatting tool</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>TDS : friendly force awareness</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Messaging system</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Videoteleconferencing</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>The Lessons learnt from NRF5 participation can be sorted in
          three points:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>First of all, from the user's point of view, for maximum
              efficiency it would be easier to have only one workstation to
              access directly to the right information instead of using a
              swivel chair and disquettes (or USB keys). Another aspect of
              this point of view is to adopt the maxim "train as you fight",
              and as such it is highly desirable to have the ability to use
              NATO and French tools on the same network.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From CIS engineers' point of view, the complexity the
              Information Exchange Gateway (IEG) imposes the need for a
              specific CIS team dedicated to the support of this gateway. It
              is not easy to deploy and configure it. On the other hand, using
              only one IP network between NATO and France has eased the
              overall deployment. The compromise that should be made is to
              avoid the deployment of those gateways on theatre where the
              skilled human resource is rare.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>From the interoperability point of view, it is much easier
              to have only one network to enable people to access the services
              they need.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-fr4">
        <title>Situation today</title>
        <para>The actual situation is the result of successive deployment made
        when the different systems were available. Each time the participation
        of a French unit was required an extension of the NATO system was
        establish to connect them. The result is that each functional system
        has added direct link and specific network to enable the required
        exchange of information. The number of transmission links has grown
        and equally the number of gateways and crypto devices. One of the
        links might be overloaded at a period of the day but we are not able
        to use another link that might be free at the same time. The teams in
        charge of these equipments have no centralized management tool and no
        possibility to improve the quality of service for the different
        communities of users.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-fr5">
        <title>Optimization and rationalization of NATO links</title>
        <para>The first step proposed is to rationalize the transmission
        links. For the moment, direct connections between each French location
        to the NATO network have been established. Hence the number of leased
        lines is important and to allow a communication at NATO secret level
        between Brest and Toulon for NATO purposes the communication is done
        via SHAPE. The optimization is not done on the different links and the
        level of redundancy for each location is relatively low. The proposed
        way to improve the actual situation is to:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Have 2 BME for permanent purposes (1 NATO Point Of Presence
            close to Paris and 1 for ACCS)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>1 BME for each HRF headquarters</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Establish 2 transmission links between Paris, Lyon and
            NATO</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Create links within the French network to avoid having to go
            back to the NGCS for communications between 2 sites, working for
            NATO purposes, located in France.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <figure id="v1a3-frfig02" float="0">
          <title>Future Interconnection</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/v1a3-fr02.svg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-fr6">
        <title>Setting up of a unique logical network</title>
        <para>The main objective for the NATO Secret network (FR NNS) is to
        give the opportunity for the end-user to have only one computer on his
        desk accessing all the needed services. The first step is to take into
        account the messaging and webaccess services to enable the access to
        ICC, MCCIS, BICES-webserver, WISE and CRONOS. All the "supporting"
        services like DNS, PKI, NTP will be available for the different
        systems. The flows of information between the national side and the
        NATO sides will be filtered in the appropriate gateway.</para>
        <figure id="v1a3-frfig03" float="0">
          <title>IP Interconnectivity</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/v1a3-fr03.svg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>The target is to share the access also for other systems like
        ADAMS, LOGREP, LOGDATA,..and facilitate the evolution towards
        NMS.</para>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-fr7">
          <title>Short term solution</title>
          <para>The availability of the FR NNS is needed for the validation
          phase of the new maritime system that France is developing: SIC21.
          This system will have to exchange information with MCCIS and several
          others NATO systems. As this validation phase will start during
          summer 2007, it is envisaged to use the IEG that was used during the
          NRF5 rotation with some minor changes (authorization of MCCIS
          flows). At the same period of time, the air community will start to
          move on the NNS: the CASPOA (Analysis and Simulation centre) for air
          operations preparation, which is a NATO Centre of Excellence,
          located in Taverny (close to Paris), the CCOA (Air Operation Centre)
          located in Lyon and the CDAOA (Air Defence and Air Operations
          Command) located in Paris will be connected.</para>
          <para>At the end of 2008, all the ICC and MCCIS clients located in
          France should be able to work directly from their computers on the
          NNS. This means on the contrary that the people located on the
          theatre will still require direct links to NATO WAN.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-fr8">
          <title>Mid term objective</title>
          <para>Two aspects will be considered after the starting up of this
          network. On one side new clients will have the opportunity to access
          those services and on the other side new services will be added on
          the network. The new clients concerned by this migration on NNS are
          the squadrons and air headquarters that can participate in NRF/HRF
          such as flying units, ARS, Ships and headquarters and the new
          headquarters created in France The pace for moving the units will be
          based on the next rotation of NRF where France is playing a
          component command role.</para>
          <para>For NRF 11, France will be Land Component Command and still
          keeps two options for its interconnection. The first would be to use
          the FR NNS and the second to have a direct connection to NSWAN. The
          choice is depending on the organization of the Joint Force Command
          leading the rotation.</para>
          <para>For the NRF 12 France, Air Component command, it is assumed
          that the FR NNS will be used as it was done during the rotation 5.
          The only difference would be the availability of more
          services.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-fr9">
          <title>CRONOS integration in FR NNS</title>
          <para>The actual network is obsolescent. It was built in 1999 and
          some client workstations were deployed in various locations. France
          has contracted a support with a company to install and maintain the
          various computers. This contract is coming to its end, thus there is
          an opportunity to re-analyse the relevance of such a contract and
          the associated cost. Some clients will not be connected with the
          contractor because there are out of the boundary of the initial
          contract. France has made the decision to int grate this "service"
          in the FR NNS. No more upgrade of the actual network is planned; all
          the new users will be connected via the FR NNS.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-fr10">
          <title>ICC integration in FR NNS</title>
          <para>France will use the opportunity of the movement of the
          different headquarters during the 2007-2008 period to setup an
          architecture that will support all the workstations spread out in
          many places in France. The upgrade of ICC from the actual version to
          2.7.1, then 2.8 will give an ideal integration period to migrate
          towards the new approach. After that migration it is assumed that
          network upgrades will be necessary for the air community for the
          arrival of ACCS. All the network evolutions will be taken into
          account by the FR NNS network manager.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-fr11">
        <title>Ongoing work</title>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-fr12">
          <title>Interfaces between NS, NNS and MS</title>
          <para>During operations, usually a Mission Secret network is
          deployed. To enable interconnection between network handling NATO
          Secret information and network handling Mission Secret information,
          it will be necessary to develop an IEG Case C. The location of this
          gateway is still under discussion and need to be further
          investigated. The main objective for this interconnection is to
          offer all the NATO IP services to the different communities of
          interest in the theatre.</para>
          <figure id="v1a3-frfig04" float="0">
            <title>Interconnecting MS Network</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/v1a3-fr04.svg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          <para>The management of such a network composed of systems managed
          by NATO bodies and national teams will need to be worked out to
          develop Service Level Agreement between the network providers (NATO
          and national) so that availability seen from the users' point of
          view is maximal.</para>
          <para>The other challenge will be to ease access to the right
          information. Having authorized the interconnection of the NATO and
          the national systems does not mean that the various people in the
          different Headquarters are accessing the information of interest to
          them.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-fr13">
          <title>IP networks not on NNS</title>
          <para>Some systems are currently under development and a more
          accurate analysis must be undertaken to verify how and when they
          could go on the national network. That is the case for ACCS and
          Bi-SC-AIS. This analysis should be followed by a testing phase to
          ensure that the system continue to provide the services it is
          supposed to provide.</para>
          <para>For other services, like videoteleconferencing, France will
          setup a separate network because of bandwidth constraints. When the
          quality of service will be spread on all the IP networks, and
          operational priorities agreed within the nations, this could evolve
          towards a unique network on which all the services would be made
          available.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-fr14">
          <title>Non IP networks</title>
          <para>If there is a clear thread to use an IP network for exchanging
          most of the data needed for command and control functions, it must
          be recognize that non-IP networks will last for at least 5 years.
          Thus it is important for the services that they support to guarantee
          that the interoperability between the non-IP systems within NATO
          nations and PfP nations will continue until the transition phase to
          IP is accomplished. The services concerned are real-time service
          (e.g. Link 16, circuit between radar and CAOC,...), telegraphy,
          circuit switched and packet switched services.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-fr15">
          <title>NNEC perspectives</title>
          <para>To foster and federate initiatives to improve military actions
          effectiveness within a coalition force, information is the key
          element. Information management and effect control to reach the
          desired end-st te have to be taken into account joint, inter-agency
          and international aspects development of interoperability, using
          state of the art methods will accelerate adaptation towards using
          enterprise services across the nations and appropriate networking.
          The necessity to accelerate the acquisition of the systems and to
          optimise spending will tailor the experimentation process. In order
          to take advantage of all the technology opportunities, a structured
          but pragmatic approach will be taken to enable the different program
          managers to take into account the interoperability challenges in an
          international context. In particular, studies need to be done to
          identify the criteria to determine when Service Oriented
          Architecture is the right approach and, when appropriate, propose a
          migration plan in accordance with the other nations involved.</para>
          <figure id="v1a3-frfig05" float="0">
            <title>French Battlelab</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/v1a3-fr05.svg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="v1s2-nl">
      <title>Netherlands</title>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-nl1">
        <title>Policy and direction</title>
        <para>NEC is essential for the innovation of military operations and
        recognised as a priority in Defence policy. This policy is reflected
        in the three courses that are followed to promote the specific
        implementation of NEC in the armed forces:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Improvement of the adaptability of the armed forces for
            participation in multinational, joint, combined and interagency
            coalitions;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Improvement of the ability of the armed forces to
            innovate;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Contribution to the implementation of an integrated
            multinational NII.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Due to the priority given to NEC, the Secretary-General
        established an NEC steering group. This group is tasked with the
        promotion of innovation of military action by giving direction to the
        development of NEC. The Director of Operational Policy, Requirements
        and Plans of the Defence Staff provides central direction to the
        development of NEC and manages the NEC steering group. Nearly all
        parties involved in the transformation of the Defence organisation are
        represented in the steering group. The group is chaired by the Deputy
        Director for Requirements (of the Defence Staff). The tasks of the
        steering group include:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Promoting the development of innovative military
            concepts;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Promoting the adaptability and interoperability of Dutch
            capabilities in multinational (NATO, EU, ad hoc)
            coalitions;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Monitoring the implementation;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Informing and advising the civilian leadership about
            relevant subjects;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Formulating, on an annual basis, an NEC plan as an input to
            the Defence plan, to be able to monitor the progress in the
            development of NEC and to lay the foundation for future
            requirements; and</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Contributing to the preparation and harmonisation of Dutch
            positions in meetings of relevant international consultation
            forums.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-nl2">
        <title>Implementation of national NII</title>
        <para>The Netherlands armed forces will be tasked with implementing
        the national segment of NII, the Dutch NII, which can be integrated
        into larger coalitions. In this process, the main areas of attention
        are:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Design</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>The NII must be designed in such a way that it can support
            networked operations. It requires agreements on common
            architecture, the use of technologies and standards, but also on
            basic data and the management of these data.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Realisation</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>Through investment programmes and concrete projects, the NII
            hardware, software and services components, as well as the
            interfaces between those components, will be implemented.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Implementation and
            maintenance</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>This mainly concerns agreements and measures to ensure that
            the new technical possibilities are in fact being used. Everything
            depends on the willingness to share information. This area of
            attention also includes information management and control.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Protection</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>Arrangements must be agreed, measures must be taken and
            investments must be made to ensure the security of NII as well as
            the reliability of the information supply.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-nl3">
        <title>The development of NEC</title>
        <para>NEC cannot be bought. Furthermore, the realisation of NEC is an
        evolutionary process without a strictly defined beginning or end. It
        is a process of growth, comparable to the process of change that many
        organisations go through in order to stay up-to-date in the field of
        information and communication technology. Doctrines, processes,
        command and control, organisations, personnel and materiel must
        develop in a coherent and evolutionary way. That, therefore, is the
        approach that the Defence organisation will use towards the
        development of NEC. As a result, NEC will be introduced into the
        Netherlands armed forces in a gradual and manageable way. This
        approach is characterised by the following principles:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>combination of bottom-up activities aimed at the development
            of the necessary information infrastructure and top-down
            activities aimed at concept development with regard to the future
            capabilities;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>a step-by-step approach, i.e. a learning path where
            experiments are used, in close cooperation with developers and
            users, to reduce the risks as much as possible and make users
            aware of the new possibilities of NEC as soon as possible;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>co-evolutionary approach: the balance among the various
            aspects of development is constantly monitored.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>For several NEC systems, the Defence organisation takes itself
        the lead in the development. This approach is different to the
        approach used by many other nations, who develop specifications and
        delegate the actual development to industry based upon these
        specifications. TITAAN and ISIS, for example, are being developed by
        the Dutch Army itself, with support of industry.</para>
        <para>The Defence organisation distinguishes three types of innovation
        on the path towards NEC:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Technological
            innovation</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>The development, application and implementation of new
            technology bring about changes in the physical domain.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Process-driven
            innovation</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>The adaptation of organisational processes and the
            implementation of new operational concepts also causes changes in
            the information domain.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Organisational
            innovation</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>The structure, standards and culture of the organisation and
            the individual change, causing the cognitive social domain to
            change too.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>Taking into consideration the three types of innovation, there
        are five NEC levels, if we also include the zero situation - the
        platform-centric level. Using these levels can help the Defence
        organisation define its ambitions and requirements clearly and can
        also provide insight into the adaptability and interoperability of a
        military capability. These levels are respectively Isolated (1),
        Deconfliction (2), Coordination (3), Collaboration (4) and Coherent
        effects (5).</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-nl4">
        <title>Critical success factors for the implementation of NEC</title>
        <para>Critical factors on which a successful implementation of NEC in
        the Netherlands armed forces will depend, include:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Requirements evaluation and
            procurement</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>In the processes of requirements evaluation and procurement,
            NEC-related requirements must be taken into account structurally.
            This means that attention must be paid not only to the capability
            that is acquired, but also to the future role of that capability
            and its integration in the network. Flexible and incremental
            procurement strategies, in which the insight into the functional
            demands and the best way to meet those demands gradually increase,
            tie in with this. This also requires a more intensive cooperation
            with the industry. In the development of new capabilities,
            NEC-requirements will be taken aboard in the design, just as is
            the case now with the Joint Strike Fighter.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Information Management development
            under architecture</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>In order to establish the Dutch NII and to steer the
            development of the required Information Management infrastructure
            in the right direction, there must be an architecture available
            which is used effectively. The Defence Information Management
            Architecture (DIVA) will be developed further for this
            purpose.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Scientific research and operational
            experiments</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>This is necessary to be able to evaluate the usability of
            new concepts and technologies, thus reducing the risk of making
            high costs that turn out to be unnecessary and irreversible
            choices that turn out to be wrong.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">The development of NEC competencies
            and the design of C2 processes</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>It is clear that NEC will have a considerable impact on the
            human element in the Netherlands armed forces. The success of the
            implementation of new technology, systems and concepts and the
            improvements in performance that these should bring about is
            wholly dependent on the presence of the willingness and the
            competencies to actually use them.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Central coordination and international
            cooperation</emphasis>
            </para>
            <para>The ideal situation would be that national and international
            agreements are made so that the various NEC processes will be able
            to reinforce one another. In order to achieve this, there must be
            central coordination and international cooperation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-nl5">
        <title>Examples research and experiments</title>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-nl6">
          <title>Experimenting - JPOW</title>
          <para>CHANIA (CRETE) - In Joint Project Optic Windmill (JPOW), the
          computers of all participating countries are linked together, for
          interoperability is an integral concept throughout JPOW. "Three,
          two, one, fire", a Greek officer, headphones over his coalblack
          hair, counts down. A trembling explosion; a grey white cloud of
          smoke like a small cauliflower. An orange-coloured rocket races up
          from the launch site and hisses its way into a cloudless sky.
          Shortly before the projectile intercepts a small target aircraft, it
          is destroyed from the ground, and its shattered remains fall into
          the ice-blue Mediterranean waters off the coast near the NATO
          shooting range on the rocky island of Crete. This pandemonium is
          repeated three times. It is D-Day in the international air defence
          exercise Joint Project Optic Windmill. As a highlight, the Guided
          Missile Group of the De Peel airforce base shoots four ageing
          rockets into the firmament. JPOW is somewhere in between Star Wars,
          Star Trek and the US Strategic Defence Initiative. The foundation of
          the project was laid by the Netherlands, motivated by the first Gulf
          war (Source: Defensiekrant (MOD periodical), 20 April 2006).</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-nl7">
          <title>Experimenting - SENECA</title>
          <para>In 2005, the Defence organisation, along with TNO and THALES,
          carried out the first Dutch Joint NEC experiment. This experiment
          involved setting up a distributed experimenting environment which
          linked several locations together. Simulated operational sea, land
          and air systems successfully networked their actions in a single
          scenario. The experiment demonstrated the added value of the
          development of a Simulation Environment for NEC Assessment (SENECA)
          that provides opportunities for frequent experimenting.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-nl8">
        <title>Examples NEC in practice</title>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-nl9">
          <title>Optimal use of information</title>
          <para>The maritime dimension traditionally has a strong
          multinational orientation. Individual units must be interoperable to
          be able to function in a multinational flotilla. A recent example
          (late 2005 - early 2006) was the Dutch contribution to Task Force
          150, which was responsible for so-called maritime security
          operations in an area stretching from the coast of Somalia to the
          Arabian Gulf. TF 150 consisted of a great variety of navy vessels
          (including an air defence and command frigate), maritime patrol
          vessels, unmanned aircraft and shipborne helicopters. All these
          means contributed to the joint mission: identifying and detecting
          suspect vessels, boarding and searching vessels, collecting
          information and halting suspect vessels and arresting their crew.
          Through use of the American CENTRIX network and the Coalition Forces
          Intelligence Cell, the vessels could exchange information (such as
          photographs) with each other and with shore authorities directly by
          e-mail and chat, thus ensuring that the waiting time for merchant
          ships could be reduced to a minimum.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1s4-nl10">
          <title>ISIS</title>
          <para>Task Force Fox was a NATO force that was intended to protect
          the international observers who were tasked with monitoring the
          implementation of the peace plan for Macedonia in 2001-2002. In this
          multinational coalition with Germans, Frenchmen and Italians under
          Dutch leadership, the language barrier was, considering the
          operational circumstances, a real problem. Because information was
          shared with the coalition partners using ISIS, and this information
          was also represented graphically, there would soon be a shared
          understanding of the operational situation and emerging crises could
          be overcome swiftly and effectively. It is also thanks to ISIS that
          Task Force Fox has gone down in history as a successful NATO
          mission.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="v1s2-spain">
      <title>Spain</title>
      <sect3 id="vis3-esp1">
        <title>Policy and Direction</title>
        <para>National policies and directives support the bringing in of the NEC model nationally as they do its contribution to the multinational efforts. Both, information superiority and interoperability are considered a force multiplier/booster at the Spanish Military Strategy. The National Defence Act speaks of a call to "urge a transformation of our Armed Forces in line with a new model which would give them advanced technological capabilities". The Organic Law of National Defence and the Military Planning Directive requires that "Armed Forces are to be organized and trained in such an advanced technological manner that they will thus enjoy combat advantage, fewer losses and less damage and be networking operative"</para>
        <para>Aware of the very high number of actors and lines of work involved on Spanish NEC, in order to assure the proper co-ordination, CHOD set up a NEC Study and Developing Board (CEDENEC). This commission comes under the Chief of the Joint Staff responsibilities and is presided over by the Head of the CIS Division drawing its members from Defence staff HQ Spain and the HQs of each of the Services along with the Materiel and Armaments Board (DGAM), the CIS Inspectorate (IGECIS) and the Policy Board (DIGENPOL).</para>
        <para>This organization gives the specific structure set up for the improving of the initiatives coherence that bring in other pertinent bodies, and for the generating proposals including those approaches required to make of Spanish NEC a reality and its contribution to NATO NEC a fact. This working whole structure, that includes a working groups subestructure and is supported by the Spanish NEC Office, is charged with giving leadership to NEC during its initial phases by answering questions as to its definition, objectives, requirements, criteria as to its functional structure, information infrastructure, interoperability and any other matter that might have an effect on the development of NEC. It is also to promote the NEC knowledge within the Spanish Armed Forces, specially to all the involved bodies in its definition and development and to manage NEC related information.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="vis3-esp2">
        <title>Shaping up Spanish NEC</title>
        <sect4 id="vis3-esp2-1">
          <title>Pre-emption: Strategic Framework and Complexity Management</title>
          <para>Spain is aware that there is no single sequence of long-term planned baselines, but an approximate direction of progress, frequently reviewed and adapted to changing technologies, requirements and constraints. Therefore, CEDENEC believes that the best planning strategies under a high level of uncertainty and risk are no longer those that deliver optimum results in the very specific circumstances anticipated, but those that are robust enough to perform acceptably in a variety of potential scenarios. As such a strategic framework to answer the what-for, the what, the how and the when of the undertaking should be and should allow a balance among stability and flexibility.</para>
          <para>The Spanish NEC Strategic Framework is under CEDENEC's development and covers what Spain must achieve in order to fulfil the operational requirements; Lays down the strategic lines of work including those related with conceptual development, methodology and best practices, design and implementation and shared awareness; Establishes the global plans which include the strategic lines of work and; Goes into details as to short term plans. As it is to be the case for any rolling strategy, operational and technical analysis and studies (including those lessons learned) are to be continuously improving upon this strategic framework. Last but not least in importance is the human dimension including morale, leadership, training, education and, doctrine. The strategic framework is also aimed to this aspects.</para>
          <para>This strategic framework is to be considered within the Spanish Military Planning Process as well as within those efforts made of Defence bodies having technical responsibilities, research and development competences along with acquisitions responsibilities. In this situation the efforts towards the rolling orientation of running capabilities, programs and initiatives are going to be more important than ever.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="vis3-esp2-2">
          <title>Operational and Technical Interoperability Awareness</title>
          <para>It is more important than ever to keep alive the operational and technical interoperability awareness that Spain has held essential for so many years and backed by her participating in different demonstrations, exercises and experiments.</para>
          <para>It is to note Spanish technical experimentation at CWID initiatives. Spanish industry, universities and military bodies with technical competences play a part in the CWID demonstration. A Pilot model for SOA interoperability services, the Spanish Military Messaging System, Spanish web map services and web feature services or COP services have been put to work within latest NATO CWID. As it happened to be within other nations, Spain has its own national CWID. As such, middleware for sensors at C2 networks, or broad band mobile communications for tactical deployments, or tactical mini terminals for satellite band X communications have also been given demonstration airings.</para>
          <para>Spain is also working on supporting infrastructures for experimentation, training and exercises. Noteworthy here is that Spain is working towards the setting up of a Laboratory for NEC experiments (CENEC) where any practical solutions put forward are to be measured against those operative demands. Advanced joint simulation facilities are to be keep financed next year. NEC related prototypes have been delivered to our Operational Post Command.</para>
          <para>Following the NATO approach the development of our systems is in keeping with NC3TAv7 and NAFv2. Spain is analyzing  its architectures views evolution in keeping with NAFv3 and NISP.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="vis3-esp2-3">
          <title>Follow-on</title>
          <para>The main effort within the short to medium term must be towards achieving the Spanish NEC strategy for the managing of this complex endeavour and its concomitant experimental support demands.</para>
          <para>In the medium to long term Spain expects to be able to have the run of a fully operative working whole structure, this taking into its scope civilian organizations and other ministries.</para>
          <para>If there were something that could be called an international net-ready certification Spain could be deeply involved in it. Systems processes, capabilities and even acquisitions programmes could be verified on the basis of net-ready criteria or, to put it in another way: systems, processes, capabilities and acquisition programmes associated with network enabled capabilities could have what it might be call a "net-ready stamping". An interoperability authenticity stamp which would be, but of course, anchored upon the international determination it is concerned with. Which all means that an evaluation of existing systems will be called for to check out whether the net-ready criteria have been satisfied be it nationally or within any given coalition.</para>
          <para>The Spanish acquisition process is aligned with NATO Phased Armaments Programming System (PAPS). This process came up for review under a new proposal.  Among other aspects, it's under consideration a set of criteria that allows PAPS documents go further in the process, in order to enable rationalization as well as the necessary evolution in aspects such as technology.</para>
          <para>Spain's ultimate vision is of a real federation of military and civilian services and its cross utilization for crisis management and current operations. Civilian and military bodies would natuarally provide any that were to be needed, services that would thus endow us with powerful dual capabilities for defence and security.</para>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="vis3-esp3">
        <title>Implementation of the Spanish Core NII: The Spanish Military Command and Control System (SMCM)</title>
        <para>In order to solve the interoperability and information flow problems caused by a fragmentary approach, the solution adopted is to define and implement a new C2 system, the SMCM (Joint C2 system),  which will become the basic CIS infrastructure on which the specific services will be built. Of course this new system integrates the military telecommunications that have been integrated in a single joint system for many years (the Military Telecomunication System - STM) and is designed from the beginning to solve the shortfalls and problems of the existing information capabilities.</para>
        <para>Its Military Information System (SIM) incremental process has been divided into 3 increments and a previous definition phase. In this definition phase, it has been developed and approved the Concept of Operation of the System, the System Planning and Funding. The first increment objective is to implement and provide a set of common services, like both PKI and Directory Services and the priority services like Military  Messaging System. The system is to be deployed in the principal nodes (Joint, Land, Air and Maritime Headquarters, etc.) and is to be accredited to manage information upon National SECRET, NATO CONFIDENTIAL and CONFIDENTIAL UE level. The second increment includes the implementation of the specific functional services, the accreditation to NATO SECRET and SECRET UE, and it is planned to deploy the system to 400 nodes approximately. The last increment it is planned to provide all the functional area services and evolve the system to comply with the Network Enabled Capability. Of course, our will to set up this increments as schedule is tied to the available budgeting and funding.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="vis3-esp4">
        <title>POC</title>
        <para>ESPNEC@oc.mde.es</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="v1s2-sweden">
      <title>Sweden</title>
      <para>Authors: <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Peder Blomqvist, Swedish Defence Material
            Administration</para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-ndb">
        <title>The Swedish Network Based Defence (NBD) concept</title>
        <para>The Swedish Armed Forces has adopted the concept of Network
        Based Defence (NBD) as its main strategy to achieve Network Ready
        Capabilities. NBD is also the method for Swedish force transformation
        to Joint Operations and Capabilities and thus a fast, flexible and
        co-ordinated deployment of Reaction Force Units within national
        boundaries as well as a partner in an international mission. The NBD
        concept is the Swedish approach to retain the benefit of the
        Revolution in Military Affairs (RMA) and is similar to the Network
        Enabled Capabilities (NEC) and the Net-Centric Operations Warfare
        (NCOW) concepts.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-ndb2">
        <title>Development of a Command and Control System within the NBD
        concept</title>
        <para>The Swedish Armed Forces has within the concept of NBD since
        2001 been developing frameworks, concepts, principles, rules and
        recommendations, as enablers and guidance for design, construction and
        operation of the methods, services and technology solutions that
        should form the foundations and infrastructure of a future Command and
        Control System. The goal is to deploy the target architecture and
        infrastructure of the C2-system within the year of 2010. The C2-system
        is being developed with interoperability and the usage of open
        standards and commercial products (COTS) in focus. Gradually the
        C2-system infrastructure will develop into a full-featured Net-centric
        C4ISTAR-system with incorporated functionality for other legacy
        systems as well as new systems.</para>
        <para>The Swedish Armed Forces has during 2006 established a NBD
        Development Centre under the command of Chief of Development.</para>
        <para>Sweden has adopted a Concept Development and Experimentation
        (CD&amp;E) process based on international examples. One of the
        purposes of this process is to guarantee or secure
        interoperability.</para>
        <para>Sweden has conducted experiments in three different military
        command levels and also in Multi-National Experimentation (MNE)
        events.</para>
        <figure id="v1f4-swfig01" float="0">
          <title>Transformation Roadmap</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/v1a3-sw01.svg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <figure id="v1f5-swfig02" float="0">
          <title>CD&amp;E Model</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/v1a3-sw02.svg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-ndb3">
        <title>Development Strategy and Methodology</title>
        <para>The development is a joint effort between the Swedish Armed
        Forces, the Swedish Defence Materiel Administration (FMV), the Swedish
        Defence Research Agency (FOI), the National Defence College (FHS), the
        industry and other partners. The development is based on an
        overarching architecture approach with concepts and principles for
        System, Services, Information and Life-Cycle management. The
        development strategy is to use an evolutionary development methodology
        with continuous and parallel research and development of methods,
        knowledge, organisation and technology. The results are tested,
        verified and validated in experiments and demonstrators, and then
        carefully packaged in form of generic principles, design rules and
        methods. These will gradually build up the target architecture with
        re-usable foundations and reference architectures for further
        development of service-oriented systems and components for net-centric
        environments. The Swedish Armed Forces development of the NBD joint
        Command and Control Information System (SWECCIS) results in the
        knowledge and erudition of building NBD operational systems.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-ndb4">
        <title>Development Milestones for the Command and Control System
        2004-2010</title>
        <para>Autumn 2004: New development opportunities</para>
        <para>Autumn 2005: Common situational information</para>
        <para>Spring 2006: Common situational awareness</para>
        <para>Autumn 2006: New opportunities for co-ordination</para>
        <para>2007-2010: Final design and procurement of the Command and
        Control System Information Infrastructure<footnote><para>If decided by the Swedish Government</para></footnote></para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-ndb5">
        <title>Interoperability</title>
        <para>In autumn 2004 Sweden made a strategic decision to adopt current
        NATO standards and frameworks for C3-systems interoperability and to
        participate in and contribute to NATO's development of NNEC-based
        standards and frameworks, where possible as a partner nation. Lessons
        learned from the adoption of NATO standards and open standards and
        solutions create an environment that increases interoperability among
        crisis management agencies.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-ndb6">
        <title>Main objectives of the Network Based Defence (NBD)</title>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Interoperability</emphasis> - Ability to act in Joint
        Operations together with national and international partners, both
        military and civil. This can be achieved through standardisation and
        harmonisation of concepts, procedures and architecture.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Situation Adaptiveness</emphasis> - Flexible
        configuration and management of units, for given tasks and new
        opportunities. Dynamical configuration of Situation Adopted Systems,
        from a Baseline Architecture of resources and services. Well defined
        suites of Capability Packages for different scenarios.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Common Situational Awareness</emphasis> - Common
        Situational Information adopted for each user needs. Role-based
        situation picture and information access. Location and terminal
        independent distribution of data. Automated as well as on-demand
        collection, aggregation, fusion, processing, analysis, predictions and
        presentation of data and information from multiple sources.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Command Superiority</emphasis> - Swedish NBD
        experiment has showed that information that are fast distributed
        through out the Network and not compiled in centralised nodes empowers
        the lower echelon's to seize opportunities according to commander's
        intent as they come along.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Cost effectiveness</emphasis> - Flexible configuration
        will give us the ability to reuse and reconfigure systems and services
        in minutes instead of months/years. This together with the ability to
        bring along legacy systems should mean that the risk of building
        systems that are obsolete when operational also reduces the risk of
        wrongly spent money.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Precision Engagement</emphasis> - Co-ordinated and
        well balanced engagement, precise in time and location. This can be
        achieved by obtaining decision superiority.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-ndb7">
        <title>The Service Demonstrator</title>
        <para>The Swedish Defence Architecture project together with FM
        <emphasis>Ledsyst</emphasis> developed a set of concepts that supports
        a Service Based Systems approach where services can be assembled on
        demand into SitSyst, Situation adapted systems. A SitSyst is dedicated
        to solve a particular problem area or support a specific mission.
        These ideas and concepts were implemented during 2003 in a platform
        called <emphasis>The Service Demonstrator. The Service
        Demonstrator</emphasis> is a test system developed within Ledsyst in
        order to support the development towards a network centric defence.
        The purpose of the demonstrator is primarily to support the
        methodology development for network centric warfare.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis>The Service Demonstrator</emphasis> have continuously
        been updated and improved up until now. More system elements have been
        added and improvements have been made concerning stability, user
        functionality, application integration etc. Central concepts for
        <emphasis>The Service Demonstrator</emphasis> are SitSyst, dynamic
        addition and removal of services, creation of roles and authorization
        for solving specific tasks.</para>
        <para>Built on experiences from the Service Demonstrator and lessons
        learned the development of a more extensive service based system,
        <emphasis>BasePlatform</emphasis>, began in 2005. The current version
        of <emphasis>BasePlatform</emphasis> specifies a platform design that
        addresses core functionality such as service infrastructure, security,
        scalability, flexibility etc.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-ndb8">
        <title>FMA- An Enterprise Architecture for Future Systems in the
        Swedish Armed Forces</title>
        <para>SAF Enterprise Architecture (FMA) for the 21st century is under
        development. Swedish Armed Forces needs to co-ordinate and synchronise
        different resources (personnel, technology and information) enabling
        them to perform right activity, in right time frame and in right area.
        These resources are co-ordinated and synchronised within an
        organisation. To synchronise all these mutual dependent systems and
        their development over time is the complex challenge that Swedish
        Armed Forces Enterprise Architecture shall support Swedish Armed
        Forces to master. The purpose of FMA is to obtain tools for enabling
        interoperability in co-operation with society in general and
        international co-operation partners as well. Another important aspect
        is to give conditions for re-use of resources within the frame of NBD.
        SAF engagement systems must therefore be developed against a
        harmonisation and towards one common structure of present and new
        structures. This development shall be supported through supplying an
        Architecture Framework (FM AR) containing overarching rules
        for:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>How to describe a system</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Methods for build and use systems</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Competencies/roles in these systems</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1s3-ndb9">
        <title>National NNEC Approaches</title>
        <para>Some Swedish examples of key strategic programmes project
        experiences, products and best practice, lessons learnt, that can
        perhaps be of interest for the NATO and PfP nations.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>FM LedsystT FMLS2010 Network Based Defence
            experiences</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Documentation experiences (SwAF Architecture Framework,
                NAF v2)</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>SOA implementation experiences and best practice</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>Service Demonstrator experiences and best
                practice</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>NBD concepts, definitions and best practice</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>System concept</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Service concept</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Situation Adopted System concept (SitSyst)</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Information concept</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Life-cycle management concept</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>NBD Systems Development methodology work and</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>SwAF Enterprise Architecture development and NATO NAF 3
            adjustment effort.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>FM AR Concepts and models</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>NAF v2 and NAF v3 (pragmatic approach) documentation
                experiences and best practice</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>SWECCIS Reference Architecture experiences (Swedish Command
            and Control Information System), target architecture for SWECCIS
            2008.</para>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>NAF v3 (pragmatic approach), documentation experiences
                and best practice</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The SwAF ERP project (PRIO) and the service oriented
            requirement specification work.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="v1c-uk1">
      <title>The UK Network Enabled Capability</title>
      <para>The UK has adopted the term Network Enabled Capability (NEC) as it
      captures it's intent to invest in networks as a means of maximizing the
      capability inherent in current and future platforms. The UK is using the
      term "Network Enabled Capability" since it gives due weight to both the
      platform capability and the network, and is consonant with their work on
      Effects Based Operations, Knowledge superiority and Decision
      Superiority.</para>
      <para>The NEC goal is to radically enhance our operational capability by
      improving the way we share and use information , with the key objective
      of providing a coherent conceptual and technical framework to link
      sensors, decision-makers and effectors.</para>
      <para>The US concept of Network Centric Warfare, put into practice in
      Afghanistan, is a key driver. In the same way that precision guided
      munitions demonstrated in the Gulf war acted as a driver for change in
      UK and other forces, the success of the US' strategy, implement through
      a tight linkage between sensors, communications, information, and
      weapons systems is causing the UK to look at how it would fight the next
      conflict.</para>
      <para>Lessons learned have emphasized the importance of interoperability
      in the joint and coalition environment.</para>
      <para>It is important to understand that the path to NEC is an
      evolutionary one that builds on existing equipment programmes, concepts
      and structures but delivers increased joint capability. The parallel
      evolution of the other UK Lines development (Concept &amp; Doctrine,
      Structure, Equipment &amp; Technology, People, Training, Sustainment) is
      an essential part of the progress towards a full Defence capability
      Existing processes will provide the links.</para>
      <para>The diagram below shows the underlying principles in the UK in
      building its NEC.</para>
      <figure id="v1c-uknecthemes" float="0">
        <title>NEC Themes</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/v1a3-uknecthemes.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The table below summaries the key themes of the UK's NEC</para>
      <table>
        <title>UK NEC Themes</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Effects Synchronization</entry>
              <entry>Achieving the desired effects through the synchronisation
              of activities within and between mission groups.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Agile Mission Groups</entry>
              <entry>Enabling the dynamic creation and configuration of task
              oriented mission groups that share understanding and that employ
              and co-ordinate available assets to deliver the desired
              effect.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Dynamic Collaborative Interworking</entry>
              <entry>Enabling agile command and control within and between
              mission groups through the ability to concurrently plan and
              execute operations in a way that is dynamic, continuous and
              synchronised. Thus, it allows all entities (including
              non-frontline MoD bodies, Other Government Departments,
              industry, academia and public services as well as the military)
              to work together dynamically to meet changing mission
              needs.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Shared Understanding</entry>
              <entry>Enabling each user to generate an understanding of the
              battlespace that is appropriate and adequate to their task and
              consistent with the understanding of other users. This
              understanding covers the interpretation of the situation
              (current situation, its history, and potential developments of
              all battlespace participants) and of Command Intent (the effects
              and outcomes higher command wants to achieve.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Full Information Accessibility</entry>
              <entry>Enabling users to search, manipulate and exchange
              relevant information of different classifications (respecting
              security constraints) captured by, or available in, sources
              internal and external to the battlespace.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Resilient Information Infrastructure</entry>
              <entry>Enabling information is managed coherently across the
              battlespace and that the potential for secure and assured
              connectivity is provided to all battlespace users.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Inclusive Flexible Acquisition</entry>
              <entry>Co-ordinating processes across MOD, OGDs and industry
              that promotes the rapid insertion of new technologies,
              facilitates coherence between acquisition programmes and
              provides an incremental approach to delivering and sustaining
              'net-ready platforms'</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>Further information can be found at: <ulink url="http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/CorporatePublications/ScienceandTechnologyPublications/NEC/">http://www.mod.uk/DefenceInternet/AboutDefence/CorporatePublications/ScienceandTechnologyPublications/NEC/</ulink></para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="v1c-us1">
      <title>United States</title>
      <sect3 id="v1c-us2">
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>The United States' Department of Defense (DOD) pioneering theory
        of Net-Centric Operations and Warfare (NCOW) has fundamentally changed
        how the United States plans for and engages in military operations.
        NCOW seeks to translate an information advantage into a competitive
        war-fighting advantage through the robust networking of well informed
        geographically dispersed forces allowing new forms of organizational
        behavior. This "networking" utilizes information technology via a
        robust network to allow increased information sharing, collaboration,
        and shared situational awareness, which theoretically allows greater
        self-synchronization, speed of command, and mission
        effectiveness.</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="v1c-us3">
        <title>Net Centric Efforts</title>
        <sect4 id="v1c-us4">
          <title>The Global Information Grid (GIG) Bandwidth Expansion
          Program</title>
          <para>The Global Information Grid Bandwidth Expansion (GIG-BE)
          Program was a major Department of Defense (DOD) net-centric
          transformational initiative executed by DISA. GIG-BE created a
          ubiquitous "bandwidth-available" environment to improve national
          security intelligence, surveillance and reconnaissance, information
          assurance, as well as command and control. Through GIG-BE, DISA
          leveraged DOD's existing end-to-end information transport
          capabilities, significantly expanding capacity and reliability to
          locations worldwide.</para>
          <para>This program provided increased bandwidth and diverse physical
          access to approximately 87 critical sites in the continental United
          States (CONUS), Pacific Theater, and European Theater. These
          locations are interconnected via an expanded GIG core.</para>
          <para>GIG-BE provides a secure, robust, optical terrestrial network
          that delivers very high-speed classified and unclassified Internet
          Protocol (IP) services to key operating locations worldwide.</para>
          <para>After extensive component integration and operational testing,
          implementation began in the middle of the 2004 fiscal year and
          extended through calendar year 2005. The initial implementation
          concentrated on six sites used during the proof of initial
          operational capability, achieved on Sept. 30, 2004. On Dec. 20,
          2005, the GIG-BE program achieved the milestone of Full Operational
          Capability.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1c-us5">
          <title>Transformational Communications Satellite System
          (TSAT)</title>
          <para>The TSAT Program is actually just one node in a broad spectrum
          of programs known as the Transformational Communications
          Architecture (TCA). In 2001, the United States Department of Defense
          (DOD) initiated a Transformational Communications Study to
          accelerate the delivery of advanced capabilities with state-of-the
          art technology to the field.</para>
          <para>The study concluded that the United States Military's existing
          program plan would not meet forecast communications requirements. It
          also suggested that there was a window of opportunity to provide an
          architectural framework for a compatible communications system
          across the Department of Defense and the intelligence community -
          one that could increase U.S. capabilities by a factor of ten.</para>
          <para>Those conclusions, plus ongoing experience in the Global War
          on Terror and new technology developments like UAVs, helped shape
          the Transformational Communications Architecture (TCA).</para>
          <para>TSAT is intended to provide internet-like capability that
          extends high-bandwidth satellite capabilities to deployed troops
          worldwide, and delivers an order of magnitude increase in available
          military bandwidth. Using laser communications inter-satellite links
          to create a high data-rate backbone in space, TSAT will be one of
          the key enablers for the American vision of Network Centric
          Warfare.</para>
          <para>A visual image from a UAV that would take 2 minutes to process
          with the Milstar II satellite system would take less than a second
          with TSAT. A radar image from a Global Hawk UAV (12 minutes), or a
          multi-gigabyte radar image from space-based radar (88 minutes),
          would also take less than a second with the TSAT network. Best of
          all, the recipient can be on the move with a relatively small
          receiver, anywhere in the world.</para>
          <para>The TSAT system is currently scheduled to launch in
          2013-2016.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1c-us6">
          <title>Wide-Band Satellite Communications</title>
          <para>Wide-Band Satellite communications provides ubiquitous
          communications with optical quality bandwidth to mobile and tactical
          users.</para>
          <para>The Wideband Gapfiller Satellite program and the Advanced
          Wideband System will augment and eventually replace the Defense
          Satellite Communications System (DSCS) in 2009 or 2010. These
          satellites will transmit several gigabits of data per second-up to
          ten times the data flow of the satellites being replaced.</para>
          <para>Protected communications will be addressed by a global
          extremely high frequency (EHF) system, composed of the Advanced
          Extremely High Frequency System and Advanced Polar System. These
          systems are expected to provide about ten times the capacity of
          current protected satellites (the Milstar satellites). Narrowband
          needs are supported by the UFO (Ultrahigh-frequency Follow-On)
          constellation, which will be replaced by a component of the Advanced
          Narrowband System.</para>
          <para>Capacity gains in these systems will also be matched by
          improved features, such as multiple high-gain spot beams that are
          particularly important for small terminal and mobile users.
          Satellite, terminal, control, and planning segments will utilize
          emerging technology to ensure the best capability for the cost.
          Coordination among ground, air, and space segments and between
          government and commercial assets will help ensure deployment of the
          most efficient, effective, and affordable communications
          systems.</para>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1c-us7">
          <title>Net-Centric Enterprise Services</title>
          <para>Net-Centric Enterprise Services (NCES) is a Department of
          Defense program, managed by the Defense Information Systems Agency
          (DISA), to develop information technology infrastructure services
          for future systems used by the United States military to support the
          broad range of applications and data used in a net-centric
          enterprise. There are nine core enterprise services defined in the
          Network Centric Operations and Warfare - Reference Model
          (NCOW-RM):</para>
          <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
            <listitem>
              <para>Storage </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Mediation </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>User Assist </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>IA (Information Assurance) </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>ESM (Enterprise Service Management) </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Messaging </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Discovery </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Application </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Collaboration</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
          <para>NCES maps these nine services to four product areas:</para>
          <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
            <listitem>
              <para>Enterprise Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) Foundation
          </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Content Discovery &amp; Delivery </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Enterprise Collaboration </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Defense On-Line Portal</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </sect4>
        <sect4 id="v1c-us8">
          <title>Horizontal Fusion</title>
          <para>Horizontal Fusion (HF) program refers to the net-centric
          applications and content needed to provide analysts and war fighters
          with the ability to make sense of complex and ambiguous situations.
          Within HF, the first implementation of a Service Oriented
          Architecture (SOA) in the Department of Defense was achieved. The
          demonstration proved that the realization of a Net-Centric
          environment is technically feasible using legacy investments.
          Horizontal fusion is not just a single program, but a portfolio of
          net-centric initiatives using a common architecture and integration
          process. Recent initiatives include the following:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Department of State: Net-Centric
          Diplomacy</emphasis>. Net-Centric Diplomacy is an initiative aimed
          at enhancing war fighters' ability to gain situational understanding
          about adversaries and their operating environment by providing a
          full range of diplomatic reporting from worldwide posts to the
          collateral space, provided upon demand via net-centric DOD
          information services accessible through the MARS portal. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Environment Visualization
          (EVIS)</emphasis>. EVIS produces forecasted weather effects on
          tactical missions and makes these available and advertised through
          the enterprise, enabling a user to access high resolution,
          mission-tailored weather effects summaries and related map overlays,
          and do this within their tactical decision-making cycle. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Information Assurance / Certification
          and Accreditation Process</emphasis>. IA/CA will provide streamlined
          certification and accreditation services; makes recommendations and
          advocates for policy changes to support the certification and
          accreditation of net-centric operations. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Joint Surveillance Target Attack Radar
          System (Joint STARS)/ Affordable Moving Surface Target Engagement
          (AMSTE)</emphasis>. Joint STARS/AMSTE brings a sophisticated
          moving-object tracking capability to Horizontal Fusion that enables
          tracking more targets with greater accuracy. Joint STARS/AMSTE can
          push these tracks to a ground station using either a line of sight
          or beyond line of sight data link, with the ground station
          converting both the moving target indicator reports and tracks into
          an XML message and sending it to the MAJIIC initiative for
          publication. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Knowledge Management in a Net-Centric
          Environment (KMINCE)</emphasis>. Based on the National Ground
          Intelligence Center's mission, KMINCE provides tactical data,
          intelligence reports, publishing/posting tools, and collaboration
          functions within a web-accessible, service oriented environment.
          KMINCE allows operational users to search tactical databases through
          a Federated Search interface, build and post intelligence products
          within the collateral space and collaborate within the Horizontal
          Fusion MARS portal. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Multi-Sensor Aerospace-Ground Joint
          ISR Interoperability Coalition (MAJIIC)</emphasis>. MAJIIC enhances
          U.S. joint and coalition ISR data interoperability and MAJIIC
          enhances information sharing via the development, testing, and
          implementation of data standards, XML schemas, and leading edge
          Web-based enterprise services. MAJIIC will "post-before-processing"
          to the collateral space U.S. and coalition near-real-time ISR sensor
          data and mission situational awareness information for discovery and
          smart-pull by Mars Portal users and value-adding command, control,
          communications, computers (C4), ISR systems. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Net-Centric Geospatial-Intelligence
          Services (NGS)</emphasis>. NGS is a portlet on the Mars portal that
          provides the nation's war fighters and senior policymakers with
          access to geospatial intelligence (GEOINT), the exploitation and
          analysis of imagery and geospatial information to describe, assess
          and visually depict physical features and geographically referenced
          activities on Earth. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Network Basic Language Translation
          Services (NetBLTS)</emphasis>. Network Basic Language Translation
          System (NetBLTS) enables non-linguists to quickly triage foreign
          documents and provides a translation aid to linguists. NetBLTS
          provides Optical Character Recognition (OCR), machine translation,
          and document management and indexing. Users can save extracted
          keywords and phrases, document translations, and foreign documents
          to a database repository for future analysis. The repository is
          accessible through the Horizontal Fusion Federated Search
          application. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Non-Obvious Relationship Awareness
          (NORA)</emphasis>. NORA discovers relationships among people and
          organizations to answer the question, "Who knows whom?" and can be
          accessed by the war fighter through the Mars Portal and collateral
          space. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Trusted Wisdom</emphasis>. Trusted
          Wisdom provides secure, mobile, real-time posting of reporting from
          field collectors. Information is tagged and accessible in the
          collateral space, where communities of interest can host rapid
          analysis and fusion of field collector reporting and technical
          collection data, and serve as venue for field collector, analyst,
          and war fighters to interact and rapidly develop fused actionable
          intelligence. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Visual Enterprise Monitoring
          (VEM)</emphasis>. VEM provides a "window to the information flow"
          within a network to increase commanders' and decision-makers'
          overall situational awareness. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Visualization/Information Dominance
          (V/ID)</emphasis>. V/ID bridges traditionally separate analytic
          processes, including data preparation and exploitation, and
          Web-enables it through data extraction, analysis and tagging, via
          the commercial ClearForest ClearTags entity extractor. Visualization
          capability is enhanced/enabled using the commercial Starlight
          toolkit. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Coalition Shared Intelligence
          Networked Environment (COSINE)</emphasis>. COSINE combines
          analysis/production-sharing and cross-coalition information
          management married to a CENTRIXS -like secure network structure for
          intelligence exchange and content-based information security and
          release management capabilities that will allow individual coalition
          domains to quickly connect secure coalition command, control, and
          intelligence systems, share information and coordinate with both
          allied and coalition partners in a timely (near real-time) secure
          manner, and dynamically alter access to information when the need
          arises. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Cooperative Engagement Capability
          (CEC)</emphasis>. CEC webTracks initiative provides access to the
          CEC sensor network's real-time air track picture and make it
          accessible to a variety of clients via intelligent pull to allow
          tailoring of the data requested for either current or historical
          track data and underlying measurement data, or streaming data to
          constantly update track movements. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Extensible Tactical C4I Framework
          (XTCF)</emphasis>. XTCF is an open, extensible, plug-and-play
          architecture that will transform command and control data management
          services by providing an architecture that will rapidly add new
          value-added services and get new content providers and consumers
          quickly onto the collateral space in a dynamic battle space. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Global Net-Centric Surveillance and
          Targeting (GNCST)</emphasis>. GNCST is developing a capability to
          demonstrate model-based fusion of upstream data from multiple
          intelligence sources to detect, locate and identify time-critical
          targets and targets of national interest, and to distribute target
          reports to tactical users via collateral networks in tactically
          relevant timelines. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Integration of Non-Traditional
          Information Sources (INTIS)</emphasis>. INTIS uses non-traditional
          sensors, the F/A-18 Hornet and the AH-64 Apache, to provide secure,
          rapid delivery of hostile surface-to-air missile and anti-aircraft
          electronic intelligence to the war fighter and the intelligence
          community, aiding in fast updates of the common operating picture
          and more accurate targeting information. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Naval Research Lab (NRL) Sensor
          Node</emphasis>. Provides an airborne node on the collateral space
          for target location and detection to support ground troops and joint
          strike forces directly, by posting "sensor products" (e.g., imagery,
          data, reports) and alerts for immediate use in operational planning
          by various Web-enabled users. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Ocean Surveillance Information System
          Evolutionary Development (OED)</emphasis>. As the only operational
          command, control, communications, computer, and intelligence system
          trusted to provide multi-level secure capability, OED supports the
          customers of US and partner Joint Intelligence Centers with
          information tailored to their clearance level, area of interest, and
          need to know. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Secure Mobile Networks</emphasis>.
          Provides the war-fighter with secure, robust voice and data
          communication networks which enable collaboration even in highly
          dynamic, unpredictable, mobile wireless environments. Secure Mobile
          Networks are intelligent, resilient, and self-configuring networks
          that allow access to global assets in the field even when direct
          links with reach back communications are not available. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Trusted Workstation (TWS)</emphasis>.
          TWS provides intelligence analysts and operational war fighters with
          on-demand simultaneous access to common and mission-critical desktop
          applications running at multiple security domains from a single
          ultra-thin-client workstation. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Ubiquitous Automated Information
          Manager (U-AIM)</emphasis>. U-AIM enables the aiming of external
          information resources to automatically discover, access, associate,
          and prioritize intelligence and information products, and focus and
          allocate resources on high priority information needs through a
          simple Web application that allows the war fighter to continuously
          formulate target or event nomination and receive alerts, all
          tailored to the war fighter's role and mission. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Warrior's Edge</emphasis>. The Army's
          Warrior's Edge represents a dynamic ad hoc networked local sensing
          environment comprising soldiers and unattended and robotic sensors,
          each providing a user-tailored perspective of the combat situation
          to the war fighter during changing conditions to maximize mission
          success.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect4>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="v1s1-Industry-NEE">
    <title>Industry Network Enabled Efforts</title>
    <para>NNEC will be a federation of NATO and National systems the
    utilization of common standards is paramount for achieving the goals of
    NNEC. The vast majority of standards implemented in NNEC are expected to
    be open standards; so working with industry has been recognized as
    providing benefits to both NATO and industry. NATO monitors and evaluates
    the work from these industrial organizations and if found relevant
    incorporates their concepts in the development of the NISP.</para>
    <para>Industry is also recommending a time phased approach for
    implementing systems. For example, Gartner described a life cycle approach
    to using standards at a symposium it held in October 2004<footnote><para>Gartner Symposium IREXPO 2004, Lake Buena Vista, Florida, 17-22
        October 2004</para></footnote>. This approach is depicted in <xref linkend="v1f6-GA" /></para>
    <figure id="v1f6-GA" float="0">
      <title>Life Cycle Approach to Using Standards</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/v1-ga.svg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>The first phase is the emerging period, in which new technologies
    appear that may represent a significant advance (this is equivalent to
    emerging standards in the NISP). Once proven the standards may qualify for
    mainstream status, which means that they can be adopted without conditions
    (this is similar to mandatory standards in the NISP).</para>
    <para>Eventually, newer standards emerge and mainstream standards move
    into the containment stage, that is, the standards are supported, but they
    are not suitable for new applications. Finally, t e retirement stage is
    reached, in which funding has been allocated to replace or retire the
    standards, and no further support will be provided.</para>
  </sect1>
</appendix>