<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                   Vol 6 - A N N E X - F 
 ***************************************************************** 
-->

<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v6f-rdtm">
    <title>NISP Rationale - Traceability Matrix</title>

    <sect1 id="v6f-rdtm-B-1-int">
      <title>Introduction</title>

<para>The NISP specifies the minimum set of communication and
      information technology standards to be mandated for the acquisition of
      all NATO C3 systems. In order to assist planners and developers of
      future C3 systems and major upgrades to existing C3 systems, it also
      contains a set of emerging standards. In order to be able to judge on
      the timeframe in which mandatory standards will phase out, or emerging
      will become mandatory, a standards Traceability Matrix has been
      developed. It tracks NOSWG decisions for including or deleting standards
      and also keeps history of why these decisions have been taken. The
      matrix is meant to provide a quick overview of all NISP standards and is
      considered complementary to the NISP Rationale Document. It is both a
      "forward looking" and "history" document, i.e. it guides acquisition and
      development of new and emerging information systems, and gives an
      indication what standards are fading out (thus providing a baseline
      towards which standards existing systems should move). It could also
      answer questions why certain standards have been selected, and while
      others have been disregarded. The purpose of the Traceability Matrix is
      to provide background on the NOSWG decisions on why NISP standards have
      been selected, deleted or are considered fading. It should be seen as an
      integral part of both the NISP as well as the Rationale Document.</para>
<para>The Traceability Matrix identifies each NISP service area, and
      presents all associated standards in tabular form in the same order as
      the NISP. The tables refine each service area into one or more
      functional classes, with each class mapping to one or more mandatory,
      emerging, or fading standards in a life-cycle history column. A Remarks
      column provides optional information on why this standard has been
      selected, deleted or is considered fading as of NISP version 3. For
      earlier versions of the NISP no tracking has taken place. Where a
      mandatory standard has been identified against a particular service
      class or sub-class, the implication is that the standard should be
      offered at the boundary interface. Where an emerging standard is
      identified, the expectation is that it is likely to become mandatory,
      but that for the time being it does not fulfil all of the criteria for
      mandation. Where a standard is considered fading, the belief is that the
      standard, although currently still supported by the market, will be
      overtaken by newer technology in the short term. Projects are to take
      this into account in their planning.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v6f-rdtm-B-2-omat">
	<title>Operational Mission / Activities / Tasks</title>
      <?dbmerge area="omat"?>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v6f-rdtm-B-3-uis">
	<title>User Information Services</title>
      <?dbmerge area="uis"?>
    </sect1>
  
    <sect1 id="v6f-rdtm-B-4-ts">
	<title>Technical Services</title>
     <?dbmerge area="ts"?>
    </sect1>
 
    <sect1 id="v6f-rdtm-B-5-ias">
 	<title>Information Assurance</title>
     <?dbmerge area="ias"?>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v6f-rdtm-B-6-esm">
 	<title>Service Management and Control</title>
      <?dbmerge area="esm"?>
    </sect1>

</appendix>
