<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 6 -   A N N E X - C
*****************************************************************  
-->

<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v6c-refmod">
    <title>Reference Models</title>

    <para>By definition, a reference model is an abstract framework for
    understanding the relationships among the entities within a specified
    environment. It enables the development of specific architectures using
    consistent standards or specifications supporting that environment.</para>

    <para>A basic reference model will consists of the smallest set of
    unifying concepts, rules and relationships within a particular problem
    area, and is independent of specific standards, technologies,
    implementations, or other concrete details.</para>

    <para>The relationship between the Reference Model and the implementation
    of a particular abstract concept is illustrated in <xref linkend="v1e-trm" />.</para>

    <para>Reference models are a standard definitive document or conceptual
    representation of a system or process. It provides a structure which
    allows the modules and interfaces of a system to be described in a
    consistent manner. In the context of near-future NATO environments, member
    nations could use these general models in designing architectures for
    net-enabled systems and platforms. These models represent the mid-term
    common framework that NATO nations can build to. A common framework is one
    of the keys to ensuring interoperability.</para>

    <para>General reference models presented by industry do not take into
    account the typical Military or NATO unique situation. In the far-term,
    the NNEC approach will require us to establish a NATO Reference Model for
    services that tailored to complement the NATO mission.</para>

    <para>Reference models are a standard definitive document or conceptual
    representation of a system or process. It provides a structure which
    allows the modules and interfaces of a system to be described in a
    consistent manner. In the context of future NATO environments, member
    nations can use these models in designing architectures for net-enabled
    systems and platforms.</para>

    <para>Such assets can then participate in an NCO environment, by acting as
    interoperable nodes on a fixed or mobile ad hoc network. Once an element
    operates as a node, it can discover and register its needs and
    capabilities on a network, and use that network to communicate, interact
    and function with other nodes. The ultimate result is greater mission
    effectiveness.</para>

    <sect1 id="v1e-s1">
      <title>Platform Oriented Architecture Reference Models</title>

      <sect2 id="v1e-s2">
        <title>The NATO Technical Reference Model (NTRM)</title>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s3">
          <title>Purpose</title>

          <para>Within the context of information systems, a Technical
          Reference Model (TRM) is a generally accepted construct that
          provides a basic set of concepts and a conceptual framework for
          identifying and resolving standards issues.</para>

          <para>The main purpose of the NATO TRM (NTRM) is to structure the
          standards listed in the NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles
          (NISP). As such, it should be a stable model and modifications
          should be made very carefully.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s4">
          <title>Structure</title>

          <para>The NTRM focuses on separating data from applications and
          applications from the computing platform. This is a key principle
          when striving to attain a true open system environment. The NTRM
          provides the definitions necessary for designing and defining
          architectures and related service components. It also identifies
          service areas (i.e., capabilities that have been grouped together by
          functions), as well as their interfaces.</para>

          <para>As indicated above, the NTRM is designed to decouple the
          application and external environment from the platform. This allows
          for portability of the application and independence from the
          external devices (e.g., disk, mouse, keyboard, LAN). This is
          accomplished by defining the application program interface (API) and
          external environment interface (EEI) accordingly.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s5">
          <title>Basic Entities and Interfaces</title>

          <para>The basic elements of the NTRM are those identified in the
          POSIX OSE Reference Model. This model includes 3 classes of entities
          and 2 types of interfaces as follows:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Application Software Entity</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Application Program Interface (API)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Application Platform Entity</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>External Environment Interface (EEI)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>External Environment Entity</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <figure id="v1e-trm">
            <title>NTRM Services View</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="../figures/nato-trm.svg" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s6">
            <title>Application Software Entity</title>

            <para>The Application Software Entity includes both mission area
            and support applications.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Mission-area or user applications implement specific
                user requirements (e.g., personnel, material, and management).
                This application software may be COTS, GOTS, custom developed,
                or consist of a combination thereof.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Support applications (e.g., email and word processing)
                can be used to develop mission area specific applications or
                could be made readily available to the user. There are six
                support application categories:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Multimedia,</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Communications,</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Business Processing,</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Environment Management,</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Database utilities,</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Engineering support.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </sect4>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s7">
            <title>Application Platform Entity</title>

            <para>The Application Platform Entity contains the system services
            and the physical environment services. It is the second layer of
            the NTRM and includes the services in which information processing
            functionality is built.</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Service Areas are defined in <xref linkend="v1e-saNTRM" />.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Physical Environment services address the requirements
                for establishing the data interchange interface between
                physical resources and enable bus or communications link
                boards to address their peers in another node or system. They
                may also enable links to address processors or enable
                processors to address memory registers.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </sect4>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s8">
            <title>External Environment Entity</title>

            <para>The External Environment Entity consists of external
            services that interact with the physical environment services of
            the application platform entity. These services are classified
            into the general categories of user services (e. g., mouse,
            display), information exchange services (e.g., memory stick) and
            communications services (e.g., LAN, WAN).</para>
          </sect4>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s9">
            <title>Interfaces</title>

            <para>The Interfaces include both Application Programming
            Interfaces (API) and External Environment Interfaces
            (EEI)):</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The APIs are the interface between the application
                software entity and the application platform. They constitute
                a collection of standards-based interfaces,</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The External Environment Interfaces (EEI) are defined as
                the interfaces between the application platform and the
                external environment across which services are available,
                primarily in support of system and application software
                interoperability. User and data portability are provided
                directly by the EEI and provide the interfaces between the
                application platform entity and the external
                environment.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>A concept of internal interfaces (IIs), not included in the
            previous version of the model, complements the notions of APIs and
            EEIs:</para>

            <para>IIs are the interfaces within the system entities, both
            between sub-entities at the same level and sub-entities at
            different levels where sub-entities at a higher level make use of
            services offered by a lower level one. (A direct communication
            between two sub-entities at the same level is only possible at the
            lowest level).</para>

            <para>The interfaces are in principle supported or realized by
            commonly defined data models and structures (e.g., ACP 133 B
            Schema Information for Directory Services).</para>

            <para>Users should assess their own requirements and create a
            listing of services, interfaces, and standards that satisfy their
            own mission-area needs in conjunction with the NTRM
            accordingly.</para>

            <para>In addition, the NTRM can accommodate a wide variety of
            general- and special purpose systems. From the perspective of the
            application software entity, these services are provided by an
            application platform whether the particular services are provided
            from the local platform or from remote platforms that may comprise
            one or more nodes of a larger distributed system. The NTRM can
            also be applied in a distributed environment and networked
            environment.</para>

            <para>The objective of the NTRM is to provide a complete, as well
            as extensive set of features and capabilities. The NTRM provides
            consistency for user applications from a broader community in
            order to address interoperability, open systems, acquisition, and
            management issues associated with commercial off-the-shelf (COTS)
            and Government off-the-shelf (GOTS) products.</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-saNTRM">
          <title>Service Areas of the NTRM</title>

          <para>The System Services of the Application Platform Entity are
          used to structure the standards listed in the NISP. The classes and
          sub- classes described in the NISP are to be considered part of the
          NTRM. The 12 System Services areas are:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">User Interface Services.</emphasis>
              These services define how users may interact with an
              application. The term user interface in this context means a
              graphical user interface (GUI). Standards are not only required
              for setting up and managing graphical windows, but also for the
              toolkit and generic 'look and feel'.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Management Services.</emphasis>
              The management of data is central to most systems. To improve
              interoperability, data should be defined independently from the
              processes that create or use it, and should be maintained and
              shared among many processes.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Interchange
              Services.</emphasis> These services provide support for the
              interchange of data between applications. They are designed to
              handle data interchange between applications on the same or on
              heterogeneous platforms.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Graphics Services.</emphasis> These
              services provide functions required for creating and
              manipulating graphics.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Communication Services.</emphasis>
              These services provide distributed applications support for data
              access and applications interoperability in heterogeneous or
              homogeneous networked environments.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Operating System
              Services.</emphasis> These services are the core services needed
              to operate and administer the application platform and provide
              an interface between applications software and platform.
              Application programmers will use operating system services to
              obtain operating system functionality.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Internationalization
              Services.</emphasis> Within the context of the NTRM,
              internationalization provides a set of services and interfaces
              that allow a user to define, select, translate and switch
              between different culturally related application environments
              supported by the particular implementation. Character sets and
              data representation services include the capability to input,
              store, manipulate, retrieve, communicate, and present data
              independently of the coding scheme used. This includes the
              capability to maintain and access a central character set
              repository of all coded character sets used throughout the
              platform.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">System Management
              Services.</emphasis> Information systems are composed of a wide
              variety of diverse resources that must be managed effectively to
              achieve the goals of an open system environment. While the
              individual resources (such as printers, software, users,
              processors) may differ widely, the abstraction of these
              resources as managed objects allows for their treatment in a
              uniform manner.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Security Services.</emphasis>
              Different groups of individuals within and across the various
              NATO applications need to work with specific sets of data
              elements. Access to these sets of data elements is to be
              restricted to authorized users. Satisfaction of this requirement
              has traditionally been accomplished by the implementation of
              separate information systems. Organizations cannot continue to
              afford to implement separate information systems to satisfy this
              requirement, nor is it effective to require the user to change
              interface components every time the need arises to operate with
              a different restricted data set. Significant benefit will accrue
              when an individual information system can effectively support
              the needs of different groups of users and data sets.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Distributed Computing
              Services.</emphasis> These services provide specialized support
              for applications that may be physically or logically dispersed
              among computer systems in a network, but yet wish to maintain a
              co-operative processing environment. The classical definition of
              a computer becomes blurred as the processes that contribute to
              information processing become distributed across a facility or a
              network. As with other cross-cutting services, the requisite
              components of distributed computing services typically exist
              within particular service areas.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Software Engineering
              Services.</emphasis> The procedural aspect of an application is
              embodied in the programming languages used to code it.
              Additionally, professional system developers require methods and
              tools appropriate to the development and maintenance of
              applications.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">Common C2 Applications
              Services.</emphasis> These services provide the ability to view
              data (i.e., share) in a common way across the network. Common C2
              Applications Services promote interoperability among diverse
              functional mission area domains and may be executed between both
              individual and multiple functional application domain
              areas.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v1e-s10">
        <title>NCOE Component Model (NCM)</title>

        <para>The NTRM provides the structural basis for defining the NCOE
        (NATO Common Operating Environment) Component Model (NCM).</para>

        <figure id="v1e-ref-cm">
          <title>The NCOE Component Model</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../figures/ncoe-cm.svg" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The principal components of the NCM (see <xref
        linkend="v1e-ref-cm" />) include:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Kernel Services.</emphasis> The Kernel
            Services are that subset of the NCOE component segments, which are
            required for all compliant platforms. At a minimum, this sub-set
            would consist of the operating system, windowing software,
            security services, segment installation software and an executive
            manager.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Infrastructure Services.</emphasis>
            Infrastructure services are those services that directly support
            the flow of information across NATO systems. Infrastructure
            services provide a set of integrated capabilities that the
            applications will access to invoke NCOE services.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Common Support Application
            Services.</emphasis> Common Support Application Services provide
            services to process and view data in a common way (share data)
            across the network. The NCOE common support application services
            promote interoperability among various Mission
            Applications.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Network Services.</emphasis> The NCOE
            Network Services constitute the basic interface between the
            platform and the underlying networking infrastructure and include
            the Internet Sub-layer services.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Application Programming
            Interfaces</emphasis>. Applications are integrated into the NCOE
            through a common set of Application Programming Interfaces (APIs).
            The APIs are invoked by the applications and services as required
            <footnote>
                <para>The term API is to be understood in a local sense (e.g.
                APIs between components interfaced on a user desktop), as well
                as in a distributed sense (e.g. interfaces from legacy or
                external components using an Object Request Broker (ORB)
                through IDL interfaces).</para>
              </footnote>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Data Component Definition</emphasis>.
            The data component refers to the way in which data is taken into
            account in the NCOE and is related to the main components of the
            NCOE (Common Support Application Services, Infrastructure
            Services, Kernel Services) and even, out of NCOE components, in
            the strictest sense, to Mission Applications.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Support Services</emphasis>. The NCOE
            Support Services include Methods &amp; Tools, Information
            Repository, Training Services, System Management and
            Security.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v1e-s11">
      <title>Service Oriented Architecture Reference Models</title>

      <sect2 id="v1e-s12">
        <title>What is SOA?</title>

        <para>Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) is a paradigm for organizing
        and using distributed capabilities that may be under the control of
        different ownership domains. It is natural in such a context to think
        of one person’s needs being met by capabilities offered by someone
        else or, in the world of distributed computing, one computer agent’s
        requirements being met by a computer agent belonging to a different
        owner. There is not necessarily a one-to-one correlation between needs
        and capabilities; the granularity of needs and capabilities vary from
        fundamental to complex, and any given need may require the combining
        of numerous capabilities while any single capability may address more
        than one need. The perceived value of SOA is that it provides a
        powerful framework for matching needs and capabilities and for
        combining capabilities to address those needs.</para>

        <para>Visibility, interaction, and effect are key concepts for
        describing the SOA paradigm. <emphasis
        role="bold">Visibility</emphasis> refers to the capacity for those
        with needs and those with capabilities to be able to see each other to
        interact. Visibility is typically enhanced through the use of metadata
        to describe such aspects as functional and technical requirements,
        related constraints and policies, and mechanisms for interaction. For
        maximum visibility, metadata must be in a form in which its syntax and
        semantics are widely accessible and understandable.</para>

        <para>Whereas visibility introduces the possibilities for matching
        needs to capabilities (and vice versa), <emphasis
        role="bold">interaction </emphasis> is the activity of using the
        capability. Typically mediated by the exchange of messages, an
        interaction proceeds through a series of information exchanges and
        invoked actions. There are many facets of interaction; but they are
        all grounded in a particular <emphasis role="bold">execution context
        </emphasis> – the set of technical and business elements that together
        form a path between those with needs and those with capabilities and
        that permit information to be exchanged, actions to be performed and
        provides a decision point for any policies and contracts that may be
        in force.</para>

        <para>The purpose of using a capability is to realize one or more
        <emphasis role="bold">real world effects</emphasis>. At its core, an
        interaction is “an act” rather than “an object” and the result of a
        interaction is an effect (or a set/series of effects).</para>

        <para>The expected effects, together with relevant preconditions
        associated with those effects, should be made visible as part of the
        capability metadata and form an important part of the assessment as to
        whether a given capability matches similarly described needs. It is
        not possible to describe every possible effect of using a capability:
        indeed a cornerstone of SOA is that such knowledge is not
        necessary.</para>

        <para>A concept that is considered central to SOA has not yet been
        mentioned – that of <emphasis role="bold">service</emphasis>. Both
        needs and capabilities exist outside of SOA. What distinguishes SOA is
        the perceived improvement in bringing needs and capabilities together.
        <emphasis role="bold">In SOA, services are the mechanism by which
        needs and capabilities are brought together.</emphasis> SOA is not the
        solution of domain problems but rather a way of organizing a wider
        array of possibilities to generate a domain solution. By itself, SOA
        does not provide a solution to a difficult domain problem where a
        satisfactory solution does not already exist. SOA can, however,
        provide an organizing and delivery paradigm that enables one to get
        more value from use of both solutions which are locally “owned” and
        solutions under the control of others. It also enables one to express
        solutions in a way that makes it easier to modify or evolve the
        identified solution or to try alternate domain solutions.</para>

        <para>The concepts of visibility, interaction, and effect apply
        directly to services in the same manner as these were described for
        the general SOA paradigm. Visibility is promoted by the <emphasis
        role="bold">service description</emphasis> which contains the
        information necessary to interact with the service and describes this
        in such terms as the service inputs, outputs, and associated
        semantics. The service description also conveys what is accomplished
        when the service is invoked and the conditions for invoking the
        service. In general, entities (people and organizations) offer
        capabilities through services and act as <emphasis role="bold">service
        providers</emphasis>. Those with needs who make use of capabilities
        through their associated services are referred to as <emphasis
        role="bold">service consumers</emphasis>. The service description
        allows prospective consumers to decide if the service is suitable for
        their current needs and establish whether a consumer satisfies the
        requirements, if any, of the service provider to be permitted
        access.</para>

        <para>Having described what is SOA, it is appropriate to note several
        things which are related but are not necessary attributes or
        restrictions.</para>

        <para>SOA identifies necessary aspects of interactions involving
        multiple ownership domains; however, it does not directly embody
        concepts relating to ownership.</para>

        <para>SOA is commonly implemented using Web services, but services can
        be made visible, support interaction, and generate effects through
        other implementations.</para>

        <para>By following a Service-Oriented Architecture NATO nations can
        then participate in an NNEC environment, by acting as interoperable
        nodes on a fixed or mobile ad hoc network. Once an element operates as
        a node, it can discover and register its needs and capabilities on a
        network, and use that network to communicate, interact and function
        with other nodes. The ultimate result is greater mission
        effectiveness.</para>

        <para>In February of 2005, the Organization for the Advancement of
        Structured Information Standards (OASIS) started standards work to
        define an SOA reference model (SOA-RM) by establishing a technical
        committee for that sole purpose.</para>

        <para>The goal of OASIS SOA-RM technical committee is to "establish a
        Reference Model to encourage the continued growth of specific and
        different SOA implementations whilst preserving a common layer that
        can be shared and understood between those or future
        implementations."</para>

        <para>Achievement of their goals for this reference model will be done
        by defining the fundamental nature of SOA, and emerge with a common
        vocabulary and understanding of SOA. As such, it will provide a
        conforming reference that treats SOA as a powerful abstract model that
        is independent of the various inevitable technology evolutions.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v1e-s13">
        <title>The Benefits of Service Oriented Architecture</title>

        <para>The main drivers for SOA-based architectures are the requirement
        to facilitate the manageable growth of large-scale enterprise systems,
        the requirement to facilitate Internet-scale provisioning and use of
        services and the requirement to reduce costs in organization to
        organization cooperation.</para>

        <para>The value of SOA is that it provides a simple scalable paradigm
        for organizing large networks of systems that require interoperability
        to realize the value inherent in the individual components. Indeed,
        SOA is scalable because it makes the fewest possible assumptions,
        including about the network and also minimizes any trust assumptions
        that are often implicitly made in smaller scale systems.</para>

        <para>An architect using SOA principles is better equipped, therefore,
        to develop systems that are scalable, evolvable and manageable. It
        should be easier to decide how to integrate functionality across
        ownership boundaries. For example, a large company that acquires a
        smaller company must determine how to integrate the acquired IT
        infrastructure into its overall IT portfolio.</para>

        <para>Through this inherent ability to scale and evolve, SOA enables
        an IT portfolio which is also adaptable to the needs of a specific
        problem domain or process architecture. The infrastructure SOA
        encourages is also more agile and responsive than one built on an
        exponential number of pair-wise interfaces. Therefore, SOA can also
        provide a solid foundation for business agility and
        adaptability.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v1e-s14">
        <title>Overview of the Model</title>

        <para>A key concept of SOA is that of <emphasis role="bold">service
        </emphasis>. In general, entities (people and organizations) create
        capabilities to solve or support a solution for the problems they face
        in the course of their business. SOA is a way to organize the world
        around this key concept of service. The noun “service” is defined in
        dictionaries as “The performance of work (a function) by one for
        another.” However, service, as the term is generally understood, also
        combines the following related ideas:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The capability to perform work for another</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The specification of the work offered for another</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The offer to perform work for another</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>These concepts emphasize a distinction between a capability and
        the ability to bring that capability to bear in the context of SOA,
        where the capability exists independently of SOA. The term service
        should, therefore, be understood as a set of separate, yet
        interrelated and more precise concepts. These concepts are an offer,
        interaction and effect.</para>

        <para>The concept of an <emphasis role="bold">offer</emphasis> follows
        directly from the dictionary definition of service: 'by one' and 'for
        another.' In general terms, an offer is a proposal; made by providers
        which may possess a capability that address a need. In order to use a
        service, it is necessary to know that it exists, what is accomplished
        if the service is invoked, how the service is invoked, and other
        characteristics. Collectively this is the service <emphasis
        role="bold"> visibility</emphasis>. When given an explicit searchable
        form, this information allows, for example, prospective consumers to
        decide if the service is suitable for their current needs and
        establish whether a consumer satisfies any requirements of the service
        provider to be permitted access. This information constitutes the
        <emphasis role="bold"> service description</emphasis>.</para>

        <para>The convergence of a capability and a need results in an
        <emphasis role="bold">interaction</emphasis>. In an SOA, interaction
        is effected by exchanging information between service providers and
        consumers. Typically this is achieved by exchanging messages using a
        standardized protocol; however, there are many modalities possible for
        interacting with services.</para>

        <para>At its core, an interaction is “an act” rather than “an object.
        Therefore, interaction is the focus of the interfaces and behaviour
        necessary to support the interaction. Recall that interaction may, and
        typically does, involve crossing ownership boundaries. SOA identifies
        some of the necessary aspects of interactions involving multiple
        ownership domains; however, it does not directly embody concepts
        relating to ownership.</para>

        <para>The final key concept is the <emphasis role="bold">real world
        effect</emphasis> of using services; it is always the case that there
        is an intended purpose to providing a service and similarly to using a
        service. Given that there is often an ownership boundary between the
        service provider and consumer, there is a natural distinction to be
        drawn between the public interactions with a service and the private
        actions of both the service provider and consumer. This distinction
        maintains and encourages independence of each service participant
        which, in turn, greatly enhances the scalability and security
        attributes of SOA. Focus can be directed to the public aspects of
        using a service by examining the <emphasis
        role="bold">conditions</emphasis> of using a service and the <emphasis
        role="bold">expectations</emphasis> that arise as a result of using
        the service. Service conditions are loosely associated with the
        <emphasis role="bold">service policies</emphasis> and the expectations
        with <emphasis role="bold">service contracts </emphasis>.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v1e-s15">
        <title>The SOA Reference Model</title>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s16">
          <title>Service</title>

          <para>A <emphasis role="bold">service</emphasis> is a means to
          access to one or more capabilities, where the access is provided
          using a prescribed interface and is exercised consistent with
          constraints and policies as specified by the service description. A
          service is provided by one entity – the <emphasis
          role="bold">service provider </emphasis> – for use by others, but
          the eventual consumers of the service may not be known to the
          service provider and may demonstrate uses of the service beyond the
          scope originally conceived by the provider,</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Information returned in response to a request,</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>A change to the shared state of defined entities,
              or</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Some combination of the above.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Note, the <emphasis role="bold">service consumer</emphasis> in
          (1) does not typically know how the information is generated, e.g.
          whether it is extracted from a database or generated dynamically; in
          (2), the service consumer does not typically know how the state
          change is effected. In either case, the service consumer would need
          to provide input parameters required by the service and the service
          would return information, status indicators, or error descriptions,
          where both the input and output are as described by the data model
          exposed through the published service interface. Note that the
          service may be invoked without requiring information from the
          consumer (other than a command to initiate action) and may
          accomplish its functions without providing any return or feedback to
          the consumer.</para>

          <para>The service concept above emphasizes a distinction between a
          capability that represents some functionality created to address a
          need and the point of access to bring that capability to bear in the
          context of SOA. It is assumed that capabilities exist outside of the
          SOA. In actual use, maintaining this distinction may not be critical
          (i.e. the service may be talked about in terms of being the
          capability) but the separation is pertinent in terms of a clear
          expression of the nature of SOA and the value it provides.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s17">
          <title>Service description</title>

          <para>The service description represents the information needed in
          order to use a service. It may be considered part of or the complete
          set of the metadata associated with a service.
          In any case, the service description overlaps and shares many common
          properties with service metadata. In most cases, there is no one
          “right” set of metadata but rather the metadata content depends on
          the context and the needs of the parties using the associated
          entity. The same holds for a service description. While there are
          certain elements that are likely to be part of any service
          description, most notably the data model, many elements such as
          function and policy may vary.</para>

          <para>Best practice suggests that the service description should be
          represented using a standard, referenceable format. Such a format
          facilitates the use of common processing tools (such as discovery
          engines) that can, in turn, capitalize on the service
          description.</para>

          <para>While the concept of a SOA supports use of a service without
          the service consumer needing to know the details of the service
          implementation, the service description makes available critical
          information that a consumer needs in order to decide whether or not
          to use a service. In particular, a service consumer must possess the
          following items of information:</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>That the service exists and is <emphasis role="bold">
              reachable</emphasis> (i.e., the service is <emphasis
              role="bold"> visible</emphasis> to the service consumer and
              there are sufficient mechanisms in place for the service
              participants to be able to interact);</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>That the service performs a certain function or set of
              functions;</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>That the service operates under a specified set of
              constraints and policies;</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>That the service will (to some implicit or explicit
              extent) comply with policies as prescribed by the service
              consumer;</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>How to interact with the service in order to achieve
              the required objectives, including the format and content of
              information exchanged between the service and the consumer and
              the sequences of information exchange that may be
              expected.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>

          <para>Subsequent sections of this document will deal with these
          aspects of a service in detail but the following subsections will
          describe the relationship of these information items to the service
          description.</para>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s18">
            <title>Service Reachability</title>

            <para>A service description should include sufficient data to
            permit a service consumer and service provider to exchange
            information. This might include metadata (such as the location of
            the service and what information protocols it supports and
            requires) and information that allows the service consumer to
            determine if the service is currently reachable or not.</para>
          </sect4>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s19">
            <title>Service Functionality</title>

            <para>Item 2 relates to the need to unambiguously express the
            function(s) of the service and the real world effects that result from it being invoked. This portion of the
            description needs to be expressed in a way that is generally
            understandable by service consumers but able to accommodate a
            vocabulary that is sufficiently expressive for the domain for
            which the service provides its functionality. The description of
            functionality may include, among other possibilities, a textual
            description intended for human consumption or identifiers or
            keywords referenced to specific machine-processable definitions.
            For a full description, it may be useful to indicate multiple
            identifiers or keywords from a number of different collections of
            definitions.</para>

            <para>Part of the description of functionality may include
            underlying technical assumptions that determine the limits of
            functionality exposed by the service or of the underlying
            capability.</para>
          </sect4>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s20">
            <title>Policies Related to a Service</title>

            <para>Items 3 and 4 from Section 2.2.4.2 relate to the service
            description’s support for associating constraints and policies
            with a service and providing necessary information for prospective
            consumers to evaluate if a service will act in a manner consistent
            with the consumer’s constraints and policies.</para>

            <para>In some situations the consumer may similarly provide an
            indication of its constraints and policies to support a service’
            need to do a similar evaluation of suitability. Thus, both
            prospective consumers and providers are likely to use the service
            description to establish what Section 2.2.5.3 refers to as the
            <emphasis role="bold">execution context</emphasis>.</para>
          </sect4>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s21">
            <title>Service Interface</title>

            <para>The service interface is the means referred to in Item 5 for
            interacting with a service. It includes the specific protocols,
            commands, and information exchange by which actions are initiated
            that result in the real world effects as specified through the
            service functionality portion of the service description.</para>

            <para>The specifics of the interface should be syntactically
            represented in a standard referenceable format. These prescribe
            what information needs to be provided to the service in order to
            exercise its functionality and/or the results of the service
            invocation to be returned to the service consumer. This logical
            expression of the set of information items associated with the
            consumption of the service is often referred to as the service
            data model. It should be noted that the particulars of the
            standard referenceable format is beyond the scope of the reference
            model. However, requiring that mechanisms be available (in order
            to define and retrieve such definitions) is fundamental to the SOA
            concept.</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s22">
          <title>Descriptions and Metadata</title>

          <para>One of the hallmarks of a Service Oriented Architecture is the
          degree of documentation and description associated with it;
          particularly machine processable descriptions – otherwise known as
          metadata.</para>

          <para>The purpose of this metadata is to facilitate integration,
          particularly across ownership domains. By providing public
          descriptions, it makes it possible for potential participants to
          construct applications that use services and even offer compatible
          services. Standardizing the formats of such metadata reduces the
          cost and burden of producing the descriptions necessary to promote
          reuse and integration.</para>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s23">
            <title>The roles of description</title>

            <para>An important additional benefit of metadata – as opposed to
            informal natural language descriptions – is its potential to
            facilitate automated software development. Both service providers
            and service consumers can benefit from such automation – reducing
            the cost of developing such systems.</para>

            <para>For example, metadata can be used as a basis of discovery in
            dynamic systems. Metadata can assist in managing a service,
            validating and auditing usage of services which may also be
            simplified by rich metadata. It can also help ensure that
            requirements and expectations (regarding the content of any data
            interchanged) are properly interpreted and fulfilled.</para>
          </sect4>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s24">
            <title>The Limits of Description</title>

            <para>There are well-known theoretic limits on the effectiveness
            of descriptions – it is simply not possible to specify, completely
            and unambiguously the precise semantics of a service. There will
            always be unstated assumptions made by the describer of a service
            that must be implicitly shared by readers of the description. This
            applies to machine processable descriptions as well as to human
            readable descriptions.</para>

            <para>Fortunately, complete precision is not necessary either –
            what is required is sufficient precision to enable required
            functionality.</para>

            <para>Another kind of limit of service descriptions is more
            straightforward: whenever a repository is searched using any kind
            of query there is always the potential for zero or more responses.
            There may be many reasons why a multiplicity of responses is
            returned: there might be several versions of the service, there
            might be competing services that offer overlapping functionality
            and there might be services from multiple different
            providers.</para>

            <para>In the case that there is more than one response, this set
            of responses has to be converted into a choice of a single service
            in order for a service consumer to ensure the required function
            performed. In a multi-provider scenario, that choice must also
            take into account real world aspects of the service – such as
            whether the service consumer can identify the provider, can or
            should trust the provider, and whether the provider is reliable
            and timely in delivering the service offered. It is unlikely that
            all such factors can be easily and securely encoded in
            descriptions and search criteria.</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v1e-s25">
        <title>Interacting with Services</title>

        <para>Interacting with a service involves exchanging information with
        the service and performing actions against the service. In many cases,
        this is accomplished by sending and receiving messages, but there are
        other modes possible that do not involve explicit message
        transmission. However, for simplicity, we often refer to message
        exchange as the primary mode of interaction with a service. The forms
        of information exchanged and understood, together with the mechanisms
        used to exchange information, constitute the <emphasis
        role="bold">service interface </emphasis> –.</para>

        <para>The key concepts that are important in understanding what it is
        involved in interacting with services are the <emphasis role="bold">
        data model</emphasis>, the <emphasis role="bold">process model
        </emphasis>, the <emphasis role="bold">execution context</emphasis>
        and the <emphasis role="bold">expectations</emphasis> about the
        interaction.</para>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s26">
          <title>Data Model</title>

          <para>The data model of a service is a characterization of the
          information associated with the use of the service.</para>

          <para>The scope of the data model includes the format of exchanged
          information, the structural relationships within documents and the
          definition of terms used. Typically, only information about, and
          data potentially included in, an exchange with a service are
          generally considered as being part of that service's data
          model.</para>

          <para>There are two important aspects of a data model that are
          important in interpreting information exchange – the structure of
          the information and the meaning assigned to elements of the
          information. Particularly for information that is exchanged across
          an ownership boundary, the interpretation of strings and other
          tokens in the information is a critical part of the semantics of the
          interaction.</para>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s27">
            <title>Structure</title>

            <para>Understanding the representation, structure and form of
            information exchanged is a key initial step in ensuring effective
            interactions with a service. There are several levels of such
            structural information; ranging from the encoding of character
            data, through the use of formats such as XML, SOAP and
            schema-based representations.</para>

            <para>A described data model typically has a great deal to say
            about the form of messages, about the types of the various
            components of messages and so on. However, pure “typed”
            information is not sufficient to completely describe the
            appropriate interpretation of data.</para>
          </sect4>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s28">
            <title>Semantics and Ontology</title>

            <para>The primary task of any communication infrastructure is to
            facilitate the exchange of information and the exchange of intent.
            For example, a purchase order combines two somewhat orthogonal
            aspects: the description of the items being purchased and the fact
            that one party intends to purchase those items from another party.
            Even if for exchanges that do not cross any ownership boundaries,
            exchanges with services have similar aspects: this is an update to
            the customer profile with these changes.</para>

            <para>Especially in the case where the exchanges are across
            ownership boundaries, a critical issue is the interpretation of
            the data. This interpretation must be consistent between the
            participants in the service interaction. Consistent interpretation
            is a stronger requirement than merely type (or structural)
            consistency – the tokens in the data itself must also have a
            shared basis.</para>

            <para>An ontology is a formal description of terms and the
            relationships between them in a given context. It will include
            information about how terms should be interpreted within a given
            context, constraints on and functions of valid values for the data
            and associated properties, as well as information about possible
            relationships of some terms to other terms (hierarchical,
            class/sub class, associative, dependent, etc.).</para>

            <para>The role of explicit ontologies in an SOA is to provide a
            firm basis for selecting correct interpretations for elements of
            information exchanged.</para>

            <para>Ontologies also provide a point of context to facilitate the
            reinterpretation of data. Such a reinterpretation is effectively
            represented as a particular traversal of the graph of concepts and
            relationships embodied in the ontology. How much automation of
            ontology walking is appropriate will depend on the nature of the
            service and the service participants.</para>

            <para>Note that, for the most part, it is not expected that
            service consumers and providers would actually exchange ontologies
            in their interaction – the role of the ontology is a background
            one – it facilitates sound interactions. Hence ontology references
            are mostly to be found in <emphasis role="bold">service
            descriptions</emphasis>.</para>

            <para>More specifically, and in order for a service to be
            consistent, the service should make consistent use of terms as
            defined in an ontology. Specific domain semantics are beyond the
            scope of this reference model; but there is a requirement that the
            service interface enable providers and consumers to identify
            unambiguously those definitions that are relevant to their
            respective domains.</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s29">
          <title>Behavioural model</title>

          <para>The second key requirement for successful interactions with
          services is knowledge of the process or temporal aspects of
          interacting with the service. Loosely, this can be characterized as
          knowledge of the actions on, responses to and temporal dependencies
          between actions on the service.</para>

          <para>For example, in a security-controlled access to a database
          service, the actions available to a service consumer might include
          presenting credentials, requesting database updates and reading
          results of queries. The security may be based on a
          challenge-response protocol. For example, the initiator presents an
          initial token of identity, the responder presents a challenge and
          the initiator responds to the challenge in a way that satisfies the
          service. Only after the user’s credentials have been verified will
          any action that queries and/or updates the database be accepted. The
          sequences of actions involved are a critical aspect of the knowledge
          required for successful use of the secured database service.</para>

          <para>There are other aspects of the behaviour of services that are
          important. These include, for example, whether the service is
          transactional, idempotent or long running. As a particular example,
          a service that supports updating an account balance with a
          transaction is typically idempotent; i.e., the state of the account
          would not be affected should a subsequent interaction be attempted
          for the same transaction.</para>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s30">
            <title>Action model</title>

            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">action model</emphasis> of a
            service is about the individual actions that may be invoked
            against the service. Of course, a great portion of the behaviour
            resulting from an action may be private; however, the expected
            public view of a service surely includes the implied effects of
            actions.</para>
          </sect4>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s31">
            <title>Process Model</title>

            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">process model</emphasis>
            characterizes the temporal relationships between actions and
            events associated with interacting with the service. It is fairly
            common to partition the process model associated with a service
            into two levels: the particular sequences of operations needed to
            achieve single service exchanges and longer term transactions.
            These two levels may be nested – a long running transaction is
            often composed of sequences of exchange patterns.</para>

            <para>Note that although the process model is an essential part of
            this Reference Model, its extent is not completely defined. In
            some architectures the process model will include aspects that are
            not strictly part of SOA – for example, in this reference model we
            do not address the orchestration of multiple services – although
            orchestration and choreography may be part of the process model of
            a given architecture. At a minimum, the process model must cover
            the interactions with the service itself.</para>
          </sect4>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s32">
            <title>Higher-order attributes of processes</title>

            <para>Beyond the straightforward mechanics of interacting with a
            service there are other, higher-order, attributes of services’
            process models that are also often important. These can include
            whether the service is <emphasis
            role="bold">idempotent</emphasis>, whether the service is
            <emphasis role="bold">long-running</emphasis> in nature and
            whether it is important to account for any <emphasis
            role="bold">transactional</emphasis> aspects of the
            service.</para>

            <para>A service is <emphasis role="bold">idempotent</emphasis> if
            subsequent attempts to perform identical transactions are
            discounted. For example, it often important that a bank will only
            cash a check once – subsequent attempts to cash the same check
            should be ignored, rejected or initiate an alert process. Note
            that idempotency is not the same as effect-free or stateless: a
            service that always returns the same results is idempotent, but
            only by virtue of the fact that it does not change from invocation
            to invocation.</para>

            <para>Idempotency is an important attribute of a service in an
            environment where there is a significant possibility that the
            interaction between the service provider and consumer may be
            interrupted – whether by a network issue or simply one of the
            parties dropping out. A strategy for recovering from such a
            breakdown is to attempt to repeat the interaction – an idempotent
            service is required to ignore such repetitions should the
            transaction have been completed beforehand.</para>

            <para>A service is <emphasis role="bold">long-running</emphasis>
            if the activities engendered by an interaction are likely to
            persist beyond the immediate interaction itself. For example, a
            classic book selling service might be viewed as a long-running
            service: the activity started by the purchase of the book may take
            days or weeks to complete. It can be important to account for a
            long-running process as it has implications for the kinds of
            infrastructure needed – both by the service provider and by the
            service consumer – in order to be able to keep track of the
            progress of the interaction.</para>

            <para>Often, once a business-level contract has been agreed on, it
            can be difficult or impossible to simply cancel the consequences
            of the agreement. This is particularly an issue when the agreement
            of several parties is necessary simultaneously. For example,
            booking a vacation may require a flight ticket as well as a hotel
            room – without either component the result is not a vacation.
            However, the airline typically will not have a relationship with
            the hotel. If there are no hotel rooms available for the proposed
            vacation then the airline ticket will need to be cancelled.</para>

            <para>The process of reversing a previously completed transaction
            – backing out of the airline booking for example – is likely to be
            quite different to the process for the original transaction;
            possibly even involving a different service. Knowledge of such
            compensatory actions is a key aspect of interacting with <emphasis
            role="bold">transactional</emphasis> services.</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s33">
          <title>Actualized Services</title>

          <para>The <emphasis role="bold">execution context</emphasis> of a
          service interaction is the set of infrastructure elements, process
          entities and policy assertions that are deployed as part of the
          instantiated service interaction. In effect, the execution context
          defines the point of contact between abstractions such as service
          descriptions which are mostly about the potential for interaction
          and an actually executing service. It is the point of measurement
          between the service description and reality, between theory and
          practice.</para>

          <para>The execution context is not limited to one side of the
          interaction; rather it concerns the totality of the interaction –
          including the service provider, the service consumer and the common
          infrastructure needed to mediate the interaction.</para>

          <para>The execution context is central to many aspects of a service
          interaction. It defines, for example, the decision point for any
          policy enforcement relating to the service interaction. Note that a
          policy decision point is not necessarily the same as an enforcement
          point: an execution context is not by itself something that lends
          itself to enforcement. On the other hand, any enforcement mechanism
          of a policy is likely to take into account the particulars of the
          actual service interaction.</para>

          <para>The execution context also allows us to distinguish services
          from one another. Different instances of the same service – denoting
          interactions between a given service provider and different service
          consumers for example – are distinguished by virtue of the fact that
          their execution contexts are different.</para>

          <para>Finally, the execution context is also the context in which
          the interpretation of data that is exchanged takes place – it is
          where the symbol grounding happens as it were. A particular string
          has a particular meaning in a service interaction in a particular
          context – the execution context.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v1e-s34">
        <title>Real World Effect</title>

        <para>There is always a particular purpose associated with interacting
        with a service. Conversely, a service provider (and consumer) often
        has a priori conditions that apply to its interactions. The service
        consumer is trying to achieve some result by interacting with the
        service, as is the service provider. At first sight, such a goal can
        often be expressed as “trying to get the service to do something” This
        is sometimes known as the <emphasis role="bold">real world effect
        </emphasis> of using a service.</para>

        <para>The internal actions that a service providers and consumers
        perform as a result of participation in service interactions are, by
        definition, private and fundamentally unknowable. By unknowable we
        mean both that external parties cannot see others’ private actions
        and, furthermore should not have explicit knowledge of them. Instead
        we focus on the state that is shared between the parties – the
        <emphasis role="bold"> shared state</emphasis>. Actions by service
        providers and consumers lead to modifications of this shared state;
        and that in turn leads to modified <emphasis
        role="bold">expectations</emphasis> by the participants.</para>

        <para>Note that there does not need to be a third party to act as a
        kind of escrow for the shared state between service providers and
        consumers. The elements of the shared state are inferred from the
        communication that has occurred between the participants together with
        other context as necessary. Of course, in the case where adjudication
        is a possibility, it becomes prudent to record the interaction – so
        that disputes can be arbitrated.</para>

        <para>Although there is not necessarily a one-to-one correspondence,
        the natural container for the conditions applying to a service is the
        <emphasis role="bold">service policy</emphasis>. Similarly, the
        natural container for the expectations arising from a service is the
        <emphasis role="bold">service contract</emphasis>.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v1e-s35">
        <title>Policies and Contracts</title>

        <para>A <emphasis role="bold">policy</emphasis> represents some
        constraint or condition on the use, deployment or description of an
        owned entity as defined by any participant. A <emphasis
        role="bold">contract</emphasis>, on the other hand, represents an
        agreement by two or more parties. Like policies, agreements are also
        about the conditions of use of a service; they may also constrain the
        expected real world effects of using a service. The reference model is
        focused primarily on the concept of policies and contracts as they
        apply to services. We are not concerned with the form or
        expressiveness of any language used to express policies and
        contracts.</para>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s36">
          <title>Service Policy</title>

          <para>A policy is a statement of the obligations, constraints or
          other conditions of use of a given service that expresses intent on
          the part of a participant. More particularly, policies are a way for
          expressing the relationship between the <emphasis
          role="bold">execution context</emphasis> and the <emphasis
          role="bold">data</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">behaviour
          models</emphasis> associated with the service.</para>

          <para>Conceptually, there are three aspects of policies: the policy
          assertion, the policy owner (sometimes referred to as the policy
          subject) and policy enforcement.</para>

          <para>For example, the assertion: “All messages are triple-DES
          encrypted is an assertion regarding the forms of messages. As an
          assertion, it is measurable: it may be true or false depending on
          whether the traffic is encrypted or not. Policy assertions are often
          about the way the service is realized; i.e., they are about the
          relationship between the service and its execution context.</para>

          <para>A policy always represents a participant’s point of view. An
          assertion becomes the policy of a participant when they make it
          their policy. This linking is normally not part of the assertion
          itself. For example, if the service consumer declares that “Al
          messages are triple-DES encrypted”, then that reflects the policy of
          the service consumer. This policy is one that may be asserted by the
          service consumer independently of any agreement from the service
          provider.</para>

          <para>Finally, a policy may be enforced. Techniques for the
          enforcement of policies depend on the nature of the policy.
          Conceptually, service policy enforcement amounts to ensuring that
          the policy assertion is consistent with the real world. This might
          mean preventing unauthorized actions to be performed or states to be
          entered into; it can also mean initiating compensatory actions when
          a policy violation has been detected. An unenforceable constraint is
          not a policy; it would be better described as a wish.</para>

          <para>Policies potentially apply to many aspects of SOA: security,
          privacy, manageability, Quality of Service and so on. Beyond such
          infrastructure-oriented policies, participants may also express
          business-oriented policies – such as hours of business, return
          policies and so on.</para>

          <para>Policy assertions should be written in a form that is
          understandable to, and processable by, the parties to whom the
          policy is directed. Policies may need to be automatically
          interpreted, depending on the purpose and applicability of the
          policy and whether it might affect whether a particular service is
          used or not.</para>

          <para>A natural point of contact between service participants and
          policies associated with the service is in the service description. It would be natural for the service description
          to contain references to the policies associated with the
          service.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s37">
          <title>Service Contract</title>

          <para>Where a policy is associated with the point of view of
          individual participants, a contract represents an agreement between
          two or more participants. Like policies, contracts can cover a wide
          range of aspects of services: quality of service agreements,
          interface and choreography agreements and commercial
          agreements</para>

          <para>Thus, following the analysis above, a service contract is a
          measurable assertion that governs the requirements and expectations
          of two or more parties. Unlike policy enforcement, which is usually
          the responsibility of the policy owner, contract enforcement may
          involve resolving disputes between the parties to the contract. The
          resolution of such disputes may involve appeals to higher
          authorities.</para>

          <para>Like policies, contracts may be expressed in a form that
          permits automated interpretation. Where a contract is used to codify
          the results of a service interaction, it is good practice to
          represent it in a machine processable form. This facilitates
          automatic service composition, for example. Where a contract is used
          to describe over-arching agreements between service providers and
          consumers, then the priority is likely to make such contracts
          readable by people.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v1e-s38">
        <title>Visibility</title>

        <para>For a service provider and consumer to interact with each other
        they have to be able to ‘see’ each other. This is true for any
        consumer/provider relationship – including in an application program
        where one program calls another: without the proper libraries being
        present the function call cannot complete. In the case of SOA
        visibility needs to be emphasized because it is not necessarily
        obvious how service participants can see each other to
        interact.</para>

        <para>Visibility is the relationship between service consumers and
        providers that is satisfied when they are able to interact with each
        other. Preconditions to visibility are awareness – typically the
        initiator in a service interaction must be aware of the other parties
        – willingness – the parties must be predisposed to interactions – and
        ability – the participants must be able to exchange information as
        part of a service interaction.</para>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s39">
          <title>Awareness</title>

          <para>A key aspect of visibility is awareness – both the service
          provider and the service consumer must have information that would
          lead them to know of the other’s existence. Technically, the prime
          requirement is that the initiator of a service interaction has
          knowledge of the responder. The fact of a successful initiation is
          often sufficient to inform the responder of the other’s
          existence.</para>

          <para>Awareness of service offerings is often mediated by various
          discovery mechanisms. For a service consumer (say) to discover a
          service provider, the service provider must be capable of making
          details of the service (notably service description and policies)
          available to potential consumers; and consumers must be capable of
          finding that information.</para>

          <para>Service discoverability requires that the service description
          and policy – or at least a suitable subset thereof – be available in
          such a manner and form that, directly or indirectly, an awareness of
          the existence and capabilities of the service can become known to
          potential consumers. The extent to which the discovery is “pushed by
          the service provider, “pulled” by a potential consumer, subject to a
          probe or another method, will depend on many factors.</para>

          <para>For example, a service provider may advertise and promote
          their service by either including it in a service directory or
          broadcasting it to all consumers; potential consumers may broadcast
          their particular service needs in the hope that a suitable service
          responds with a proposal or offer or a service consumer might also
          “probe” a entire network to determine if suitable services exist.
          When the demand for a service is higher than the supply, then by
          advertising their needs, potential consumers are likely to be more
          effective then service providers advertising offered
          services.</para>

          <para>One way or another, the potential consumer must acquire a
          sufficient description to evaluate whether the service matches their
          expectations and, if so, the method for the consumer to establish a
          contract and invoke the service.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s40">
          <title>Willingness</title>

          <para>Associated with all service interactions is intent – it is an
          intentional act to initiate and to participate in a service
          interaction. For example, if a service consumer discovers a service
          via its description in a registry, and the consumer initiates an
          interaction, if the service provider does not cooperate then there
          can be no interaction. In some circumstances it is precisely the
          correct behaviour for a service to fail to respond – for example, it
          is the classic defence against certain denial-of-service
          attacks.</para>

          <para>The extent of a service participant’s willingness to engage in
          service interactions may be the subject of policies. Those policies
          may be documented in the service description.</para>

          <para>Of course, willingness on the part of service providers and
          consumers to interact is not the same as a willingness to perform
          requested actions. A service provider that rejects all attempts to
          cause it to perform some action may still be fully willing and
          engaged in interacting with the consumer.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s41">
          <title>Reachability</title>

          <para>A service consumer may have the intention of interacting with
          a service, and may even have all the information needed to
          communicate with it. However, if the service is not reachable, for
          example if there is not communication path between the consumer and
          provider, then, effectively, the service is not visible to the
          consumer.</para>

          <para>Reachability is the relationship between service participants
          where they are able to exchange information as part of service
          interactions. Reachability is closely connected to the concept of
          execution context – an important requirement
          for an execution context is to establish that service participants
          can communicate with each other.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="v1e-s42">
        <title>SOA Attributes</title>

        <table id="v1e-t1">
          <title>Implementation of SOA Attributes</title>

          <tgroup cols="7">
            <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="25*" />

            <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="18*" />

            <colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="14*" />

            <colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="14*" />

            <colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="14*" />

            <colspec colname="col6" colnum="6" colwidth="14*" />

            <colspec colname="col7" colnum="7" colwidth="14*" />

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>SOA Attribute</entry>

                <entry>Feature</entry>

                <entry>Year 2</entry>

                <entry>Year 3</entry>

                <entry>Year 4</entry>

                <entry>Year 5</entry>

                <entry>Year 6</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Applications</entry>

                <entry>Enterprise Management</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>15%</entry>

                <entry>30%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Discovery</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>20%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Messaging</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Mediation</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Collaboration</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Security</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>15%</entry>

                <entry>30%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Storage</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Application</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Assistance</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Catalogue</entry>

                <entry>Description Language</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>20%</entry>

                <entry>40%</entry>

                <entry>60%</entry>

                <entry>80%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Instance</entry>

                <entry>Definition Language</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>20%</entry>

                <entry>40%</entry>

                <entry>60%</entry>

                <entry>80%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Publications</entry>

                <entry>Unicast</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>25%</entry>

                <entry>50%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Multicast</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>25%</entry>

                <entry>50%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Broadcast</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>25%</entry>

                <entry>50%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Anycast</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Discovery</entry>

                <entry>Registry</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>20%</entry>

                <entry>40%</entry>

                <entry>60%</entry>

                <entry>80%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Directory</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>30%</entry>

                <entry>60%</entry>

                <entry>90%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Data Model</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Contract</entry>

                <entry>Low Level</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>High Level</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>The previous table, <xref linkend="v1e-t1" />, is a suggested generalized outline
        on when SOA attributes should be implemented within the mid-term time
        frame. A value of zero percent indicates that implementation should
        begin in that year. Conversely, a value of a hundred percent indicates
        that implementation should end in that year. Naturally, measurable
        metrics to quantify progress would have to be agreed upon by the NATO
        nations.</para>

        <table id="v1e-t3">
          <title><emphasis>Far-term SOA Attributes</emphasis></title>

          <tgroup cols="7">
            <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="26*" />

            <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="19*" />

            <colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="10*" />

            <colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="10*" />

            <colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="10*" />

            <colspec colname="col6" colnum="6" colwidth="10*" />

            <colspec colname="col7" colnum="7" colwidth="10*" />

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">SOA Attribute</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Feature</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Year 6</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Year 7</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Year 8</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Year 9</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Year 10</emphasis></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Applications</entry>

                <entry>Enterprise Management</entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Discovery</entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Messaging</entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Mediation</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Collaboration</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Security</entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Storage</entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Application</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Assistance</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Descriptions</entry>

                <entry>Description Language</entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Definitions</entry>

                <entry>Definition Language</entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Publications</entry>

                <entry>Unicast</entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Multicast</entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Broadcast</entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Anycast</entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Discovery</entry>

                <entry>Repository</entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Directory</entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Data Model</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Contract</entry>

                <entry>Low Level</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>High Level</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>

                <entry> </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s43">
          <title>Service Application</title>

          <para>A service is a contractually defined behaviour that can be
          implemented and provided by a service provider of choice for use by
          service consumer. The term “services” does not imply web services;
          although, web services are well known implementations of SOA. Other
          specialized implementations include J2EE<footnote>
              <para>Sun Microsystems® Java 2® Platform, Enterprise Edition
              (J2EE) defines the standard for developing component-based,
              multi-tier, enterprise applications.
              http://java.sun.com/j2ee/</para>
            </footnote> and .NET<footnote>
              <para>Microsoft® .NET is a set of Microsoft software
              technologies for connecting information, people, systems, and
              devices. www.microsoft.com/net/</para>
            </footnote>.</para>

          <para>The following service group is called the NATO Information
          Infrastructure Core Enterprise Services (NII-CES). NII-CES services
          are available enterprise-wide and are independent of Cross COI
          Services. They are considered the building blocks upon which Cross
          COI Services are created.</para>

          <para>Capability Areas</para>

          <para>Service Management Control</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Enterprise Management</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Application</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Assistance</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Information Assurance</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Security</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Information and Integration</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Discovery</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Mediation</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Storage</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Communication</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Messaging</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Collaboration</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Community of Interests</para>

          <para>Users and Missions</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s44">
          <title>Service Catalogue</title>

          <para>The service catalogue information consists of the constraints
          and policies that define the usage context and functionality of the
          service. This enables service consumers, human or another service,
          to examine the service description and evaluate the following
          questions:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>What does the service do?</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Is it relevant to my mission?</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>The declaration may also include details about any implied
          process or other legal or business terms that occur when the service
          is invoked. For example, if a service consumer invokes a service
          that places a purchase order to the service provider, and the
          execution is successful, it may result in a financial responsibility
          to the service provider or some other legal entity.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s45">
          <title>Service Type</title>

          <para>Service type information includes all information that is
          needed to know how to use or how to produce a service of a specific
          type. It includes information on service interfaces, protocols and
          achievements.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s46">
          <title>Service Instance</title>

          <para>While the nature of the services themselves may vary, a common
          standard for declaring a service is desirable when building an
          infrastructure. The service instance consists of the technical
          parameters, constraints and policies that define the terms to invoke
          the service instance. Every service should include a service
          definition in a standardized format. This enables service consumers,
          human or another service, to examine the service definition and
          evaluate the following questions:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>How can I bind to a service?</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>What security protocols (if any) must be used with
              it?</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s47">
          <title>Service Publication</title>

          <para>A service must communicate its service description in an
          accessible manner to potential consumers. It does so by using one of
          several advertising method; catalogue or webpage publishing,
          Pulling, or Pushing.</para>

          <para>In the Pull methodology, potential service consumers request
          the service provider to send them the service description. This pull
          methodology may be invoked as a service itself.</para>

          <para>In the Push methodology, the service provider, or its agent,
          sends the service description to potential service consumers. The
          push and pull methodologies may work together to facilitate
          advertising services through a third party in a pattern of publish
          and subscribe.</para>

          <para>Different models for the push methodology include:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Unicast (point-to-point) is a methodology where the
              service provider sends a message from a single source to a
              single destination.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Multicast (point-to-multipoint) is a parallel
              communication pattern in which a source host sends a message to
              a group of destination hosts. This is different from sending
              multiple serial unicast (point-to-point) messages to each of the
              destination hosts.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Broadcast (point-to-all points) is a methodology where the
              service provider sends a transmission to all message consumers
              on a fabric.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Anycast (point-to-point-to-multipoint) is a methodology
              that assigns a private address to several message consumers on a
              fabric. The message sender does not know or care who consumes
              the message or the details of the message’s distribution
              list.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s48">
          <title>Service Discovery</title>

          <para>Discovery occurs when a potential consumer obtains information
          about the existence of a service, its applicable parameters and
          terms. Discovery does not constitute authorization to execute
          against the service; although these details may be included in the
          discovery pattern.</para>

          <para>Service discovery may include the following steps:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Finding and selecting achievements that suits the need of
              the service consumer</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Finding and selecting service types that produces the
              selected achievements</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Finding and selecting service instances of the selected
              service types</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Finding and using services based on type can be easily
          automated, while finding and using services based on description or
          ontology is still difficult to automate.</para>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s49">
            <title>Implementing advertising and discovery</title>

            <para>The publishing and discovery components of SOA may be
            implemented in many ways, including using a registry/repository or
            a services directory. Although using these may make discovery
            easier, an SOA requires neither of them.</para>
          </sect4>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s50">
            <title>Registry/Repository</title>

            <para>A Registry/Repository is a component where users can store
            and manage artefacts required for their enterprise to function.
            This includes artefacts that require sharing among more than one
            user (such as XML schemas and web-service descriptions). The
            repository component provides an intrinsic storage mechanism that
            is bound to the registry such that the registry knows about any
            auditable events to the artefacts in the repository.</para>
          </sect4>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s51">
            <title>Services Directory</title>

            <para>A Directory is an interface that provides information to
            bind to artefacts. Those who own or control the artefacts may make
            an entry into the directory to reference the artefact and explain
            how to bind to it. Others may retrieve this information and use it
            to bind to the artefacts. The main drawback of the directory is
            that it has no control or notification if an artefact is deleted,
            changed or replaced, and the directory may not be able to indicate
            these events to users.</para>

            <para>Both Registry/Repository and Directory implementations allow
            for federation (also called replication). This functionality
            allows content from one implementation to be replicated or
            referenced from within other implementations.</para>

            <para>Several standards exist to constrain Registry/Repository and
            Directory implementations. The most prevalent standards are
            ISO/IEC 11179 Part 315 (an ISO standard for metadata registries),
            the OASIS ebXML Registry-Repository Technical Specifications16 and
            the OASIS Universal Description and Discovery Interface (UDDI)
            Technical Specification</para>

            <para>The OASIS UDDI specification is available from the OASIS
            website under the technical committee’s home page area at
            www.oasis-open.org/committees/tc_home.php?wg_abbrev=uddi-spec.</para>

            <para>Standards such as Bluetooth TM use a broadcast-type
            methodology to advertise their services to other Bluetooth devices
            that are within range.</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s52">
          <title>Service Data Model</title>
          <para>When invoking a service, certain parameters may be required to help the service fulfil the service request.  The service may also pass parameters back to the service consumer.  To understand any required parameters serialization, an artefact is required to specify the associated data models for the services.  Even if no parameters are used, SOA requires a base component to declare this in a format that is understandable to service consumers.</para>
          <sect4 id="v1e-s53">
            <title>Known implementations</title>
            <para>The W3C’s WSDL10 can be used to express that related schema fragments constrain XML instance data being passed in and out of services.  ebXML’s Collaboration Protocol Profile11 also references a schema for instance data being used in a service or collaboration of services.  Both of these implementations are not specifically dependent on the W3C’s XML Schema19 format; yet most implementations use it.</para>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s54">
          <title>Service Contract</title>

          <para>A service contract is not an actual legal document. Instead,
          the service contract specifies a set of technical data, and possibly
          business information. The contract is between whoever is providing
          the Web service, and whoever is consuming the Web service. Put in
          the simplest terms, the contract provides details about the service
          being offered by the provider. By agreeing to a contract, both sides
          understand exactly what will be provided.</para>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s55">
            <title>Low Level</title>

            <para>A service contract can operate at a lot of different levels.
            A low-level contract expresses how you communicate, and what the
            expectations of communications are. But that low-level contract is
            not nearly as important as the higher-level contracts. At a
            minimum, will contain:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Service description</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Service interface details</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Service inputs/outputs</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </sect4>

          <sect4 id="v1e-s56">
            <title>High Level</title>

            <para>This higher-level contract is far more important because
            these contracts frequently have business implications, not just
            technical implications. For example, a contract may include
            details of how the service will be authenticated, and so have
            details about authentication, encryption and authorization. A
            typical high-level contract could include the following:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Description of service</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Details interface to the service</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Service inputs/outputs</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>How service will be authenticated</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>How service will be authorized</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>What type of encryption will be used</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Service level agreements (Availability, response time,
                etc)</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Charges to use the service</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </sect4>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v1e-s57">
      <title>Network-Enabled Operations (NEO-RM)</title>

      <para>A NATO Network Enabled Operations Reference Model (NEO-RM) should
      be created during the mid-term time frame. The best course of action to
      create such a document would be build upon similar existing doctrine
      used at the national level by some NATO members.</para>

      <para>The NEO RM, describes all of the activities required to establish,
      use, operate, and manage the network enabled enterprise information
      environment to include: the generic user-interface, the
      intelligent-assistant capabilities, the network enabled capabilities
      (i.e., core services, Community of Interest services, and environment
      control services), and the enterprise management components. It also
      describes a selected set of key standards that will be needed as the NEO
      capabilities of a seamless communications network backbone are
      realized.</para>

      <para>The NEO-RM is to describe the evolving NATO enterprise aspects of
      an objective net-enabled information environment. The NEO-RM, as
      designed, serves as a common, enterprise-level, reference model for
      NATO’s net-enabled operations, such as the expeditionary NATO Response
      Force (NRF), and for current and future acquisition programs to
      reference. A shared vision of the enterprise information environment
      will assist decision makers promote enterprise-wide unity of
      effort.</para>

      <figure id="v1e-nneo">
        <title>NATO Network-Enabled Operations: The Future</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/nneo.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <sect2 id="v1e-s58">
        <title>NEO Attributes</title>

        <table id="v1e-t2">
          <title>Implementation of NEO attributes</title>

          <tgroup cols="7">
            <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="24*" />

            <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="18*" />

            <colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="14*" />

            <colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="14*" />

            <colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="14*" />

            <colspec colname="col6" colnum="6" colwidth="14*" />

            <colspec colname="col7" colnum="7" colwidth="14*" />

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>NCOW Attribute</entry>

                <entry>Features</entry>

                <entry>Year 2</entry>

                <entry>Year 3</entry>

                <entry>Year 4</entry>

                <entry>Year 5</entry>

                <entry>Year 6</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Internet Protocol</entry>

                <entry>Automated Configuration</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>25%</entry>

                <entry>50%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Large Address Space</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>25%</entry>

                <entry>50%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Secure &amp; Available Communications</entry>

                <entry>Hardened Against Denial of Service</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>10%</entry>

                <entry>20%</entry>

                <entry>30%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Core Network Encryption</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>20%</entry>

                <entry>40%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Edge to Edge Encryption</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>25%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Only Handle Information Once (OHIO)</entry>

                <entry>Use Known Repositories</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>25%</entry>

                <entry>50%</entry>

                <entry>75%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Post in Parallel</entry>

                <entry>Post Data Before Processing</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>20%</entry>

                <entry>40%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Smart Pull</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>20%</entry>

                <entry>40%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Service Agreements</entry>

                <entry>Service Contract</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Quality of Service</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data Centric</entry>

                <entry>Metadata</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>30%</entry>

                <entry>60%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry></entry>

                <entry>Metadata Registry</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Application Diversity</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>10%</entry>

                <entry>20%</entry>

                <entry>30%</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Assured Sharing</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry>-</entry>

                <entry>0%</entry>

                <entry>20%</entry>

                <entry>40%</entry>

                <entry>60%</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>The previous table, <xref linkend="v1e-t2" />, is a suggested generalized outline
        on when NEO attributes should be implemented within the mid-term time
        frame. A value of zero percent indicates that implementation should
        begin in that year. Conversely, a value of a hundred percent indicates
        that implementation should end in that year. Naturally, measurable
        metrics to quantify progress would have to be agreed upon by the NATO
        nations.</para>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s59">
          <title>Internet Protocol (IP)</title>

          <para>The Internet Protocol (IP) is a protocol used by source and
          destination hosts for communicating data across a packet-switched
          inter-network. Data in an IP inter-network are sent in blocks
          referred to as packets. No setup of "path" is needed before a host
          tries to send packets to a host it has previously not communicated
          with.</para>

          <para>The Internet Protocol provides an unreliable datagram service
          (also called best effort); i.e. It makes almost no guarantees about
          the packet. The packet may arrive damaged, it may be out of order
          (compared to other packets sent between the same hosts), it may be
          duplicated, or it may be dropped entirely. If an application needs
          reliability, it is provided by other means, typically by upper level
          protocols transported on top of IP.</para>

          <para>Inter-network routers, forward IP packets across
          interconnected layer 2 networks. The lack of any delivery guarantees
          means that the design of packet switches is made much simpler. (Note
          that if the network does drop, reorder or otherwise damage a lot of
          packets, the performance seen by the user will be poor, so most
          network elements do try hard to not do these things - hence the best
          effort term. However, an occasional error will produce no noticeable
          effect.)</para>

          <para>In a network-enable NATO, there is a need for support for an
          unlimited number of site addresses for wireless communications
          devices, remote sensors, vehicles and precision-guided munitions.
          Therefore, with any large-scale operation, the current finite number
          of IP addresses becomes a resource that must be managed and closely
          monitored.</para>

          <para>The ad-hoc nature of future NATO operations dictates the need
          for easily configurable networks. Since most of the devices
          connected to NATO networks will be mobile devices, a device must be
          able to arbitrarily change locations on the Internet and still
          maintain existing connections.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s60">
          <title>Secure and Available Communications</title>

          <para>Security requires that systems and users are protected against
          attack, disruptions, and threats. Data must also be kept private and
          free of malicious or corrupted content as it travels throughout the
          enterprise. And the network infrastructure itself must be protected
          against exposure to attacks that impacts internal servers and end
          user systems. In the mid-term time frame the initial goal is
          encryption for the core network, and the final goal is edge-to-edge
          encryption with a network that is hardened against denial of
          service.</para>

          <para>Ensuring availability means that systems themselves are always
          available, and that information is readily accessible to users and
          other authorized individuals, especially as it relates to regulatory
          compliance and legal discovery. Migrating older, yet still useful,
          data poses an added challenge to availability, as users still demand
          immediate access and IT requires high degrees of ease and automation
          to achieve this.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s61">
          <title>Only Handle Information Once (OHIO)</title>

          <para>A key feature of network-enabled NATO is the ability to
          provide individual soldiers and commanders with relevant timely
          information. But pushing information to users in the area of
          operation is difficult because the number of items that can link to
          the network exceeds the current messaging protocol’s ability to
          assign addresses. Technologies that allow wireless systems to plug
          into tactical and theatre networks seamlessly without straining
          resources may permit the military to deploy more network-enabled
          devices.</para>

          <para>This capability fits into a concept known as “only handle
          information once” (OHIO), where an information producer posts data once
          but permits authorized users to access it. This approach differs
          from requiring the producer to know the address of every user that
          may want the information.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s62">
          <title>Post in Parallel</title>

          <para>All NATO participants or business process owners make their
          data available on the network as soon as it is created. Posting data
          does not mean just making accessible, it also means tagging
          (describing) the data appropriately for its content. Processing of
          data will be done as needed by specialized web services invoked by
          the data consumer.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s63">
          <title>Smart Pull</title>

          <para>The two solutions in use for data synchronization are called
          “Push” and “Pull”. Smart Pull is just a further refinement of the
          Pull solution.</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Push solutions involve the server notifying the device
              that data is available. Solutions to this usually require some
              type of infrastructure to manage the distribution of
              notifications to the network enabled-devices. For example, the
              solution might involve using the mobile phone service provider’s
              SMS system or might be a custom built system like that created
              by Research in Motion (RIM) for their Blackberry communications
              network.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Pull solutions put the burden on the network-enabled
              device to go retrieve data. They’ve historically been simple
              implementations using techniques like calling the server on some
              regular time interval or maybe even relying on the user to
              initiate the data sync.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Generally the immediate notification of push is desirable,
          however when building our own applications, the simplicity of pull
          is more attractive. This is where Smart Pull comes in. An example of
          the concept of smart pull that has been gained a lot of attention
          since the announcement is the Microsoft Messaging and Security
          Feature Pack (MMSF). MMSF provides Windows Mobile 5.0 Smartphone
          with full connectivity to their Exchange server, keeping Outlook
          data up-to-date including receiving email as soon as it arrives at
          the server. The technique used to maintain synchronization is
          basically a long-running web service call.</para>

          <para>The smart pull mechanism seems like the kind of solution that
          will address many common scenarios faced when developing mobile
          applications that require close synchronization with a server.
          Applications encourage discovery; users can pull data directly from
          the network or use value-added discovery services.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s64">
          <title>Data Centric Approach</title>

          <para>In a data-centric approach the data separate from
          applications, or services. Communications between services occurs by
          posting data. The steps involved in a data-centric approach
          are:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Analyze how the data is used and moved as it flows through
              the system to better understand how to store and use it.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Describe data or tag data to facilitate a system level
              view. This involves describing data <emphasis
              role="bold">and</emphasis> describing the context under which it
              was collected or generated.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Build services around data. Services are just the methods
              to manage data.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s65">
          <title>Application Diversity</title>

          <para>Users can pull multiple services to access same data (e.g.,
          for collaboration). This idea reinforces the underlying concept of
          the data being independent of the services that manipulate the
          data.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s66">
          <title>Assured Sharing</title>

          <para>Assured sharing means trusted accessibility to net resources,
          such as: data, services, apps, people, collaborative environment,
          etc. Access is assured for authorized users, but denied for
          unauthorized users by maintaining thorough security policies.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s67">
          <title>Quality of Service</title>

          <para>Data timeliness, accuracy, completeness, integrity, and ease
          of use.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="v1e-s68">
      <title>Information Systems Interoperability Reference Model
      (ISIOP-RM)</title>

      <para>A successful case of interoperability is demonstrated in NATO’s
      efforts to standardize small arms. It was politically unattainable, for
      domestic industrial base reasons, to standardize on a common rifle and
      pistol for all NATO countries. But NATO did standardize on ammunition;
      the standard pistol round is 9mm. The interoperable ammunition solution
      gained interoperability -- the real need -- without imposing unpalatable
      commonality requirements. Such interoperability can also be achieved
      with information systems.</para>

      <sect2 id="v1e-s69">
        <title>Interoperability Attributes</title>

        <table id="v1e-t4">
          <title></title>

          <tgroup cols="6">
            <colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="38*" />

            <colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="24*" />

            <colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="14*" />

            <colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="14*" />

            <colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="14*" />

            <colspec colname="col6" colnum="6" colwidth="14*" />

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Interoperability
                Attribute</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Year 2</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Year 3</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Year 4</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Year 5</emphasis></entry>

                <entry><emphasis role="bold">Year 6</emphasis></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Inter-Network</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Modularity</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Data</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Shared processes</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Interoperable procedures</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Cognitive interoperability</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Doctrinal interoperability</entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>

                <entry></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s70">
          <title>Inter-Network</title>

          <para>Communications interoperability can be defined by the ability
          to inter-network. Because of the confederated nature of NATO,
          heterogeneous communications networks are necessary, and
          unavoidable; the key to interoperability is that they can be
          concatenated together using routers. Each discrete communications
          network is a routable network.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s71">
          <title>Modularity</title>

          <para>Information systems are made up of sense, decide and act
          functions that rest upon the communications. This layer of the Model
          deals with the modularity of these functions and the complexity of
          information systems, which can be explained by nesting and
          chaining.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s72">
          <title>Data</title>

          <para>Data element interoperability is a clear requisite to
          information system interoperability. This is the abstract layer
          where this discussion of data, meta-data and meta-meta-data belongs.
          A key issue is semantic equivalences.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s73">
          <title>Shared Processes</title>

          <para>This is a software engineering concept. At its trivial level
          reusable code obviously enhances interoperability but that is a side
          effect of what is essentially an economy effort in code production.
          At a more mature level, mobile code and portable code are the
          pertinent issues.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s74">
          <title>Interoperable Procedures</title>

          <para>Operating procedures is the level at which we tend to shift
          from systems engineering to human factors in the layered Model. This
          is the domain long inhabited by Standard Operating
          Procedures.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s75">
          <title>Cognitive Interoperability</title>

          <para>Cognitive Interoperability has to do with shared situation
          awareness. Information systems are interoperable at this layer if
          decision makers in two different systems are seeing coherent
          pictures of the information presented.</para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3 id="v1e-s76">
          <title>Doctrinal Interoperability</title>

          <para>This is a human factor that leads to coherency and uniformity
          of action. Different decision makers, when presented with the same
          information will be making similar decisions. The usual doctrinal
          tensions of uniformity versus creativity are still present and
          certainly not resolved by this Model. The Model only serves to
          illustrate the level of abstraction where such discussion
          belongs.</para>

          <para>Where the reference models, described in the previous section,
          laid out the framework for a networked-enabled NATO, it is the
          technologies that are projected to be available during the mid-term
          period are going to enable the implementation of a network-enabled
          NATO, during this time frame.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v1e-s77">
      <title>Business Process Infrastructure Framework (BPIF)</title>
      <para>Within the wide area of relevant information technologies, this work has focused on a particular field referred to as Business Process Infrastructure Framework (BPIF).  Although highly relevant, this is by no means a well defined or even well established field.  Instead, an important part of this work has been to find a working definition and scope for the field.</para>
      <para>As a starting point, the intent has been to describe technologies that in various ways support business processes. As almost any information technology available can be said to do this, we have focused on those technologies that most explicitly have to do with this kind of support. Furthermore, as service orientation is a known fundamental architectural concept for future NNEC solutions, the definition of BPIF assumed here has been limited to that kind of solutions. From the outset, we have also seen technologies for service description and discovery, which also is part of the Swedish responsibility, as such a fundamental ingredient of BPIF, that it is included as a subfield within BPIF.</para>
      <para>An important basis for this work has also been the FMA Technology Support Study, June 2005, that points out and describes some central areas of technology development, in particular within the field of distributed system architecture. Parts of the material from that report have also been reused here, although somewhat rearranged to fit the current scope.</para>
      <para>Within this scope, this report presents the first steps toward a complete description of the field of BPIF, and includes</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>a definition of the field,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>a structure that divides the field into a number of aspects,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>a brief overview of each of these aspects,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>a list of candidate technologies (with an emphasis of existing or emerging standards) with a bearing on BPIF, and</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>A mapping of the candidate technologies onto the BPIF subfields.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Currently, the terms used in this report are those traditionally used in the general development of the various technologies that are presented. However, in the more specific context where the results of this report are to be applied, an adaptation of some terms to that context will probably be needed.</para>
      <sect2 id="v1e-s78">
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>This section consists of two main parts. The first part is a definition of the field of business process infrastructure frameworks (BPIF), which divides the field into four main aspects. These aspects are described one by one. The descriptions both introduce some central concepts, and provide an overview of technology fields that support the aspects.</para>
        <para>Many relevant technologies do not fit into a single of the aspects or technology fields addressed in the first part. The second part of the document is therefore a listing of potentially relevant technologies, along with brief descriptions of the technologies and which aspects of BPIF they support.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="v1e-s79">
        <title>Definition</title>
        <para>At operational level, business processes are key components for the realization of an organization’s tasks, in particular those tasks that represent the main and externally exposed capabilities of the organization. A business process is a realization of a work flow that may involve several subtasks and decision points. Often, a business process also involves the collaboration of several organizations where each organization will contribute in parts of the operations. Setting up and running a business process is thus an important and often complex task in any operation.</para>
        <para>Although business processes have traditionally been treated mostly in a commercial context, they are also relevant as means of organizing operations in a context like NNEC. However, to successfully make use of the concept of business processes, in particular in a very dynamic context, a framework for engineering and management of business processes is needed, i.e., a business process infrastructure framework (BPIF).</para>
        <para>Today, there are technologies that provide at least partial support for a BPIF. Most of those technologies that provide the most explicit support for business processes are based on the concepts of services and service oriented architecture (SOA), and we will in fact limit our definition of BPIF in this context to include only service based solutions. However, few if any complete frameworks for service based business processes exist that provide the consistent technology reference model needed here. Therefore, we will address this field in terms of four aspects or concerns:</para>
        <para>Distributed systems: Many practical business processes involve the collaboration of several organizations and systems. Therefore, a BPIF needs to be based on distributed system technologies. With service based solutions in focus, service oriented architecture (SOA) is an obvious field of distributed system technologies to consider, but there are also other trends in distributed system technologies that may provide essential support for the implementation of a BPIF.</para>
        <para>Service selection: With services as key components for the realization of a business process, it is of course important that relevant services can be found. Normally, this is not just a matter of finding services that provide the right capabilities, but also to make sure that other requirements and constraints are fulfilled regarding, for example, quality of service (QoS) and policies. Specific concerns for this aspect are thus both the description of services, and means of finding and identifying the right services.</para>
        <para>Process composition: Once suitable services are available, they need to be combined into sequences and decision points that represent the required work flow of the business process. Also it is necessary to make sure that service providers and consumers in the work flow interact properly in accordance with the intentions behind each service. Support for this aspect must include the description of business processes in these terms so that their setup and deployment can be made more or less automatic.</para>
        <para>Management and infrastructure. This aspect concerns deployment, configuration, contracts, and policies for business processes. Typically, business processes will need to involve components that are distributed over heterogeneous environments and different organizations. This stresses the need for technologies that can provide a manageable infrastructure and execution context.</para>
        <figure id="v1e-bpif"><title><emphasis>BPIF Overview</emphasis></title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="../figures/BPIF.svg"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Each of these aspects can also be treated as a technology area where technologies already exist or development of new technologies is going on. However, much development in each area has a scope or orientation that is beyond the particular needs for a BPIF.  Therefore our treatment of each area will not cover its full extent, but rather be limited to parts that are related to BPIF needs.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v1e-s80">
      <title>NNEC Profile</title>
      <figure id="v1e-nnecp"><title>NNEC Profile</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/nnecProfile.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
<para>The items in the figure above are:<itemizedlist><listitem>Enterprise service synonym for NNEC Service Type</listitem>
<listitem>ENTERPRICE SERVICE is a type of NNEC SERVICE classified by the capability (service) area in which it is delivering its services</listitem>
<listitem>SERVICE CATEGORY is a TAXONOMY ELEMENT that structures ENTERPRISE SERVICES in a group with the same objectives</listitem>
<listitem>SERVICE GROUP is a TAXONOMY ELEMENT that structures ENTERPRISE SERVICES in a group with the main objectives</listitem>
<listitem>SERVICE LAYER is a TAXONOMY ELEMENT that structures ENTERPRISE SERVICES in a group of the same family </listitem>
<listitem>SERVICE AREA is a TAXONOMY ELEMENT that structures ENTERPRISE SERVICES in a group of the same nature</listitem>
<listitem>SERVICE COMPOSITION is the orchestration of a NNEC service in terms of Enterprise service</listitem>
<listitem>ENTERPRISE service is a construction element of a ENTERPRISE SERVICE realizing a CIS part of a CAPABILITY PACKAGE</listitem>
<listitem>CAPABILITY PACKAGE is a combination of national (military and civilian) and NATO funded infrastructure, operations, and maintenance, manpower, and associated costs that, with the military forces and other essential requirements, enable a NATO commander to achieve a specific military required capability.</listitem>
<listitem>SIOP (Service Inter Operability Point) is a linking point that ensures that ENTERPRISE SERVICES of different making but with the same SIP can interact with each other</listitem>
<listitem>SIP (Service Interface Profile) is a description of requirements of A SIOP that give guidance to engineers in realizing ENTERPRISE COMPONENTS</listitem>
<listitem>IPP (Interoperability Performance Paramter) Is an indicator of the required quality of service of a SIOP according to the CM</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
    </sect1>

  <sect1 id="v1c-transition">
    <title>Transition from Platform Oriented to Service Oriented Models</title>

    <para>Information technology is undergoing a fundamental shift from
    platform-centric computing to network-centric computing. Platform-centric
    computing emerged with the widespread proliferation of personal computers
    and the global business environment. These factors and related
    technologies have created the conditions for the emergence of
    network-centric computing. This shift from platform to network is what
    enables the more flexible and more dynamic network-centric operation. The
    shift from viewing partners as independent to viewing partners as part of
    a continuously adapting ecosystem fosters a rich information sharing
    environment.</para>

    <para>This shift is most obvious in the explosive growth of the internet,
    intranets, and extranets. Internet users no doubt will recognize
    transmission control protocol/internet protocol (TCP/IP), hypertext
    transfer protocol (HTTP), hypertext markup language (HTML), Web browsers
    (such as Netscape Navigator, and Microsoft's Internet Explorer), search
    engines, and JavaTM Computing. These technologies, combined with
    high-volume, high-speed data access (enabled by the low-cost laser) and
    technologies for high-speed data networking (hubs and routers) have led to
    the emergence of network-centric computing. Information "content" now can
    be created, distributed, and easily exploited across the extremely
    heterogeneous global computing environment. The "power" or "payoff" of
    network-centric computing comes from information-intensive interactions
    between very large numbers of heterogeneous computational nodes in the
    network, where the network becomes the dynamic information grid
    established by interconnecting partners participating in a collaborative,
    coalition environment. At the structural level, network-centric warfare
    requires an operational architecture to enable the common processes to be
    shared by all parties.</para>

    <para>The fabric for enabling net-centric operations is Service-Oriented
    Architectures (SOA). SOA is enterprise architecture that leverages
    heterogeneity, and thus inherently platform-neutral. It is focused on the
    composition of Services into flexible processes and is more concerned with
    the Service interface and above (including composition metadata, security
    policy, and dynamic binding information), more so than what sits beneath
    the abstraction of the Service interface. SOA requires a different kind of
    platform, because runtime execution has different meanings within SOA. SOA
    is to enable business users and business process architects to compose
    Services into processes, and then manage and evolve those processes, in a
    declarative fashion. Runtime execution of such processes is therefore a
    metadata-centric operation of a different kind of platform --a
    Service-oriented composite application platform.</para>

    <para>Network-centric warfare is characterized by new concepts of speed of
    command and self-synchronization.</para>

    <para>The most important SOA within an enterprise is the one that links
    all its systems. Existing platforms can be wrapped or extended in order to
    participate in a wider SOA environment. NATO use of the NISP will provide
    a template for new systems development, as well as assist in defining the
    path for existing systems to migrate towards net-centric
    operations.</para>
  </sect1>

</appendix>