<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<book lang="en">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles</title>
	<titleabbrev>NISP</titleabbrev>
    <subtitle>Introduction</subtitle>
    <corpauthor>C3B Interoperability Profiles Capability Team</corpauthor>
    <productname class="trade">Allied Data Publication</productname>
    <biblioid class="pubnumber">ADatP-34</biblioid>
    <volumenum>1</volumenum>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>12.0</revnumber>
        <date>18 Mar 2019</date>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>NISP NATO Interoperability Standards Profiles</keyword>
      <keyword>ADatP-34</keyword>
      <keyword>Allied Data Procedure 34</keyword>
      <keyword>STANAG 5524</keyword>
      <keyword>STANAG</keyword>
      <keyword>IP CaT</keyword>
      <keyword>Interoperability Profiles Capability Team</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <subjectset><subject><subjectterm>DO NOT REMOVE</subjectterm></subject></subjectset>
  </bookinfo>
<!--
 *****************************************************************
       C H A P T E R 1 - Introduction and Background
 *****************************************************************
-->
<chapter id="v1c-Introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>The NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles (NISP) is developed by the NATO Consultation, Command and Control (C3) Board Interoperability Profiles Capability Team (IP CaT).</para>
<para>The NISP will be made available to the general public as ADatP-34(K) when approved by the C3 Board<footnote><para>AC/322-N(2018)0049-REV1-AS1 approved ADatP-34(K)</para></footnote>.
</para>
<para>The included interoperability standards and profiles (Volume 2) are <emphasis role="bold">mandatory</emphasis> for use in NATO common funded Communications and Information Systems (CIS). Volume 3 contains <emphasis role="bold">candidate</emphasis> standards and profiles.</para>
<para>In case of conflict between any recommended non-NATO<footnote><para>ISO or other recognized non-NATO standards organization</para></footnote> standard and relevant NATO standard, the definition of the latter prevails.</para>
<para>In the NISP the keywords "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" are to be interpreted as described in [IETF RFC 2119].</para>
<table frame="all" id="v1-abbreviations">
<title>Abbreviations</title>
<tgroup align="left" cols="2">
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Abbreviation</entry>
<entry>Full Text</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>ABB</entry><entry><para>Architecture Building Block</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>ACaT</entry><entry><para>Architecture Capability Team</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>ACP</entry><entry><para>Allied Communications Publication</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>AdatP-34</entry><entry><para>Allied Data Publication - Cover publication for the NISP</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>BSP</entry><entry><para>Basic Standards Profile</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>C3</entry><entry><para>Consultation, Command and Control</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>CCEB</entry><entry><para>Combined Communications Electronic Board (military communications-electronics organization established among five nations: Australia, Canada, New Zealand, United Kingdom, and the United States)</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>CESF</entry><entry><para>Core Enterprise Services Framework</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>COI</entry><entry><para>Community of Interest</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>CIAV (WG)</entry><entry><para>Coalition Interoperability Assurance and Validation (Working Group)</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>CIS</entry><entry><para>Communication and Information Systems</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>CWIX</entry><entry><para>Coalition Warrior Interoperability eXploration, eXperimentation, eXamination eXercise</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>DOTMLPFI</entry><entry><para>Doctrine, Organization, Training, Materiel, Leadership, Personnel, Facilities and Interoperability</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>EAPC</entry><entry><para>Euro-Atlantic Partnership Council</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>FMN</entry><entry><para>Federated Mission Networking</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IOP</entry><entry><para>Interoperability Point</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IP CaT</entry><entry><para>Interoperability Profiles Capability Team</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>MIP</entry><entry><para>Multilateral Interoperability Programme</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>NAF</entry><entry><para>NATO Architecture Framework</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>NDPP</entry><entry><para>NATO Defence Planning Process</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>NISP</entry><entry><para>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>NIST</entry><entry><para>National Institute of Standards and Technology</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>NGO</entry><entry><para>Non govermental organization</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>RFC</entry><entry><para>Request for Change</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SDS</entry><entry><para>Service Data Sheet</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>SIOP</entry><entry><para>Service Interoperability Point</para><para>Definition is to be found in EAPC(AC/322)D (2006)0002-REV 1): SIOP is a reference point within an architecture where one or more service interfaces are physically or logically instantiated to allow systems delivering the same service using different protocols to interoperate.</para><para>Note: A service interoperability point serves as the focal point for service interoperability between interconnected systems, and may be logically located at any level within the components, and its detailed technical specification is contained within a service interface profile.</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SIP</entry><entry><para>Service Interface Profile</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>SME</entry><entry><para>Subject Matter Expert</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SOA</entry><entry><para>Service Oriented Architecture</para></entry></row>
<row><entry>STANAG</entry><entry><para>NATO abbreviation for <emphasis role="bold">STAN</emphasis>dardization <emphasis role="bold">AG</emphasis>reement, which set up processes, procedures, terms, and conditions for common military or technical procedures or equipment between the member countries of the alliance.</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>TACOMS</entry><entry><para>Tactical Communication Programme</para></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<sect1 id="v1-Purpose">
<title>Purpose of the NISP</title>
<para>NISP gives guidelines to capability planners, programme managers and test managers for NATO common funded systems in the short or mid-term timeframes.</para>
<para>The NISP prescribes the necessary technical standards and profiles to achieve interoperability of Communications and Information Systems in support of NATO's missions and operations. In accordance with the Alliance C3 Strategy (ref. C-M(2014)0016) all NATO Enterprise (ref. C-M(2014)0061) entities shall adhere to the NISP mandatory standards and profiles in volume 2.</para>
<para>Other activities that assure interoperability within the alliance should list their profiles in the NISP.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="v1-Audience">
<title>Intended Audience</title>
<para>The intended audience of the NISP are all stakeholders in the NATO Enterprise, and Allied and Partner nations involved in development, implementation, lifecycle management, and transformation to a federated environment.</para>
<para>There are specific viewpoints that are mapped to the NISP structure. NISP gives guidelines to:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>capability planners involved in NDPP and NATO led initiatives</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>programme managers for building NATO common funded systems</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>test managers for their respective test events (such as CWIX, CIAV, etc.)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>national planning and programme managers for their national initiatives</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>Specific NATO or national views to the NISP based on data export to external planning and management systems will be possible upon delivery of an updated version of the NISP Exchange Specification in 2019.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="v1c-concepts">
<title>Basic Concepts</title>
<para>This chapter gives an overview to understand the data in volume 2 and volume 3.</para>
<sect1 id="v1c-standards">
<title>Standards</title>
<!-- Define the term Standard-->
<para>Standards (their content) are defined and managed in their life cycle by standardization bodies with their own timetable. A standard may have life cycle status such as emerging, mature, fading, or obsolete. Different standardization bodies may use their own lifecycle status definitions. NISP takes lifecyle status of standards into account, but does not copy them into the NISP database. For aspects of obligation status for standards in planning and programmes, see the next paragraph.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="v1c-stanag">
<title>STANAG</title>
<!-- Define the term STANAG see AAP-03-->
<para>STANAG's are managed by the NATO Standardization Office (NSO). NATO STANAG's that are promulgated shall be considered mandatory only for NATO common-funded systems. If NISP references a STANAG, the obligation status for it is only informative. The NSO maintains the obligation status in their own process of standardization.</para>
<para>Some older STANAG's combine the agreement and the actual specification into one single document. NISP references the specification part.</para>
<para>Some STANAG's and NATO Standards included in the NISP are not yet registered in the NSO database. To indicate this, in the NISP tables the publication number starts with "NSO-Expected" instead of "NSO" and in the index, they are grouped under "NATO Standardization Office (expected in the future)".</para>
<para>For some STANAG's, the status in the NISP deviates from the status according to the NSO. For example, the NISP contains mandatory STANAGs that are Superseded or Cancelled according to the NSO. Also the NISP contains candidate STANAGs that are already Promulgated according to the NSO. For those STANAG's, this deviation is documented in a footnote.</para>
<para>When a STANAG is not yet Promulgated, this is identified by including "Study" or "RD" (Ratification Draft) in the publication number.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="v1c-profiles">
<title>Interoperability Profiles</title>
<para>Profiles define the specific use of standards at a service interoperability point (SIOP) in a given context. Profiles support prerequisites for programmes or projects and enable interoperability implementation and testing.</para>
<para>Interoperability Profiles provide combinations of standards and (sub)profiles for different CIS and identify essential profile elements including:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Capability Requirements and other NAF architectural views</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Characteristic protocols</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Implementation options</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Technical standards</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Service Interoperability Points, and</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>The relationship with other profiles such as the system profile to which an application belongs.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>


<para>The NISP now defines the <emphasis role="bold">obligation status</emphasis> of profiles and standards as "mandatory" or "candidate".
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Mandatory</emphasis>: The application of standards or profiles is enforced for NATO common funded systems in planning, implementing and testing. NATO STANAGS's that are promulgated shall be considered mandatory. Nations are invited to do the same nationally to promote interoperabilty for federated systems and services. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Candidate</emphasis>: 
The application of a standard or profile shall only be used for the purpose of testing and programme / project planning. The standard or profile must have progressed to a stage in its life-cycle and is sufficiently mature and is expected to be approved by the standardization body in the foreseeable future. This implies, that from a planning perspective, the respective standard or profile is expected to become mandatory during execution of the programme. A candidate standard or profile should not stay in volume 3 for more than 3 years.
</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>Profiles shall be updated if referenced standards change. Profiles are dynamic entities by nature. NATO captures this dynamic situation by updating profiles once a year in the NISP. Profile owners are responsible for the versioning of their profiles. Profile reviews are required every 2 years by their owners to ensure their accuracy and continued relevance.</para>
<para>Proposed profiles (and standards) can be accepted as candidates in order to follow their developments and to decide if they can be promoted to mandatory standards and profiles. In some cases proposed standards and profiles can be readily accepted directly as mandatory.</para>
<para>Interoperability Profiles can reference other Interoperability Profiles to allow for maximal reuse.</para>
<para>Further information and guidance on creation of profiles is available in <xref linkend="v1-profileguidance"/>.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
  <title>Basic Standards Profile</title>
<para>Within the NISP, the “<emphasis>Basic Standards Profile</emphasis>” specifies the technical, operational, and business standards that are generally applicable in the context of the Alliance and the NATO Enterprise. For a specific context, such as Federated Mission Networking, separate profiles may be defined that apply specifically to that context or related architectures. The standards that are cited may be NATO standards, or other agreed international and open standards.</para>

<para>As there is no overarching alliance architecture, each standard is associated with elements of the C3 Taxonomy. A distinction must be made between applicability of a standard, and conformance to the standard. If a standard is applicable to a given C3 Taxonomy element, any architecture that implements such an element need not be fully conformant with the standard. The degree of conformance may be judged based on the specific context of the project. For example, to facilitate information exchange between C2 and logistics systems it may be sufficient to implement only a subset of concepts as defined in JC3IEDM (STANAG 5525).</para>

<para>The “Basic Standards Profile” contains “agreed” as well as “candidate” standards.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="v1s-otherConcepts">
<title>Creating relationships to other concepts and planning objects within NATO</title>
<para>Different initiatives and organizations have developed new concepts to govern developments in the interoperability domain. These concepts have logical relationship to the NISP.</para>
<sect2 id="v1s-ABB">
<title>Architecture Building Block</title>
<para>An Architecture Building Block (ABB) is a constituent of the architecture model that describes a single aspect of the overall model
<footnote><para>TOGAF 9.1 Specification</para></footnote>.</para>
<sect3 id="v1c-abbc"><title>Characteristics</title>
<para>ABBs:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Capture architecture requirements; e.g., business, data, application, and technology requirements</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Direct and guide the development of Solution Building Blocks</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="v1c-abbsc"><title>Specification Content</title>
<para>ABB specifications include the following as a minimum:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Fundamental functionality and attributes: semantic, unambiguous, including security capability and manageability</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Interfaces: chosen set, supplied</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Interoperability and relationship with other building blocks</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Dependent building blocks with required functionality and named user interfaces</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Map to business/organizational entities and policies</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="v1s-FMNspirals">
<title>FMN Spiral Specifications</title>
<para>Federated Mission Networking (FMN) Spiral<footnote><para>Annex B TO Volume I - Implementation Overview, NATO FMN Implementation Plan v4.0 dated: 23 September 2014, Terms and Definitions</para></footnote>  Specifications encompass "an evolutionary cycle that will raise the level of maturity of federated mission networking capabilities over time".</para>
<para>The FMN spiral specification contain the following sections
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>architecture</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>instructions</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>profiles, and</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>requirements specifications.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
The Mandatory and Candidate FMN Spiral Profiles, in context for FMN Affiliates, are listed in the NISP Volumes 2 and 3.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="v1s-CPs">
<title>Capability Packages</title>
<para>Profiles will be referenced in the NISP for specified NATO Common Funded Systems or Capability Packages and may include descriptions of interfaces to National Systems where appropriate.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="v1c-InfoOrganization">
    <title>Organization of the NISP Information</title>
<para>This chapter gives an overview of the new structure of all three volumes.</para>
<sect1 id="v1s-structure">
    <title>NISP Structure</title>
    <para>The structure of the NISP is organized to list and categorize the standards and profiles according to their usage in NATO. It contains three volumes:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Volume 1</emphasis> - Introduction: This volume introduces basic concepts, provides the management framework for the configuration control of the NISP and the process for handling Request for Change (RFC). It includes also guidance on development of interoperability profiles.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Volume 2</emphasis> - Agreed Interoperability Standards and Profiles: This volume lists agreed interoperability standards and profiles, mandatory for NATO common funded systems. These should support NATO and National systems today and new systems actually under procurement or specification.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Volume 3</emphasis> - Candidate Interoperability Standards and Profiles: This Volume lists informative references to Standards and Interoperability Profiles, such as drafts of NATO specifications, that may be used as guidance for future programmes.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Volume 2 is normative for NATO common funded systems and Volume 3 is informative.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="v1c-ISCPP">
    <title>Interoperability in Support of Capability Planning</title>
    <para>The following documents form the foundation to understand the embedding of NISP into NDPP and architecture work:
<table frame="all" id="v1t-NDPPdocs">
<title>NDPP References</title>
<tgroup align="left" cols="2">
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Document</entry>
<entry>Document Reference</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><para>Alliance C3 Strategy Information and Communication Technology to prepare NATO 2020 (20 July 2018)</para></entry>
<entry><para>Alliance C3 Strategy C-M(2019)0037</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>Alliance C3 Policy (25 April 2016)</para></entry>
<entry><para>C-M(2015)0041-REV1</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>NATO Defence Planning Process (NDPP)</para></entry>
<entry><para>PO(2016)0655 (INV)</para></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</para>
    <para>The NATO Defence Planning Process (NDPP) is the primary means to identify the required capabilities and promote their timely and coherent development and acquisition by Allies and Partners. It is operationally driven and delivers various products which could support the development and evolution of more detailed C3 architecture and interoperability requirements. The development of NDPP products also benefits from input by the architecture and interoperability communities, especially the NISP, leading to a more coherent development of CIS capabilities for the Alliance.</para>
<para>The work on Enterprise, Capability, and programme level architecture will benefit from the NISP by selecting coherent sets of standards for profiles. </para>
<para>More information on how the NISP supports the NDPP can be found in Annex B.</para>
</chapter>
<chapter id="v1c-ConfigurationManagement">
    <title>Configuration Management</title>
   <para>The NISP is updated once a year to account for the evolution of standards and profiles.
</para>

      <para>Request for Change (RFC) to the NISP will be processed by the IP CaT, following the process in the graphic below:</para>
      <figure id="v1f6-RFCP" float="0">
        <title>RFC Handling Process</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/rfcp-proc.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>


      <para>The RFC contains all information required for the NISP management by IP CaT; The detailed information about standard or profile is handed over as attachments to this form. A notional RFC form with example information is presented below:

<figure id="v1f6-RFCP4" float="0">
        <title>RFC Notional Form</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/RFCPex4.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
</para>
<para>The primary point of contact for RFC submission is the IP CaT. RFCs may be submitted to the <ulink url="http://nhqc3s.hq.nato.int">IP CaT via the Change web site</ulink> or via email to <ulink url="mailto:herve.radiguet@act.nato.int ">herve.radiguet@act.nato.int</ulink> with attachments.</para>
<para>Review of RFCs will be coordinated with the responsible C3 Board substructure organizations where appropriate.</para>
<para>The IP CaT reviews the submissions in dialog with national and international bodies. Based on that review, the RFC will be formally processed into the next version of the NISP; or returned to the originator for further details; or rejected. The IP CaT will attempt to address all RFCs submitted by 1 September into the next NISP release. RFCs submitted after this date may be considered for inclusion at the discretion of the IP CaT, or will be processed for the following NISP release.</para>


<sect1 id="v1s1-UpdateProcess">
<title>NISP Update Process</title>
<para>The new NISP version is submitted to the C3 Board by end of the year after internal review by the IP CaT. The version under review is a snapshot in time of the status of standards and profiles.</para>
<para>The database of standards and profiles maintained by the IP CaT is the definitive source of the current status of standards and profiles.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="v1s1-Products">
<title>NISP Products</title>
<para>The NISP is published in several formats:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Documentation in <ulink url="https://nhqc3s.hq.nato.int/Apps/Architecture/NISP/index.html">HTML</ulink> and <ulink url="https://nhqc3s.hq.nato.int/Apps/Architecture/NISP/PDFcoverdoc.html">PDF</ulink> Formats</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Website and searchable <ulink url="https://nhqc3s.hq.nato.int/Apps/Architecture/NISP2/default.aspx">online Database</ulink></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Data export in XML format</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="v1c-CoordinationNations">
<title>National Systems Interoperability Coordination</title>
      <para>Coordination of standards and profiles between Nations and NATO are critical for interoperability.
        As a result of the C3 Board substructure reorganization,  participants in IP CaT are subject matter experts (SME) and are no longer national representatives.
        SME's should therefore coordinate with national and C3 Board representatives to ensure national perspectives are presented to IP CaT. As such, each of the
        IP CaT SMEs is responsible for:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Appropriate and timely coordination of standards and profiles with respect to interoperability with national systems;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Coordination of the SME input including coordination with national SMEs of other C3 Board substructure groups; and</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Providing appropriate technical information and insight based on national market assessment.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
<para>National level coordination of interoperability technical standards and profiles is the responsibility of the C3 Board.
When the latest version of NISP is approved by the C3 Board, it will become the NATO Standard covered by STANAG 5524 Edition 2.
This STANAG contains the agreement of the participating nations regarding usage of the mandatory standards and profiles in the NISP.
</para>
</chapter>


  <chapter id="v1c-stdsGuidance">
    <title>Interoperability Standards Guidance</title>

    <para>The NISP references Standards from different standardization bodies<footnote><para>In case of conflict between any recommended non-NATO standard and relevant NATO standard, the definition of
the latter prevails.</para></footnote>. In the case of a ratified STANAG, NATO standardization procedures apply. The NISP only references these STANAG’s without displaying the country-specific reservations. The country-specific reservations can be found in the NATO Standardization Office's NATO  Standardization Document Database.</para>

    <para>The Combined Communications Electronics Board (CCEB) nations will use NISP Volume 2 to publish the interoperability standards for the CCEB under the provisions of the NATO-CCEB List of Understandings (LoU)<footnote><para>References: NATO Letter AC/322(SC/5)L/144 of 18 October 2000, CCEB Letter D/CCEB/WS/1/16 of 9 November 2000, NATO Letter AC/322(SC/5)L/157 of 13 February 2001</para></footnote>.</para>

    <para>The NISP organizes the standards using the structure of the latest approved baseline of NATO's C3 Taxonomy. A graphical representation of this taxonomy is given in the following figure and a description of it can be obtained at: <ulink url="https://tide.act.nato.int/tidepedia/index.php/C3_Taxonomy">https://tide.act.nato.int/tidepedia/index.php/C3_Taxonomy</ulink>. Currently, the standards only address a subset of the services in the taxonomy, mainly services in the group Technical Services. For some standards it is indicated that an appropriate mapping to the C3 Taxonomy could not yet be made.
      <figure
        id="f1-c3taxy"
        float="0">
        <title>C3 Taxonomy</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata
              format="PNG"
              fileref="../figures/c3-taxonomy.svg"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata
              fileref="../figures/c3-taxonomy.svg"
              format="SVG"
              width="80%"
              scalefit="1"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
</para>
    <para>In principle, NISP only contains or references standards or related documents, which are generally available for NATO/NATO member nations/CCEB.</para>
    <para>However, a subset of documents may only be available for those nations or organizations, which are joining a specific mission or are members of a special working group. The membership in these activities is outside the scope of NISP.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="v1c-Applicability">
    <title>Applicability</title>
    <para>The mandatory standards and profiles documented in Volume 2 will be used in the implementation of NATO Common Funded Systems. Participating nations agree to use the mandatory standards and profiles included in the NISP at the Service Interoperability Points and to use Service Interface Profiles among NATO and Nations to support the exchange of information and the use of information services in the NATO realm.</para>

  </chapter>

<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    PROFILE Guidance
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol1-ProfileGuidance.xml"
    xpointer="v1-profileguidance" />

<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    NISP and Architecture
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol1-NISP-Arch.xml"
    xpointer="v1-NISPArchitecture" />

<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    SIP Template
 *****************************************************************
-->
<!--
  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol1-sipTemplate.xml"
    xpointer="v1-sip" />
-->
<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    Change Log
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol1-NISPChangeLog.xml"
    xpointer="v1-RecordOfChanges" />

<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    Change Log Details
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol1-NISPChangeLogDetails.xml"
    xpointer="v1-ChangeLog" />

<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    RFCs
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol1-rfcs.xml"
    xpointer="v1-RFCs" />

</book>
