<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix
 id="v1-RecordOfChanges">
  <!--
 *****************************************************************
       Annex - Record of Changes
 *****************************************************************
-->
    <title>Changes from NISP Version 9 (I) to NISP Version 10 (J)</title>
<para>
The NISP Version 10 - ADatP-34(J) incorporates many changes, including:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Quality control of attributes added to the database of version 9.
Verification and cleanup of standards and profiles by reponsible parties.
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Inclusion of new standards and profiles;</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Update to new standard versions;</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Removal of retired standards;</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Removal of standards, that have not been claimed by responsible parties;</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Removal of Profiles:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Profile A - Minimum Interoperability profile,</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Profile C - Web services Profiles(but keeping the related standards),</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Profile D - AMN,</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Profile E - CES Implementation Specification</para></listitem>
     </itemizedlist></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>Profile F – Service Interface Profile Template (moved to volume 1 for guidance).</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist></para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Incorporation of C3 Service Taxonomy (Version 2) as reference for standards - and profile structuring</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>New functionality in the online database viewer to make NISP fit for purpose.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>New orchestration in the printed format to better match stakeholders viewpoints and to focus on the obligation type for NATO common funded systems.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Volume 1: Updated to reflect all basic concepts and management processes</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Volume 2: Mandatory standards and profiles</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Volume 3: Candidate standards and profiles</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Actualisation of the basic concepts in volume 1 along with the newest developments in NATO and FMN concepts, resulting in new status definition of the managed objects (standards and profiles) within NISP.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Standards (their content) are defined and managed in their life cycle by standardisation bodies with their own timetable. A standard may have status like emerging, mature, fading, obsolete, but different standardisation bodies use their own status definition.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Interoperability Profiles define the specific use of standards at a service interoperability point (SIOP) in a given mission context and for a specific scope. Interoperability Profiles define prerequesites for programs and projects to make technical interoperability working. We define the obligation status of profiles as candidate, mandatory or historical (only for archive purposes within the database). Interoperability Profiles have to be updated, if referenced standards are changing. They are dynamic objects by nature. NATO captures this dynamic situation by updating profiles once a year in the NISP.  All outdated concepts have been removed from the profile guidance (moved from Volume 3 to an Appendix of Volume 1). New profile concepts developed by different bodies within NATO will be incorporated in 2017.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Creating relation to other concepts and planning objects within NATO Architecture Building Blocks</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Mission Threads define Service Interoperability Points at workflow-hand-over points,  defining a mission context to Profiles.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Spiral Specifications (FMN) contain architecture, instructions, profiles, and requirements specification and intend to make interoperability working in all aspects. They are continously developed as spirals an have an defined obliation status for NATO common funded systems.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<table frame="all" id="v1c-changes">
            <title>Change Log</title>
            <tgroup
              align="left"
              cols="7">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Type<footnote><para><emphasis role="bold">Types - A</emphasis>: Addition; <emphasis role="bold">D</emphasis>: Deletion;<emphasis role="bold"> U</emphasis>: Updated; <emphasis role="bold">E</emphasis>: Errata correction</para></footnote>
</entry>
                  <entry>Edition</entry>
                  <entry>Volume</entry>
                  <entry>Section,Paragraph,etc.</entry>
                  <entry>Description</entry>
                  <entry>RFCP</entry>
                  <entry>Remarks</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
		<row>
                  <entry>U</entry>
                  <entry>I</entry>
                  <entry>1</entry>
                  <entry>Introduction</entry>
                  <entry>Updated footnote to be determined</entry>
                  <entry></entry>
                  <entry></entry>
                </row>
		<row>
                  <entry>D</entry>
                  <entry>3</entry>
                  <entry>Annex</entry>
                  <entry>B to H</entry>
                  <entry>All profiles now hyperlinked baseline documents</entry>
                  <entry></entry>
                  <entry></entry>
                </row>
		<row>
                  <entry>U</entry>
                  <entry>2,3</entry>
                  <entry>Annex</entry>
                  <entry>A</entry>
                  <entry>Updated to reference profiles using hyperlinks</entry>
                  <entry></entry>
                  <entry></entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
</appendix>

