<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 1 -   A N N E X - B
*****************************************************************  
-->
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v1D-CMnisp">
  <title>Configuration Management of NISP</title>

  <sect1 id="v1D-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Updating of the NISP and its associated database will be conducted
    by a managed, rolling review process which will take into account
    information on standards available from a wide variety of sources. The
    IP CaT acts as the hub for this maintenance activity, supported by the
    NHQC3Staff and NC3A personnel as required.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="v1D-CMorg">
    <title>CM Organization</title>

    <para>For the NISP, authority to act as the Configuration Management Board
    (CMB) lies with the NATO C3 Representatives on behalf of the NATO C3 Board. The IP CaT acts as the Configuration Control
    Board (CCB), to which all RFCP's must be submitted for evaluation,
    approval and inclusion. In conducting this task, the IP CaT will be
    supported by the NC3A (in technical and procedural considerations) and in
    particular instances by working groups where specific technical advice and
    reference may be required. Thus the CM organisation for the NISP may be
    represented as follows:</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">CMB for the NISP is responsible
    for:</emphasis></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>National Endorsement of the NISP</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Promulgation of the NISP throughout NATO</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Monitoring and highlighting project elements which are not in
        conformance with the NISP</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Replying to originators as to the
        acceptance/modification/rejection of their RFCPs</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">CCB for the NISP is responsible
    for:</emphasis></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Processing Change Requests</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Updating and Maintaining the NISP documents</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Assessing related technical developments for inclusion</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Coordination with NC3Staff, Sub-committees and Working
        Groups</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Review and evaluate projects compliance with NISP</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Technical advice and support</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Reporting/recommending new versions to the NC3REPs.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The information updating process is based on Requests For Change
    Proposal (RFCP's).</para>

    <para>Approval of RFCP's will be coordinated with the responsible subject
    matter experts when appropriate. In situations where a timely response is
    requested by the RFCP submitter, the IP CaT will make its recommendation
    directly to the NC3REPS. The paragraphs below contain a detailed
    description of the RFCP process and the form for submitting RFCPs.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="v1D-1RFCP">
    <title>Request for Change Proposal (RFCP)</title>

    <para>Updates to the NISP are handled through Requests For Change Proposal
    (RFCP). RFCPs are usually reviewed at regularly scheduled IP CaT meetings.
    RFCPs deemed urgent are handled in an expedited manner, outside the normal
    meeting schedule of the IP CaT with a reply to the RFCP originator within
    two weeks. Requests for Changes Proposal (RFCP) to the NISP will be
    processed by the IP CaT following the process outlined in <xref
    linkend="v1D-figRFCP" />.</para>

    <figure id="v1D-figRFCP">
      <title>RFCP Handling Process</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../figures/rfcp-proc.svg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="v1E1-Coordination">
    <title>Role and Responsibilities of the NC3B Substructure</title>

    <para>The NC3B sub-committees will contribute to the development of the
    NISP in their respective C3 areas of responsibility by responding to the
    RFCP as indicated above. The co-ordination of NISP development effort
    throughout the NC3B sub-structure should be based on the following
    guidance.</para>

    <para>RFCPs are handled at the IP CaT and national levels. The normal
    procedure for handling RFCPs call for the IP CaT to review the status of
    the RFCPs presented at its previous meeting, their content is discussed
    and the IP CaT defines its position with respect to these RFCPs. If the
    RFCP issue is covered by other working groups, these groups must be
    formally requested to provide comments. National representatives may look
    for some additional review of the RFCPs at a national level. Significant
    problems identified in this process should be brought to the attention of
    the IP CaT within a period of eight weeks. The final deadline is however
    the date of the meeting of the final review of the NISP. This period is
    meant to encourage tasking of national experts to verify national
    positions and to co-ordinate with national representatives in other
    working groups.</para>

<!-- Ken: The following paragraph is wrong -->


    <para>The secretaries of the SCs will constitute the primary point of
    co-ordination with the IP CaT, to help the ISSC/IP CaT to obtain the
    adequate support from each SCs working structure;</para>

    <para>In special cases, specific requests for information or even
    questionnaires will be sent to the relevant Committees/WGs, in order to
    receive expert views on specific issues, technologies, or other relevant
    information.</para>

<!-- Ken: The following paragraph is wrong -->

    <para>The IP CaT Chairman (or suitably delegated IP CaT representatives)
    will be available to participate in any SCs or SC/WGs meeting when
    necessary or required.</para>

    <para>RFCPs requiring a response in a more timely manner will be handled
    by the IP CaT outside its scheduled meetings and within a two week period
    from receipt of the RFCP. The IP CaT will use a web based collaboration
    tool, to discuss and develop a recommendation regarding these urgent RFCPs. The IP CaT recommendation will
    be passed directly to the NC3REPS, via its secretary, for approval by the
    NC3REPS. Once approved by the NC3REPS, the NISP database will be updated
    to reflect the NC3REPS decision.</para>

    <para>The chairman IP CaT will give an annual update to the NC3REPS and all
    Sub-Committees (SC) highlighting the RFCPS handled by the IP CaT
    including:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>RFCPS related to the POW of Sub-Committees</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>IP CaT recommendations for standard status to be reviewed by
        Sub-Committee</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="v1D-RESOURCES">
    <title>Resources</title>

    <para>As described above, the CM organisation is dependent on resource
    contributions from NATO and the NATO nations through their participation
    in the various committees and working groups involved in the CM process.
    This support will typically take the form of reviews and submitting RFCPs
    and to exercise the responsibilities of the CMB and CCB.</para>

    <para>As NISP custodian, the IP CaT annually determines the overall update
    task requirement and associated resources necessary for its completion.
    Tasks that will be undertaken by national sources will be initially
    consolidated under the IP CaT. Those that can be more effectively
    undertaken by the NC3A (e.g. specialist technical or procedural support),
    will be endorsed by the IP CaT as part of the NC3A Programme of Work, and
    funded from NC3B resources.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="v1D-BASELINE">
    <title>Baseline</title>

    <para>The rationale for establishing a formal NISP Baseline derives from
    the interdependency of all volumes, and the need to maintain coherence
    throughout their individual and collective content, in particular across
    Volumes 2 through 5.</para>

    <para>When a version of the NISP is considered updated, that is, all
    applicable RFCP's submitted have been actioned, it will be baselined by
    the IP CaT for release to the NC3B and recommended for promulgation to
    NATO. This Baseline applies to the NISP in its entirety, regardless of
    whether any particular volume has been subject to RFCP procedure or not
    since the previous Baseline was issued, and replaces the previous Baseline
    in totality. It signifies a specific point in the update cycle of the NISP
    as described previously.</para>

    <para>Standards and profiles will be maintained in an online database that
    will be updated when approved by the authorized authority.</para>

	<para>The formal publication of the NISP, ADatP-34 will be developed in accordance with AAP-3: Procedures for the Development, Preparation, Production and the Upgrading of NATO Standardization Agreements (STANAGs) and Allied Publications (APs).</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="v1D-Guidance">
    <title>Request for Change Proposal (RFCP) Guidance</title>

    <para>In order to process any RFCP it is important to provide as much
    information as possible.</para>

    <para>Changes should outline the key elements of the proposed
    change(s), references to associated documentation and description of
    perceived technology trend (if appropriate). Changes should only be
    proposed in areas where a technology is gaining a broad market acceptance
    and mature product base.</para>

    <para>Requests for new standards will address details such as
    a full specification title, description of applicability, and reference to
    a Web address or other source. Changes to, or deletion, of existing
    standards will require appropriate support justification.</para>

    <para>Under normal circumstances, changes to mandatory standards will have already,
 for example a standard possibly proposed as maturing from 'emerging' to 'mandatory'.</para>

    <para>Rationale for changes must be adequately supported with
    implementation evidence in order to allow the review process to
    proceed.</para>

<para>The rationale used by the IP CaT for determining the selection of standards and profiles for inclusion in the NISP will be part of the IP CaT Standard Operating Procedures.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="v1D-form">
    <title>RFCP Form</title>

    <para>The form for submitting RFCPs is shown below:</para>

    <table>
      <title>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles (NISP) Request For
      Change Proposal</title>

      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec align="left" />

        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry align="left">REQUESTING ORGANIZATION</entry>

            <entry align="center"></entry>
          </row>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry><para>Point of Contact</para> <para>Full Address</para>
            <para>Tel, fax, email</para></entry>

            <entry></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Date of Request</entry>

            <entry></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Urgency of Request</para> <para>Normal</para>
            <para>Urgent</para></entry>

            <entry></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Which Volume (1,2,3,4,5,6)</entry>

            <entry></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>Type of Change</para> <para>(e.g. mandatory standard,
            emerging near term standard, new profile)</para></entry>

            <entry></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Classification of change request</entry>

            <entry></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Rational for change (add supporting text as
            appropriate)</entry>

            <entry></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><emphasis role="bold">IP CaT RESPONSE</emphasis></entry>

            <entry></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Date of response to originator</entry>

            <entry></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>Acceptance/refusal (with rationale for decision)</entry>

            <entry></entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry><para>For urgent RFCPs</para> <para>Date of NC3B
            decision</para> <para>Date of database update</para></entry>

            <entry></entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>Submit form to: Secretary IP CaT</para>
  </sect1>
</appendix>
