<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<book lang="en">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles</title>
	<titleabbrev>NISP</titleabbrev>
    <subtitle>Introduction (2016 Edition)</subtitle>
    <corpauthor>C3B Interoperability Profiles Capability Team</corpauthor>
    <productname class="trade">Allied Data Publication 34</productname>
    <biblioid class="pubnumber">ADatP-34</biblioid>
    <volumenum>1</volumenum>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>9.8</revnumber>
        <date>12 December 2016</date>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>NISP NATO Interoperability Standards Profiles</keyword>
      <keyword>ADatP-34</keyword>
      <keyword>Allied Data Procedure 34</keyword>
      <keyword>STANAG 5524</keyword>
      <keyword>STANAG</keyword>
      <keyword>IP CaT</keyword>
      <keyword>Interoperability Profiles Capability Team</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <subjectset><subject><subjectterm>DO NOT REMOVE</subjectterm></subject></subjectset>
  </bookinfo>
<!--
 *****************************************************************
       C H A P T E R 1 - Introduction and Background
 *****************************************************************
-->
<chapter id="v1c-Introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>The NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles (NISP) is developed by the NATO Consultation, Command and Control (C3) Board Interoperability Profiles Capability Team (IP CaT).</para>
<para>The NISP will be made available to the general public as ADatP-34(J) when approved by the C3 Board
<footnote><para>TBD</para></footnote>.</para>
<para>The included interoperability standards and profiles (Volume 2) are <emphasis role="bold">mandatory</emphasis> for use in NATO common funded Communications and Information Systems (CIS).Volume 3 contains <emphasis role="bold">candidate</emphasis><footnote><para>A candidate standard or profile may be mature enough to be used in future programmes after 1 to 2 years.</para></footnote> standards and profiles.</para>
<para>In case of conflict between any recommended non-NATO<footnote><para>ISO or other recognized non-NATO standards organization</para></footnote> standard and relevant NATO standard, the definition of the latter prevails.</para>
<para>In the NISP the keywords "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED",
          "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
          "OPTIONAL" are to be interpreted as described in [IETF RFC 2119].</para>

<table frame="all" id="v1-abbreviations">
<title>Abbreviations</title>
<tgroup align="left" cols="2">
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Abbreviation</entry>
<entry>Full Text</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row><entry>C3</entry><entry><para>Consultation, Command and Control</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IP CaT</entry><entry><para>Interoperability Profiles Capability Team</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>NISP</entry><entry><para>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>TACOMS</entry><entry><para>Tactical Communication Programme</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>MIP</entry><entry><para>Multilateral Interoperabiltiy Programme</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>NDPP</entry><entry><para>Nato Defence Planning Process</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>FMN</entry><entry><para>Federated Mission Networking</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>CWIX</entry><entry><para>Coalition Warrior Interoperability eXploration, eXperimentation, eXamination eXercise</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>CIAV (WG)</entry><entry><para>Coalition Interoperability Assurance and Validation (Working Group)</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>STANAG</entry><entry><para>NATO abbreviation for Standardization Agreement, which set up processes, procedures, terms, and conditions for common military or technical procedures or equipment between the member countries of the alliance.</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SIOP</entry><entry><para>Service Interoperability Point.</para><para>Definition is to be found in EAPC(AC/322)D (2006)0002-REV 1): SIOP is a reference point within an architecture where one or more service interfaces are physically or logically instantiated to allow systems delivering the same service using different protocols to interoperate.</para><para> 
Note: A service interoperability point serves as the focal point for service interoperability between interconnected systems, and may be logically located at any level within the components, and its detailed technical specification is contained within a service interface profile.</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>IOP</entry><entry><para>A definition of "IOP" will be incorporated in 2017: from MC-593 (23. February 2015) Minimum level of C2 service capabilities in support of combined joint NATO led operations.</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>EAPC</entry><entry><para>Euro-Atlantic Partnership Council</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>NAF</entry><entry><para>NATO Architecture Framework</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>ABB</entry><entry><para>Architecture Building Block</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>RFCP</entry><entry><para>Request for Change Proposal</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>AdatP-34</entry><entry><para>Allied Data Publication - Cover publication for the NISP</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>CIS</entry><entry><para>Communication and Information Systems</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>ACaT</entry><entry><para>Architecture Capability Team</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>SME</entry><entry><para>Subject Matter Experts</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>CCEB</entry><entry><para>Combined Communications Electronic Board (military communications-electronics organisation established among five nations: Australia, Canada, New Zealand, United Kingdom, and the United States)</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>COI</entry><entry><para>Community of Interest</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>DOTMLPFI</entry><entry><para>Doctrine, Organization, Training, Materiel, Leadership and education, Personnel, Facilities and Interoperability</para></entry>
</row>
<row><entry>NGO</entry><entry><para>Non govermental organisation</para></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<sect1 id="v1-Purpose">
<title>Purpose of the NISP</title>
<para>NISP gives guidelines to capability planners, programme managers and test managers for NATO common funded systems in the short or mid-term timeframes.</para>
<para>The NISP prescribes the necessary technical standards and profiles to achieve interoperability of Communications and Information Systems in support of NATO's missions and operations. In accordance with the Alliance C3 Strategy (ref. C-M(2014)0016) all NATO Enterprise<footnote><para>The NATO Enterprise has been identified in C-M(2014)0061</para></footnote> entities shall adhere to the NISP prescribed standards and profiles in volume 2.</para>
<para>Other initiatives, that assure interoperability within the coalition (like TACOMS, MIP, MSA, Archive) should list their profiles in the NISP.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="v1-Audience">
<title>Intended Audience</title>
<para>The intended audience of the NISP are all stakeholders in the NATO Enterprise, and Allied and Partner nations involved in development, implementation, lifecycle management, and transformation to a federated environment.</para>
<para>There are specific viewpoints, that are mapped to the NISP structure. NISP gives guidelines to:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>capability planners involved in NDPP and NATO led initiatives (e.g. FMN)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>programme managers for building NATO common funded systems</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>test managers for their respective test events (such as CWIX, CIAV, etc.)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>national planning and programme managers for their national intiatives</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
<para>Specific NATO or national views to the NISP, based on data export to external planning and management systems will be possible upon delivery of the NISP Exchange Specification in 2017.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="v1c-concepts">
<title>Basic Concepts</title>
<para>With Version 10, basic concepts are adopted to reflect newer developments within NATO. This chapter intends to give an overview to understand the data in volume 2 and volume 3.</para>
<sect1 id="v1c-standards">
<title>Standards</title>
<!-- Define the term Standard-->
<para>Standards (their content) are defined and managed in their life cycle by standardisation bodies with their own timetable. A standard may have life cycle status such as emerging, mature, fading, or obsolete. Different standardisation bodies may use their own lifecycle status definitions. NISP takes lifecyle status of standards into account, but does not copy them into the NISP database. For aspects of obligation status for standards in planning and programmes, see the next paragraph.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="v1c-stanag">
<title>STANAG</title>
<!-- Define the term STANAG see AAP-03-->
<para>STANAG's are managed by the NATO Standardization Organization (NSO). Depending on the ratification status, they become mandatory only for NATO funded systems. If NISP references a STANAG, the obligation status for it is only informative. The NSO maintains the obligation status in their own process of standardisation.</para>
<para>Some STANAGS are managed by NATO as mandatory to specific programmes and projects. They can be seen as defacto profiles.</para>
<para>Some older STANAG's combine the agreement and the actual specification into one single document. NISP references the specification part.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="v1c-profiles">
<title>Interoperability Profiles</title>
<para>Profiles define the specific use of standards at a service interoperability point (SIOP) in a given context. Profiles support prerequesites for programmes or projects and enable interoperability implementation and testing.</para>
<para>Interoperability Profiles provide collections of standards and (sub)profiles for different CIS.</para>
<para><!--move this up in the stack after para 11 -->The NISP now defines the <emphasis role="bold">obligation status</emphasis> of profiles and standards as "mandatory" or "candidate". 
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Mandatory</emphasis>: The application of standards or profiles is enforeced for NATO common funded systems in planning, implementating and testing. Nations are invited to do the same nationally to promote interoperabilty for federated systems and services. </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Candidate</emphasis>: The application of profile and standards shall be planned for future programmes. The standard or profile is mature enough to be used  in programmes in 1 to 2 years. This implies, that from a planning perspective, this standard or profile may become mandatory at the time, the programme starts. A candidate standard or profile shall stay in volume 3 no longer than 2 years, unless explicitely marked as an exception to this rule.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Historical</emphasis>: A third status, called "historical" is used only for long term preservation purposes within the NISP database.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>Profiles have to be updated, if referenced standards are changing. Profiles are dynamic entities by nature. NATO captures this dynamic situation by updating profiles once a year in the NISP. Responsible bodies are responsible for the versioning of their profiles. Profile reviews are required every 2 years by their owners to ensure their accuracy and continued relevance.</para>
<para>Proposed profiles (and standards) can be accepted as candidates in order to follow their developments and to decide if they can be promoted to mandatory standards and profiles. In some cases proposed standards and profiles can be readily accepted directly as mandatory.</para>
<para>Interoperability Profiles identify essential profile elements including:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Capability Requirements and other NAF architectural views,</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>characteristic protocols,</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>implementation options,</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>technical standards,</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Service Interoperability Points, and</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>the relationship with other profiles such as the system profile to which an application belongs.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>Interoperability Profiles can reference other Interoperability Profiles to allow for maximal reuse.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="v1s-otherConcepts">
<title>Creating relationships to other concepts and planning objects within NATO</title>
<para>Different initiatives and organisations have developed new concepts to govern developments in the interoperability domain. These concepts have logical relationship to the NISP.</para>
<sect2 id="v1s-ABB">
<title>Architecture Building Block</title>
<para>A constituent of the architecture model that describes a single aspect of the overall model
<footnote><para>TOGAF 9.1 Specification</para></footnote>.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="v1s-FMNspirals">
<title>FMN Spiral Specifications</title>
<para>FMN Spiral<footnote><para>ANNEX B TO VOLUME I - IMPLEMENTATION OVERVIEW, NATO FMN IMPLEMENTATION PLAN v3.0 DATED: 8 JULY 2014, TERMS AND DEFINITIONS</para><footnote>  Specifications encompass "an evolutionary cycle that will raise the level of maturity of federated mission networking capabilities over time".</para>
<para>The FMN spiral specification contain the following sections
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>architecture,</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>instructions,</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>profiles, and</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>requirements specifications.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
The Mandatory and Candidate FMN Spiral Profiles are listed in the NISP Volumes 2 and 3.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="v1s-CPs">
<title>Capability Packages</title>
<para>Profiles will be referenced in the NISP for specified NATO Common Funded Systems or Capability Packages and may include descriptions of interfaces to National Systems where appropriate.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="v1c-InfoOrganization">
    <title>Organization of the NISP Information</title>
<sect1 id="v1s-structure">
    <title>NISP Structure</title>
    <para>In general, systems development approaches suggest a clean line of reasoning from requirements capturing, to architecture, to portfolio planning, to design and build via testing to implementation and utilization and finally to retirement. NISP adresses mainly the phases of portfolio planning, build and test phases of the system lifecycle. NISP data export (planned for 2017) will enable the support of other phases by other management bodies in NATO or nations.</para>
    <para>The structure of the NISP is determined by several factors:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Ease of use of the NISP for planners and programme managers; and</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Nature and properties of standards and profiles.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The NISP contains three volumes:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Volume 1</emphasis> - Introduction and Management: This volume introduces basic concepts, provides the management framework for the configuration control of the NISP and the process for handling Request for Change Proposals (RFCP). It includes also guidance on development of interoperability profiles.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Volume 2</emphasis> - Mandatory standards and profiles: This volume lists agreed interoperability standards and profiles, mandatory for NATO common funded systems. These should support NATO and National systems today and new systems actually under procurement or specification.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Volume 3</emphasis>– Candidate standards and profiles: This Volume provides Standards and Interoperability Profiles for programmes to start in 1 to 2 years.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>Volume 2 is normative for NATO common funded systems and Volume 3 is informative.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="v1c-ISCPP">
    <title>Interoperability in Support of Capability Planning</title>
    <title>Architecture and Interoperability in the Context of NATO Defence Planning</title>
    <para>The following documents form the foundation to understand the embedding of NISP into NDPP and architecture work:
<table frame="all" id="v1t-NDPPdocs">
<title>NDPP References</title>
<tgroup align="left" cols="3">
<thead>
<row>
<entry>Document</entry>
<entry>Document Reference</entry>
<entry>Homepage</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry><para>Alliance C3 Strategy Information and Communication Technology to prepare NATO 2020 (7 March 2014)</para></entry>
<entry><para>Alliance C3 Strategy C-M(2014)0016</para></entry>
<entry><para>https://tide.act.nato.int/tidepedia/index.php/Alliance_C3_Strategy</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>Alliance C3 Interoperability Policy by the NATO C3 Board (17 February 2015)</para></entry>
<entry><para>Alliance C3 Interoperability Policy AC/322-D(2015)0002</para></entry>
<entry><para>https://tide.act.nato.int/tidepedia/index.php/NATO_C3_Interoperability_Policy</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>C3 Enterprise Architecture Policy (15 December 2015)</para></entry>
<entry><para>C3 Enterprise Architecture Policy AC322-D(2015)0030</para></entry>
<entry><para>https://tide.act.nato.int/tidepedia/index.php/NATO_C3_Enterprise_Architecture_Policy</para></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><para>NATO Defence Planning Process (NDPP)</para></entry>
<entry><para> </para></entry>
<entry><para>https://tide.act.nato.int/tidepedia/index.php/NATO_Defence_Planning_Process_(NDPP)</para></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</para>
    <para>The NATO Defence Planning Process (NDPP) is the primary means to identify the required capabilities and promote their timely and coherent development and acquisition by Allies and Partners. It is operationally driven and delivers various products which could support the development and evolution of more detailed C3 architecture and interoperability requirements. The development of NDPP products also benefits from input by the architecture and interoperability communities, especially the NISP, leading to a more coherent development of CIS capabilities for the Alliance.</para>
<para>The work on Enterprise, Capability, and programme level architecture will benefit from the NISP by selecting coherent sets of standards for profiles. </para>
</chapter>

  <chapter id="v1c-ABB">
    <title>Architecture Building Blocks</title>
    <sect1 id="v1c-abbc"><title>Characteristics</title>
<para>ABBs:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Capture architecture requirements; e.g., business, data, application, and technology requirements</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Direct and guide the development of Solution Building Blocks</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="v1c-abbsc"><title>Specification Content</title>
<para>ABB specifications include the following as a minimum:
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Fundamental functionality and attributes: semantic, unambiguous, including security capability and manageability</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Interfaces: chosen set, supplied</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Interoperability and relationship with other building blocks</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Dependent building blocks with required functionality and named user interfaces</para>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Map to business/organizational entities and policies</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>

<chapter id="v1c-ConfigurationManagement">
    <title>Configuration Management</title>
   <para>The NISP is updated once a year to account for the evolution of standards and profiles. Updates to the NISP are handled through a "Requests for Change Proposal" (RFCP) process, initiated by any stakeholder or 
by specific processes for review purposes, initiated by the IP CaT. </para>
<sect1 id="v1s1-NISP-RFCP">
      <title>Request for Change Proposal (RFCP)</title>
      <para>Request for Change Proposal (RFCP) to the NISP will be processed by the IP CaT, following the process in the graphic below:</para>
      <figure id="v1f6-RFCP" float="0">
        <title>RFCP Handling Process</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/rfcp-proc.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The RFCP contains all information required for the NISP management by IP CaT; The detailed information about standard or profile is handed over as attachments to this form. A notional RFCP form with examples is presented below:</para>
<para><figure id="v1f6-RFCP1" float="0">
        <title>RFCP Notional Form</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/RFCPex1.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
</para>
<para><figure id="v1f6-RFCP2" float="0">
        <title>RFCP Example 1</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/RFCPex2.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
</para>
<para><figure id="v1f6-RFCP3" float="0">
        <title>RFCP Example 2</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/RFCPex3.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
</para>
<para><figure id="v1f6-RFCP4" float="0">
        <title>RFCP Example 3</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/RFCPex4.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
</para>
<para>The primary point of contact for RFCP submission is the IP CaT. RFCPs may be submitted to the IP CaT via the web site or via mail to the indicated mail adress with attached standard form.</para>
<para>Review of RFCPs will be coordinated with the responsible C3 Board substructure organizations where appropriate.</para>
<para>The IP CaT reviews the submissions in dialog with national and international bodies. Based on that review, the RFCP will be formally processed into the next version of the NISP; or returned to the originator for further details; or rejected.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="v1s1-UpdateProcess">
<title>NISP Update Process</title>
<para>The new verison NISP is submitted to the C3 Board by end of the year after internal review by the IP CaT. The version under review is a snapshot in time of the status of standards and profiles.</para>
<para>The database of standards and profiles maintained by the IP CaT is the definitive source of the currents status of standards and profiles. </para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="v1s1-Products">
<title>NISP Products</title>
<para>Documentation in HTML and PDF Formats</para>
<para>Website and searchable online Database</para>
<para>Data export in a standard format will be available in 2017.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
<chapter id="v1c-CoordinationNations">
<title>National Systems Interoperability Coordination</title>
      <para>Coordination of profiles and standards between Nations and NATO are critical for interoperability. The IP CaT, as the result of the C3 Board sub structure reorganization, does not provide a forum for the statement of national technical efforts. Rather it is up to each of the SMEs represented on the IP CaT to work with national and C3 Board representation to ensure thoughtful coordination of interoperability requirements. As such, each of the IP CaT SMEs is responsible for:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Appropriate and timely coordination of standards and profiles with respect to interoperability with national systems;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Coordination of the SME input including co-ordination with national SMEs of other C3 Board substructure groups; and</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Providing appropriate technical information and insight based on national market assessment.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
<para>National level coordination of interoperability technical standards and profiles is the responsibility of the C3 Board.  As a result, when the NISP is approved by the C3 Board, the NISP provides national agreement on the NATO interoperability standards and profiles.</para>
</chapter>


  <chapter id="v1c-stdsGuidance">
    <title>Interoperability Standards Guidance</title>
    <para>The NISP references Standards from different standardization bodies<footnote><para>In case of conflict between any recommended non-NATO standard and relevant NATO standard, the definition of
the latter prevails.</para></footnote>. In the case of a ratified STANAG, NATO Standardization procedures apply. The NISP only references these STANAG’s without displaying the country-specific reservations. The country-specific reservations can be found in the NATO Standardization Agency Standards database.</para>
    <para>The Combined Communications Electronics Board (CCEB) nations will use NISP Volume 2 to publish the interoperability standards for the CCEB under the provisions of the NATO-CCEB List of Understandings (LoU)<footnote><para>References:NATO Letter AC/322(SC/5)L/144 of 18 October 2000, CCEB Letter D/CCEB/WS/1/16 of 9 November 2000, NATO Letter AC/322(SC/5)L/157 of 13 February 2001</para></footnote>.</para>
    <para>The NISP organizes the standards into five service areas, following NATO's C3 Taxonomy (Version 2, 10 November 2015). A graphical representation of this taxonomy is given in the following figure and a description of it can be obtained at: https://tide.act.nato.int/tidepedia/index.php/C3_Taxonomy
<figure id="f1-c3taxy" float="0">
<title>C3 Taxonomy</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata align="center" fileref="../figures/c3-taxonomy.svg"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure></para>
    <para>In principle, NISP only contains or references standards or related documents, which are generally available for NATO/NATO member nations/CCEB.</para>
    <para>However, a subset of documents may only be available for those nations or organisations, which are joining a specific mission or are members of a special working group. The membership in these activities is outside the scope of NISP.</para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="v1c-Applicability">
    <title>Applicability</title>
    <para>The mandatory standards and profiles documented in Volume 2 will be used in the implementation of NATO Common Funded Systems. Participating nations agree to use the mandatory standards and profiles included in the NISP at the Service Interoperability Points and to use Service Interface Profiles among NATO and Nations to support the exchange of information and the use of information services in the NATO realm.</para>

  </chapter>

<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    PROFILE Guidance
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol1-ProfileGuidance.xml"
    xpointer="v1-profileguidance" />

<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    NISP and Architecture
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol1-NISP-Arch.xml"
    xpointer="v1-NISPArchitecture" />

<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    SIP Template
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol1-sipTemplate.xml"
    xpointer="v1-sip" />
<!--
 *****************************************************************
                    Change Log
 *****************************************************************
-->

  <xi:include
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="vol1-NISPChangeLog.xml"
    xpointer="v1-RecordOfChanges" />

</book>
