<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
*****************************************************************
                   Vol 1 -   A N N E X - A
*****************************************************************  
-->

<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<appendix id="v1a-LOU">
    <title>NATO-CCEB List of Understandings (LoU)</title>
	<para>Editorial Note:  The intent of the NATO-CCEB LoU remains extant even though from 2007 onwards the NISP replaced the NC3TA, the NCSP became extinct, the NATO Overarching Architecture, the NNEC evolved considerably and the NC3B organization changed.</para>
    <sect1 id="v1s1-np-lou-nc">
      <title>List of Understandings between NATO and the CCEB</title>

      <para><emphasis role="underline">References:</emphasis></para>
	<orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>NATO Letter AC/322(SC/5)L/144 of 18 October 2000</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>CCEB Letter D/CCEB/WS/1/16 of 9 November 2000</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>NATO Letter AC/322(SC/5)L/157 of 13 February 2001</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>

      <para><emphasis role="underline">Purpose</emphasis></para>

      <para>The purpose of this document is to provide an enduring record of
      the understandings that have been reached between NATO and the Combined
      Communications Electronics Board (CCEB) in regard to the harmonization
      of the NATO and CCEB technical architectures</para>

      <para><emphasis role="underline">Background</emphasis></para>

      <para>At reference 1, NATO (through the ISSC) noted the parallel
      activities in NATO and the CCEB to develop a multi-national technical
      architecture. As this represented an opportunity to converge on a single
      technical architecture NATO extended an invitation to Australia and New
      Zealand, as non-NATO members of the CCEB, to participate as non-voting
      observers in the NATO Open Systems Working Group (NOSWG) meetings and
      on-line discussions. NATO (via the ISSC) assured Australia and New
      Zealand that their technical contributions would be accorded the same
      consideration as all other participants in NOSWG meetings.</para>

      <para>The CCEB, at reference 2, accepted these invitations and confirmed
      that it was a CCEB priority to develop a single technical architecture
      to enhance interoperability between NATO and CCEB nations. Collaborative
      work with NATO and CCEB subject matter experts in early 2001
      demonstrated that harmonization of the relevant sections of the CCEB and
      NATO technical architectures was achievable. Further collaborative
      effort throughout 2001 resulted in a harmonized technical architecture
      consisting relevant portions of NCSP Ver 2, ACP140A and CCEB Pub
      1007.</para>

      <para>To ensure that a single technical architecture would recognize the
      needs of all CCEB nations, the CCEB sought clarification on Australia
      and New Zealand participation in technical architecture development and
      maintenance. Of particular note were the equity arrangements and
      opportunities for Australia and New Zealand to contribute to and
      influence future technical architecture development, and access to all
      relevant standards and documents referenced in the NATO technical
      architecture. The ISSC has assured the CCEB that technical contributions
      from Australia and New Zealand will be accorded the same consideration
      as those submitted by all other participants at NOSWG meetings at
      reference C and that the ISSC will support the release of relevant NATO
      documents to Australia and New Zealand, subject to NATO Policy regarding
      the release of NATO documents to non-NATO nations and NATO Security
      Policy. Subsequently the CCEB confirmed its intention, subject to
      acceptance of the NATO NCSP Vol 4 version 3 by all CCEB nations, to
      adopt it as its technical architecture.</para>

      <para>The September 2001 NATO Open Systems Working Group meeting drafted a List of Understandings
      to document agreements and processes that would provide an enduring
      record for future NOSWG participants of the background of the technical
      architecture harmonization initiative, and the continuing role of
      Australia and New Zealand (as non-NATO nations) in this activity.</para>

      <para><emphasis role="underline">List of
      Understandings</emphasis></para>

      <para>The following understandings and undertakings have been agreed
      between NATO and the CCEB in regard to the harmonization of current and
      future versions the NATO and CCEB technical architectures:</para>

      <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
        <listitem>
          <para>NATO desires that the NC3TA be acceptable to all the CCEB
          nations.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The CCEB intends to adopt NC3TA Volume 4 (NCSP) as the CCEB
          technical architecture following its acceptance by the all CCEB
          member nations.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The CCEB desires that the scope of NC3TA Volume 4 (NCSP) be
          comparable to ACP140A and the rationale for NCSP standards selection
          be detailed in a NATO document able to be referenced in CCEB
          policy.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Australia and New Zealand, as non-NATO members of the CCEB,
          are invited to participate as observers and their technical
          contributions will be accorded the same consideration as those
          submitted from all other participants in NOSWG meetings. Being
          non-NATO nations, Australia and New Zealand acknowledge that they
          are not able to vote in NOSWG matters.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The CCEB will note any variances in CCEB interoperability
          standards in the remarks column of the NCSP standards tables with
          the remark 'For CCEB interoperability the standard is ...'</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If necessary, Australia and New Zealand will develop and
          publish national supplements to document national variances or
          exceptions to NC3TA NCSP standards. These instances are expected to
          be rare. Any nationally approved Australian and New Zealand national
          supplements to the NC3TA NCSP will be forwarded to the NOSWG
          Secretary for formal distribution to all NATO nations.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Any Request For Change Proposals (RFCPs) or amendments
          proposed to the NC3TA NCSP (Volume 4) by NATO nations will be
          distributed in accordance with NATO policy for the release of NATO
          documents to non-NATO nations (via email to the maximum extent
          possible in accordance with NATO Policy on the use of the Internet)
          by the NOSWG Secretary to the Australian and New Zealand
          representatives to the NOSWG for staffing nationally within
          Australia and New Zealand.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Australia and New Zealand will be provided access (in a
          readable electronic format wherever possible) to all standards and
          documents listed in the NC3TA NCSP to the maximum extent possible in
          accordance with NATO policy for the release of NATO documents to
          non-NATO nations and NATO Security Policy. The United Kingdom will
          sponsor release of the relevant NATO documents to Australia and New
          Zealand.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>As necessary, the United Kingdom Mission in NATO will act as
          the Point of Contact for distribution of all NC3TA NCSP documents
          between NATO and Australia and New Zealand.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect1>

</appendix>
