<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../schema/dtd/docbkx45/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY nisp-web-mainpage "http://nisp.nc3a.nato.int/">
]>
<book lang="en">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles</title>
    <subtitle>Introduction and Management</subtitle>
    <corpauthor>C3 CCSC NATO Open Systems Working Group</corpauthor>
    <productname class="trade">Allied Data Publication 34</productname>
    <biblioid class="pubnumber">ADatP-34</biblioid>
    <volumenum>1</volumenum>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>4.20</revnumber>
        <date>6 April 2011</date>
        <revremark></revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>NISP NATO Interoperability Standards Profiles</keyword>
      <keyword>ADatP-34</keyword>
      <keyword>Allied Data Procedure 34</keyword>
      <keyword>STANAG 5524</keyword>
      <keyword>STANAG</keyword>
      <keyword>NOSWG</keyword>
      <keyword>NATO Open System Working Group</keyword>
    </keywordset>
    <productnumber>$Id$</productnumber>
  </bookinfo>
  <!-- 
 *****************************************************************
       C H A P T E R 1 - Introduction and EXECUTIVE SUMMARY
 ***************************************************************** 
Typical draft text : This document is a draft under development by the NATO Open Systems Working Group (NOSWG) under the authority the NATO Consultation, Command and Control Board (NC3B).
In due course it is expected to be noted by the NATO C3 Board making the Volume 2 standards and profiles mandatory for use in NATO common funded systems, and to be made available to the general public as a replacement for ADatP-34(D).

-->
  <chapter id="v1c-Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
<para>This agreed document was developed by the NATO Open Systems Working Group (NOSWG) under the authority the NATO Consultation, Command and Control Board (NC3B). It was noted by the NATO C3 Board making the Volume 2 standards and profiles mandatory for use in NATO common funded systems, and made available to the general public as a replacement for ADatP-34(D).</para>

  </chapter>
<!-- 
 *****************************************************************
                    C H A P T E R - 2
 ***************************************************************** 
-->
  <chapter id="v1c-purpose">
    <title>Purpose of the NISP</title>
    <para>The NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles (NISP) provides the
    necessary guidance and technical components to support project
    implementations and transition to NATO Network Enabled Capability (NNEC).
    Also the Combined Communications Electronics Board (CCEB) nations use the
    NISP to publish the interoperability standards for the CCEB under the
    provisions of the NATO-CCEB List of Understandings (LoU) detailed in <xref linkend="v1a-LOU" /> of this volume. In addition, in order to support
    the Prague Capabilities Commitment (PCC), more emphasis is placed on interoperability profiles to support
    the NRF and transition from today's legacy systems to NNEC.</para>
    <para>The purpose of the NISP is to:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Encourage Nations to use the same standards as within the NATO CIS implementations in NATO led operations;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Serve as the principal source of technical guidance for
        management of NATO CIS project implementations and transition to
        NNEC;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Track technology developments in order to optimise application
        development;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Identify and manage all applicable CIS standards as a baseline
        for optimising programmes and project selection and adherence;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Assess CIS products for NATO application;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Support architecture-based CIS programme development and
        evolution;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Provision of technical reference and rationale to promote and
        optimise NATO CIS interoperability;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Promote NATO internal, Nation to NATO and Nation to Nation
        interoperability;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Provide guidance on transformation to NNEC;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Identify applicable Design Rules to support cooperation in
            federated common missions with proven solutions;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Identify applicable Profiles as a baseline for optimising
            service and standards implementation and utilization to support
            cross-domain scenarios.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The stakeholders of the NISP are all NNEC stakeholders involved in development, implementation, lifecycle management, and transformation to an NNEC environment. Stakeholder review will take place periodically and the results reflected in this section.</para>
    <para>This document provides a general description of the current version of the
    NISP. Volume 1 of the six volumes deals with the NISP purpose,
    the structure and the process of collecting standards from
    stakeholders, including the configuration management and
    publication of the NISP. Volume 2 focuses on near-term
    implementation (i.e.  present<footnote><para>Date of Approval by
    the NC3REPS on behalf of the NC3B</para></footnote> to 2 years in
    the future), Volume 3 focuses on mid-term implementation (2 to 10
    years in the future). Volume 4 provides Interoperability Profile Guidance and references. Volume 5 provides Design Rule Guidance and references. Volume 6 contains a number of appendices relevant to the NISP.</para>
    <para>The mandatory standards and profiles documented in Volume 2 will be used in the
    implementation of NATO Common Funded Systems. Participating nations agree to use the mandatory standards and profiles included in the NISP at the Service Interoperability Points and to use Service Interface Profiles among NATO and Nations to support the exchange of information and the use of information services in the NATO realm.</para>
  </chapter>
  <!-- 
 *****************************************************************
       C H A P T E R 3 - NISP STRUCTURE
 ***************************************************************** 
-->
  <chapter id="v1c-Structure">
    <title>NISP Structure</title>
    <para>The structure of the NISP is determined by several factors:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ease of use for the users of the NISP;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Implementation strategy of the NNEC vision;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Nature of standards, profiles and design rules.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Partitioning the NISP into timeframes of near and mid-term was
    influenced by the NNEC FS, national NEC development and industry
    best practices. One common thread through all these efforts is the need to
    partition NATO CIS implementations and transition to NNEC into well
    defined time periods which are:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Near-term: 0 to 2 years;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Mid-term: 2 to 10 years;</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The NISP reflects these timeframes in individual volumes. To provide
    consistency between these volumes and ease of tracking technology trends
    and influences, each of the volumes has similar structures
    containing major sections dealing with:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Technology</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Standards</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Transition</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>These similar structures enable one to focus in on a stakeholders area of
    interest and to track this area of interest as it transforms towards the NNEC paradigm.</para>
    <para>Standards are the focus of volume 2 and 3. The standards referenced in these volumes provide an overview of those standards that must be taken into account when developing profiles and architectures within the applicable period of time.</para>
    <para>The profiles in volume 4 are based on mission requirements which
    influence required services and interoperability points.</para>
    <para>The NISP contains the five following main volumes:</para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Volume 1 - Overview and Management</emphasis>:
    This volume provides the management framework for the development and
    configuration control of the NISP and includes the general management
    procedures for the application of the NISP in NATO C3 systems development
    and the process for handling Request for Change Proposals (RFCP).</para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Volume 2 - Near-term</emphasis>: This volume provides the interoperability standards and profiles in the near-term period. This is the short term
step describing the state of-the-art of NATO and National systems today and the framework for new systems actually under procurement or specification. For new  systems, it contains near-term standards, profiles, and technologies to support the initial steps towards Networking and Information Infrastructure (NII).</para>
    <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Volume 3 - Mid-term</emphasis>: This volume will describe the evolution from platform based legacy systems to the federated Network Enabled Capabilities environment where the functionality is made generally available as &#x201C;services on the net&#x201D;. Ultimately the goal is that the functionality of the most useful services shall be available to authorized users in each situation. The focus of the volume is on the mid-term perspective having a time frame of 2 to 10 years into the future from the publication of this version of the NISP. This timeframe encompasses the realization of a fully network enabled NATO environment.</para>

<para><emphasis role="bold">Volume 4 - Profiles</emphasis>: This volume provides Guidance on the development of Interoperability Profiles and references to published profiles. Interoperability Profiles aggregate references to the characteristics of other profiles types to provide a consolidated perspective. Interoperability Profiles identify essential profile elements including Capability Requirements and other NAF architectural views, characteristic protocols, implementation options, technical standards, Service Interoperability Points, and the relationship with other profiles such as the system profile to which an application belongs. Interoperability profiles will be referenced in the NISP for a specified NATO Common Funded System or Capability Package to include descriptions of interfaces to National Systems where appropriate.
</para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">Volume 5 - Design Rules</emphasis>: This volume provides Guidance on the development of Design Rules and references to published design rules.
</para>
    <para>In addition to these five volumes, the NISP includes an Annex volume containing the following appendicies:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Services and Interoperability Points in Platform Oriented and SOA Environments;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>NATO, National and Industry NEC Implementation Approaches;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Reference Models used in volumes 2 through 5 to structure and organise the standards and technologies;</para>
      </listitem>
<listitem><para>Enterprise Service Bus (ESB) Profile in the Service Oriented Architecture (SOA) context;</para>
</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Technology standards will transition through a life-cycle. This
    life-cycle is used to refine the categorisation of standards within volumes 2 and 3 and is also a key to providing guidance on the use of
    standards in the development and transition of NATO CIS. The NISP has adopted the five categories of in the life-cycle of standards shown below
    in <xref linkend="v1f1-stdscat" />.</para>
    <figure id="v1f1-stdscat" float="0">
      <title>Standards Categories</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../figures/stdscat1.svg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>Proposed standards can be accepted as emerging standards in order to
    follow their developments and decide if they can be promoted to mandatory
    standards. In some cases proposed standards can be readily accepted as
    mandatory standards. Emerging standards have been partitioned into
    specific categories of emerging near-term, and emerging
    mid-term to better support the transition to NNEC. Similarly, containment
    standards have been classified as either fading or retired.</para>
    <para>A short description of each category is described below:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Mandatory</emphasis>: A standard is
        considered <emphasis role="bold">mandatory</emphasis> if it is mature
        enough to be used immediately. This means that it may both be applied
        within existing systems and in within mid-term future planned
        systems.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Emerging near-term</emphasis>: A standard
        is considered <emphasis role="bold">emerging near-term</emphasis> if
        it is mature enough to be used within the 0 - 2 year time frame of
        Volume 2.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Emerging mid-term</emphasis>: A standard
        is considered <emphasis role="bold">emerging mid-term</emphasis> if it
        is sufficiently mature to be used within the current or next planned
        systems. This means that it may be applied within future mid-term
        planned systems. However they may not be immediately suitable if, for example
        there is insufficient support from commercial
        companies or because the underlying technology is considered not
        mature enough.  In these latter cases they could be categorized as <emphasis role="bold">Emerging far-term</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Fading</emphasis>: A standard is
        considered <emphasis role="bold">fading</emphasis> if the standard is
        still applicable for existing systems. The standard however is
        becoming obsolete or will be replaced by a newer version or another
        standard. Except for legacy systems or interoperability with legacy
        systems, the standard may not be used.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Retired</emphasis>: A standard is
        considered <emphasis role="bold">retired</emphasis> if the standard,
        that has been used in the past, is not applicable for existing
        systems.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Rejected</emphasis>: A standard is
        considered <emphasis role="bold">rejected</emphasis> if, while it was
        still emerging, it is considered unsuitable for use within
        NATO.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>Each standard in the NISP has a set of categories allocated to it
    that are applicable to the timeframe covered:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Volume 2 - Near-term: Category can be &#x201C;Mandatory&#x201D;, &#x201C;Emerging
        near-term&#x201D;, &#x201C;Fading&#x201D; or &#x201C;Retired&#x201D;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Volume 3 - Mid-term: Category can be &#x201C;Emerging mid-term&#x201D;; and
        &#x201C;rejected&#x201D;;</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Volume 3 - Far-term: Category can be &#x201C;Emerging far-term&#x201D; and
        &#x201C;rejected&#x201D;.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <sect1 id="v1s1-nsd">
      <title>NISP Structure Drivers</title>
      <para>In general, systems development approaches suggest a clean line of
      reasoning from requirements capturing to architecture, to design and
      build via testing to implementation and utilisation and finally to
      retirement. In practice there is not always an opportunity (time or
      money) for such a &ldquo;clean&rdquo; approach and compromises must be made: from
      requirements immediately to build and implementation. In recognition of
      this fact NATO has developed a parallel track approach, which allows some
      degree of freedom in the systems development approach. Although
      variations in sequence and speed of the different steps in the approach
      are possible, some elements need to be present in one form or another.
      Architecture, including the selection of appropriate standards and
      technologies, is such a mandatory step.</para>
      <para>In a top-down execution of the systems development approach,
      architecture will provide guidance and overview to the required
      functionality and the solution patterns, based on long-standing and
      visionary operational requirements. In a bottom-up execution of the
      approach, usually responding to urgent requirements and operational
      imperatives, architecture will be used to assess and validate chosen
      solution in order to align with the longer term vision.</para>
      <para>The NISP is a major tool for the architecture work and must be
      suitable for use in the different variations of the systems development
      approach.</para>
<para>SOA, NNEC Roadmap milestones, and the agreed Overarching Architecture also influence the structure of the NISP.</para>
    <sect2 id="v1s2-NISP-Appl">
      <title>NATO Interoperability Standards and Profiles Application to
      Architectures</title>
      <para>The NATO Interoperability Directive (NID) defines what types of
      architectures are to be developed within NATO: namely Baseline
      Architectecture (BA), Target Architecture (TA), Reference Architecture
      (RA), and Overarching Architecture (OA). These architecture types can be
      related to the NISP Volumes 2 and 3 as follows:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Volume 2 contains the standards mostly applicable to the TA's
          and BA's;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Volume 3 contains the standards mostly applicable to the
          RA's and OA.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>In particular the relationship with the Overarching Architecture
      is of a reciprocal nature. The OA also provides inputs to the NISP by
      identifying the technology areas that in the future will require
      standards. The OA also provides guidance on the coherence of standards
      by indicating in which timeframe certain standards and profiles are
      required.</para>
      <para>The work on RA's and TA's will benefit from the NISP by selecting
      coherent sets of standards for profiles and design rules.</para>
    </sect2></sect1>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="v1c-Management">
    <title>NISP and Configuration Management Process</title>
    <para>The NISP has to be periodically updated to account for enhancements
    in technology. Updates to the NISP are handled through Requests For Change
    Proposal (RFCP). RFCPs are usually reviewed at regularly scheduled NOSWG
    meetings. RFCPs deemed urgent are handled in an expedited manner, outside
    the normal meeting schedule of the NOSWG with a reply to the RFCP
    originator within two weeks.</para>
    <para>The six volume version of the NISP will be submitted to the NC3 Board in the first quarter of each year after internal review by the NOSWG. The version under review is a snapshot in time of the status of standards and profiles. The NISP database of standards and profiles is the definitive source of the currents status of standards and profiles. The database will be updated as soon as the RFCP has been approved by the appropriate authority (NC3 Board).</para>
    <sect1 id="v1s1-NISP-Update">
      <title>NISP Update Process</title>
      <para>Updating of the NISP and its associated database will be conducted
      by a managed, rolling review process which will take into account
      information on standards available from a wide variety of sources. The
      NOSWG acts as the hub for this maintenance activity, supported by the
      NHQC3Staff and NC3A personnel as required. The information updating
      process is based on Requests For Change Proposal (RFCPs).</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v1s1-RFCP">
      <title>Request for Change Proposal (RFCP)</title>
      <para>Request for Changes Proposal (RFCP) to the NISP will be processed
      by the NOSWG following the process outlined in the <xref linkend="v1f6-RFCP" /> below:</para>
      <figure id="v1f6-RFCP" float="0">
        <title>RFCP Handling Process</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../figures/rfcp-proc.svg" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>The primary point of contact for RFCP submission is the Secretary
      NOSWG. RFCPs may be submitted to the NOSWG through a number of
      channels, including:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>NOSWG National representatives (for non-voting National
          representatives see NATO-CCEB List of Understandings (LoU) at <xref linkend="v1a-LOU" />);</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Strategic Command representatives;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NATO Agencies representatives;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Other Sub Committees of the NC3 Board, and their
          substructures;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NC3Board Staff representatives;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>NATO working groups / committees responsible for a specific
          standards domain;</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Approval of RFCPs will be coordinated with the responsible
      sub-committees where appropriate. In situations where a timely response
      is requested by the RFCP submitter, the NOSWG will make its
      recommendation directly to the NC3REPS. <xref linkend="v1D-CMnisp" />
      contains a detailed description of the RFCP process and the form for
      submitting RFCPs.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v1s1-CoordinationPMO">
      <title>Coordination with NATO PMOs</title>
      <para>The co-ordination with the NATO Programme Management Offices
      (PMOs) is primarily realised through the Strategic Commands
      representatives to the NOSWG. In addition, the NOSWG POW development
      takes into account the requirements of NATO programmes, which is derived
      from the programme increment currently under design.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="v1s1-CoordinationNational">
      <title>National Systems Interoperability Coordination</title>
      <para>Each of the national NOSWG representatives is responsible
      for:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Providing the NOSWG with the appropriate and timely inputs
          with respect to interoperability with national systems;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Co-ordination of the national position, including
          co-ordination with national representatives of other
          sub-committees;</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Providing the NOSWG with the appropriate technical information
          based on the national market assessment.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
  <xi:include href="vol1-annexA.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xpointer="v1a-LOU" />
  <xi:include href="vol1-annexB.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xpointer="v1D-CMnisp" />
</book>
